Foreign Policy

As the majority of the Italian states were in their internal constitution works of art, that is, the fruit of reflection and careful adaptation, so was their relation to one another and to foreign countries also a work of art. That nearly all of them were the result of recent usurpations was a fact which exercised as fatal an influence in their foreign as in their internal policy. Not one of them recognized another without reserve; the same play of chance which had helped to found and consolidate one dynasty might upset another. Nor was it always a matter of choice with the despot whether to keep quiet or not. The necessity of movement and aggrandizement is common to all illegitimate powers. Thus Italy became the scene of a 'foreign policy' which gradually, as in other countries also, acquired the position of a recognized system of public law. The purely objective treatment of international affairs, as free from prejudice as from moral scruples, attained a perfection which sometimes is not without a certain beauty and grandeur of its own. But as a whole it gives us the impression of a bottomless abyss.

Intrigues, armaments, leagues, corruption and treason make up the outward history of Italy at this period. Venice in particular was long accused on all hands of seeking to conquer the whole peninsula, or gradually so to reduce its strength that one state after another must fall into her hands. But on a closer view it is evident that this complaint did not come from the people, but rather from the courts and official classes, which were commonly abhorred by their subjects, while the mild government of Venice had secured for it general confidence. Even Florence, with its restive subject cities, found itself in a false position with regard to Venice, apart from all commercial jealousy and from the progress of Venice in Romagna. At last the League of Cambrai actually did strike a serious blow at the state which all Italy ought to have supported with united strength.

The other states, also, were animated by feelings no less unfriendly, and were at all times ready to use against one another any weapon which their evil conscience might suggest. Lodovico il Moro, the Aragonese kings of Naples and Sixtus IV — to say nothing of the smaller powers — kept Italy in a constant perilous agitation. It would have been well if the atrocious game had been confined to Italy; but it lay in the nature of the case that intervention and help should at last be sought from abroad — in particular from the French and the Turks.

The sympathies of the people at large were throughout on the side of France. Florence had never ceased to confess with shocking naïveté its old Guelph preference for the French. And when Charles VIII actually appeared on the south of the Alps, all Italy accepted him with an enthusiasm which to himself and his followers seemed unaccountable. In the imagination of the Italians, to take Savonarola for an example, the ideal picture of a wise, just and powerful saviour and ruler was still living, with the difference that he was no longer the emperor invoked by Dante, but the Capetian King of France. With his departure the illusion was broken; but it was long before all understood how completely Charles VIII, Louis XII and Francis I had mistaken their true relation to Italy, and by what inferior motives they were led. The princes, for their part, tried to make use of France in a wholly different way. When the Franco-English wars came to an end, when Louis XI began to cast about his diplomatic nets on all sides, and Charles of Burgundy to embark on his foolish adventures, the Italian Cabinets came to meet them at every point. It became clear that the intervention of France was only a question of time, even though the claims on Naples and Milan had never existed, and that the old interference with Genoa and Piedmont was only a type of what was to follow. The Venetians, in fact, expected it as early as 1462. The mortal terror of the Duke Galeazzo Maria of Milan during the Burgundian war, in which he was apparently the ally of Charles as well as of Louis, and consequently had reason to dread an attack from both, is strikingly shown in his correspondence. The plan of an equilibrium of the four chief Italian powers, as understood by Lorenzo the Magnificent, was but the assumption of a cheerful optimistic spirit, which had outgrown both the recklessness of an experimental policy and the superstitions of Florentine Guelphism, and persisted in hoping for the best. When Louis XI offered him aid in the war against Ferrante of Naples and Sixtus IV, he replied, 'I cannot set my own advantage above the safety of all Italy; would to God it never came into the mind of the French kings to try their strength in this country! Should they ever do so, Italy is lost.' For the other princes, the King of France was alternately a bugbear to themselves and to their enemies, and they threatened to call him in whenever they saw no more convenient way out of their difficulties. The popes, in their turn, fancied that they could make use of France without any danger to themselves, and even Innocent VIII imagined that he could withdraw to sulk in the North, and return as a conqueror to Italy at the head of a French army.

Thoughtful men, indeed, foresaw the foreign conquest long before the expedition of Charles VIII. And when Charles was back again on the other side of the Alps, it was plain to every eye that an era of intervention had begun. Misfortune now followed on misfortune; it was understood too late that France and Spain, the two chief invaders, had become great European powers, that they would be no longer satisfied with verbal homage, but would fight to the death for influence and territory in Italy. They had begun to resemble the centralized Italian states, and indeed to copy them, only on a gigantic scale. Schemes of annexation or exchange of territory were for a time indefinitely multiplied. The end, as is well known, was the complete victory of Spain, which, as sword and shield of the Counter-Reformation, long held the papacy among its other subjects. The melancholy reflections of the philosophers could only show them how those who had called in the barbarians all came to a bad end.

Alliances were at the same time formed with the Turks too, with as little scruple or disguise; they were reckoned no worse than any other political expedients. The belief in the unity of Western Christendom had at various times in the course of the Crusades been seriously shaken, and Frederick II had probably outgrown it. But the fresh advance of the oriental nations, the need and the ruin of the Greek empire, had revived the old feeling, though not in its former strength, throughout Western Europe. Italy, however, was a striking exception to this rule. Great as was the terror felt for the Turks, and the actual danger from them, there was yet scarcely a government of any consequence which did not conspire against other Italian states with Muhammad II and his successors. And when they did not do so, they still had the credit of it; nor was it worse than the sending of emissaries to poison the cisterns of Venice, which was the charge brought against the heirs of Alfonso, King of Naples. From a scoundrel like Sigismondo Malatesta nothing better could be expected than that he should call the Turks into Italy. But the Aragonese monarchs of Naples, from whom Muhammad — at the instigation, we read, of other Italian governments, especially of Venice — had once wrested Otranto (1480), afterwards hounded on the Sultan Bajazet II against the Venetians. The same charge was brought against Lodovico il Moro. 'The blood of the slain, and the misery of the prisoners in the hands of the Turks, cry to God for vengeance against him,' says the state historian. In Venice, wherethe government was informed of everything, it was known that Giovanni Sforza, ruler of Pesaro, the cousin of the Moor, had entertained the Turkish ambassadors on their way to Milan. The two most respectable among the popes of the fifteenth century, Nicholas V and Pius II, died in the deepest grief at the progress of the Turks, the latter indeed amid the preparations for a crusade which he was hoping to lead in person; their successors embezzled the contributions sent for this purpose from all parts of Christendom, and degraded the indulgences granted in return for them into a private commercial speculation. Innocent VIII consented to be gaoler to the fugitive Prince Djem, for a salary paid by the prisoner's brother Bajazet II, and Alexander VI supported the steps taken by Lodovico il Moro in Constantinople to further a Turkish assault upon Venice (1498), whereupon the latter threatened him with a Council. It is clear the notorious alliance between Francis I and Soliman II was nothing new or unheard of.

Indeed, we find instances of whole populations to whom it seemed no particular crime to go over bodily to the Turks. Even if it were only held out as a threat to oppressive governments, this is at least a proof that the idea had become familiar. As early as 1480 Battista Mantovano gives us clearly to understand that most of the inhabitants of the Adriatic coast foresaw something of this kind, and that Ancona in particular desired it. When Romagna was suffering from the oppressive government of Leo X, a deputy from Ravenna said openly to the legate, Cardinal Giulio Medici: 'Monsignore, the honourable Republic of Venice will not have us, for fear of a dispute with the Holy See; but if the Turk comes to Ragusa we will put ourselves into his hands.'

It was a poor but not wholly groundless consolation for the enslavement of Italy then begun by the Spaniards that the country was at least secured from the relapse into barbarism which would have awaited it under the Turkish rule. By itself, divided as it was, it could hardly have escaped this fate.

If, with all these drawbacks, the Italian statesmanship of this period deserves our praise, it is only on the ground of its practical and unprejudiced treatment of those questions which were not affected by fear, passion or malice, Here was no feudal system after the northern fashion, with its artificial scheme of rights; but the power which each possessed he held in practice as in theory. Here was no attendant nobility to foster in the mind of the prince the medieval sense of honour, with all its strange consequences; but princes and counsellors were agreed in acting according to the exigencies of the particular case and to the end they had in view. Towards the men whose services were used and towards allies, come from what quarter they might, no pride of caste was felt which could possibly estrange a supporter; and the class of the condottieri, in which birth was a matter of indifference, shows clearly enough in what sort of hands the real power lay; and lastly, the government, in the hands of an enlightened despot, had an incomparably more accurate acquaintance with its own country and that of its neighbours than was possessed by northern contemporaries, and estimated the economical and moral capacities of friend and foe down to the smallest particular. The rulers were, notwithstanding grave errors, born masters of statistical science. With such men negotiation was possible; it might be presumed that they would be convinced and their opinion modified when practical reasons were laid before them. When the great Alfonso of Naples was (1434) a prisoner of Filippo Maria Visconti, he was able to satisfy his gaoler that the rule of the House of Anjou instead of his own at Naples would make the French masters of Italy; Filippo Maria set him free without ransom and made an alliance with him. A northern prince would scarcely have acted in the same way, certainly not one whose morality in other respects was like that of Visconti. What confidence was felt in the power of self-interest is shown by the celebrated visit which Lorenzo the Magnificent, to the universal astonishment of the Florentines, paid the faithless Ferrante at Naples — a man who would be certainly tempted to keep him a prisoner, and was by no means too scrupulous to do so. For to arrest a powerful monarch, and then to let him go alive, after extorting his signature and otherwise insulting him, as Charles the Bold did to Louis XI at Peronne (1468), seemed madness to the Italians; so that Lorenzo was expected to come back covered with glory, or else not to come back at all. The art of political persuasion was at this time raised to a point — especially by the Venetian ambassadors — of which northern nations first obtained a conception from the Italians, and of which the official addresses give a most imperfect idea. These are mere pieces of humanistic rhetoric. Nor, in spite of an otherwise ceremonious etiquette, was there in case of need any lack of rough and frank speaking in diplomatic intercourse. A man like Machiavelli appears in his Legazioni in an almost pathetic light. Furnished with scanty instructions, shabbily equipped, and treated as an agent of inferior rank, he never loses his gift of free and wide observation or his pleasure in picturesque description.

A special division of this work will treat of the study of man individually and nationally, which among the Italians went hand in hand with the study of the outward conditions of human life.

War as a Work of Art

It must here be briefly indicated by what steps the art of war assumed the character of a product of reflection. Throughout the countries of the West the education of the individual soldier in the Middle Ages was perfect within the limits of the then prevalent system of defence and attack: nor was there any want of ingenious inventors in the arts of besieging and of fortification. But the development both of strategy and of tactics was hindered by the character and duration of military service, and by the ambition of the nobles, who disputed questions of precedence in the face of the enemy, and through simple want of discipline caused the loss of great battles like Crécy and Maupertuis. Italy, on the contrary, was the first country to adopt the system of mercenary troops, which demanded a wholly different organization; and the early introduction of firearms did its part in making war a democratic pursuit, not only because the strongest castles were unable to withstand a bombardment, but because the skill of the engineer, of the gun-founder and of the artillerist — men belonging to another lass than the nobility — was now of the first importance in a campaign. It was felt, with regret, that the value of the individual, which had been the soul of the small and admirably organized bands of mercenaries, would suffer from these novel means of destruction, which did their work at a distance; and there were condottieri who opposed to the utmost the introduction at least of the musket, which had been lately invented in Germany. We read that Paolo Vitelli, while recognizing and himself adopting the cannon, put out the eyes and cut off the hands of the captured schioppettieri of the enemy, because he held it unworthy that a gallant, and it might be noble, knight should be wounded and laid low by a common, despised foot soldier. On the whole, however, the new discoveries were accepted and turned to useful account, till the Italians became the teachers of all Europe, both in the building of fortifications and in the means of attacking them. Princes like Federigo of Urbino and Alfonso of Ferrara acquired a mastery of the subject compared to which the knowledge even of Maximilian I appears superficial. In Italy, earlier than elsewhere, there existed a comprehensive science and art of military affairs; here, for the first time, that impartial delight is taken in able generalship for its own sake which might, indeed, be expected from the frequent change of party and from the wholly unsentimental mode of action of the condottieri. During the Milano-Venetian war of 1451 and 1452, between Francesco Sforza and Jacopo Piccinino, the headquarters of the latter were attended by the scholar Gian Antonio Porcello dei Pandoni, commissioned by Alfonso of Naples to write a report of the campaign. It is written, not in the purest, but in a fluent Latin, a little too much in the style of the humanistic bombast of the day, is modelled on Caesar's Commentaries, and interspersed with speeches, prodigies and the like. Since for the past hundred years it had been seriously disputed whether Scipio Africanus or Hannibal was the greater, Piccinino through the whole book must needs be called Scipio and Sforza Hannibal. But something positive had to be reported, too, respecting the Milanese army; the sophist presented himself to Sforza, was led along the ranks, praised highly all that he saw, and promised to hand it down to posterity. Apart from him the Italian literature of the day is rich in descriptions of wars and strategic devices, written for the use of educated men in general as well as of specialists, while the contemporary narratives of northerns, such as the Burgundian War by Diebold Schilling, still retain the shapelessness and matter-of-fact dryness of a mere chronicle. The greatest dilettante who has ever treated in that character of military affairs, Machiavelli, was then busy writing his Arte della Guerra. But the development of the individual soldier found its most complete expression in those public and solemn conflicts between one or more pairs of combatants which were practised long before the famous 'Challenge of Barletta' (1503). The victor was assured of the praises of poets and scholars, which were denied to the northern warrior. The result of these combats was no longer regarded as a divine judgement, but as a triumph of personal merit, and to the minds of the spectators seemed to be both the decision of an exciting competition and a satisfaction for the honour of the army or the nation.

It is obvious that this purely rational treatment of warlike affairs allowed, under certain circumstances, of the worst atrocities, even in the absence of a strong political hatred, as, for instance, when the plunder of a city had been promised to the troops. After the forty days' devastation of Piacenza, which Sforza was compelled to permit to his soldiers (1447), the town long stood empty, and at last had to be peopled by force. Yet outrages like these were nothing compared with the misery which was afterwards brought upon Italy by foreign troops, and most of all by the Spaniards, in whom perhaps a touch of oriental blood, perhaps familiarity with the spectacles of the Inquisition, had unloosed the devilish element of human nature. After seeing them at work at Prato, Rome and elsewhere, it is not easy to take any interest of the higher sort in Ferdinand the Catholic and Charles V, who knew what these hordes were, and yet unchained them. The mass of documents which are gradually brought to light from the Cabinets of these rulers will always remain an important source of historical information; but from such men no fruitful political conception can be looked for.

The Papacy

The papacy and the dominions of the Church are creations of so peculiar a kind that we have hitherto, in determining the general characteristics of Italian states, referred to them only occasionally. The deliberate choice and adaptation of political expedients, which gives so great an interest to the other states, is what we find least of all at Rome, since here the spiritual power could constantly conceal or supply the defects of the temporal. And what fiery trials did this state undergo in the fourteenth and the beginning of the fifteenth century, when the papacy was led captive to Avignon! All, at first, was thrown into confusion; but the pope had money, troops and a great statesman and general, the Spaniard Albornoz, who again brought the ecclesiastical state into complete subjection. The danger of a final dissolution was still greater at the time of the schism, when neither the Roman nor the French pope was rich enough to reconquer the newly lost state; but this was done under Martin V, after the unity of the Church was restored, and done again under Eugenius IV, when the same danger was renewed. But the ecclesiastical state was and remained a thorough anomaly among the powers of Italy; in and near Rome itself, the papacy was defied by the great families of the Colonna, Orsini, Savelli and Anguilara; in Umbria, in the Marches and in Romagna, those civic republics had almost ceased to exist, for whose devotion the papacy had showed so little gratitude; their place had been taken by a crowd of princely dynasties, great or small, whose loyalty and obedience signified little. As self-dependent powers, standing on their own merits, they have an interest of their own; and from this point of view the most important of them have already been discussed.

Nevertheless, a few general remarks on the papacy can hardly be dispensed with. New and strange perils and trials came upon it in the course of the fifteenth century, as the political spirit of the nation began to lay hold upon it on various sides, and to draw it within the sphere of its action. The least of these dangers came from the populace or from abroad; the most serious had their ground in the characters of the popes themselves.

Let us, for this moment, leave out of consideration the countries beyond the Alps. At the time when the papacy was exposed to mortal danger in Italy, it neither received nor could receive the slightest assistance either from France, then under Louis XI, or from England, distracted by the Wars of the Roses, or from the then disorganized Spanish monarchy, or from Germany, but lately betrayed at the Council of Basel. In Italy itself there was a certain number of instructed and even uninstructed people whose national vanity was flattered by the Italian character of the papacy; the personal interests of very many depended on its having and retaining this character; and vast masses of the people still believed in the virtue of the papal blessing and consecration; among them notorious transgressors like Vitelozzo Vitelli, who still prayed to be absolved by Alexander VI, when the pope's son had him strangled. But all these grounds of sympathy put together would not have sufficed to save the papacy from its enemies, had the latter been really in earnest, and had they known how to take advantage of the envy and hatred with which the institution was regarded.

And at the very time when the prospect of help from without was so small, the most dangerous symptoms appeared within the papacy itself. Living, as it now did, and acting in the spirit of the secular Italian principalities, it was compelled to go through the same dark experiences as they; but its own exceptional nature gave a peculiar colour to the shadows.

As far as the city of Rome itself is concerned, small account was taken of its internal agitations, so many were the popes who had returned after being expelled by popular tumult, and so greatly did the presence of the Curia minister to the interests of the Roman people. But Rome not only displayed at times a specific anti-papal radicalism, but in the most serious plots which were then contrived, gave proof of the working of unseen hands from without. It was so in the case of the conspiracy of Stefano Porcari against Nicholas V (1453), the very pope who had done most for the prosperity of the city. Porcari aimed at the complete overthrow of the papal authority, and had distinguished accomplices, who, though their names are not handed down to us, are certainly to be looked for among the Italian governments of the time. Under the pontificate of the same man, Lorenzo Valla concluded his famous declamation against the gift of Constantine with the wish for the speedy secularization of the states of the Church.

The Catilinarian gang, with which Pius II had to contend (1460), avowed with equal frankness their resolution to overthrow the government of the priests, and its leader, Tburzio, threw the blame on the soothsayers, who had fixed the accomplishment of his wishes for this very year. Several of the chief men of Rome, the Prince of Taranto and the condottiere Jacopo Piccinino were accomplices and supporters of Tiburzio. Indeed, when we think of the booty which was accumulated in the palaces of wealthy prelates — the conspirators had the Cardinal of Aquileia especially in view — we are surprised that, in an almost unguarded city, such attempts were not more frequent and more successful. It was not without reason that Pius II preferred to reside anywhere rather than in Rome, and even Paul II was exposed to no small anxiety through a plot formed by some discharged abbreviators, who, under the command of Platina, besieged the Vatican for twenty days. The papacy must sooner or later have fallen a victim to such enterprises, if it had not stamped out the aristocratic factions under whose protection these bands of robbers grew to a head.

This task was undertaken by the terrible Sixtus IV. He was the first pope who had Rome and the neighbourhood thoroughly under his control, especially after his successful attack on the House of Colonna, and consequently, both in his Italian policy and in the internal affairs of the Church, he could venture to act with a defiant audacity, and to set at nought the complaints and threats to summon a Council which arose from all parts of Europe. He supplied himself with the necessary funds by simony, which suddenly grew to unheard-of proportions, and which extended from the appointment of cardinals down to the granting of the smallest favours. Sixtus himself had not obtained the papal dignity without recourse to the same means.

A corruption so universal might sooner or later bring disastrous consequences on the Holy See, but they lay in the uncertain future. It was otherwise with nepotism, which threatened at one time to destroy the papacy altogether. Of all the nipoti, Cardinal Pietro Riario enjoyed at first the chief and almost exclusive favour of Sixtus. He soon drew upon him the eyes of all Italy, partly by the fabulous luxury of his life, partly through the reports which were current of his irreligion and his political plans. He bargained with Duke Galeazzo Maria of Milan (1473) that the latter should become King of Lombardy, and then aid him with money and troops to return to Rome and ascend the papal throne; Sixtus, it appears, would have voluntarily yielded to him. This plan, which, by making the papacy hereditary, would have ended in the secularization of the papal state, failed through the sudden death of Pietro. The second nipote, Girolamo Riario, remained a layman, and did not seek the pontificate. From this time the nipoti, by their endeavours to found principalities for themselves, became a new source of confusion to Italy. It had already happened that the popes tried to make good their feudal claims on Naples in favour of their relatives! But since the failure of Calixtus III, such a scheme was no longer practicable, and Girolamo Riario, after the attempt to conquer Florence (and who knows how many other places) had failed, was forced to content himself with founding a state within the limits of the papal dominions themselves. This was justifiable in so far as Romagna, with its princes and civic despots, threatened to shake off the papal supremacy altogether, and ran the risk of shortly falling a prey to Sforza or the Venetians, when Rome interfered to prevent it. But who, at times and in circumstances like these, could guarantee the continued obedience of nipoti and their descendants, now turned into sovereign rulers, to popes with whom they had no further concern? Even in his lifetime the pope was not always sure of his own son or nephew, and the temptation was strong to expel the nipote of a precedessor and replace him with one of his own. The reaction of the whole system on the papacy itself was of the most serious character; all means of compulsion, whether temporal or spiritual, were used without scruple for the most questionable ends, and to these all the other objects of the Apostolic See were made subordinate. And when they were attained, at whatever cost of revolutions and proscriptions, a dynasty was founded which had no stronger interest than the destruction of the papacy.

At the death of Sixtus, Girolamo was only able to maintain himself in his usurped principality of Forlì and Imola by the utmost exertions of his own, and by the aid of the House of Sforza, to which his wife belonged. In the conclave (1484) which followed the death of Sixtus — that in which Innocent VIII was elected — an incident occurred which seemed to furnish the papacy with a new external guarantee. Two cardinals, who, at the same time, were princes of ruling houses, Giovanni d'Aragona, son of King Ferrante, and Ascanio Sforza, brother of the Moor, sold their votes with the most shameless effrontery; so that, at any rate, the ruling houses of Naples and Milan became interested, by their participation in the booty, in the continuance of the papal system. Once again, in the following conclave, when all the cardinals but five sold themselves, Ascanio received enormous sums in bribes, but without cherishing the hope that at the next election he would himself be the favoured candidate.

Lorenzo the Magnificent, for his part, was anxious that the House of Medici should not be sent away with empty hands. He married his daughter Maddalena to the son of the new pope — the first who publicly acknowledged his children — Franceschetto Cibò, and expected not only favours of all kinds for his own son, Cardinal Giovanni, afterwards Leo X, but also the rapid promotion of his son-in-law. But with respect to the latter, he demanded impossibilities. Under Innocent VIII there was no opportunity for the audacious nepotism by which states had been founded, since Franceschetto himselfwas a poor creature who, like his father the pope, sought power only for the lowest purpose of all — the acquisition and accumulation of money. The manner, however, in which father and son practised this occupation must have led sooner or later to a final catastrophe — the dissolution of the state. If Sixtus had filled his treasury by the sale of spiritual dignities and favours, Innocent and his son, for their part, established an office for the sale of secular favours, in which pardons for murder and manslaughter were sold for large sums of money. Out of every fine 150 ducats were paid into the papal exchequer, and what was over to Franceschetto. Rome, during the latter part of this pontificate, swarmed with licensed and unlicensed assassins; the factions, which Sixtus had begun to put down, were again as active as ever; the pope, well guarded in the Vatican, was satisfied with now and then laying a trap, in which a wealthy misdoer was occasionally caught. For Franceschetto the chief point was to know by what means, when the pope died, he could escape with well-filled coffers. He betrayed himself at last, on the occasion of a false report (1490) of his father's death; he endeavoured to carry off all the money in the papal treasury, and when this proved impossible, insisted that, at all events, the Turkish prince, Djem, should go with him, and serve as a living capital, to be advantageously disposed of, perhaps to Ferrante of Naples. It is hard to estimate the political possibilities of remote periods, but we cannot help asking ourselves the question, if Rome could have survived two or three pontificates of this kind. Even with reference to the believing countries of Europe, it was imprudent to let matters go so far that not only travellers and pilgrims, but a whole embassy of Maximilian, King of the Romans, were stripped to their shirts in the neighbourhood of Rome, and that envoys had constantly to turn back without setting foot within the city.

Such a condition of things was incompatible with the conception of power and its pleasures which inspired the gifted Alexander VI (1492—1503), and the first event that happened was the restoration, at least provisionally, of public order, and the punctual payment of every salary.

Strictly speaking, as we are now discussing phases of Italian civilization, this pontificate might be passed over, since the Borgias are no more Italian than the House of Naples. Alexander spoke Spanish in public with Cesare; Lucrezia, at her entrance to Ferrara, where she wore a Spanish costume, was sung to by Spanish buffoons; their confidential servants consisted of Spaniards, as did also the most ill-famed company of the troops of Cesare in the war of 1500; and even his hangman, Don Micheletto, and his poisoner, Sebastian Pinzon Cremonese, seem to have been of the same nation. Among his other achievements, Cesare, in true Spanish fashion, killed, according to the rules of the craft, six wild bulls in an enclosed court. But the Roman corruption, which seemed to culminate in this family, was already far advanced when they came to the city.

What they were and what they did has been often and fully described. Their immediate purpose, which, in fact, they attained, was the complete subjugation of the pontifical state. All the petty despots, who were mostly more or less refractory vassals of the Church, were expelled or destroyed; and in Rome itself the two great factions were annihilated, the so-called Guelph Orsini as well as the so-called Ghibel-line Colonna. But the means employed were of so frightful a character that they must certainly have ended in the ruin of the papacy, had not the contemporaneous death of both father and son by poison suddenly intervened to alter the whole aspect of the situation. The moral indignation of Christendom was certainly no great source of danger to Alexander; at home he was strong enough to extort terror and obedience; foreign rulers were won over to his side, and Louis XII even aided him to the utmost of his power. The mass of the people throughout Europe had hardly a conception of what was passing in Central Italy. The only moment which was really fraught with danger — when Charles VIII was in Italy — went by with unexpected fortune, and even then it was not the papacy as such that was in peril, but Alexander, who risked being supplanted by a more respectable pope. The great, permanent and increasing danger for the papacy lay in Alexander himself, and, above all, in his son Cesare Borgia.

In the nature of the father, ambition, avarice and sensuality were combined with strong and brilliant qualities. All the pleasures of power and luxury he granted himself from the first day of his pontificate in the fullest measure. In the choice of means to this end he was wholly without scruple; it was known at once that he would more than compensate himself for the sacrifices which his election had involved, and that the simony of the seller would far exceed the simony of the buyer. It must be remembered that the vice-chancellorship and other offices which Alexander had formerly held had taught him to know better and turn to more practical account the various sources of revenue than any other member of the Curia. As early as 1494, a Carmelite, Adam of Genoa, who had preached at Rome against simony, was found murdered in his bed with twenty wounds. Hardly a single cardinal was appointed without the payment of enormous sums of money.

But when the pope in course of time fell under the influence of his son Cesare Borgia, his violent measures assumed that character of devilish wickedness which necessarily reacts upon the ends pursued. What was done in the struggle with the Roman nobles and with the tyrants of Romagna exceeded in faithlessness and barbarity even that measure to which the Aragonese rulers of Naples had already accustomed the world; and the genius for deception was also greater. The manner in which Cesare isolated his father, murdering brother, brother-in-law and other relations or courtiers, whenever their favour with the pope or their position in any other respect became inconvenient to him, is literally appalling. Alexander was forced to acquiesce in the murder of his best-loved son, the Duke of Gandia, since he himself lived in hourly dread of Cesare.

What were the final aims of the latter? Even in the last months of his tyranny, when he had murdered the condottieri at Sinigaglia, and was to all intents and purposes master of the ecclesiastical state (1503), those who stood near him gave the modest reply that the duke merely wished to put down the factions and the despots, and all for the good of the Church only; that for himself he desired nothing more than the lordship of the Romagna, and that he had earned the gratitude of all the following popes by riding them of the Orsini and Colonna. But no one will accept this as his ultimate design. The Pope Alexander himself, in his discussions with the Venetian ambassador, went further than this, when committing his son to the protection of Venice: 'I will see to it,' he said, 'that one day the papacy shall belong either to him or to you.' Cesare certainly added that no one could become pope without the consent of Venice, and for this end the Venetian cardinals had only to keep well together. Whether he referred to himself or not we are unable to say; at all events, the declaration of his father is sufficient to prove his designs on the pontifical throne. We further obtain from Lucrezia Borgia a certain amount of indirect evidence, in so far as certain passages in the poems of Ercole Strozza may be the echo of expressions which she as Duchess of Ferrara may easily have permitted herself to use. Here, too, Cesare's hopes of the papacy are chiefly spoken of; but now and then a supremacy over all Italy is hinted at, and finally we are given to understand that as temporal ruler Cesare's projects were of the greatest, and that for their sake he had formerly surrendered his cardinalate. In fact, there can be no doubt whatever that Cesare, whether chosen pope or not after the death of Alexander, meant to keep possession of the pontifical state at any cost, and that this, after all the enormities he had committed, he could not as pope have succeeded in doing permanently. He, if anybody, could have secularized the States of the Church, and he would have been forced to do so in order to keep them. Unless we are much deceived, this is the real reason of the secret sympathy with which Machiavelli treats the great criminal; from Cesare, or from nobody, could it be hoped that he 'would draw the steel from the wound', in other words, annihilate the papacy — the source of all foreign intervention and of all the divisions of Italy. The intriguers who thought to divine Cesare's aims, when holding out to him hopes of the kingdom of Tuscany, seem to have been dismissed with contempt.

But all logical conclusions from his premises are idle, not because of the unaccountable genius which in fact characterized him as little as it did Wallenstein, but because the means which he employed were not compatible with any large and consistent course of action. Perhaps, indeed, in the very excess of his wickedness some prospect of salvation for the papacy may have existed even without the accident which put an end to his rule.

Even if we assume that the destruction of the petty despots in the pontifical state had gained for him nothing but sympathy, even if we take as proof of his great projects the army, composed of the best soldiers and officers in Italy, with Leonardo da Vinci as chief engineer, which followed his fortunes in 1502, other facts nevertheless wear such a character of unreason that our judgement, like that of contemporary observers, is wholly at a loss to explain them. One fact of this kind is the devastation and maltreatment of the newly won state, which Cesare still intended to keep and to rule over. Another is the condition of Rome and of the Curia in the last decades of the pontificate. Whether it were that father and son had drawn up a formal list of proscribed persons, or that the murders were resolved upon one by one, in either case the Borgias were bent on the secret destruction of all who stood in their way or whose inheritance they coveted. Of this money and movable goods formed the smallest part; it was a much greater source of profit for the pope that the incomes of the clerical dignitaries in question were suspended by their death, and that he received the revenues of their offices while vacant, and the price of these offices when they were filled by the successors of the murdered men. The Venetian ambassador Paolo Capello announces in the year 1500: 'Every night four or five murdered men are discovered — bishops, prelates and others — so that all Rome is trembling for fear of being destroyed by the duke [Cesare].' He himself used to wander about Rome in the night-time with his guards, and there is every reason to believe that he did so not only because, like Tiberius, he shrank from showing his now repulsive features by daylight, but also to gratify his insane thirst for blood, perhaps even on the persons of those unknown to him.

As early as the year 1499 the despair was so great and so general that many of the papal guards were waylaid and put to death. But those whom the Borgias could not assail with open violence fell victims to their poison. For the cases in which a certain amount of discretion seemed requisite, a white powder of an agreeable taste was made use of, which did not work on the spot, but slowly and gradually, and which could be mixed without notice in any dish or goblet. Prince Djem had taken some of it in a sweet draught, before Alexander surrendered him to Charles VIII (1495), and at the end of their career father and son poisoned themselves with the same powder by accidentally tasting a sweetmeat intended for a wealthy cardinal. The official epitomizer of the history of the popes, Onofrio Panvinio, mentions three cardinals, Orsini, Ferrerio and Michiel, whom Alexander caused to be poisoned, and hints at a fourth, Giovanni Borgia, whom Cesare took into his own charge — though probably wealthy prelates seldom died in Rome at that time without giving rise to suspicions of this sort. Even tranquil scholars who had withdrawn to some provincial town were not out of reach of the merciless poison. A secret horror seemed to hang about the pope; storms and thunderbolts, crushing in walls and chambers, had in earlier times often visited and alarmed him; in the year 1500, when these phenomena were repeated, they were held to be cosa diabolica. The report of these events seems at last, through the well-attended jubilee of 1500, to have been carried far and wide throughout the countries of Europe, and the infamous traffic in indulgences did what else was needed to draw all eyes upon Rome. Besides the returning pilgrims, strange white-robed penitents came from Italy to the North, among them disguised fugitives from the papal state, who are not likely to have been silent. Yet none can calculate how far the scandal and indignation of Christendom might have gone before they became a source of pressing danger to Alexander. 'He would,' says Panvinio elsewhere, 'have put all the other rich cardinals and prelates out of the way, to get their property, had he not, in the midst of his great plans for his son, been struck down by death.' And what might not Cesare have achieved if, at the moment when his father died, he had not himself been laid upon a sickbed! What a conclave would that have been, in which, armed with all his weapons, he had extorted his election from a college whose numbers he had judiciously reduced by poison — and this at a time when there was no French army at hand! In pursuing such a hypothesis the imagination loses itself in an abyss.

Instead of this followed the conclave in which Pius III was elected, and, after his speedy death, that which chose Julius II — both elections the fruits of a general reaction.

Whatever may have been the private morals of Julius II, in all essential respects he was the saviour of the papacy. His familiarity with the course of events since the pontificate of his uncle Sixtus had given him a profound insight into the grounds and conditions of the papal authority. On these he founded his own policy, and devoted to it the whole force and passion of his unshaken soul. He ascended the steps of St Peter's chair without simony and amid general applause, and with him ceased, at all events, the undisguised traffic in the highest offices of the Church. Julius had favourites, and among them were some the reverse of worthy, but a special fortune put him above the temptation to nepotism. His brother, Giovanni della Rovere, was the husband of the heiress of Urbino, sister of the last Montefeltro Guidobaldo, and from this marriage was born, in 1491, a son, Francesco Maria della Rovere, who was at the same time papal nipote and lawful heir to the duchy of Urbino. What Julius elsewhere acquired, either on the field of battle or by diplomatic means, he proudly bestowed on the Church, not on his family; the ecclesiastical territory, which he found in a state of dissolution, he bequeathed to his successor completely subdued, and increased by Parma and Piacenza. It was not his fault that Ferrara too was not added to the dominions of the Church. The 700,000 ducats which were stored up in the Castel Sant' Angelo were to be delivered by the governor to none but the future pope. He made himself heir of the cardinals, and, indeed, of all the clergy who died in Rome, and this by the most despotic means; but he murdered or poisoned none of them. That he should himself lead his forces to battle was for him an unavoidable necessity, and certainly did him nothing but good at a time when a man in Italy was forced to be either hammer or anvil, and when personality was a greater power than the most indisputable right. If, despite all his high-sounding 'Away with the barbarians!' he nevertheless contributed more than any man to the firm settlement of the Spaniards in Italy, he may have thought it a matter of indifference to the papacy, or even, as things stood, a relative advantage. And to whom, sooner than to Spain, could the Church look for a sincere and lasting respect, in an age when the princes of Italy cherished none but the sacrilegious projects against her? Be this as it may, the powerful, original nature, which could swallow no anger and conceal no genuine good-will, made on the whole the impression most desirable in his situation — that of the pontefice terribile. He could even, with a comparatively clear conscience, venture to summon a Council to Rome, and so bid defiance to that outcry for a Council which was raised by the opposition all over Europe. A ruler of this stamp needed some great outward symbol of his conceptions; Julius found it in the reconstruction of St Peter's. The plan of it, as Bramante wished to have it, is perhaps the grandest expression of power in unity which can be imagined. In other arts besides architecture the face and the memory of the pope live on in their most ideal form, and it is not without significance that even the Latin poetry of those days gives proof of a wholly different enthusiasm for Julius than that shown for his predecessors. The entry into Bologna, at the end of the Iter Julii Secundi, by the Cardinal Adriano da Corneto, has a splendour of its own, and Giovan Antonio Flaminio, in one of the finest elegies, appealed to the patriot in the pope to grant his protection to Italy.

In a constitution of his Lateran Council, Julius had solemnly denounced the simony of the papal elections. After his death in 1513, the money-loving cardinals tried to evade the prohibition by proposing that the endowments and offices hitherto held by the chosen candidate should be equally divided among themselves, in which case they would have elected the best-endowed cardinal, the incompetent Raphael Riario. But a reaction, chiefly arising from the younger members of the Sacred College, who, above all things, desired a liberal pope, rendered the miserable combination futile; Giovanni Medici was elected — the famous Leo X.

We shall often meet with him in treating of the noonday of the Renaissance; here we wish only to point out that under him the papacy was again exposed to great inward and outward dangers. Among these we do not reckon the conspiracy of the Cardinals Petrucci, De Saulis, Riario and Corneto (1517), which at most could have occasioned a change of persons, and to which Leo found the true antidote in the unheard-of creation of thirty-one new cardinals, a measure which had the additional advantage of rewarding, in some cases at least, real merit.

But some of the paths which Leo allowed himself to tread during the first two years of his office were perilous to the last degree. He seriously endeavoured to secure, by negotiation, the kingdom of Naples for his brother Giuliano, and for his nephew Lorenzo a powerful North Italian state, to comprise Milan, Tuscany, Urbino and Ferrara. It is clear that the pontifical state, thus hemmed in on all sides, would have become a mere Medicean appanage, and that, in fact, there would have been no further need to secularize it.

The plan found an insuperable obstacle in the political conditions of the time. Giuliano died early. To provide for Lorenzo, Leo undertook to expel the Duke Francesco Maria della Rovere from Urbino, but reaped from the war nothing but hatred and poverty, and was forced, when in 1519 Lorenzo followed his uncle to the grave, to hand over the hard-won conquests to the Church. He did on compulsion and without credit what, if it had been done voluntarily, would have been to his lasting honour. What he attempted against Alfonso of Ferrara, and actually achieved against a few petty despots and condottieri, was assuredly not of a kind to raise his reputation. And this was at a time when the monarchs of the West were yearly growing more and more accustomed to political gambling on a colossal scale, of which the stakes were this or that province of Italy. Who could guarantee that, since the last decades had seen so great an increase of their power at home, their ambition would stop short of the States of the Church? Leo himself witnessed the prelude of what was fulfilled in the year 1527; a few bands of Spanish infantry appeared — of their own accord, it seems — at the end of 1520, on the borders of the pontifical territory, with a view of laying the pope under contribution, but were driven back by the papal forces. The public feeling, too, against the corruptions of the hierarchy had of late years been drawing rapidly to a head, and men with an eye for the future, like the younger Pico della Mirandola, called urgently for reform. Meantime Luther had already appeared upon the scene.

Under Adrian VI (1522—3), the few and timid improvements, carried out in the face of the great German Reformation, came too late. He could do little more than proclaim his horror of the course which things had taken hitherto, of simony, nepotism, prodigality, brigandage and profligacy. The danger from the side of the Lutherans was by no means the greatest; an acute observer from Venice, Girolamo Negro, uttered his fears that a speedy and terrible disaster would befall the city of Rome itself.

Under Clement VII the whole horizon of Rome was filled with vapours, like that leaden veil which the scirocco drew over the Campagna, and which made the last months of summer so deadly. The pope was no less detested at home than abroad. Thoughtful people were filled with anxiety, hermits appeared upon the streets and squares of Rome, foretelling the fate of Italy and of the world, and calling the pope by the name of Antichrist; the faction of the Colonna raised its head defiantly; the indomitable Cardinal Pompeo Colonna, whose mere existence was a permanent menace to the papacy, ventured to surprise the city in 1526, hoping, with the help of Charles V, to become pope then and there, as soon as Clement was killed or captured. It was no piece of good fortune for Rome that the latter was able to escape to the Castel Sant' Angelo, and the fate for which he himself was reserved may well be called worse than death.

By a series of those falsehoods, which only the powerful can venture on, but which bring ruin upon the weak, Clement brought about the advance of the Germano-Spanish army under Bourbon and Frundsberg (1527). It is certain that the Cabinet of Charles V intended to inflict on him a severe castigation, and that it could not calculate beforehand how far the zeal of its unpaid hordes would carry them. It would have been vain to attempt to enlist men in Germany without paying any bounty, if it had not been well known that Rome was the object of the expedition. It may be that the written orders to Bourbon will be found some day or other, and it is not improbable that they will prove to be worded mildly. But historical criticism will not allow itself to be led astray. The Catholic king and emperor owed it to his luck and nothing else that pope and cardinals were not murdered by his troops. Had this happened, no sophistry in the world could clear him of his share in the guilt. The massacre of countless people of less consequence, the plunder of the rest, and all the horrors of torture and traffic in human life show clearly enough what was possible in the Sacco di Roma.

Charles seems to have wished to bring the pope, who had fled a second time to the Castel Sant' Angelo, to Naples, after extorting from him vast sums of money, and Clement's flight to Orvieto must have happened without any connivance on the part of Spain. Whether the emperor ever thought seriously of the secularization of the States of the Church, for which everybody was quite prepared, and whether he was really dissuaded from it by the representations of Henry VIII of England, will probably never be made clear.

But if such projects really existed, they cannot have lasted long: from the devastated city arose a new spirit of reform both in Church and state. It made itself felt in a moment. Cardinal Sadoleto, one witness of many, thus writes:

If through our suffering a satisfaction is made to the wrath and justice of God, if these fearful punishments again open the way to better laws and morals, then is our misfortune perhaps not of the greatest ... What belongs to God He will take care of; before us lies a life of reformation, which no violence can take from us. Let us so rule our deeds and thoughts as to seek in God only the true glory of the priesthood and our own true greatness and power.

In point of fact, this critical year, 1527, so far bore fruit that the voices of serious men could again make themselves heard. Rome had suffered too much to return, even under a Paul III, to the gay corruption of Leo X.

The papacy, too, when its sufferings became so great, began to excite a sympathy half religious and half political. The kings could not tolerate that one of their number should arrogate to himself the rights of papal gaoler, and concluded (18 August 1527) the Treaty of Amiens, one of the objects of which was the deliverance of Clement. They thus, at all events, turned to their own account the unpopularity which the deeds of the imperial troops had excited. At the same time the emperor became seriously embarrassed, even in Spain, where the prelates and grandees never saw him without making the most urgent remonstrances. When a general deputation of the clergy and laity, all clothed in mourning, was projected, Charles, fearing that troubles might arise out of it, like those of the insurrection quelled a few years before, forbade the scheme. Not only did he not dare to prolong the maltreatment of the pope, but he was absolutely compelled, even apart from all considerations of foreign politics, to be reconciled with the papacy which he had so grievously wounded. For the temper of the German people, which certainly pointed to a different course, seemed to him, like German affairs generally, to afford no foundation for a policy. It is possible, too, as a Venetian maintains, that the memory of the sack of Rome lay heavy on his conscience, and tended to hasten that expiation which was sealed by the permanent subjection of the Florentines to the Medicean family of which the pope was a member. The nipote and new duke, Alessandro Medici, was married to the natural daughter of the emperor.

In the following years the plan of a Council enabled Charles to keep the papacy in all essential points under his control, and at one and the same time to protect and to oppress it. The greatest danger of all — secularization — the danger which came from within, from the popes themselves and their nipoti, was adjourned for centuries by the German Reformation. Just as this alone had made the expedition against Rome (1527) possible and successful, so did it compel the papacy to become once more the expression of a world-wide spiritual power, to raise itself from the soulless debasement in which it lay, and to place itself at the head of all the enemies of this Reformation. The institution thus developed during the latter years of Clement VII, and under Paul III, Paul IV, and their successors, in the face of the defection of half Europe, was a new, regenerated hierarchy, which avoided all the great and dangerous scandals of former times, particularly nepotism, with its attempts at territorial aggrandizement, and which, in alliance with the Catholic princes, and impelled by a new-born spiritual force, found its chief work in the recovery of what had been lost. It only existed and is only intelligible in opposition to the seceders. In this sense it can be said with perfect truth that the moral salvation of the papacy is due to its mortal enemies. And now its political position, too, though certainly under the permanent tutelage of Spain, became impregnable; almost without effort it inherited, on the extinction of its vassals, the legitimate line of Este and the house of della Rovere, the duchies of Ferrara and Urbino. But without the Reformation — if, indeed, it is possible to think it away — the whole ecclesiastical state would long ago have passed into secular hands.

Patriotism

In conclusion, let us briefly consider the effect of these political circumstances on the spirit of the nation at large.

It is evident that the general political uncertainty in Italy during the fourteenth and fifteenth centuries was of a kind to excite in the better spirits of the time a patriotic disgust and opposition. Dante and Petrarch, in their day, proclaimed loudly a common Italy, the object of the highest efforts of all her children. It may be objected that this was only the enthusiasm of a few highly instructed men, in which the mass of the people had no share; but it can hardly have been otherwise even in Germany, although in name at least that country was united, and recognized in the emperor one supreme head. The first patriotic utterances of German literature, if we except some verses of the Minnesänger, belong to the humanists of the time of Maximilian I and after, and read like an echo of Italian declamations. And yet, as a matter of fact, Germany had been long a nation in a truer sense than Italy ever was since the Roman days. France owes the consciousness of its national unity mainly to its conflicts with the English, and Spain has never permanently succeeded in absorbing Portugal, closely related as the two countries are. For Italy, the existence of the ecclesiastical state, and the conditions under which alone it could continue, were a permanent obstacle to national unity, an obstacle whose removal seemed hopeless. When, therefore, in the political intercourse of the fifteenth century, the common fatherland is sometimes emphatically named, it is done in most cases to annoy some other Italian state. But those deeply serious and sorrowful appeals to national sentiment were not heard again till later, when the time for unity had gone by, when the country was inundated with Frenchmen and Spaniards. The sense of local patriotism may be said in some measure to have taken the place of this feeling, though it was but a poor equivalent for it.

译者导读

托马斯·莫尔（St.Thomas More，又称Sir Thomas More，1478—1535），英格兰政治家、人文主义学者及欧洲空想主义创始人。1478年生于伦敦的一个法学家庭，毕业于牛津大学，曾任律师、国会议员、财政副大臣、国会下院议长、大法官。1535年因反对亨利八世兼任教会首脑而被处死。

莫尔最著名的作品《乌托邦》全名为《关于最完美的国家制度和乌托邦新岛的既有益又有趣的全书》，该书用拉丁语写成，约于1516年出版。莫尔在牛津大学攻读古典文学期间广泛阅读了柏拉图、伊壁鸠鲁、亚里士多德等人的作品，并深受人文主义和柏拉图思想的影响，后来有评论家将《乌托邦》称为柏拉图《理想国》的续篇。乌托邦一词源于希腊语，意为“没有的地方”或“好地方”，寓意一个虚构的美好地方。莫尔采用对话的方式，通过主人公拉斐尔的叙述以游记小说的表现形式描绘了一个理想社会。

《乌托邦》分为两部。第一部中，莫尔借拉斐尔之口揭露了当时英国社会的各种弊端，对十六世纪初欧洲国家，尤其是英国的政治制度和社会制度进行了尖锐的讽刺和深刻的揭露，并将批判的矛头直指私有制。莫尔对当时英国社会的描述及批判与第二部中乌托邦的描写形成鲜明的对比和反衬。第二部中，莫尔系统地介绍了乌托邦这个神秘岛国的政治、经济、科学文化、社会生活、宗教及外交。大至政治、经济、外交等社会制度，小至婚嫁、饮食、着装等社会习俗，莫尔无不进行了详尽细致的描述，将乌托邦这一神秘的国度活灵活现地展现在读者的眼前。政治上民主，经济上平等，生活上健康积极，宗教上自由宽容，外交上友好和平，乌托邦社会的各个方面都具有社会主义制度的雏形，小说《乌托邦》也开创了社会主义小说的先河。马克思和恩格斯称赞《乌托邦》一书显示出“共产主义思想的微光”。但由于历史的局限性，《乌托邦》也具有一定的片面性，例如，书中提到的“平均主义”在当时生产力水平低下的社会中根本行不通，只能是一种空想，然而这并不影响《乌托邦》成为不朽之作。

《乌托邦》最大的贡献在于第一个提出了消灭私有制、建立公有制的问题，并对社会主义制度的构想进行了详尽的描述，提出了一套完整的社会主义体系和具体原则。莫尔以这种独特的方式表达了对当时英国统治阶级的强烈不满和严厉的批判，并以一个空想的国度来寄托自己的社会理想。然而，在当时，莫尔不可能对资本主义有全面和深刻的认识，也无法寻得实现他所构想的社会制度的正确途径，因此“乌托邦”成为了空想的代名词。译者在翻译过程中力图使用最简洁的语言准确传达原著的意义，并对文中一些词汇作了简要的注解，以期读者能对这一不朽著作有更准确、更清晰的理解。

莫尔致彼得·贾尔斯的信

我亲爱的彼得·贾尔斯，我真不好意思寄给你这本关于乌托邦国家的小书，因为让你等了将近一年时间，而你一定期望在一个半月之内就能得到这本书。你知道在这本书中我不难找到我自己的主题，也不必苦苦思索一种合适的形式——我必须做的事情就是将拉斐尔对我们讲的内容复述一下而已。不必在措辞上费神太多，因为他在语言风格上并没有特别的润色——一切都是随时的即兴交谈，并且你也知道，他的拉丁语也不像他的希腊语那样好。因此，我越是接近他简朴的即席语言表达风格，我就越是贴近真实，在这种情况下，我所担心的也是应该担心的所有内容就是真实性。

是的，彼得，我知道。那么多的工作都已准备就绪，实际上我没有要做的事情了。告诉你吧，在其他任何情况下，创作和组织像这样的一本书，即使是有天赋、有学问的人也需要投入大量的时间来构思。如果既要尊重这一风格又要准确，我也就没有时间和精力来完成它了。但事实上，我免除了所有那些头痛的事情。我的工作只是将我所听到的记录下来，这确实极为容易——可是，其他的许多事情忙得我都没有一点时间来做这项极为容易的工作。我一直忙于法院的事情，或是参与辩护，或是主持审判，或是民事案件，或是刑事案件。再有就是总有因为公事或是出于礼貌要去拜访的人。我实际上整天在外面忙，与其他人打交道——剩余的时间就是与家人在一起，因此，我自己就没有剩下时间写作了。

你知道，我回家后必须与妻子聊天，与孩子们交流，与仆人讨论事情。我把这些也当作我应尽的义务，因为如果我不想在自己家中做一个陌生人，就绝对有必要这样做。除此之外，一个人应该善待一起生活的人，不管是谨慎选择为伙伴，或者只是由于偶然的机会或家族关系而共同生活——即应该尽量善待而不能损害他们，也不能把仆人变为主人。

因此，一天天、一月月，乃至一年年就这样悄然流逝。你可能会问，那么我何时写作呢？好了，到目前为止我还没有提及睡眠，或者是吃饭——许多人在吃饭上消耗的时间与睡眠一样多——其实我所获得的仅有时间都是我从睡眠和吃饭中偷来的。这些时间不多，因此我的进展就比较缓慢——但是至少还是有些时间，所以我已经最后完成了《乌托邦》这本书，现在寄给你，我亲爱的彼得，希望你能够阅读它，如有遗漏的地方就告诉我，我对那个得分感到相当的自信——因为我仅仅希望我的学问和智力能够达到我的记忆水准——但是我并不太自信我什么也没有忘记。

如你所知，我的年轻助手约翰·克莱门，那时也跟我们在一起。凡是有些教育价值的谈话我都决不让他错过，因为他已经开始在拉丁语和希腊语方面展现了希望，我期待着他有朝一日成就大事。对了，他使我感到有一个很难确定的细节问题。根据我的回忆，拉斐尔告诉我们空中城堡中的乌水河上的那座桥长五百码，但是约翰想让我把这个数字减少两百，因为他说那条河在那个地方不会超过三百码。请你根据你的记忆回忆一下正确的数字好吗？如果你同意他说的对，我就采取你一样的看法，确定我错了。但是如果你全忘记了，我就采用我的数字，因为这是我似乎记得的情况。你知道我极其想把事实搞对，有任何事情难以肯定的时候，我的任何讲述背离真实之处都不是我的意愿，因为我宁愿做老实人也不愿装聪明人。

尽管如此，最简单的解决方案就是你去问一下拉斐尔本人，或是口头，或是书面——事实上你必须去问，因为还有突然冒出来的一个小问题。我不知道是谁的错，是我、是你还是拉斐尔的错，我们从未想起来问过，而他又从未想起来告诉我们，乌托邦在新世界的哪里。我的钱不多，但我却极为愿意拿出这些钱来弥补这一过失。一方面，这使我感到相当愚蠢，我毕竟写了关于这座岛屿的故事，但却不知道它位于哪个海里。另一方面，有一两位英格兰人想去那里。尤其是有一位虔诚的神学家，他极其渴望去访问乌托邦，并不是因为无聊好奇而想去，而是因为既然那里已经成功地将基督教介绍进去了，他想进一步推进。因为他希望正式推动基督教在当地发展，他已决定设法让教皇委派他去，并实际上创设乌托邦主教。任何恳求升任的顾虑不能够阻碍他的希望。他认为这件事做起来极其正确，不是出于趋名逐利，而纯属是热情所驱。

因此，亲爱的彼得，如果你方便，能够安排面见一下拉斐尔或者是写信给他好吗？以确信我的这部作品写的东西都是全部真实的。也许你将该书拿给他看看就最好了，因为他是最有资格改正任何错误的人，而他也只有在通读全文之后，才能够改好。另外，通过这种方式，你就能发现他对我所写的他的研究结果是怎么样的态度。因为如果他计划亲自来写，他很可能不愿意我来代写——我当然也不应该将乌托邦过早地公布于众，使他的故事丧失新奇的魅力。

可是说实话，我还没有决定是否出版这部书。人们的口味差异很大，有的人极其严肃，有的人甚为苛刻，有的人偏执荒谬却对之加以蔑视，或者至少不表示感谢。大多数读者对文学一无所知——不少人蔑视文学。没有文化教养的人对任何不是完全没文化的事情都难以理解。有文化修养的人对任何不是古文体的东西都认为粗俗而加以反对。一些人只喜欢古典作品，一些人只喜欢自己的作品。一些人极为严肃不喜欢各种笑话，还有的人相当愚蠢，他们不能忍受风趣。一些人头脑迟钝，一听到一点讽刺话就害怕，就像狂犬病人听到水声一样。其他人每次站起来或坐下去都会得出不同的结论。一些旧经学派批评家，他们坐在公共酒店，以权威自居，随意谴责他人的作品。他们抓住你的作品，就像摔跤选手抓住对手的头发一样，将你摔倒，而他们自己却仍然保持不受任何伤害，因为他们无毛的脑袋完全光秃秃的——因此，没有你能够抓得住的东西。

另外有一些读者，他们即使极为欣赏一本书，也对作者没有景慕之情，这一点令人反感。他们就像失礼的来客，受到丰盛的晚宴款待之后，对邀请他们的主人连一句感谢的话也没有就回家去了。至于自愿向挑剔和不知其口味，又怀有深厚感激之情的那部分公众作出富有教益谈话的贤人，就不多说了。

但是，如我所说，一定要与拉斐尔取得联系。我之后还会想到其他问题——尽管现在开始对事物敏感已经真的晚了，我已经费尽气力写完了这本书。因此，如果他不反对的话，我是否出版该书将听从朋友的建议，尤其是要听从你的建议。

再见吧，我最最亲爱的彼得·贾尔斯，并向你美丽的妻子问好。对我的友爱始终如一吧，我比以前更加爱你了。

你忠实的

托马斯·莫尔

贾尔斯致巴斯雷德的信

安特卫普

1516年11月1日

我亲爱的巴斯雷德：

有一天你的一个伟大朋友，托马斯·莫尔——我肯定你会同意他是我们当代的一大荣耀——将与世隔绝的乌托邦的描述寄给我。目前，还很少有人了解这个岛屿，但是每个人应该都想了解它，因为他像柏拉图的《共和国》，但更好——因为它是由这样一个有天才的作者来描绘的。他把所有的事情如此栩栩如生地展现在人们眼前，通过阅读他的语句，我仿佛比过去拉斐尔的声音在我耳边回响时获得的图像更加清晰——因为交谈时我与莫尔就在一起。然而，拉斐尔讲得特别好。他显然不是在兜售别人的故事，确实是在描绘他自己在一个地方的经历，他在这里居住了相当长一段时间。我个人认为，他要比尤利西斯对这个世界的了解更多，我怀疑过去至少八百年中是否有过像他这样的人。他使我们感到万斯普赛绝对啥也没有看到。

这人好像在阐述方面也有特别的天赋——尽管我认为，与描绘我们道听途说的事物相比，我们总是能够更好地描绘我们亲眼所见的事物。但是，当我思索莫尔对同一主题类似画面式的描述时，我有时感觉到我就实际生活在乌托邦。实际上，我诚实地认为，在他对这座岛屿的描述中，有比拉斐尔自己在其所呆五年间看到的东西更多。一个人能在每一页书上看到这么多精彩的事情，使我几乎不知道首先该羡慕的是什么——他的记忆异常准确，能够一句句地写出极长的演讲——他的聪明在于能够迅速掌握每个社会邪恶的现实和潜在的原因，尽管至今大半都并不为人所知——或者他那个人风格的力量和语言的流畅，他那处理各种话题的能力，并以正确的和强有力的拉丁语来表述——尤其是他还被如此多的公务和家务所分心。但是，所有这一切对像他这样的杰出学者都似乎不必感到惊奇。另外，你对他是那么熟悉，并且那么熟悉他那异乎常人的智力，如果不是从正面来理解的话。

他所写的内容我再也想不出可以增加什么了——除了我以乌托邦语言添加了四行诗，拉斐尔在莫尔走了之后碰巧将这诗与乌托邦字母表一起给我看过。我还补充了几个页边注释。随便说一下，莫尔有一点担心，因为他不知道那座岛屿的确切地址。事实上，拉斐尔的确提起过，但仅是十分简略地偶然提起，尽管他当时的意思是以后还会谈到这个问题——因为某些不为人知的原因，我们两个都没有听到。你知道，正当拉斐尔触及到这一主题时，一个仆人来找莫尔，并且在他耳边耳语了些什么。尽管这使得我极专注地听着，但就是那个时候他的一个同事大声咳嗽——我想他是在船上患了感冒——结果拉斐尔的话一点也没有听清楚。尽管如此，在不搞清楚这一点之前我是不会罢休的，直到能够告诉你这座岛屿的确切位置、纬度等。还有，我们的朋友拉斐尔是否仍然安然无恙？因为我已经听到几个有关他的故事。有人说他已在旅途中死在某地了。有人说他已经返回祖国。还有人说他又回到了乌托邦，部分原因是他对乌托邦很怀旧，还有一部分原因是他不能忍受欧洲人的行为。

你也许惊讶的是为什么在任何地理著作中都没有提到乌托邦，但是拉斐尔本人对这个问题已给予圆满解答。他说很可能古代人已知道这座岛屿但名字不同，或者他们从来也没有听说过——因为现在总是发现一些旧地理书上从没提到过的国家。尽管如此，我也不必争论去证实我的观点，我能够求助于像莫尔这样的权威。

我理解并尊重他犹豫是否出版该书时表现出来的谦虚。尽管我个人认为，它是那种绝不应该压制那么长时间的书，而是应该尽快发行，最好是附上你的一封推荐信——因为你对莫尔的天才有特别的认识，谁能比一个多年从事公共服务并以其智慧和诚实赢得高度赞扬的人更有资格将这些合理的思想介绍给公众呢？

向所有对学术成就的赞助人致以最良好的祝愿，你也是这个时代的荣耀。

你忠实的

彼得·贾尔斯

第一部

统治艺术的伟大专家、战无不胜的英王亨利八世与尊贵的卡斯提尔国王查理殿下二人之间，近期存有相当严重的意见分歧。英王派我出使法兰德斯去讨论并解决事端，和我同行的还有我的好朋友卡斯波特·特斯托尔，一个优秀的人，最近被任命为案卷法官，大家都甚为满意。他的学问和优秀品德是我无话可说的——不是因为我担心似乎有赞成他的偏见，而是因为他们太出色了，我难以给出恰如其分的描述，而且是太众所周知了，根本不需加以描述。我不想劳神于这些显而易见的事务。

按照卡斯提尔外交使节的事先安排，我们在布鲁日见面，这些使节都是些极为杰出的人。他们的名义领队是布鲁日的市长，一个严肃的人物，但是大多数思路和发言都是出自于加塞尔城的教会长乔治·德·塞姆塞克。此人是天生的好口才，又训练有素。他还是一位法律专家，不仅禀赋好，而且是具有丰富经验的谈判高手。经过一两次会议之后，我们在若干问题上仍然没能达成一致看法，因此他们就向我们告别几天，到布鲁塞尔去听取他们国王的意见。这时，我因自己的事去了趟安特卫普。

我在那里的时候，有几个经常的来访者，但是我最喜欢的一个就是年轻的安特卫普本地人，名字叫彼得·贾尔斯。他很受当地人的尊重，而且在那座城担任着重要的职位；他真是完全值得享有最崇高的地位，因为我说不出是哪一点对我印象最为深刻，是他的聪明才智还是他的优秀品德。当然，他是一个很优秀的人，也是一个很优秀的学者。他对每个人都一视同仁，对朋友更是真诚、坦率、关爱有加，他几乎就是唯一在各个方面称得起完美的朋友了。他异常的谦虚、完全的诚实而又极为单纯。他也是一个轻松愉快的交谈者，他那诙谐的谈吐不会伤害任何人的感情。我渴望回到英国去看望我的妻子和孩子，因为我离开家已经有四个多月了。他的愉快陪伴和愉快交谈在很大程度上减轻了我的思乡之情。

一天，我在圣母院做礼拜，这是一座华丽的教堂，挤满了人。我正想回宾馆，这时正巧看到了彼得·贾尔斯和一个上了年纪的陌生人在谈话，那人面孔黝黑，留着长长的胡子，肩上随意披着一件斗篷。从他的外貌和衣服我断定他是一个船员。就在这时，彼得看到了我。他立刻走过来打招呼，接着，我还没来得及回答，他就把我拉过去指着刚刚与之交谈的那个人，问道：“你看见对面那个人了吗？我正想带他来见你。”

我回答说：“如果他是你的朋友，我当然很高兴见他。”

彼得说：“当你听说了他是哪种人的话，你肯定很高兴见他——因为当今没有人像他一样能够告诉你那么多关于陌生国家和其居民的故事了。我知道这是你急切想听到的东西。”

我说：“我猜得不太错吧，我一看到他，就想他是一个水手。”

“这一次你完全错了，”他回答道，“我的意思是，他不是巴里纽拉斯那样的水手。他更像是尤利西斯，或者甚至像柏拉图。你知道，我们的朋友拉斐尔——因为那就是他的名字，拉斐尔·诺森索——是一个大学者。他懂不少的拉丁语和大量的希腊语。因为他主要对哲学感兴趣，他集中力量研究希腊语。他发现这门学科使用拉丁语写的没有重要的东西，除了辛尼加和西塞罗的一些东西。他想看看这个世界，因此他把管理葡萄牙家产的事交给了他的兄弟们——他是葡萄牙人——就加入了亚美利哥·韦斯普奇（Amerigo Vespucci）一行。你知道人人都在读的他那本《记四次航行》的书吗？拉斐尔是他后三次航行中形影不离的旅伴，只是最后一次他没有陪他回来。相反，他几乎是强迫亚美利哥让他成为留在那个要塞上的二十四个人之中的一员。因此，他就留在了那里，按照他的意愿醉心于旅行，这是他真正关心的事情，他不介意他最终死于何地，他有两句最喜欢的名言：‘死后没棺材，青天作遮盖’，以及‘条条大路通天堂’——要不是老天的保佑，他这种态度可能导致他极大的麻烦。尽管如此，在韦斯普奇走后，拉斐尔和其他五个留在要塞上的人作了许多探险。最后，一次机缘巧合之下，他到了锡兰。从那里他转到了卡利卡特。在当地他幸运地遇到了几条葡萄牙船，最后又出乎意料地回到了本国。”

“好，非常感谢你，”我说，“我当然喜欢与这样的人交谈，你给我这样一个机会真是太感谢你了。”

我接着走向拉斐尔与他握手。我们就像人们初次介绍时通常所做的那样说了几句客套话，然后一同来到我住所的花园，在那里我们坐在草苔丛生的凳子上，开始更加自由的交谈。

拉斐尔首先告诉我们他和其他留在要塞上的人所发生的故事，从韦斯普奇离开他们谈起。通过礼貌和友好表现，他们渐渐迎合了当地居民。很快彼此不仅保持了平安相处的关系，而且还产生了好感。他们尤其是与某一位国王相处得很好，他的名字和国籍我已经忘记了。他非常慷慨地为拉斐尔及他的五个探险同伴提供了旅行的食物和资金，还有旅行使用的船只和车辆。他还提供了一位最为可靠的导游与其他各个国王取得联系，并给他们写了介绍信。就这样，在旅行了好几天之后，他们来到了一些大城镇和人口密集的地区，这里有着高标准的政治组织。

显然，在赤道上，在大多数热带地区，你会看到永不停歇的炎热炙烤着广袤的荒原。一切看上去都是那么可怕与荒凉。这里没有耕作的痕迹，也没有牲畜生活，只有毒蛇猛兽，或者是一样危险的人类。但是，如果你再往前走一些，情况就会逐渐好转。气候变得不那么酷热，地面上长满了可爱的青草，人和动物也没有那样凶猛。最后，你就到了人们居住的城镇。他们不仅彼此之间，或者与近邻之间，甚至于同相当遥远的国家都一直有着水陆贸易。

拉斐尔说：“这给了我四处旅游的机会，因为无论何时我发现有船只起航，我就问能否让我和我的朋友搭乘，他们总是很高兴地让我们上船。我们最初见到的船都是平底的，帆都是由纸草或柳枝编成，也有些是皮革的。可是，后来我们所遇到的船有尖龙骨和帆布品蓬，一般与我们的船就一样了。那里的水手还没有很好的风浪知识，但是我通过解释指南针的用法赢得了他们特别的好感。他们之前从来没有听说过指南针，因此一直相当害怕大海，除了夏天，他们是很少冒险出海的。但是现在，他们非常信赖指南针，冬天航海也不在话下了——尽管这种新的安全感还纯粹是主观的。事实上，他们过于自信反倒将一项显然有用的发明变成灾难的根源。”

要重复一遍他告诉我们的每一个地方、每一件事情需要太长的时间。另外，那也不是本书的目的。我也许会在另一本书里讲述他的故事，强调故事中最有教育意义的部分，如他在不同的文明社会中所注意到的明智安排。这些是我向他热切提问的要点，而且他也乐于将此内容加以细说。我们没有问他是否见到过魔怪，因为魔怪已经不再是新闻了。也不乏一些可怕的捕食人类的动物，夺取人们的食物，或者吞噬这里的人群；但这样的事例在聪明的社会计划中是不容易找到的。

当然，在这个新的世界他看到了很多需要谴责的东西，但他也发现了几个规则，可能为欧洲社会的改革提供一些方法。我已经说过，这些将留待以后再说。我当前的计划只是复述一下他所讲述的有关乌托邦的法律和风俗。

我必须从记录交谈开始，这就回到了最早提到过的这个共和国。在敏锐地指出地球两边都犯过的错误后——当然是有大量的错误——拉斐尔继续讨论新旧两个世界立法的更敏感特征。他似乎对每一个国家的事情都了如指掌——即使他在某处只停留一个晚上都好像呆过了一辈子。彼得·贾尔斯对此印象特别深刻。

彼得：我亲爱的拉斐尔，我不明白你为什么不到某个国王那儿去呢。我肯定任何国王都会急切地想抓住机会用你。你的知识和经验，不仅可以提供娱乐，还可以提供指导性的先例和有益的建议。同时，你还可以寻求自己的利益，并对你所有的朋友和亲戚有帮助。

拉斐尔：我真的不担心他们。我感到我对他们已经尽了我的义务。很多人拥有自己的财产，直到年老多病也不肯放弃——即使放弃也很为勉强。但是我在很年轻也很健康的时候就将我的财产分给我的亲朋好友了。我想他们应该对此已经满足了。他们不能再进一步指望我为了他们的利益去做国王奴仆了。

彼得：但愿不会！我建议是协助而不是服侍国王。

拉斐尔：那也没多大区别。

彼得：那好吧，你爱怎么叫就随意吧，但我仍然认为这是你以个人及集体形式帮助他人的最好办法，并且这也能使你的生活更愉快。

拉斐尔：我又怎么能够违背我的直觉去那样做呢？目前，我活得自由自在，我觉得我这要比大多数朝廷官员能够说的更多。另外，国王已经有相当多的人巴结他，缺了一两个像我这样的人也不会有什么大不了的困难。

莫尔：我亲爱的拉斐尔，你显然对金钱和权势不感兴趣，如果你是地球最伟大的国王的话，我对你的尊重将无以复加。但肯定的是，即使你是以个人的一些不便为代价，应用你的天赋和勤奋为公众谋福利，也是与你那令人欣赏的哲学态度一致的。要成功地做到这一点，你就必须获得某个伟大国王的信任，我知道，你能够向他提供真正的好建议。因为每一个国王都是一种源泉，涌出的是能够不断造福或危害全国人民的甘露或雨水。你有这么丰富的理论知识和丰富的实践经验，任何一个方面都足以使你成为一个理想的议事会成员。

拉斐尔：我亲爱的莫尔，你真搞错了，首先对我而言，其次是对工作本身而言。我不像你所说的那么高明，即使我是这样，通过给我自己增加许多额外工作，我仍然不能为公众作出一点点有益的事情。首先，几乎所有的国王对于战争科学的兴趣都大于对和平年代的有用技术的兴趣，而我对于前者却一窍不通，并且也不想弄通。他们更关心的是采取什么方式去夺取新的王国，而不是治理好现有王国。另外，朝廷大臣都个个聪明而自负，无需从别人那里听取意见——尽管他们必然总是巴结国王宠臣们，同意那些他们所说的最为愚蠢的话。毕竟，人人都喜欢自己的话语能够吸引别人，这是人的本性。这就像雏乌鸦总是受到父母的喜爱，母猴子总是发现自己的宝宝极为漂亮一样。

因此，在那里你有一群人极其看不起别人的观点，或者是他们自以为是。假设在这一群人中你建议一项你看来在别处被采纳的政策，或者你因此而引用历史范例，将会发生什么呢？他们的表现就好似他们的职业声誉受到危害，如果他们不能够对你的建议提出一些反对意见的话，他们的余生就显得极为愚蠢。一旦其他都不能奏效时，他们就使出最后一招，说：“这对我们祖先来说是够好的了，我们是什么人竟质疑他们的明智？”他们坐回到自己的椅子上，怀有一种就此事我不再多说一句话的神态——就好似谁要是比他的祖先更明智的话，那将是巨大的灾难！然而，我们并不准备彻底改变他们最明智的决定。只是那些不够明智的决定我们才紧紧抓住不放。在很多地方我就碰到过这种傲慢、愚蠢和固执。有一次甚至在英国我也遇见过。

莫尔：真的吗？那么，你也去过我的国家了？

拉斐尔：当然去过了。我在那里待了几个月，就是在那场可怕的大战之后不久，那场战争是以西方国家的一场革命开始的，以对反叛者可怕的大屠杀为结局的。在我逗留期间，我得到了最受人尊敬的坎特伯雷大主教约翰·莫顿的关心，他也是英国当时的大法官。我必须给你讲述一下他的事，彼得——因为我敢说没有他不知道的事情。他是一位才智非凡、德高望重、非常令人尊重的人。他中等身材，尽管他年事已高，但一点也不弯腰驼背，他那张面孔总是和蔼可亲，任何人也不会感到害怕。尽管他总是严肃而高贵，但他却很容易相处。不可否认，他对那些求他找工作的人会粗鲁些，但并没有伤害的意味。他这样做主要是来考验一下他们的智力和心理素质，因为他发现这些素质很相似，只要他们谨慎使用，这些素质也最为适于公职。他言辞精炼，讲话注意效率，而且精通法律知识。他有十分杰出的理解力和记忆力，他这两种天赋经过训练和实践得以进一步发展。

显然，国王很信任他的判断，我在这里访问时似乎整个国家都要依靠他。这几乎一点也不令人感到意外，因为他经历了从大学到法院直接转化，当他刚不算是一个儿童的时候，就参与了公共事务，要处理一系列的危机，这一艰难的历程造就了他的远见卓识。这样所学的东西是不容易忘记的。

有一次我碰巧与大主教一起进餐，当时一个英国律师也在场。我忘了是怎样谈起这个话题，但他以极大的热情谈到了对盗窃者所采取的严厉措施。

“我们随处将他们执行死刑，”他说道，“我见到过一个绞刑台就有二十人之多。这就是我所发现的奇怪事。你想很少有人漏网，为什么还有那么多盗窃犯呢？”

“这有什么奇怪呢？”我问道——因为我在大主教面前从来都是毫无忌讳地说话。“这种处理盗窃犯的方法既不公正也不是社会所期望的。作为一种处罚，它过于严厉了，但是作为一种威慑，也是无效的。小的盗窃罪不足以处以死刑，而如果只有盗窃才是他们获得食物的唯一办法的话，世界上死刑也不能制止人们盗窃。在这方面，你们英国人和其他很多国家的人一样，使我想到不称职的教书匠，他们宁可灌输学生而不去教育他们。一个好得多的办法是为每个人提供谋生之道，而不是对之施以可怕的刑法，这样任何人就不至于冒着始而盗窃继而被处死的危险。”

“对此我们已经有了足够的规定，”律师回答说，“有很多营生他们可以做。田地里也总是有活需要干。如果他们想老实谋生的话，也不困难，但是他们还是有意选择走犯罪的道路。”

“你不能轻易摆脱这种情况，”我说，“我们暂且不论那些残疾的士兵，为了国王和国家在对内或者对外战争中致残——或许是与康瓦尔叛军作战，或者是不久前与法国作战。当他回到家园，却发现由于身体致残已不能从事先前的行当，由于年龄太大又学不了其他行当。依我来说，我们暂且不考虑这些人，因为战争只是断断续续的现象。我们就来说每天都在发生的事情。

“首先，大批贵族像雄蜂一样靠别人的劳动养活自己，换句话说，靠在自己田庄上做活的佃农养活自己，通过不断提高租金压榨他们的血汗。因为这就是他们唯一的赚钱的方法——否则的话他们总是过度铺张浪费，很快破产。而且还带有一大批游手好闲的随从，他们从未学习过任何谋生的手段。他们的主人一旦亡故，或者他们自己一旦生病，就会立刻被赶出去——因为那些贵族宁愿养活那些闲客，也不愿养活病号。贵族的继承人也往往无力像先人那样维持偌大的门户。这些人如果不借用暴力，就只好挨饿。他们还有别的办法吗？当然，他们可以四处流浪直到衣衫褴褛、身体虚弱不堪。然而，在这种情况下，没有任何绅士会屈尊雇用他，农民也不会冒险去雇用他——因为他不会为了些微薄的报酬和温饱而老老实实地拿起锄头汗流浃背地帮一个穷人干活，他们在奢侈中长大，并习惯于穿着军装大摇大摆，看不起任何其他的邻居。”

“但是，我们要加以鼓励的就是这种人，”律师反驳说，“在战争年代，他是军队的支柱，因为他比普通的商人或者农民都更有精神和自尊。”

“你或许也会说，”我说，“为了战争的目的你必须鼓励盗窃。好吧，你们肯定少不了盗窃犯，只要你那样看待那些人。当然，你的确是对的——盗窃犯确实能成为能干的兵，而兵也能成为有事业心的盗窃犯。这两种职业有很多相通的地方。然而，这种毛病在你们国家尽管很猖獗，但它并不仅限于英国。它实际上流传于整个世界。比如法国，就患有一种更加严重的灾难。即使在和平时期，整个法国到处都挤满了雇佣兵——如果你这样称呼的话——这与英国养一批懒散的随从的原因很是一样。你知道，专家决定，为了公共安全必须拥有一支强有力的常备军，包括的主要是老兵——因为他们不太信任新兵，他们精心地发动战争以锻炼这些新兵，使他们盲目杀人就像是塞拉斯特所说的不能放着手不用，“就是要不断用手。”

“因此，法国通过伤心的经历才认识到养着这批野蛮畜牲是多么危险，但是，罗马、迦太基、叙利亚和许多其他国家历史上也有许多类似的教训。常备军一次一次抓住机会推翻雇佣他们的政府，毁灭了他们的土地和城市。而且这支常备军也是相当不必要的。事实已经很显然，经过精心训练的法国士兵也不能经常夸口能够战胜新招来的士兵——这点我不想多谈，以免好像在奉承你们。

“另外，一般对你所提到的那种类型的人，无论是城里的商人，还是农村里的无知农民，他们都不会害怕那些懒散的随从——除了那些身体不够健壮和勇猛者，或者那些家境贫困而意志消沉者。事实上，尽管这些随从开始时体格强健——因为绅士所要腐蚀的正是他手下的这些人——他们很快就因为无所事事、缺乏男子汉的气概、自吹自擂而趋于衰弱。因此，他们失去男子汉的气魄也不是太大的事，如果他们学会从事有用的生意和像男子汉一样工作。无论如何，我都不明白，养一大批这样扰乱和平的人以准备战争，是可能出于公共的利益？如果你不想战争的话就不必有战争，而和平是无比的重要。

“但这还不是唯一迫使人盗窃的事。还有其他因素在起作用，这就是你们这个国家的特色情况了，我认为。

“那是什么呢？”大主教问道。

“羊，”我告诉他，“这种驯服的动物，一向要求很少的食物，现在明显变得极为贪婪，变成了吃人的动物。田地、房屋、城镇，一切的一切都被他们吃掉了。更明确地说，在王国的那些出产最精致最贵重羊毛的地方，贵族和绅士们，就不用说几个圣人之类的主教了，他们对祖传地产上的收入感到不够满意了。他们不再满足于过闲适安逸的生活，这对生活一点益处也没有——他们还积极主动地要危害社会，通过将所有的田地圈起来作为牧场，不留下可以耕种的土地。他们甚至拆除房屋、毁掉城镇——当然，只留下教堂作为羊栏。尽管他们浪费于丛林和运动场地的土地还不多，这些人还毁掉了人们居住的地方，并把每块地变为荒野。

“因此，会发生什么事呢？每一个贪婪的个体都在像恶魔一样在危害他的国家，一块一块的占有土地，用一条栏栅把数千英亩地圈上。结果就是——成百上千农民被驱逐。他们有的是被欺骗或者是被迫放弃自己的财产，或者是受尽屈辱直到最后被迫卖掉自己的财产。无论是哪一种方式，这些不幸的人只好离开家园——男人、女人、丈夫、妻子、寡妇、孤儿、母亲和小孩，还有他们的雇工——人数多但不是财富的象征，只是这样一个事实，就是你没有足够的劳动力就无法种田。他们离开了他们太熟悉的家园，他们找不到任何可以安身的地方。他们的全部家当，即使能够等到适合的买主，也值钱不多。但是他们等不起，因此他们的家当卖钱很少。他们在流浪中花完这点钱之后，他们只好去盗窃而正适于被绞死吗？当然，他们总是可以成为流浪汉或者沿街乞讨，即使是这样，他们也会被作为无所事事的流浪汉抓进监狱——尽管他们极其想找到工作，但没有人愿意雇佣他们。因为他们过去就是干农活的，但没有了可以种的地，也就没有农活可干。毕竟，需要多人劳动才能产生粮食的地，用于牧羊，只需要一个牧人就够了。

“同理，粮食的生产在很多地区更贵了，而羊毛的价格也急剧高涨，穷织工买不起羊毛，这就意味着许多人就会失业。这部分地是因为一场瘟疫传染病的降临，这场疾病就在耕地改为牧场之后不久，大量羊群死亡。就好像是对土地所有者因贪婪作出的判决一样——只是他们应该患上这种病，而不是由羊来代替。

“尽管有很多羊，有了羊的市场，但羊的价格却没有降低，因为如果严格来讲不是垄断，也就是说并不是只有卖家——只有一个卖家的话就是垄断了。我的意思是说它几乎全部被几个富人所控制，这些富人不想卖就不必要卖，而他们得不到要求的价格就不想卖。这也是其他各类牲畜同样高价的原因，尤其是鉴于因为农田被毁、农业大萧条而造成的无人从事饲养牲畜。因为我所谈论的富人绝不会自己去养羊或养牛，他们只是从别人那里廉价买了瘦弱的牛羊，在他们自己的牧场把它们喂肥了，再高利润卖出。我认为这就是为什么这种情况的全部影响人们还没有感觉到。直到现在，他们仅在出售牲畜的地方高抬价格，但是，他们如果在其他地方不断采购牲畜，超过该地饲养的速度，来源市场将会逐渐减少，直到最后各处都出现牲畜短缺。

“这样，几个贪婪的人把英国最大的自然优势之一变成了一个国家的灾难。因为食物的高价位使得雇主大量减少雇佣人数——这就不可避免地意味着把那些人变为乞丐或盗贼。盗窃对有精神的人就更容易了。

“更为糟糕的是，这一令人可怜的贫穷又多与奢侈生活不协调地联系在一起。仆人、商人、甚至农场的劳动者，实际上社会的各个阶层都在讲究穿着、纵情吃喝。想想有多少妓院，包括那些以酒店、餐馆为名的场所。想想人们玩得那些不正当的游戏——骰子、纸牌、十五子棋戏、网球、滚木球、掷圈环——这都是让人很快把钱花光的办法，并把他径直送上盗窃之路。

“除掉这些害人的实践吧。制定法律来规定人人有责将毁坏的农田或乡镇恢复，或转交给那些愿意恢复的人。禁止富人囤积居奇和实际垄断市场。减少无所事事的人。振兴农业和羊毛工业，以便为那一批无业大军充分提供诚实而有用的工作——我说的无业大军不仅是指那些现有的盗贼，而且还有流浪汉和无所事事的帮闲，他们最终也将沦为盗窃犯。你不把这些事情搞好，你就无权夸口如何公正惩罚盗窃犯，因为正义比现实的需求和社会的需求更为珍贵。你们让这些人在最为糟糕的方式下生活，并且他们从很小的时候起就逐步走向堕落。最后，他们长大成人，走向犯罪，这是他们注定要走的犯罪道路，早从他们儿童时代，你就开始惩罚他们。换句话说，你造就了盗窃犯，却继而因他们盗窃而惩罚他们。”

我还没讲完，那个律师就准备给予答复。很显然，他是采用重复而不是答复的那种辩论方法的人——就好像他有一个好的记忆力就万事大吉了。

“那是一个很好的努力，”他说道，“尤其是对于一个获得间接信息的外国人，所以不够准确——正如我还要简要说明一样。我将你所说的依次举出，然后我指明你在何处因对当地情况无知所犯的错误。最后，我要批驳你的所有观点。按照这个顺序，我认为你有四个方面——”

“等一下，”大主教打断说，“这样介绍之后，你的答复似乎不会三言两语就能讲完。因此，现在就不要讲了——下次见面再讲好了。如果你们两个明天有空的话，为什么不明天讲呢？同时，我亲爱的拉斐尔，我很想听听你为何反对盗窃犯适用死刑呢？而且你认为处以什么样的刑罚才对社会更有好处呢？我深信，即使是你也感觉到盗窃应该禁止。尽管规定了死刑，但盗窃依然盛行，如果他们不再担心被处死，究竟什么力量可以制止犯罪、什么样的威慑才能见效？当然，任何减刑都将被解释为一种对犯罪的积极的诱导。”

“大人，”我说，“一个人因为他拿走了一点钱就得丧失生命，这在我看来是太不公道了。我认为，再多的财产也比不上人的生命宝贵。如果说这种惩罚不是由于金钱被盗，而是由于违反法律、侵犯正义，这一绝对正义的概念不就是绝对的不正义吗？人民真的不能认可一种体制如此独断，一点轻微的犯法就被处死，也反对斯多葛学派的律条，所有的犯罪都等量齐观——杀人和盗窃在法律上没有任何区别，尽管在公正方面这两件事情如此完全不同。

“上帝命令‘你不准杀人’——我们能把偷盗一小笔钱的盗窃者处死吗？如果这种戒律仅适用于非法杀害，有什么可以禁止人们类似地同意将强奸、私通和伪誓合法化呢？鉴于上帝甚至禁止我们杀害自身，我们真的能够相信在没有上帝的权威，纯粹是人类的规定可以互相残杀，就使杀人者不受第六戒律的制约吗？那不就更像是说这一特别的戒律不比人定的法律更有效吗？——在这种情况下，这一原则可以无限延伸，直到生活的一切领域，人类有权决定应在多大程度上执行上帝的戒律。

“根据摩西的法律（从良心上看够严厉的了，它是为那时的奴隶和反叛者设定的），盗窃者不被绞死，而仅仅是罚款。我们简直无法想象，慈悲为怀的新法律训示我们如同上帝以父亲般的慈悲训示他的儿女，竟然比旧法律更容许我们彼此残忍相待。

“所以，这就是我提反对意见的道德依据。从现实的观点来看，显然，以同样的方式惩罚盗贼和杀人犯不仅是荒唐的，而且对公众是极其危险的。如果盗贼知道杀人犯获罪并不比盗窃获罪更重的话，他自然就会杀害那个他本来只是想抢劫的人。这样如果他被逮住的话，结果也不会更糟，并且由于杀人灭口更能够掩盖罪行从而有机会逃脱。这样，我们虽然使用酷刑威慑盗窃犯，而事实上却在怂恿他们杀害无辜。

“现在回到那个普通的问题上来——什么样的惩罚更好些？若你问的是什么惩罚更糟糕的话，我会觉得更难回答。那么，对于罗马管理专家长久以来一直颇为满意的制度，我们还要怀疑其价值吗？正如我们所知，他们让那些判刑的重犯带上镣铐，终身在矿山或采石场服刑。

“尽管如此，我所了解的最好的一种安排是我在波斯旅行时见到的，就是通常被称之为陶斯陶瑞亚的一个地区。陶斯陶瑞亚人组成一个庞大又组织良好的社区，除了要给波斯国王交税以外，完全自治。因为他们离海很远，实际上被群山环绕着，他们自给自足，土地肥沃，与外部很少联系。他们绝对不想扩大疆域，他们有群山作为屏障，并向波斯伟大的国王缴纳保护费，因此它社会安全，不受外界侵略。这就意味着他们免除了兵役，因此他们的生活不算奢侈但安逸，不算真的出名或者荣耀但幸福——因为除了他们的近邻之外，我想很少有人曾经听说过他们。

“在陶斯陶瑞亚，一个人犯了盗窃罪必须将所盗窃财物归还失主，不像其他许多国家，要交给国王——根据陶斯陶瑞亚的法律，国王和盗窃犯都没有权利获得赃物。如果盗窃的物品已经不再为盗贼所有，就要用他的个人财产来抵扣赃物的价值，剩余的财产交给他的妻子儿女。他本人判处劳役。除非他使用暴力抢劫，否则不会被监禁或戴上脚镣，而是可以自由行走并被雇佣为公众服劳役。如果他放弃劳动、行动迟缓，他们也不会给他戴上锁链束缚手脚——他们通过鞭挞以使其加快速度。如果他工作努力的话，就根本不会受到很差的待遇。他要每天晚上回答点名，夜里要关起来——但是，除了要干很长时间的活之外，生活还是相当舒服。

“比如说，食物很好，由公家开支，因为罪犯是替公家干活。凑集这笔资金的办法各地都不一样。在一些地区，资金来自自愿捐赠。这种办法虽不稳定，但实际上比其他任何办法都筹集的多，因为当地人非常慈善。有的地方，拨出部分公共的税收或按人头征收一项特殊赋税来支付该项费用。也有的地方，罪犯不是为公众服劳役，而是受雇于私有企业。任何需要他们干活的人都可以去市场上雇佣他们，按日发给固定工资，但工资要比雇佣自由劳动力低得多。如果他们劳动不够努力，雇主可以鞭打。这一体制保证了他们绝不会失业，他们靠工作养活自己，同时犯人还每天为国库增加收入。

“他们都穿着一种特殊颜色的服装，别人是不穿的。他们也不剃光头，但把两耳上面的头发剪短，且削去一个耳垂。允许他们的朋友给他们食物和饮料，以及符合规定颜色的衣服。但对送钱或收钱的人来说都是死罪。自由人无论以什么理由接受任何奴隶（定罪犯人通常被如此称呼）的钱，或者奴隶接触武器，都同样会有被处死的危险。

“每个奴隶都挂一个标牌以标明他属于哪个区域，取下标牌，不在自己的区域，或与其他区域的奴隶交谈，都构成死罪。对于逃跑来说，密谋逃亡和实际逃亡是同样的冒险。对任何逃亡计划的同谋者，若是奴隶则被处死，若是自由民则罚令为奴隶。相反，揭发逃亡计划的自由人将获得现金奖励，若揭发者是奴隶，则恢复自由。在任何一种情况下，对以上两种人都免于追究其同谋的罪行，其原则是：作恶到头的人决不能比及早回头的人更安全。

“这就是这一体制的运行方式，显然它是最为便利也最为人道的。它严厉惩罚犯罪，但却挽救罪犯的性命，以这种方式对待他们，使他们变成好公民，用自己的后半生弥补过去犯下的罪过。

“事实上，他们很少有重新犯罪的危险。对于长途旅行者来说，他们通常被认为是最为安全的向导，旅行者可以雇佣他们打接力，走过一个地区就雇佣该区域的奴隶。你知道，奴隶没有劫路的工具。他们不允许携带武器。如发现他们身上带钱，就证明他们有罪。他们如果一旦被捕，自然就会受到惩罚。他们要想逍遥法外是一点希望都没有——因为他们的衣服和通常人的衣服绝无相同之处，除非赤身上路，怎么能够逃走而不被发现呢？——即使赤身上路，你的耳朵也会背叛你，让人认出来。

“当然，也有一种理论上的风险，就是他们可能开始密谋推翻政府。但是任何一个地区的奴隶怎么样能够组织一个大规模的举动而无需先对其他许多地区的奴隶进行试探或煽动呢？这根本是不可能的。他们连见面都不允许，不能交谈、不能打招呼，更别说共同密谋了。另外，你能否设想一下奴隶会高兴地将一个密谋泄露给他同一个区域的其他奴隶，但隐瞒密谋者是危险的，而告发者会得到很大好处？另一方面，每个奴隶都希望恢复自由，只有按照要求去做，并能让当局有理由信任他将来能走向正路——因为每年都有一批这样的人由于服从管教而被豁免。”

我接着说道，我不明白为何英国不采用这一制度。这要比被律师高度赞扬的所谓司法措施产生更好的效果。

听到这话，我们那位有学问的朋友——我指的是那位律师——摇了摇头。

他轻蔑地一笑说道，“这套制度绝不可能在英国采用，它会将整个国家搞得极为危险。”

那是他所说的所有的话——实际上每个其他人都同意他的观点。

然后，大主教发表了自己的观点。

他说，“不给予实验，就难以预测这一体制是否奏效。但是假设国王如果要在实验阶段推迟执行死刑——先废除所有庇护权。如果结果好的话，我们再长期执行就是正当的。如果结果不好的话，原来的判刑仍将执行，这比起现在就执行，也一样有利于社会，而且一样公正。同时，也没有任何危害。事实上，我认为以同样的方式对待游民也根本不是一个坏办法。我们总是制定法律来制裁他们，但截止到目前，一点效果也没有。”

大主教的这一番话，使大家赞叹不已，但在从我口里提出时，没有人当作一回事。他们尤其喜欢涉及游民的部分，因为那是大主教自己的意见。

也许，我应该省略谈话的后半部分，因为那是很不严肃的。不过我还是得讲，它本身无害，而且与我们讨论的问题有关。当时在场的有一位清客，他想给人只是扮演一下滑稽动作，但扮演的太滑稽了。他让人笑的努力确实无效，人们倾向于笑他本人而不是笑他的笑话。但有时他的话讲得还不错，这就证明了一条谚语的真实性：如果你最初不成功，就一遍遍不停地尝试。有一个人通过评论大主教和我之间解决盗窃犯和游民的问题作出暗示，所以只剩下来确定适当的国家行动方案，以应对那些年龄太大或者是因疾病而无法谋生的穷人。

“这就交给我吧，”这位清客说道，“我会确切告诉你该做什么。事实上，我最巴不得将这类人从我面前打发走。他们总是唱着那种凄惨呼号式的乐曲来缠着我讨钱，但我从来都是分文不给的，往往不外乎两种情况——或者是我不愿意给钱，或者是我手头空空，无钱可给。因此，他们现在学会不再浪费精力了。当他们看见我经过时，就让我过去，一言不发。他们知道我或许是一位牧师，再也不想从我这里得到什么帮助了。现在，我提出一条法令，把全部乞丐分配到各个本笃会修道院，男的去做庶务修士——那是修道士的专业术语，女的做修女。”

大主教微笑着，像玩笑似的表示同意。其他人也都这样，忍着不笑。只有一个修道士例外，他明显是研究神学的。他平常是那种极其严肃的人，但他对这些挖苦牧师与修道士的话颇感兴趣，因此他也想取笑一番。

“啊，你不可能那么容易使乞丐绝迹，”他说道，“你对我们这些托钵僧修道士怎么办？”

“可是，这已经给予关照了呀，”那位清客回答道，“大主教那了不起的规定把流浪者管禁起来，让他们工作，这你不记得了吗？”

大家都看了大主教一眼，见他接受这些话，并且也没有表示不同意，因此评论受到鼓掌欢迎——只有修道士例外。那是不足为奇的，他在这番讽刺的冲击下，大发雷霆、破口大骂。他骂对方时把能想到的脏话都用上了，包括恶魔的儿子，还从《圣经》中引用了一些可怕的咒语。

这时，小丑开始认真地嘲笑起来，他显然感到得意自如。

“我亲爱的修道士，”他说，“你不必如此生气。你知道《圣经》所说，‘你们常存忍耐就能拥有灵魂’。”

“你这该死的东西，我倒不是生气，”修道士嚷道——那就是他的原话，“或者如果我生气了，但我也是没有错的。因为圣歌中这样唱道，‘你生气吧，但不要犯罪。’”

大主教很温和地告诫修道士不应该发脾气。

“我发脾气，大人，”他说，“我发脾气没有错。我说话出于一颗善良的热切之心，圣洁的人是有热切之心的。因此，圣书说，‘你殿堂的热情将我吞噬。’或者是我们在教堂中所唱的圣歌：

他们取笑伟大的以利沙，

当他上伯特利去时

秃头者的热心使他们受到惩罚。

我想那个开玩笑的家伙也许同样有所感受。”

“你的热情肯定值得信赖，”大主教说道，“但是我觉得，你若是不和一个傻瓜争论使你自己显得也犯傻的话，你的行为未必使你显得更有道行，但肯定显得更加聪明。”

“不，大人，”修道士反驳说，“我不会显得更加聪明，因为有谁能够比所罗门聪明呢？所罗门说过：‘按照傻瓜的傻话回答傻瓜’——我现在就是这样做的。我向他指出他如不小心就会掉进去的无底深坑。在以利沙那种情况下，四十二个取笑者针对一个秃头者，他的热心足以惩罚他们。这儿一个取笑者针对的是基督教世界的所有修道士，而秃头的人数所占比例很高，这个人的感觉就是那么的糟糕呀！另外，我们还有教皇的谕旨，它禁止任何人取笑我们，对取笑者可以开除教籍。”

看到这件事将没完没了，大主教示意清客走开，机智地转到另一个话题。几分钟之后，他站起身把我们打发走，因为他得去会见一些请他帮助的人们。

亲爱的莫尔，恐怕我的啰唆故事也真使你听得够累的了。要不是你很想听——并且你听得那么聚精会神，我觉得你不愿我略去谈话中的任何一个部分——我真不好意思讲这么长时间。尽管如此，谈话似乎值得重复，哪怕只是讲个大概，以便你能了解这些人的思维方式。你知道，他们对我所说的一切都很轻蔑，而看到大主教对这些话也不反对——他们接着就都表示赞同。他们如此奉承大主教，甚至于准备鼓掌，对他的马屁精的建议也几乎当真，仅仅是因为大主教当作万象而不加反对。由此你可以猜测人们对我和宫廷对我的建议会多么的轻视。

莫尔：“我亲爱的拉斐尔，我喜欢这个故事中的每一个词。你所说的每一件事都有这么多的智慧和学问。另外，它使我不仅回到了英国，而且有一种回到我童年的感觉——它使我愉快地想起大主教，我就是在他家长大的。我一开始就喜欢你，我亲爱的拉斐尔，但是你真难相信我是多么因此更加对你有好感了。然而，我仍然禁不住认为，你如果能够克服对宫廷生活的厌恶，你的建议将对公众极为有利。作为一个善良的人，这是你的责任。你爱读的作家柏拉图这样说过——只要哲学家做国王或是国王从事哲学研究，国家才有康乐。假如哲学家甚至不屑于向国王献计进言，康乐将是一件多么无限遥远的事情呀！”

拉斐尔：“噢，哲学家还没有那么坏。他们只是不愿意提出建议——事实上，许多哲学家在他们出版的著作中已经这样做了——只要是统治者能够听从他们的建议。这无疑是与柏拉图的意思是一样的。他意识到国王受童年时错误思想的影响太深不会接受任何哲学家的建议，除非他们自己成为哲学家。柏拉图从自己与代俄尼喜阿交往的经验中，学到了以上真理。假如我告诉国王让他制定明智的法律，彻底清除他心灵中的毒素，难道你料想不到我不是马上被撵走就是受到奚落吗？

例如，假如我在法国，参加内阁会议。国王亲自主持会议，所有谋臣围坐在桌旁，都在殷勤地讨论解决如下问题的方式和方法：怎样能够占住米兰不放，夺回失去的那不勒斯，然后击败威尼斯，征服意大利；更进而通知法兰德斯、布拉邦特，最终控制整个勃艮底——更不必说那些他早就梦想入侵的其他国家了。

一个谋臣建议和威尼斯达成协定，只要法王认为便利，协定便持续下去。他有事要与他们商议，并让他们享受一部分掠夺物，等到事情如愿以偿，不妨索回原物。另一位谋臣提出招募德意志雇佣兵，还有谋臣想贿赂瑞士人。更有谋臣要国王用黄金作为可以接受的礼物，消解神圣罗马帝国的怒气。又有谋臣献计须与阿拉贡国王言归于好。作为和平的保证，应把属于别人的纳瓦尔国割让给他。同时，也还有谋臣建议让卡斯提尔国王上钩，使他指望与法国联姻，并用固定的年金收买他宫廷上某些贵族，使之支持法国。

现在有一个最为苦恼的问题——怎么样对付英国？显然，第一步必须安排和平谈判，对于一个脆弱的联盟，充其量只能通过严肃的契约去加强，称他们为朋友，但必须把他们看作潜在的敌人。所以，苏格兰人必须有所准备，英格兰人一有动静，就让苏格兰人抓住机会对他们下手。也可能要暗中支持某个流亡在外的贵族——既有条约，就不好公开支持——赞助他对于英国王位的要求，借此限制一个不堪信任的国王。

在这一问题上，大家都很卖力，许多杰出的人才都在提出属于战争性质的建议，而我这个无足轻重的拉斐尔站起来提出完全不同的方针。我建议国王忘了意大利、待在本国。我告诉他法国已经够大的了，一个人难以治理好，因此，真的不必要为拓宽疆土担忧了。

然后，我就给他讲述乌托邦岛东南方闹兰迪亚国家的历史故事。依据一些古老的婚姻关系，闹兰迪亚国王认为自己是另一个王国的合法继承人，因此，他的人马发动了战争以夺取该王国。最后他们赢得了胜利，结果却发现要保住这个王国带来的麻烦与夺去它所花的气力一样大，经常有内部叛乱和外部入侵的骚扰，他们不得不经常作战加以保护或加以制裁，因而绝没有机会退伍，同时他们也就堕落了。他们的金钱流出国外，他们为了别人的区区野心而献出生命。国内的情况也不比战争时更安全，因为受到杀人和盗窃风气的鼓励，道德风尚败坏。法律受到蔑视，因为国王要关注两个王国，因此任何一个王国都不能治理得宜。

鉴于如果他们对此采取一些措施的话，这种令人失望的状况就将肯定持续下去。闹兰迪亚人最终决定采取一个行动，就是非常礼貌地请求国王看他想保留哪一个王国。

“你不能两个都保留，”他们解释道，“因为半个国王难以统治那么多人。因为即使我们是许多强人，照顾我们还是一个全身心的工作。

因此，这位模范的国王被迫将这个新的王国让给了一位朋友——自己去管理原来的王国——他的朋友后来不久就被赶走了。

我也提醒法国国王，即使他的确开始了这些战争，并在所有这些不同国家制造混乱，他仍然会发现他已经毁掉了自己，还毁掉了他的人民，最后却一场空。所以，我建议他集中精力将祖传的王国治理好，尽力使之美丽而繁荣，爱惜臣民并为臣民所爱，同他们一同生活并妥善对他们加以管理，放弃所有拓宽疆域的念头，因为他所统辖的土地对他已经绰绰有余了。

那么，你告诉我，亲爱的莫尔，你认为他将怎样回应我的建议？

莫尔：不是太好，我必须承认。

拉斐尔：现在我们再设想另一种情况。假设国王的某些财政谋士筹划如何聚敛财富。某个人建议国王在支付时将货币升值，当他收进时，可将其贬值。这样就可以产生如下效果，即刻增加他的收入减少他的支出。另一个人建议国王应该虚张声势作战，为他额外税收提供借口。然后，在他自己认为合适的时候庄严地讲和，作出姿态好像是为了老百姓的利益，因为慈悲的统治者不忍心生灵涂炭。第三个人提醒他一些过时的法典，因长期不用而荒废的法典——每个人都触犯它，因为没有人意识到它的存在——督促国王对不遵守法典的人课以罚金。这是最大的生财之道，且最为名正言顺，又以执法为幌子。第四个人建议他对一些犯罪通过立法规定严厉罚款，尤其是处罚反社会类型的犯罪。这样，他可以从出卖这些法律免责权来收取金钱。这就可以保证受到公众的欢迎，又有双重进项：既向贪图横财而陷入法网的人勒索罚金，又从另一些人收取专门的管理金。当然，这些价格是依据国王的道德品质的比例而变化。他的原则越高，他就越不愿意让任何人侵害公共利益——因此这种特别管理费也就越高。

第五个人建议国王将法官约束起来，这样他们总是作出有利于国王的判决。他应该召见法官到王宫，向他们当面咨询他的法律地位。他可能明显很是不当，但其中一个法官肯定能够发现一个击败正义的漏洞。无论是他这样做的动机是什么——或是存心不同于别人，或是不喜欢明显的东西，或是仅仅为邀宠——结果都一样。很快，每个法官都会有自己的不同意见，会出现争议，最简单的事实要受到质疑。这就正好给国王一个很好的机会来根据自己的利益解释法律。每个人都会同意，或者是害怕，或者是出于礼貌。最后，这一解释大胆地作为法庭的判决。毕竟，有很多种方法来证明国王作出的判决是合理的。或者颠倒其意思，或者是凭借无可争议的国王特权，对有责任心的法官来说，国王特权高出任何法律。

大家都赞成格拉苏的名言，就是如果你要维持一个部队，你的钱总是不够的。大家一般也都同意一个国王即使很想做错事也不能做，因为一切都归国王所有，包括这个国家的每一个人，并且私人财产是不存在的，除非国王足以善良而不去巧取豪夺。他应该总是减少这种临时私有财产的最低限度，因为他的安全依赖于禁止他的国民过于富有或过于自由。因为国民一旦拥有过多的财富和自由，就不愿意忍受不公正和压迫。但贫困可以使他们迟钝而顺服，遏制他们高贵的反抗精神。

这时，我起身争辩，说做这些事情不是明智之举，且有损于国王的荣誉，因为他的威望和安全系于国民的富裕，而不是系于自己的富裕。

我问他：“你为什么不认为他们选出你做国王首先是为了他们自己的利益，而不是你的利益呢？他们的意图是让你勤于朝政，使他们的生活更加安逸，保护他们免受不公待遇。因此，国王的工作就是关心国民而不是你个人的幸福——正如牧羊人的工作，严格来说，他的工作就是喂饱羊，而不是喂饱他自己。至于国民穷就能维持安全的理论，是与事实完全矛盾的。乞丐是社会上争吵最凶的一部分人。还有比不满于生活现状的人更可能造反的吗？还有比一无所有的人更为冲动去为了个人的利益将一切都搞乱的吗？

“没有，如果一个国王被他的国民如此憎恶、蔑视的话，他就不能使他们遵守秩序，除非通过暴力、敲诈、查抄把他们都沦为乞丐，那他还不如辞去王位。这种保持王位权势的手段可能使国王徒有虚名，而毁掉了国王尊严。国王统治的不是繁荣幸福的人民，而是一群乞丐，这样的国王就毫无尊严可言了。这点正是令人敬仰的斐布里希的意见，他宁愿治理富有的国民，而不愿自己富有。诚然，一个人享受奢侈的生活而其他所有的人都在呻吟哀嚎，这个人就几乎不能被称之为国王，而更像一个管理监狱的人。

“简而言之，一个庸医不可能给人治好病而不给这个人带来另一种病。一个国王不降低生活水平就不能为制止犯罪的话，应该承认他并不知道怎么样治理自由民。他应该从戒除自己的弊病——自傲和懒惰开始，因为这两个弊病使得他受到人们的憎恶和蔑视。他必须依靠自己为生而无损于他人。他应该量入为出。他应该制止犯罪，正确引导人们，而不是任之发展而事后惩罚。他不应该实施那些长期不用的法律——尤其是如果没有，而人们却生活得很好者。并且，他绝不发明一种罪行，以此为借口征收罚款——任何私人都不允许这样不诚实地做事。”

我然后继续给他讲述一个距乌托邦不远的国家——哈佩兰德的制度。他们的国王在登基那一天举行庄严的献祭，宣誓他所持有的黄金或者白银的价值绝不超过一千英镑。显然，这一制度是从一位非常贤明的国王开始的，这位国王更加关心的是国家的福利，而不是他自己的福利。他认为这将阻止皇室的财富积累到导致国家贫困的程度，之所以选择这样一个数字，是因为他计算过这些资金将足以制止革命或抵抗侵略，但不足以鼓励一个国王拥有对外征服的野心。这是他的主要想法，但不是仅就这一个想法。他还希望这一安排能够保障总是足够的流通资金供普通的交易所用，并且国王没有不正当敛财的动机，因为不允许他持有超过法律所规定数字限度的金额。这样的国王使坏人害怕，受好人爱戴。——但是，如果我这些话是讲给那些决计持相反观点的人，你认为他们会听我的吗？

莫尔：当然，他们不会听你的。但是我不能责备他们。坦率地说，我不明白你那样说的意图，或者是你为何给他们提出明明知道他们不会接受的建议呢？这样做有什么好处吗？怎么能够期待他们采取一种完全不熟悉又与他们所有偏见相抵触的思维路线呢？这类事情在一个友好的交谈中是很有意思的，但内阁会议上，有重要决策需要作出，这些经院哲学就彻底没有了地位。

拉斐尔：这确实就是我所说的——宫廷与哲学无缘。

莫尔：当然与经院哲学无缘，而经院哲学所谈论的是纯粹的思想，它与环境无关。但是一种更具文明形式的哲学却深知自己活动的舞台，尽管按照场景讲话，并在演出中扮演适当的角色。这是你应该采用的那类哲学。否则，将像普劳塔斯的戏剧演出时，一群家奴正在舞台上傻玩，你却披上哲学家的外衣走上舞台，朗诵《屋大维娅》剧本中对尼禄皇帝的争辩。当然，把一场戏弄成又悲又喜的杂烩，还不如扮演一个哑巴角色更好些吧？即使你的贡献对前面的演出是一种进步，但由于其效果的不协调，你将毁掉整个演出。你要尽力使当前的演出获得成功——不要因为你碰巧想起另外一个你更加喜欢的戏而毁掉整个剧本。

同样的规则可以应用到宫廷中的政治生活。如果你不能彻底根除错误的主张，不能称心满意地治理好积久的弊端，那不是你不面对公共生活的借口。在风暴中，你不能因为控制不了风就将船抛弃。

另一方面，不要将完全崭新的主张强加于人，那些对此新主张持有偏见的人肯定不会接受。你必须间接地工作。你必须尽你力所能及地机智地做事，凡是你不能使之好转的事就尽量少出错。因为事情永远不会完美无瑕，除非人是完美的——我不能期望他们在近几年内完美无缺！

拉斐尔：那种方法的唯一优点，就是在真正努力治疗他人精神病时，我可能发现他们没有那么精神失常。但我必须讲实话，我必须说那些你反对的事情。我不知道哲学家说谎话是不是对，但那绝对不是我做事的方式。另外，尽管他们可能被我所说的话所激怒，但我看不出普通的事情为何被看得那么荒谬。它不像我推荐的柏拉图所设想的共和国制度，或者是推荐乌托邦现在的制度。尽管那些制度无疑要比我们的制度优越，但他们看来是很离奇的，因为他们的制度是以共有财产而不是以私有财产为基础的。

当然，他们可以不喜欢我的建议。他们已经对某一行动路线下了决心，自然也就不喜欢有人指出前途有危险及告知让他放弃这一切。但是，除此之外，我的谈话内容有哪些是不能够或者不应该到处提出的呢？如果我们绝不讲那些可能被认为非传统的话，担心它听起来荒谬可笑。我们即便是在基督教国家，对救世主的一切教导也不张扬。但这都是救世主最不愿意做的事情。他难道没有告诉弟子他对他们附耳低声所说的话应该到屋顶上公开宣扬吗？在现代习俗方面，他的大部分教导比我的任何建议都差异很大。除非他的教条已经得到精明的传道士的修改——无疑依据的是你的建议！

这些传教士势必认为：“我们将绝不会按照基督教的准则来调节人的行为，因此，就让我们调整基督教的准则来适应人的行为。这样，至少二者之间就会有某些关联。”

然而，我不明白他们这样做有何好处。他们只是使得人们更加心安理得地去做坏事罢了——那就是我在内阁会议上所能够做的一切。因为我只能做两件事，要么投票反对我的同僚，那几乎与根本不投票相同；或者是投票赞成我的同僚，在这种情况下，如同特楞斯戏中的密西欧一样，我将“助长他们的疯狂”。

至于你提到的间接工作方法，当一切都无济于事的时候，至少要极力机智行事，并尽量不要搞坏。我也很难能够看到这会起到作用。在宫廷中你不能不发表自己的意见，或者仅仅是默许他人的犯罪。你必须公开支持最糟糕的政策，支持最有害的决议。如果你对一个坏的法律不显出足够的热情，你将被看作是间谍甚至于是叛徒。另外，当你与这样的同僚共事时，你有什么机会做好事呢？你绝不会改造他们——他们更可能是带坏你，不管你是多么好的人。通过与他们的交往，你要么会丧失自己的正直，要么会习惯于隐瞒他们的愚蠢和邪恶。你所提到的间接的方法的实际结果就是这样！

在柏拉图的书中有一个愉快的形象，它解释了为什么一个明智的人有权不参与政治事务。他看到人们涌向街头，回身被如注的大雨淋湿。他不能说服他们进屋避雨。他知道，如果他也出去的话，他也会一样被淋湿。因此，他只是自己待在家里，因为他对别人的愚蠢无能为力，只好用这样的想法安慰自己：“还好，尽管他们被淋湿了，我没事的。”

不过，我亲爱的莫尔，我把内心的感想告诉你，我觉得，只要有私有财产，并且任何事情都以金钱来衡量，你就不可能得到真正的正义和成功——除非你认为最坏的人过着最好的生活是正义的，或者是极少数人瓜分所有的财富，你认为这称得上国家繁荣——其余的人只是过着凄惨生活的话，这少数人不会完全感到幸福。

实际上，当我想到乌托邦公正和贤明的制度时，他们法律那么少，但一切都管理的那么有效。意识到每个人的所得都与平均繁荣相一致——当我将乌托邦与许多资本主义国家比较时，发现资本主义国家总是制定新的法规，但却绝对称不上管理的好。那里每天都通过几十项法律，但仍然不能足以保证他们获得、保持或安全地标示出自己所谓的私有财产——为什么有层出不穷的法律诉讼呢？——当我想到这一切，我就更加赞成柏拉图，就更不奇怪他不肯为反对平等原则的城市立法了。很显然像他这样的伟大哲人当然清楚，健康社会的基本条件就是物资的平均享有——这在资本主义社会是不可能的。因为，当每一个有权获得他所能获得的物资时，所有的财产不管有多少，都将落在一小部分人手中。这就意味着这里每个人都是贫困的。财富总是与善良成反比的。富人极为贪婪、肆无忌惮、毫无用处，而穷人朴实、谦虚，他们的日常工作对社会的利益远大于对他们自己的利益。

换句话说，我相信，除非你废除了私有财产，否则你决不会得到公正的物资分配，人的生活也绝对得不到满意的组织。只要私有制存在，人类中的绝大部分，也就是最为优秀的一部分，都将不可避免背负贫穷、困苦和苦恼的重担。我不是说这个重担不能减轻，但你确实无法取消它。你当然可以规定一些法律，限制每个人所允许拥有的资金和土地。通过适当的立法，你可以保持国王和臣民之间的权力平衡。你可以通过法律手段，防止卖官鬻爵，不允许因公务而个人得以铺张浪费——否则的话，他就会通过欺骗及敲诈去充实私囊，这些职位是以财富而不是贤明作为基本任职资格。这一类法律将肯定能够减轻症状，就像不治之症的病人因为不间断的医治可以获得拖延。但只要私有财产继续下去，那就绝对无法治愈。如果你专心治疗某一个局部，你会加重其他部分的病情。对一个人是良药，而对另一个人则是毒药——因为你不抢劫甲的你就不能支付给乙。

莫尔：我不同意。我不相信在共产主义制度下，你能享有合理的生活标准。因为没有人愿意辛勤劳动，总是物资缺少。由于缺乏利益驱动，每个人都变得懒惰，并依靠他人为己工作。然后，物资极为短缺时，不可避免的结果就是一系列的流血与暴乱，因为谁都没有合法的手段来保护他自己的劳动产品——尤其是在没有了对当局的尊重的情况下，我无从想象在一个没有阶级的社会中将会是一种什么状况。

拉斐尔：你会持有这种观点，那是因为你是不能想象它将是什么状况——无论如何，你也不能确切知道。但是，你若和我一起到过乌托邦，像我一样到处看看的话——我在那里居住了五年之久，你知道，我离开那里的唯一原因就是我想告诉人们这个新的世界——你是第一位承认没有看到过组织得如此井然有序的国家。

彼得：我必须说明，我发现很难相信，那个新世界比我们这个古老的世界的一切都组织得更加秩序井然得多。我应该认为我们同他们一样聪明有才智，我们的文明更加悠久。它因此能够体现悠久的经验积累的成果，而借助这些经验，我们使得生活更加舒适——就更不用说几次偶然的发现了，它是精心计划所决不能实现的。

拉斐尔：如果你读过他们的历史书，你对他们文明年代就能作出更加正确的判断了。若是我们必须相信那些记载，那么，我们这儿还没有人类生活的时候，那个新世界就已经有城市了。至于你所说的聪明才智和偶然发现，没有理由认为只有我们才有。我们可以比他们聪明也可以没他们聪明，但我深信不疑的是他们的实干和勤奋远远超出了我们。根据他们的记录，他们对于我们的活动一无所知，他们称呼我们为赤道那边的人——只知道一千两百年前，一个偶然的机会，一只遭风暴的船曾经在乌托邦岛失事。包括几个罗马人和埃及人的幸存者游上岸，在岛上住下来。

现在，这就使你了解到他们很好地利用了这一机会。凡是罗马帝国有用的技艺，他们或是从这些乘船失事的外来人学会了，或者是从得到的线索自己研究加以发现。我们这半球与他们的仅仅一次接触，他们竟因此获益匪浅。但是，如果有类似的事件发生，一个乌托邦的人飘到我们的国土上，我们会忘记得一干二净，正如我认为人们将会很快忘记我曾经到过那里一样。他们一见到我们，就立即采纳了欧洲所有的好主张——但是，我怀疑我们是否能够很快采用他们更加优越的制度。我认为，那就是主要原因，为什么尽管他们的才智和自然资源都不如我们，但在政治和经济上却领先我们那么多。

莫尔：在那种情况下，我亲爱的拉斐尔，我恳求你把这个岛描述一番，不要说得太简略——从不同的方面给我们详细讲述一遍——包括地理、社会、政治、法律诸方面——事实上，凡是你认为我们想了解而又不了解的一切事物。

拉斐尔：我再喜欢不过了，因为那些情况我还记忆犹新。但是你知道，说来话长呀。

莫尔：那好啊，我们到里面共进午餐吧，餐后我们随意支配整个下午的时间。

拉斐尔：就这么办吧。

于是我们入内就餐。饭后，我们回到了原处，坐在原来的那条长凳上，吩咐仆人莫来打扰。然后，彼得·贾尔斯和我就请拉斐尔兑现他的许诺。见我们真的要听他讲，他沉思了片刻，整理了一下思路，便开始了如下的讲述。

第二部

拉斐尔：乌托邦岛屿中部最宽，约达二百英里。全岛大部分都与此宽度差不了太多，只是两端逐渐尖削呈圆弧形，就像是用圆规画出来的一样，从一头到另一头周围五百英里。因此，你可以将该岛画为新月形状，两角间有长约十一英里的海峡。海水通过这个海峡流入，然后展开成的一个大湖——尽管它看上去像一个巨大的平静水塘，因为它被陆地环绕，完全不受风的侵袭，水面平静，波澜不惊。这样，整个岛国的内部几乎成为一个港口，航船可以驶向四面八方，这对每个人都有用。

港口甚为险要，布满浅滩和暗礁。几乎就在入口中间，有一岩石矗立水面之上，因为高出水面，所以对航行没有危险，其上建有堡垒，常年驻扎守军。但其他岩石都是暗礁，极其危险。仅有乌托邦人才知道哪里的水道安全，因此，没有乌托邦人领航，外国船只实际上不可能进入海湾。即使是本地居民，如果没有岸上的明显标志作为指引，也足够危险的——这些标志一经移位，不管有多少敌军战舰，都将被诱趋于灭亡。当然，在岛的另一边也有许多港湾，但是它们到处都防御极佳，有天然的或人工的防御工程，少数守兵就可轻易阻止强军近岸。

据说，或许你自己实际上也能看得出，乌托邦最初并不是一个岛屿而只是半岛。尽管如此，他被某个名为乌托普的人所征服——由他给这个岛起了个名字——而它过去的名字为萨斯库劳铁——乌托普也负责将岛上未开化的淳朴居民培养成为现在这样，或许是世界上最文明的国度。他一登上岛屿并控制了这个国家后，立即在本岛连接大陆的一面掘开连接乌托邦和大陆的十五英里的地峡，这样海水就环绕了小岛。担心如果他让当地居民将这样的工程完全干完可能产生怨恨，就让所有士兵也都参与了进去。有了这么多劳力参与，任务完成得异常快速，使大陆一边的人们惊讶失色，他们当初还在嘲笑整个设想呢。

岛上有五十四座壮丽的大城市，语言、法律、习俗和机构设置都一样。它们依据同样的计划来建造，只要地势许可的话，它们都建得看上去完全相同。两地之间的最小距离是二十四英里，最大距离也不超过一天的步行路程。

每个城市每年有三名富有经验的老年公民到艾尔卡索集会商讨该岛的一般事宜。艾尔卡索被看作首都，因为它地处全国中心，全国各地都容易抵达。土地这样安排，每个城市每一个方向都至少有十二英里长的区域，而较远的一面更远些，即两地间能达到的最大距离。每个城都没有丝毫去拓展疆域的欲望，因为它们认为自己是土地的耕种者，而不是占有者。

农村中到处是间隔适宜的农场住宅，配有农具，市民依次到这里居住。每个农户至少居住四十个成年人，外加长期依附的农奴二人，由一对德高望重的老年夫妇经营，每三十户由一名管片员负责。每户每年有在农村住满两年的二十人返回城市，其空额由城市来的另外二十人填补。这些新来者从已经在这儿住过一年因而较熟悉耕作的人接受训练。一年之后，这些受训者又变成了施训者，如此循环。这一制度减少了缺乏粮食的危险。如果大家都是不懂农业生产的新来者，就可能出现缺粮危机。

一般是在农村干两年，这样任何人都不会被迫从事颇为艰苦的工作时间太久，但对那些喜欢农村生活的人——很多人都喜欢农村的生活——可以获得特别许可多几年。农业人员的职责是负责耕地、养殖牲畜、砍伐木材，视方便而定或经陆路或经水路把木材运往城里。他们用巧妙的方法大规模养鸡。母鸡不用孵蛋，人们用同样的温度一次性地大量孵化——结果呢，小鸡一破壳，就把饲养员当作妈妈，跟着他到处跑。

他们养的马不多，也不是真正驯化的，这些马用来供作骑马训练。犁地和拉车都用牛，他们承认牛不如马跑得快，但是乌托邦人说马野性而很少得病。牛养起来省事、费用也少，并且它们超过服役年龄，还可供食用。

谷物仅用来制作面包，因为他们不喝啤酒，仅喝葡萄酒、苹果或梨子酿造的酒，或只喝水。有时喝水时喜欢加上些当地盛产的蜂蜜和甘草。每个城市当局对整个地区每年消耗的食品数量虽然心中有数，但却总是生产出远远超出所需的谷物和牲畜。因此，他们还可有许多剩余为邻市居民分享。

农村里没有的任何物品，都可以在城里得到，因为每个月都有一天假期，很多人都可去城里。你只要要求城里的官员提供你所需要的东西，他就会发给你，不需要任何付款。

收获季节之前，管片员通知城市当局应派遣下乡的人数。这批收获大军就可以如期到达，如果天气晴朗，就可在二十四小时内收割完毕。

但是，我必须再讲述一下有关这些城市的情况。你只要看过一个城市，你就看到过所有的城市了，因为只要当地地形允许的话，它们都建设的一样。因此，这里我就给你举一个例子，以哪一个城市为例都无关紧要。尽管如此，显然要选择艾尔卡索，因为国会在此开会的事实使得它特别受到重视，而且也是我最为熟悉的一个城市，我在那里住过五年时间。

艾尔卡索建在一个不太陡的山坡上，呈现正方形。它从邻近山顶处往下延伸到乌水河，河宽两英里，沿河部分延伸稍长些。

乌水河源头是八十英里上游的一小股水，但由于汇入了若干支流，其中两个支流很大，因此，当它到达艾尔卡索的时候，河水宽度已经达到半英里宽。然后，河面继续加宽，直到抵达六十英里以外的大海。就在城的上边，甚至到城几英里外的上游，每隔六小时有一次潮涨潮落。涨潮时，海水灌入河水达三十英里，充满河床，河水被迫后退。这时，连远至三十英里之外的河水都是咸的，再往上游，咸味逐渐消失，流经艾尔卡索城的河水绝对是淡水。退潮时，河水又流往大海，保持清澈而无污染，直到河口。

该城由一座很好的拱桥与河的另一岸连接，桥基不是用木桩而是用巨大的石头建成。这座桥位于距海最远的地方，因此，并不妨碍船只沿城通航。还有另一条小河，它不太大，但却是宜人的平静和舒缓。它发源于艾尔卡索城所在的那座山，穿过城的中部流入乌水河。这条河的源头就在城外，人们便在外围筑有城墙，以便在外敌入侵时，河水不至于被截断、改道或被放毒污染供水。从水流出的地方到城的较低处，水都由瓦管系统流下来。在不适宜使用瓦管的地方，他们设有容积巨大的雨水池，也一样便利。

城周围建有很厚的高墙，按一定间隔筑有瞭望塔和堡垒。城的三面均有壕沟，没有水，但很宽很深，其中荆棘丛生，难以越过。剩下的一面就是那条河作为护城河。街道布局很好，有利于交通和避免风害。建筑物美观，平台屋顶，面对面建造，整条街上的房屋一字排开。房屋前面有一条宽二十英尺的大路将两边隔开。房屋后面是一个大花园，也和街道一样长，并且完全被另一条街的后面所隔开。每家房屋有一个前门通往街道，和一个后门通往花园。两个门都是双折门，便于推开和之后自动关闭。任何人都可以进去，因为没有一样东西是私有的。这些房子都是抽签分配的，大约十年调换一次。

他们特别喜欢这些花园。他们在花园里栽种果树，包括葡萄树，也有花草。他们栽培得法，事实上，我从来也没有见过如此漂亮而多产的花园。艾尔卡索人热衷于搞好花园，不仅是因为他们喜欢而且是因为街道之间有竞争最好花园的比赛。当然，很难找到任何城市特征能比这给公众带来快乐和实惠的了——这使得我想到园艺就是这座城的建立者特别感兴趣的一件事。

建立者我是指乌托普国王本人，据说是他从一开始就设计了整座城的规划。尽管如此，他将修饰和加工留给了后人去完成，因为他意识到一个人穷毕生精力也不可能完成。根据他们的历史记载，从征服之日起的一千七百六十年都写得非常翔实，最初的房子仅仅是棚舍或者是小屋，使用手头现成的木材草草建造。房子都是泥墙，屋顶呈脊状，由茅草覆盖。但是现在每个房子都很气派，为三层的楼房。墙壁用坚石或涂上泥灰，也有砖砌的，里面填以碎石。坡面的屋顶也抬升为平顶，使用一种特制水泥，虽然极为便宜但却可以比铅板还能抵抗坏天气，也能防火。他们使用玻璃窗防风，玻璃在那里使用很广泛；也有时使用涂有透明油料或琥珀的细麻布代替玻璃装窗。这样，窗子既透明又能起到密封的作用。

现在讲述他们当地的政府体系。人口按每三十户分为一组，每组每年选出一位官员，叫作斯蒂沃德。斯蒂沃德是旧的乌托邦头衔——现在称之为管片员。每十个斯蒂沃德及其所代表的住户设有一个贲慈特，或称之为高级管片员。

每个城市有两百个斯蒂沃德，他们承担选举市长的责任。他们经过严格的宣誓对认为最为合适的人秘密投票。市长必须是从所有选民所推举的四个候选人当中产生。因为全城四个区，每个区提交一个候选人名单给贲慈特议事会。市长为终身制，除非因为他有阴谋想建立暴政而遭废黜。贲慈特每年都要选举，但他们通常不更换。其他所有的任命官员都是一年一选。

如果需要，贲慈特每三天与市长开一次会，商量公务并迅速解决任何私人纠纷，尽管这些纠纷是很罕见的。他们总是邀请两位贲慈特，每天是不同的两位，来参加会议。并且有一个规定，就是任何涉及国家事务的问题，不经过三天的讨论，就不得最后作出决定。在议事会外或在大会外议论公事，就是死罪。很显然，这种措施不鼓励市长和贲慈特共谋对人民专制压迫和变革国家的宪法。正是基于同样的原因，凡是重要的事情都要提交贲慈特议事会，由贲慈特通知各人所管理的住户，在住户之间开展讨论，然后将其观点报告议事会。偶尔也有事情提交国会。

议事会还有一个规定，当天提交的问题不得在当天讨论决议。所有的讨论都必须推迟到下次参会人数多的会议。否则的话，某人就会未经思考就信口讨论，往往为自己的话辩论而不是为了公众的利益。那种人是以自己的名声来牺牲公众的利益。正是因为尽管听起来荒唐，但碍于面子不愿承认自己的主张可能是错误的——他一开始就应该先想好了再发表意见。

现在讲讲他们的工作状况。他们不分性别，都做一种工作，就是务农。他们从小学农。他们在学校学习农业理论，在附近城市农庄进行实习旅行。他们在那里不仅观看农活是如何做的，还亲自参与做一些农活，作为一种训练形式。

除了我所说的农活作为每个人的工作之外，每个人还得学习一门专项手艺。学织毛衣或织麻布，或者成为泥水匠、铁匠或木匠。那些就是所能用得上劳力的所有手艺。他们既没有水手，也没有裁缝，因为这个岛上的每一个人都身着同类衣服，只按照性别和婚否稍加区别，款式绝不改变。这些衣服看上去很舒服，穿上行动便捷，适合于冷暖天气变化——最重要的是，这些衣服都是自己做的。因此，每个人都学会一种我所提到的手艺，我所说的每个人指的是包括妇女和男子。尽管妇女因体弱给予的工作较轻，像毛织和麻纺，而男子干较重的活。

多数孩子长大都是子承父业，因为他们一般都有这种自然情感倾向。但如果一个孩子对其他某一手艺感兴趣，他就寄养在操他所喜爱的手艺的这个家庭里。当然，他的父亲或是地方当局，都关心替他找一个体面可敬的户主。当你学好一门手艺之后——如果你愿意的话，还可以准许学习另一门手艺。当你两门手艺都学好时，你可以根据你的偏好选择工作，除非另一种手艺对公众更为重要。

贲慈特的最主要事务，其实也是他们唯一的事务，就是要做到没有一个闲员，而且每个人都在从事自己的工作。但也不至于从早到晚从事劳作而筋疲力尽，累得像牛马一般。那只是奴隶的生活——然而这也如同世界上其他各地劳动人民的生活一样。乌托邦人民每天工作六个小时——上午三个小时，然后吃午饭，之后休息两个小时，下午再工作三个小时，接着吃晚饭。他们晚上八点睡觉，睡眠时间为八个小时。一天中的其他时间都随自己支配——不在偷懒和自我放纵方面浪费时间，而是很好地利用时间从事一些适宜的活动。大多数人将这些自由时间花在进修方面，因为每天上午的第一件事是有很多公共演讲。参与听讲的人出于自愿，除非挑选出来从事学术培训的人必须参加。但所有各界人士，无论男女，都挤着去听讲。我的意思是说，不同人去听不同的演讲，正是一种精神鼓舞着他们。尽管如此，如果你想这样做的话，没有什么可以阻止你将额外的时间花在你的手艺上。许多人就是这样的情况，他们没有做智力活的能力，他们搞自己的手艺还令人羡慕，因为这是符合公共精神的行为。

晚饭后有一小时娱乐时间，或者是在花园中，或者是在公共食堂。根据一年中的时间而定。有的人演奏音乐，有的人只是聊天。他们从来也没有听说过像玩骰子如此愚蠢和令人泄气的游戏了，但是他们有两种游戏，很像象棋。第一种是一类斗数，一个数“吃掉”另一个数。第二种是罪恶和美德之间的战斗，它极为巧妙地显示出罪恶之间彼此倾轧，继而又联合对抗美德。它也显示罪恶反对美德，罪恶如何聚焦力量直接对抗美德，采取什么迂回策略，美德需要什么帮助来战胜罪恶，用什么样的最好方法来阻止罪恶的袭击，以及最后通过什么来决定一方战胜另一方。

但是，为了避免你产生误会，有一点需要特别注意。既然他们每天只需工作六个小时，你可能会认为势必导致货物短缺。相反，那六个小时足够了，能够生产出舒适生活所需的一切，而且还绰绰有余。如果你考虑一下在其他国家完全不干活的人口所占的比例有多大，你就会理解为何会是这样。

首先是所有的妇女，她们占全民的一半。在一些妇女有活干的国家，男子往往闲荡不干活。而且，那伙牧师和大量的所谓宗教信徒，他们干多少活呢？再加上所有的富人，特别是那些称之为贵族和绅士的地主。包括他们家的雇员——我指的前面所提到的那帮武装的恶棍们。最后，再加上那些身强力壮的乞丐，他们假装有病，找借口乞讨。把这些人都算在一起，你一定会惊奇地发现那些为人类生产消费品的人数极少。

现在再想想，在少数劳动者中那些从事必要工作的人又是多少——因为在那里金钱是唯一衡量价值的标准，人们从事数十种不必要的行业，仅仅提供奢侈品和娱乐。即使现有的劳力分配到为满足适宜生活的少数几个行业中，也将出现产品过剩，并使得物价下降，从而使得工人难以靠干活维持生计。但是，如果你让这些所有参与无益劳动的人，和那些所有不工作的懒汉（他们每个人所消耗的别人的劳动的成果就等于两个工人所消耗的数量）都去参加做有益的事情的话，你就很快发现只需要多么少的工作时间便足以生产出生活上需要与便利所必不可少的一切，甚至于也会增加真正又自然的享乐。

乌托邦的事实也说明问题了。这里，每一座城和附近的地区中，凡是身体适于劳动的男女都要参加普通劳动，只有不到五百人免于劳动。这包括斯蒂沃德，他们尽管法律上规定免于劳动，但却自愿劳动以树立榜样。也包括哪些永久免于其他义务的人，以便能够集中精力于学术研究。这一特权自由只有经过教士的推荐以及斯蒂沃德以秘密投票的形式确认后才能获得。并且如果任何做学问的人辜负了人民的希望，他就调回去从事做工。另一方面，往往也会有这样的情况，一个工人在业余时间辛勤钻研学问，并取得很大进步，他就可以不再从事自己的手艺，提升为学者从事学问研究。

他们正是从这些人当中选出了自己的外交使节、牧师、贲慈特以及市长。过去他们把市长叫作巴桑，现在他通常被称之为侬皮袍。几乎其他所有居民如果都从事工作，而且又都是从事有益工作的话，你就可想而知他们将在不多的几个小时干很多工作了。他们的劳力问题也会减少，因为他们使用比我们更为经济的手段来应对必要的工作。例如，之所以房屋的建设工作通常吸引那么多劳力，是因为人们建起了房子，而不知爱惜财力的后人任其毁掉。因此，下一代人又得再重新建设，这要比保持原有的房子花费的代价肯定要高。事实上，经常出现这样的情况：甲建了一座很昂贵的房子，但随后就不再满足乙的挑剔口味。因此，乙就不把它看在眼里，结果它很快被毁掉了，然后在别处花钱再建一所同样昂贵的房子，但在乌托邦，一切都有国家控制，房子很少建筑在完全新的地方。房子该修的时候，哪怕不能提前维修，也会马上进行维修。这样，他们以最小的劳动代价使房子达到最大使用期限。这就意味着，建设者有时实际上无事可做。在这种情况下，他们就回到家里锯好木板，准备好石头，以便一旦有房子要建设，可以更快地建起来。

接着我们再来看看他们在衣服上省多少钱吧。他们的工作服都是粗布服装，这种衣服可以至少用上七年。当他们出入公共场合时，他们披上外套遮上工作服；衣服的颜色都一样，都是羊毛的自然色。这样，他们不仅消耗的毛绒世界上最少，而且这种材料的生产成本也最低。因为亚麻布更容易生产，所以也较多使用，但是只要亚麻是白色的和羊毛是干净的就行，他们不在乎纤维精致与否。在其他国家，一个人不会满足于不到五六件丝绸背心，而挑剔的人每人都要十多件。而在乌托邦，一人有一件就很满足了，一件一般都能穿上两年时间。他为何要更多件呢？衣服多了既不能使他更暖和，也不会使他更漂亮。

由于每个人都做有益的工作，工作量就减少到最低限度，因此，他们就不时地积累了大量的物品，可以腾出大量劳力去修补道路。如果没任何事情可干，当局通常就宣布更短的工作时间。他们从来也不强迫人们从事不必要的工作，因为整个经济的主要目的就是给每个人充裕的时间，免于体力劳动，只要是社会所允许。这样，他们就可以培养思维能力，他们认为这是幸福生活的秘诀。

现在，我最好来解释一下他们的社会安排——即社会是如何组织的，他们彼此间如何交往，以及货物如何分配等。社会的最小单位是家庭，它实际上是家的同义词。女孩子长大之后结婚，就嫁到丈夫家，但男孩子每一代都在自己家，并听从于最年长男性家长——除非他年事已高，有年纪第二大的家长接替他。

除了郊区外，每个城市都有六千个家庭。并且为了保持人口的稳定，法律规定每个家庭都不得少于十名或多于十六名成年人，因为他们不好固定孩子的数量。这一法律容易遵行，他们只要把一家中过多的成年人转到较少的一家就行了。如果一座城市的人口过多，多出的人就转到相对人口少的城市去。如果整个岛屿人口过多的话，他们就从每座城市分派出一定数量的人去附近大陆开辟聚居区，那里有很大区域当地居民还没有开垦。这样的聚居区由乌托邦人管理，但如果当地人愿意参与管理也是允许的。当地人参与管理的时候，当地人和移居者联合起来，融为一体，形成共同的生活方式，这对双方都有好处。因为在乌托邦人的管理下，那些过去被认为不能生产出够一方人所消耗的产品的土地，现在很多人都能够生产出足以供两方人使用的产品了。

如果当地人不愿意按照所要求的去做，他们就被从乌托邦人圈定的土地上逐出。如果他们反抗的话，乌托邦人便宣战——因为当一个国家否定另一国家从任何土地上获得营养的自然权利，而原来的所有者自己不使用这些土地，仅仅作为无价值的地产让其荒芜，乌托邦人认为战争是完全正义的。

一旦乌托邦任何城市人口减少，不能从岛上其他地方取得补充而不使其他市的人口减少到最低限度之下（据说历史上这种情况出现过两次，每次都是因为瘟疫流行），他们就把移居出去的人调回来充实。他们的原则就是宁愿丢失新的聚居区，也不愿意丢失乌托邦自身的任何部分。

现在我们再回到他们的社会组织上。正如我前面所说，每一个家庭都由最长的男性当家。妻子从属于丈夫，孩子从属于父母，一般来说，年轻人照顾老年人。每个市都划分为四个大小一样的区，每个区中心有自己的购物中心。任何一户的产品都存放在仓库中，然后根据不同商店的类型分发。当户主自己或家庭需要物资时，他就到其中的一个商店去领。无论他要什么，都允许他拿走货物而不需任何形式的付款，既不付现金，也不需要其他补偿。究竟有什么理由不允许给予他所需的物品呢？一切货物都有充足的供应，因此无须担心有人所求超出自己的所需。一个人知道绝对不会出现物资短缺时，还有什么理由想要储存呢？没有天生贪婪的生物，除非是担心供应短缺。或者就人类而言，贪婪是出自虚荣心，也就是你能够显示一下占有的东西超过他人就比他人好。但这类事情在乌托邦不存在。

这些购物中心包括食品市场，运到这儿的有肉和鱼，也有面包、水果和蔬菜。市外有专门的地方，在那里首先将所有的血迹和污染用流水清洗干净。牲畜的屠宰和尸体的清洗由奴隶来做。他们不让普通人屠宰动物，因为他们认为这会逐渐毁掉人性的恻隐之心。并禁止将不干净的东西或不健康的东西带进城里，因为担心污染了环境而导致疾病。

你沿着一条街走下去经常会走到一个巨大的建筑物，它有自己专有的名字。那就是斯蒂沃德住的地方，他所管理的三十户，左右两方各十五户，在此就餐。负责这些餐厅的伙食人员每天按时到食品市场去，在那里报告注册人数，并适当领取食品。

但是，医院病人最为优先。噢，对了，城区共有四家医院，就在城墙外边。每家医院大约有一个小镇那么大。这样的目的是避免过于拥挤，并有利于传染病例的隔离。这些医院管理的很好，配备有完善的各类医疗设备，护士们很体贴人也很负责，经常有很多有经验的医生，不过没有人是被迫住进医院的，实际上每个人生病时都乐于离家而住院治疗。

尽管如此，一旦医院伙食员拿到医生的订单，所有领取的最好食物都根据注册人数比例平均分配给各个餐厅。只有某些人员给予特殊照顾，如市长、主教、贲慈特和外交使节。对外国人的供应也是相同的——外国人并不多见；但是，当确实有外国人时，则为他们专门提供住宿。

在午餐和晚餐时响起喇叭声，除了那些有病待在医院或者待在家里的人外，整个斯蒂沃德居民在餐厅集合。然而，餐厅开始供应后，你也相当自由地可以从市场上带回食物。因为大家都知道除非你没办法要不你不愿意这样做。我的意思是说，尽管没有规定反对，但没有人愿意在家吃饭。一方面，在家吃饭被认为是很不好的一种形式。另一方面，就在街道旁边的餐厅中既然饭菜如此精美丰盛，一个人却自找麻烦去从事质量差的烹饪，显得也太傻了。

在这些餐厅中，所有粗活和脏活都由奴隶来干，但是食物的准备、烹调、菜单的安排都完全有值班的家庭妇女承担，因为不同的家庭有责任每天提供饭菜。其他成年人根据他们的人数在三桌或更多桌前进餐，男的背靠墙而坐，女的坐在外边，因此如果后来者感到突然不适（如孕妇经常这样），她们可以起身离开到保姆室，而不至于打扰其他人。

我说的保姆室就是留出照料母亲和婴儿的房屋。那里总是生着火并提供充足的清洁用水。还设有许多吊床，因此妈妈可以将婴儿放在床上，或者如果乐意的话，也可以解开婴儿襁褓，让其在火前面玩耍。婴儿总是由其母亲哺育，母亲死亡或生病的除外。万一母亲死亡或生病，斯蒂沃德的夫人就很快找到一个保姆。这件事并不困难，因为任何能胜任这一事情的妇女都乐意做这件事。这种慈善得到人们的普遍赞扬，孩子也总将她看作自己的亲生母亲。

保姆室也是五岁以下孩子吃饭的地方。其他孩子，那些不到结婚年龄的男女，就在餐厅内的餐桌旁等候。如果他们太年幼，就安静地站在那里。以上两种情况下，他们都没有单独的就餐时间，他们都是从成年人的餐桌上获得饭菜。

高桌正中间是一个荣光的位置，它位于大厅尽头的平台上，这里可以看到全体进餐的人。这一桌就餐的是斯蒂沃德和他的妻子，另外还有两个年龄最长的居民，因为就餐总是四人一桌。如果在斯蒂沃德区域刚好设有教堂，牧师夫妇就自然就座于斯蒂沃德席。两旁餐桌都是四位年轻人使用，接下去一桌又是四位老年人使用，整个大厅就是这样安排的。换句话说，年龄相同的人一桌，而又与不同年龄组的人交叉。他们告诉我这样安排，尊重上一辈老年人可以防止年轻人之间的言行失检，因为这些年轻人的一言一行都能够被旁边的老年人看到。

端上食物时，不是从这一头的桌子到另一头的桌子依次提供。他们首先端给那些有明显标记的老年人餐桌，然后再端给其他餐桌。尽管如此，如果某种美味不够全体享用，老年人认为合适的话可以与邻桌的其他人分享其美味食物。这样，老年人受到理所应得的尊重，而每个人最终也都有所得。

午餐和晚餐开始前有一段文学作品朗诵，但内容简短，不至于让听者厌烦。接着老年人以开朗的和略带风趣的方式讨论严肃的问题。但老年人并不是整个席间都自己长篇大论。相反，他们爱听年轻人发言，并故意引出他们的话，以便他们能够考验每一个年轻人的性格与才华，因为在这样一种宽松而又非正式的氛围中年轻人容易显示自己。

午餐时间很短，因为午餐后要接着工作，而晚餐时间倒可以放开些，因为晚餐后接着的是一整夜的就寝，他们认为一整夜的就寝有助于胃肠消化。晚餐时总有音乐，最后提供各类甜点和水果。他们燃香并喷洒香水。事实上，他们尽力使得每一位就餐者过得愉快，因为他们十分相信所有无害的乐趣都是完全合法的。

这就是城市里的生活。在农村，因为大家住处彼此相距较远，每个人都在家中用餐。当然，他们的食物与城里的一样好，因为城里人吃的东西都是由农村生产的。

现在讲述一下旅游设施。如果你想拜访一些其他城市的朋友，或者只是想看看城市本身，你通过申请很容易就会得到你们斯蒂沃德和贲慈特准许，除非你急需待在家里。你将同一批出游者一起出发，持有市长签发的集体护照，上写着你回来的日期。你可以领到一种交通工具，一名赶车驾牛的奴隶照看牛和车。但是，除非旅伴中有妇女，他们多数是不要车的，认为有车反而更加麻烦。你不必带行李，因为你无论到哪里，都和家一样，你想要啥都有。如果你在一个地方超过二十四小时，会要求你去干你那一行，这将受到当地同行的热烈欢迎。

如果你没有护照并擅自越过自己本城辖区而被逮住的话，你就会被不光彩地遣返回家，并将被作为逃亡者给予严厉的惩罚。第二次重犯将被贬为奴隶。尽管如此，如果你急于想到本城郊区游览的话，只要你父亲允许，妻子不反对的话，就不会禁止你。当然，无论在哪里，只有你做过上午或下午的活，才能受到伙食款待。但除此之外，你可以在本城辖区内自由活动。正如你待在家里一样，你正是社会中有用的一员。

你可以看出，不管在哪儿，你总是需要工作。绝没有任何借口可以偷懒。也没有酒店、没有妓院、没有诱惑的机会、没有秘密幽会之处。每个人都看着你，你实际上只好被迫干好自己的工作，并正当地利用好你的业余时间。

在这种制度下，所有的东西都必须丰富，因为所有的东西都是全体居民平均分配，很显然不可能有任何穷人或乞丐。记住，每一座城市都会派三个代表参加一年一度在艾尔卡索举行的滥套客（Lietalk）会议，或者叫议会。会上他们收集当年的生产详细情况，弄清楚哪个地区的商品生产充足和哪个地区的供应不足，就马上安排一系列调拨以平衡地区供应。这些调拨是单向的交易，不需要回报补偿。但实际上，甲城免费给予乙城的礼物由免费从丙城获得的礼物所平衡。因此，整个岛就像一个大家庭。

他们只有储备有够一年使用的物资时，才认为已经做到了能满足他们自身之需，随后一年会发生什么情况就无所谓了，其余的都出口海外。出口物有大量谷物、蜂蜜、羊毛、亚麻、木材、大红和紫色布料、生皮、黄蜡、油脂、皮革以及牲口。他们把全部出口商品的七分之一送给这些国家的穷人，其他部分则以合理价格出售。这种对外贸易不仅购买了基本进口产品，通常只是铁器，而且还可带回大量金钱。实际上，通过很长一段时间他们逐渐积累了大量的金银，多到令人难以置信。因此，他们现在并不介意是售货得到现款，还是用赊欠的办法。其实，他们几乎所有的售货都是使用赊欠的办法。可是他们对于赊欠，并不满足于私人的保证，而是必须由进口地当局签订合法合同，并密封和传递过来。付款日期一到，当局就从所涉及的私人债户收齐欠款存入公库，在提取之前可以作为资金使用。实际上，他们从来也没这样使用过，因为他们认为一个人用不着，而其他人确有用，将钱从别人处取出是不公平的。

然而，如果他们觉得有必要将这批资产的一部分借给另一个国家，他们就收回债款，因此在战时也是这样做的，因为在他们心目中战争是一件积累所有财富的事情。你知道，在任何重要危机和紧急之时，这能够起到保护他们的作用。

这些钱的主要作用就是用来为招募外国雇佣兵提供巨额资金。他们宁可使用这些人上阵冒险，也不愿使用自己人。他们深知有大量钱币也可以收买和出卖敌人，或者使其互怀鬼胎或公开动武而互相残杀。而这就是他们储存大量贵金属的唯一原因，但是他们却不视之为宝贝。事实上说出来有些难为情，担心你们难以置信——我这样担心也有一定的原因，若非亲眼所见，我也不会轻易相信。这在所难免，越是不符合我们思维习惯的事物，就越难令我们相信。正如同他们其他的制度和我们存在极大的差异，他们对待金银有不同的标准也就不足为奇了。乌托邦人自己不用钱，而是储存起来用以应付可能发生也可能永远不会发生的突发事件。

同时，他们只按作为金钱原料的金银本身的真实性质对待它们，不会超过其本身应得的价值——众所周知，金银远不及铁有用。人们没有了铁，就好比没有了火和水，将难以生存。但如果我们没有物以稀为贵的愚蠢概念，没有金银，仍能够轻松生活。然而，自然犹如仁慈而宽容的母亲，已经赐予我们一切最有用的东西，像空气、水以及我们眼前的大地，将空虚无益的东西与人类隔离开来。

倘若金银锁藏在乌托邦一间封闭安全的密室，一般人会胡猜乱想——你知道的，他们在这方面总具有一些天赋——他们会疑心这是市长及议事会的骗人伎俩，企图自己从中取利。当然，乌托邦人也可以将金银制成饮器或其他工艺品。但是，如果将其全部熔毁用作支付军饷，他们知道老百姓是不愿让出这些曾经心爱的东西的。

为了解决以上问题，乌托邦人想出了一种符合他们习惯规范的制度办法，和我们对待金银的态度截然不同——他们并非视黄金为珍宝。除非你亲眼所见，否则无法相信。这个制度规定乌托邦人的饮食用陶器及玻璃器之类制作精美而价格低廉的器皿。然而，金银也是常规材料，无论是公共厅馆还是私人住宅，主要制成粪桶溺盆之类的用具。再则套在奴隶身上的链铐也是取材于坚固的金银。因犯罪而成为可耻的人需要戴着金耳环、金戒指、金项圈以及一顶金冠。事实上，乌托邦人就是这样千方百计使金银成为可耻的标志。也就是说，一旦拿走他们身上的金银，没有人会感到有所损失，而不是像其他民族失去金银会万分悲痛，心惊胆战。

乌托邦人对待珠宝也是同样的态度。他们在海滨捡珍珠，在某些崖壁上采翠玉钻石——但他们从不刻意寻找这种东西。但是，如果他们偶然碰到，会将它们捡回去打磨加工一番，给孩子们做装饰品。刚开始，幼小的儿童会颇为得意拥有此类珠宝，等他们长大以后会明白这些东西只是托儿所的玩物，便将其扔掉，这种行为不是出于父母的劝告，而纯粹是由于自尊心——就如同我国的儿童一旦成人也扔掉洋娃娃、弹球以及护身符。乌托邦特别的制度也产生了相应奇妙的结果，浮莱图安外交使节的例子令我印象深刻。

这些外交使节到达艾尔卡索时，我正在那儿，因为他们有重要的事情前来商谈，所以乌托邦每座城市已派有三位议会代表在此等待会见。曾经到过这里的使节都很了解乌托邦的风俗习惯，知道华服盛装不受重视，穿戴丝绸会受到鄙视，黄金是可耻的标志，所以这些外交官来时总是穿得合乎场合地朴素。可是浮莱图安人住在遥远的地方，和乌托邦人平时很少来往。他们只听说过在乌托邦大家穿着一样的衣服，而且料子粗陋——便认定乌托邦所不用的东西是因为乌托邦人没有这些东西。所以这些高傲的人决心用豪华的装束把自己打扮成天神一般，让穷酸的乌托邦人在珠光宝气的装扮前眼花缭乱。

当使节团到达乌托邦，虽然只有三位使者，却跟随了一百名随从，无不穿着艳丽，大部分用丝绸制成。三位使节本人在自己的国家是身份显贵的，所以穿的金锻，戴着重金项圈及金耳环，手上还有金戒指。他们的帽子上装饰着成串的珍珠及宝石。事实上，他们装扮自己的全部饰品恰恰是乌托邦人用来处罚奴隶，污辱罪犯，以及逗孩童开心的东西。

当然，任何细节我都不会错过。这三位使节把自己身上的华丽盛装和涌到街头看他们走过的乌托邦人的衣服相比时，更洋洋得意起来。但实际情况并非他们所预料的那样受重视，反而令他们很失望。在乌托邦人看来，除了那些少数因事出过国的以外，这种华丽的排场是丢脸的。因此他们把使团中最下等的仆从当作主人来敬礼，却完全无视使节本人，把使节们当成了戴着金链的奴隶。

是呀，你还可以发现，那些已经扔掉珍珠宝石的稍大一些的孩童看见这些使节帽子上镶有珍珠宝石，都轻推他们的母亲。低声说道：

“快看呀，妈妈，多么大了还戴珍珠宝石，怎么像个小孩子呀！”

母亲们非常严肃地回答道：“小声点，孩子！我猜他可能是外国使节身边的小丑吧。”

许多乌托邦人对那些金链子很不满。

“我看那些金链子不好用，”有人说道，“看上去太细了，很容易就被奴隶挣断了，而且太松了，奴隶可以随时挣脱逃跑呀！”

这些使节在乌托邦住上一两天后，发现情况有些不对劲。乌托邦金银无数，毫不值钱，被看作极其卑贱的标志，与他们自己珍视金银的情形恰恰相反。他们看到了一个逃亡的奴隶身上所戴的金银链铐比他们三个使节一起佩戴的金子还要多。因此，他们不再炫耀，并对自己感到羞愧万分，脱下自己傲慢华丽的服饰，尤其是和乌托邦人亲切交谈后，他们更加了解那里的风俗和见解了。比如，乌托邦人很不理解，一个人可以仰视天空中群星乃至太阳，为何仍喜欢小小石头的闪闪微光。他们也不明白为何有人因为自己身上穿的是细线羊毛衣，就料想自己比其他人更加高贵。毕竟不管羊毛质地多么细，起初都是出自羊身上，且他们认为这东西再好也不过就是一只羊。

同样，乌托邦人也不理解本身毫无用处的黄金何以在世界各地目前如此受重视，甚至比活生生的人还要珍贵，而黄金的价值是由人创造，黄金本身也只是供人使用的。结果是一个木头脑袋的傻子，不正直，不懂事，只因为他拥有非常多的金币，就可以奴役大批聪明人和善良的人。同样，如果由于时运不济或是某种法律骗局（这种骗局如运气一样易使贵者贱者角色互换），之前的黄金从其主人手中转到他全家最卑微的杂役手中，这个主人无疑不久会去伺候他的旧仆人，似乎他是金钱的附属品，成为了自己仆人的仆人。但是更让乌托邦人感到惊奇而且也憎恨的是，某些人疯狂地崇拜富人，并非因为他们自己欠富人的债，或受富人的权力掌控，却仅仅因为他们富有而崇拜，尽管他们很清楚富人吝啬小气，只要还活在世上一天也不会分给他们一分钱。

乌托邦人形成这些见解一方面来自于他们成长的社会制度，因为完全不同于上面说的那种愚昧无知，也来自他们的阅读和教育。当然，并不是每一个学生都可免除其余一切工作全日学习，只有每个城市极少数从小天资聪颖爱好学问的人可以专门从事学术工作。然而所有孩子都接受基础教育，大部分公民，无分男女，都可以利用上文提到的体力劳动后的剩余时间进行学习。他们用本国语言学习各科知识，这种语言既拥有丰富的词汇，发音也悦耳动听，又极富表现力。在这个小世界的每个角落，人们都说着相同的语言，只是在其他各地或多或少运用不同程度的形式而已。

我们来到乌托邦以前，他们对任何欧洲著名的哲学家一无所知。但是在音乐、逻辑、算术以及几何各个领域，他们发现的原理就几乎赶上了我们早期的哲学家。然而尽管他们在其他多数学科方面可以和古人相提并论，但他们远不如我们现在的逻辑学家成就斐然。比如，我们的儿童在《逻辑入门》这一科中普遍要学习了限制、扩大、假定等我们独创出的各条规则，但乌托邦人还未发现其中的任何一条。关于“再概念”乌托邦人也未曾思考，甚至都无从认出人本身作为一般化的概念。现在如你所知，这样的人比任何巨人还更巨大，虽然我们解释的非常清楚，但他们还是无法理解。

另一方面，乌托邦人是天文学方面的专家，发明了多种仪器，可以精确测定日月以及他们所在半球能见到的各种天体的位置及运行。而对于占星学的星辰相生相克和根据星辰占人或所有的骗人把戏，他们视为怪诞胡说，做梦也没有想过去研究。

他们从长期实践总结的确切征兆，可以预测风雨及其他一切天气变化。如上述各种现象的起因，潮汐何以形成，海水何以含盐，总之，关于天体和宇宙的起源及本质，他们的论点和我们古代哲学家的论点大致相同。和我们古代哲学家相互之间有一定程度分歧一样，他们之间对问题的理解也存在分歧，共同创建全新的理论的学者，彼此也会秉持不同的意见。

在道德层面上，他们的争论和我们相同。他们区分了心理、生理以及环境这三类“善”。他们同样疑惑“善”这个名称是指这三者呢，还是仅仅是心理的特性。他们讨论美德及快乐，但主要的争论的是人类幸福的本质依赖于一个因素还是多个因素？关于这个问题，他们似乎过分倾向于享乐主义的观点，认为快乐是构成人类全部幸福或主要幸福的因素。尤其令人惊讶的是，他们竟援引宗教为这种放纵的学说作辩护，而他们的宗教原则即使不冷酷无情，也是认真严肃的。可以看出他们所讨论的幸福问题总是与哲学的理性和宗教的原则相关联，否则理性本身就无法定义真正的幸福。

这些原则首先认为每一个灵魂都是不灭的，是上帝创造的，灵魂生来注定享有幸福。其次，我们行善修德，在另一个世界将有所回报；我们为非作恶，死后将受到惩罚。这些固然是属于宗教的原则，然而乌托邦人主张，人们承认这些原则是出于理性。一旦你不遵守这些原则将会怎样？乌托邦人便毫不迟疑告诉你，无论多么愚笨的人都知道该如何做。你应当全力追求自己的快乐，不必顾虑对错。只不过你须力求不要贪图小的快乐而妨碍大的快乐，也不要贪图会招致痛苦后果的快乐。如果没有渴望得到的事物，何需追求严峻艰苦的德行，放弃人生的甜蜜，刻意忍受痛苦呢？乌托邦人认为这是极不明智的行为。如果没有任何好处，死后未能得到补偿，又何必一生过不快乐、悲惨的日子呢？

乌托邦人并不把每一种快乐都视为幸福——只有更高层次的快乐才能称为真正的幸福。他们也不把拥有美德视为幸福的源泉——除非这种思想与众不同。通常人们认为美德促使我们的自然本性走向幸福，正如走向至善一样，即遵循人的本性，上帝创造我们就是要我们这样生活。但是，这包括遵循人的天性，在自己的喜恶方面服从理性。而理性也教导我们，首先是人们要对全能的上帝有爱意和尊敬，因为是上帝创造了我们并使得我们能享受幸福。其次，理性劝告人们尽量过舒适快乐的生活，并帮助其他同伴也过上这样的生活。

事实上，就算是最严厉的修道者对快乐的指责也会有某些矛盾的地方。他虽然叫人经历充满苦役、睡眠不足和不够舒适的生活，但同时也劝导人尽力减轻他人的痛苦和贫困。他把改善人们生活处境的努力视为值得赞扬的人道主义行为，因为没有什么比减轻他人的痛苦，结束他们的悲哀并使他们重获生活的乐趣即追求快乐的资格，更加符合人性或更加符合自然。因此，为什么我们不遵循自然同样对待自己呢？

或者，享受生活即体验快乐是坏事，那么你不应该帮助别人追求这样的生活，而应该尽量将所有人从这种可怕的命运中解救出来——抑或，享受生活对别人来说是好事，且不只是你的专权，而应该使别人也能够享受生活，既然如此为什么自己不首先享受生活呢？毕竟，你不仅仅要对你身边的人负责，还要对自己负责，而且，大自然要你善待他人的同时并不会转过头来要你苛待自己。所以乌托邦人认为享受生活——即快乐——是大自然指示人们追求的目标，乌托邦人认为美德就是遵循自然规律。然而，大自然还要我们在追求快乐的生活时互相帮助，这样做的理由非常充分，因为没有谁能成为大自然唯一眷顾的对象，大自然对所有人都是一视同仁的。因此，大自然告诫我们，追求自身利益不能以牺牲他人的利益为代价。

在这个原则的基础上，乌托邦人认为不仅要遵守私人之间的合约，还应该遵守有关生活物资——即获得快乐的物质的分配的公共法令——这些法令或是由贤明的当政者正式颁布的，或是由未遭受任何形式的暴政和欺骗的人民一致通过的。他们认为，在法令允许的范围内追求个人利益才是明智的，另外，还要照顾公共利益，那是道德上的责任。为了使自己快乐而剥夺他人的快乐是不公平的，而将自己的快乐分加给他人是一种人道主义行为，这样做你得到的快乐将比你失去的要更多。一方面，对方通常会将利益回报给你。另一方面，由于做了好事帮助他人得到他人的喜爱和善意所产生的精神上的满足感远比失去的那一点点物质上的快乐要多得多。最后——信仰宗教的人很容易接受的观点是——上帝会给予我们永恒的大快乐来奖励我们放弃短暂快乐的作出的小小牺牲。因此，他们认为，归根结底，快乐是人类所追求的最根本的幸福，甚至包括道德行为在内。

乌托邦人认为快乐就是一种自然而然感到愉悦的身心状态或活动。在这里关键词是“自然而然”。他们认为，我们的理性和本能都驱使我们通过自然的途径享受快乐，这种快乐不会伤害他人，也不会妨碍更大的快乐或造成不良后果。然而人类却愚蠢地将本不是快乐的事物称之为快乐——好似改变定义就能轻易地改变事实一样。现在乌托邦人认为，这种事物不但不能带来快乐，反而使快乐成为不可能得到的事物——因为，一旦你适应了这种所谓的快乐，你将无法追求真正的快乐，而只是沉迷在虚幻的快乐中。这些事物本身通常并不能带来快乐，事实上大多数只会带来不愉快。可是由于不良诱惑的驱使，这些事物不仅成为了生活中最重要的快乐，甚至成为了生活的主要原因。

在追求虚假快乐的人当中，乌托邦人把我先前提及的那类人也包括在内，他们自以为穿了比别人更高级的衣服就高人一等。事实上他们在认为自己的衣服高级和自己高级这两方面都错了。从实用的观点来看，为什么穿着细毛线就比粗毛线好呢？但他们却认为细毛线当然更加高级，穿上这样高级的衣服他们就身价倍增。因而他们觉得自己有资格享有原本穿着不甚考究时所不敢觊觎的尊敬，倘若受到怠慢，他们就会愤怒不已。

谈到尊敬，看重空虚无益的尊敬不也是非常愚蠢么？别人对你脱帽下跪能给你带来什么真正的快乐呢？这能够治好你膝盖上的风湿病或者减轻你的头疼吗？当然，很多相信这种虚假快乐的人都认为自己很“高贵”并非常自负。而现今，那仅仅意味着他们有幸出生在世代富有的家庭而已，尤其是富有地产的家庭。但即使他们未曾继承到上述遗产，或早已将所继承的财产挥霍一空，他们仍然认为自己很“高贵”。

还有另一种我先前提到的人，他们贪爱珠宝，如果他得到某种稀世珍宝，尤其是当时在他的国家最值钱的珠宝，他们就会快乐似神仙——因为同样的宝石在不同的地方和时代具有不同的价值。但是他们唯恐被表象所蒙蔽，所以不取下所有镶金的外壳仔细检察宝石的本色他们是绝不会购买的。而且还必须要珠宝商郑重地保证并写下书面担保，确认宝石是正品才肯购买。但是我亲爱的先生，如果你无法辨别真假，那么假货何以无法像真货一样给你带来快乐呢？就好像对一个瞎子来说——真货和假货对你来说没有任何区别！

而现在，那些以聚集多余的财富为乐，不为别的只为欣赏的人又如何呢？他们的快乐是真正的快乐还只是虚假的快乐呢？另一种疯狂的人，他们把金子埋藏起来，永不使用，并且可能永远都不再过目。实际上，在他们担心失去这些金子的时候却刻意地使自己失掉了这些金子——因为这些金子埋在地下之后，既对金子的主人没有任何益处，也不可能对别人有任何好处，这样一来不是失去又是什么呢？然而，他却以收藏金子为乐。因为这样他似乎就不必为丢失财物而担心了。但是，假如那些财物被盗，而财物的主人十年后在不知财物被盗的情况下去世了，在财物丢失的这十年期间他照样活得好好的，那么在这十年当中这些钱财在与不在对他来说又有什么分别呢？这些钱对他来说毫无用处。

乌托邦人认为，沉迷于这类愚蠢的快乐的人还包括赌博——这是一种乌托邦人听说过但从未实践过的愚蠢行为，以及打猎和鹰猎。乌托邦人不明白，在桌子上掷色子有什么乐趣？而且，即使一开始有乐趣，那么整天玩也总该厌烦了吧？而听到一群猎狗狂吠大叫，除了令人反感外，又有什么乐趣可言呢？为何看见狗追兔比看见狗追狗更让人开心呢？

如果奔跑能使你开心的话，那么这两者的本质是一样的。但是如果你真正的乐趣在于杀戮并眼看一只动物在你面前被撕碎，那么，看到一只弱小无辜的小兔子被一只凶残的狗吞食不是应该让你感到同情才对吗？

所以，乌托邦人认为打猎有损自由人民的尊严，并将所有的打猎活动交给屠夫，我在前面说过，屠夫是奴隶。在他们看来，打猎是屠宰工作中最卑贱的一部分，因为屠夫的其他工作比打猎更实用更值得尊敬。普通的屠夫比猎人更加有节制地宰杀牲畜，他们只在必要的时候才宰杀，而猎人却以残杀可怜的小动物为乐。乌托邦人认为，除非生性残忍或者由于经常干这种野蛮的事而变得残忍，否则即使在动物之间也不会有如此血腥的杀戮。

有许许多多类似的事情通常都被当作快乐，但是乌托邦人却深信这些算不上真正的快乐，因为这些事物的本质上没有令人快乐之处。很多人的确从这些事情上获得了享受，而享受似乎就意味着感官上的快乐，但是这个争论动摇不了乌托邦人的信念。他们认为这只是坏习惯导致的主观反应，这种坏习惯使得人把不快乐的事当成快乐的，就好比孕妇有时口味坏了，会觉得板油或松节油比蜂蜜还甜。然而无论坏习惯或病态对人的判断力影响有多坏，都改变不了快乐的本质，就如同改变不了其他任何事物的本质一样。

他们把真正的快乐分为两类，精神上的快乐和肉体上的快乐。精神上的快乐包括获取知识和追求真理所获得的满足感，还包括对美好生活的回忆和对未来幸福的展望。肉体上的快乐又分为两种。第一种能让人充分感受到快感。这种快感可能是由身体消耗掉的自然热能得到补充替换所带来的，比如当我们吃饭或喝水时感到的快乐；也可能是由排泄体内一些过剩物质所带来的，例如大便、性交或任何能够减轻疼痛的摩擦或抓挠。然而，还有一种快乐，它既不来自于满足器官的需求，也不来自于减轻先前提到的不适。它以一种神秘的却又明显的方式直接触动我们的感官，占据人们的感应。这就是音乐带来的快乐。

第二种身体的快乐来自于身体的平静和协调的运作——即不受任何疾病干扰的健康的身体状态所带来的快乐。即使没有外部引发的快乐，没有精神上的不适就能给人愉悦的感觉。当然，和吃喝所带来的原始的快感相比，这种快乐并不那么明显，也不会给人以强烈的感受，尽管如此，这种快乐常常被认为是生活中最大的快乐。几乎所有的乌托邦人认为健康是非常重要的快乐，因为，健康是其他一切快乐的基础。只要有健康，就能享受快乐的生活，如果没有健康，就谈不上其他快乐。然而，失去了健康但不觉得痛苦的人，乌托邦人认为他们并不是快乐，而是麻木。

一些思想家通常主张，和谐平静的健康状态不能称为快乐，因为只有在与它的对立面相比较时才能够察觉它的存在——是的，他们对这个问题作了彻底的研究。但这个理论已经是陈旧的观点了，而现在，几乎所有人都赞同健康确实是一种快乐的观点。有这样一种争论——疾病带来痛苦，痛苦是快乐的大敌，而疾病是健康的大敌，所以健康带来快乐。他们认为不论你说疾病就是痛苦还是说疾病带来痛苦都不重要。两者的结果是一样的。同样，不论你认为健康就是快乐，或者健康带来快乐，就如同火必然带来热一样，所得出的合理的结论就是：拥有健康体魄的人才能享受快乐！

此外，他们还说，我们吃东西时，是这么回事。我们衰退的健康借助食物的力量打败饥饿。渐渐地，健康开始获胜，并且身体在这个过程中恢复了元气，并感受到使我们神清气爽的愉悦。现在，既然健康享受这种战斗之乐，那它能不为胜利而喜悦吗？或者我们设想，当健康最终恢复了固有的活力——它一直为之战斗的目标——难道它就立刻昏迷，对自己的胜利毫无意识或不加利用吗？对于除非通过它的对立面，否则健康就无法被感觉到的观点，乌托邦人认为这种说法是完全不实的。每个人都能很好地意识到健康，除非他麻木不仁或已病入膏肓。即使最迟钝最冷漠的人也会承认健康的愉悦——愉悦不就是快乐的同义词吗？

乌托邦人尤其喜欢精神的快乐，他们认为那是最重要的，并将这种快乐归因于良好的品行和问心无愧。他们最为推崇的肉体上的快乐是健康。当然，他们主张吃饭、喝水以及诸如此类的享受，但这些享受都只是为了促进健康，因为就这些享受本身而言没什么快乐——只是这些是抵御疾病侵袭的方法而已。他们认为，一个明智的人宁愿保持健康而不愿寻医问药；宁愿感受快乐，而不愿寻求安慰。同样，与其沉溺于这种快乐，还不如不要这样的快乐。因为，如果你认为这类事物能使你快乐，那你就得承认你所认为的非常幸福的生活就是不断地饥饿、口渴、发痒，然后不断地吃、喝、擦和挠——这显然会是最不愉快、最令人厌恶的生活。毫无疑问，这些快乐是最低级的快乐，因为它们非常不纯。例如，吃饭的快乐总是伴随着饥饿的痛苦，且两者比例也不平衡——因为痛苦更加强烈也更加持久。它产生于快乐之前，直到快乐和它一同消失它才停止。

所以，除非必要，乌托邦人并不过多追求这类快乐。然而他们也还是享受这种快乐，并对大自然母亲充满感激，因为她鼓励她的孩子成就了日常生活所需的一切美好的事物。试想假使我们每天用来治疗饥渴的东西，就像治疗疾病的苦药一样，生活该多么乏味！

乌托邦人珍视大自然赐予人类的特殊礼物，诸如美丽、强壮以及敏捷。他们也喜欢视觉、听觉和嗅觉上的快乐，这些是人类所特有的——因为其他任何生物都无法领略世界的美好，除寻找食物之外无法闻到任何气味，也不能区别和谐与纷争。他们认为这些是生活的调味品。

然而，他们在这一切事物中遵守这样的规定，不因小快乐而妨碍大快乐，且不因快乐而引起痛苦——他们认为不道德的快乐必然招致痛苦。但是，他们从来不去想象轻视自己的美，损耗自己的体力，把敏捷的身体变得迟钝，用绝食来损坏自己的体魄，毁掉自己的健康，或摒弃大自然的其他任何礼物，除非他们这么做是为了给他人或社会谋福利，期望上帝回报他更大的快乐。因为他们认为以虚假的名声折磨自己是非常荒谬的，这种虚假的名声不能给任何人带来好处，或者是为了锻炼自己，使自己能够抵御永远不会到来的灾难。他们认为这样的行为纯粹是一种自我毁灭，也是对大自然忘恩负义的表现——犹如，拒绝大自然的恩赐是因为不屑于从大自然获得任何东西。

好了，以上就是乌托邦人的道德观，并且，他们认为如果没有神明的启示，人类理智不可能想出更正确的观点。我们没有时间去探究他们的观点正确与否——事实上也没必要去探究，因为我的任务就是描述他们的生活方式，而不是为其辩护。

但有一件事我确信无疑。不管你们对他们的观点抱有什么样的看法，世上再也找不出比他们更繁荣的国家或更优秀的民族。身体上，他们非常敏捷，充满活力，比他们的体型所显示的更加强壮——而你不能说他们个子并不矮小。他们的土地并不很肥沃，而且气候也并不是非常好，但通过平衡的饮食，他们建立起了对恶劣气候状况的抵御机制，并通过精心耕作改善土质。其结果是，乌托邦人打破了粮食和牲畜产量的所有纪录，他们是世界上寿命预期值最高，且发病率最低的。因此，通过科学方法，他们在原本贫瘠的一个国家中创造出了奇迹。他们的才能不仅仅局限在耕作上。你还会发现他们将整座森林连根拔起然后种植到别处，这不是为了增加产量，而是通过将树林种植在靠近海、或河流、或城市，方便木材的运输——因为通过陆路运木材比运粮食更加费劲。那里的人既亲切又聪明，富有幽默感。虽然他们喜欢轻松的生活，但必要时，他们也能参加辛苦的体力劳动。除非他们不怎么喜欢这种劳动——但他们对用脑子的活从不感到厌倦。

我向他们谈起希腊文学和哲学时——由于我不认为拉丁语中有什么让他们特别喜欢的东西——他们非常渴望在我的讲解下学习原作。于是我开始给他们上课，起初只是因为我本不愿拒绝，并没有期望能取得什么成效。但很快我便意识到，有如此勤奋刻苦的学生，我的努力不会白费。他们在字母和发音的学习上毫无困难，记忆东西如此之快，背诵的如此流利，如果不是我知道自愿学习课程的学员都是通过议会批准的成熟的优秀学者，我会觉得这简直是一大奇迹。所以，在不到三年的时间里，他们精通了希腊文，并且，他们能毫不费劲地阅读任何名家的作品，除非原文中有错误。

我推测希腊文和他们的语言有某种相通的地方，所以他们觉得希腊文很容易掌握。要知道，我不禁在想他们肯定是希腊人出身，因为尽管他们的语言更像波斯语，但其中的地名和官名都保留有希腊文的痕迹。我赠送给他们一些希腊书籍——因为在我第四次出航时，我打算长期不返航，也许干脆再也不返航了，所以，我在船上装了满满一大箱子的书，而没装出售的货物。我给了他们许多柏拉图的著作，亚里士多德的著作更多，还有西俄夫拉斯塔斯的关于植物的书——但遗憾的是，这本书被严重损坏了，由于我在航海途中疏于保管，被一只猴子发现，它将书拿去玩耍，东扯掉一页，西扯掉一页，并将它们撕碎了。我带给他们的唯一一本语法书是拉斯卡里斯的，因为我并没有把狄奥多的书带来，而词典我也只给他们带了黑西基阿斯和代俄斯科里提斯的。他们也读普卢塔克的作品，这是他们最喜爱的作家，同时，他们也发现琉善的作品妙趣横生。诗歌方面有以亚里士多芬、荷马、和幼里披底斯为代表的作品——对了，还有索福克里斯的作品——用小号阿尔德排版的，历史方面，有修西得底斯和希罗多德的作品，更不消说赫罗提安的作品了。

我的朋友汤米罗德也带来了一些医学方面的书，有希波格拉底一些短文以及伽林的《小技艺》。乌托邦人很重视这些书，因为，虽然在世界各国中，乌托邦对医药的需求最少，但乌托邦人最尊重医药。他们认为医学是最有意思也是最重要学科中的一种——而且，在他们看来，对自然的探索不仅是一个愉快的过程，更是博得造物主赞许的最佳方式。因为他们设想，造物主就如艺术家一样，将宇宙不可思议的系统呈现在人类面前让人去观察——因为只有人类才有能力理解它——想必造物主一定特别喜欢仔细观察并赞赏他杰作的人，而不是那种对他的杰作视而不见，像低等动物一样在令人惊叹的奇观面前无动于衷的人。

他们通过将经过锻炼的智力运用到各学科，变得非常善于发明各种运用在日常生活中的物品。但是，有两种发明他们还得感谢我们——虽然大部分还是要归功于他们自己。因为当我们给他们看阿尔德用纸张印刷的书，并谈起一些有关印刷和造纸时——由于我们对这两门技术也知之甚少，我们没法对这些做很正确的解释——他们立刻非常聪明地推测出这些是怎么完成的。在那之前，他们只会制造皮革、树皮、或纸草手本，但现在他们立即开始造纸和印刷样本了。一开始他们并不太成功，但经过反复试验之后，他们很快便完全掌握了这两门技术，如果不是缺少原著，他们恐怕早已拥有所有的希腊书籍。实际上，他们只有我刚才提到的那些书，可是他们已经将这些书印刷出版了好几千册。

对于外国游客，如果他们才智出众，或游历过许多不同的国家见多识广，定会受到乌托邦人的热情欢迎。这就是他们如此乐意见到我们的原因，因为他们对世界其他各地所发生的事喜闻乐见。但很少有商人造访乌托邦，因为除了铁之外，乌托邦人没有什么需要进口的，而金银则是商人要从这里带回家的。至于他们自己的出口贸易，他们更愿意自己来运输而不是让外人来取，因为这样能使他们获得更多关于外部世界的经历，同时多锻炼自己的航海技术。

顺便提一下，我偶尔提到的奴隶并不是你们想象的那样，他们不是战俘、不是天生的奴隶或者从别国奴隶市场买来的。乌托邦的奴隶要么是本国犯人，要么更多的是被判刑的外国犯人，他们获得了大批这样的奴隶，有时候是花少量的钱买来的，但通常都是免费要来的。虽然乌托邦的奴隶比外国奴隶受到更严厉的处罚，但这两种奴隶都要戴着镣铐辛苦地劳作。他们的观点是这样的，如果一个受到最优越的教育和非常优秀的道德教育的人仍然要成为罪犯，这是尤其可悲的事——所以理应受到更加严厉的处罚。

另一种奴隶是外国的工人，他们自愿到乌托邦来当奴隶也不愿在自己的国家过悲惨贫困的日子。这些人受到人们的尊重，并和乌托邦的公民享受同等的待遇，只是他们工作辛苦一些，因为他们早已习惯了干重活。如果他们想要离开乌托邦，这种情况不常发生，他们完全有自由离开，还会收到乌托邦人的一件小赠品。

就如我告诉过你们的那样，如果有人生病了，他们会受到最周到的照料，并得到能够帮助恢复健康的各种药物或特殊食物。对于那些患有不治之症的病人，护士会与他们促膝交谈来减轻他们的痛苦，并想尽一切办法来缓解他们的病症。但是，如果病痛不但无药可治，还会使病人受尽病痛的折磨，一些教士和政府官员会去看望病人，并对他们说：

“让我们面对现实吧，你已经无法过正常的生活了。你已成为别人的麻烦和自己的负担——实际上你的存在早已过了死亡期限。这样的话为什么还要让病菌存活下去呢？既然活着对你来说如此痛苦，为什么还要在死亡面前犹豫？你就像被囚禁在酷刑室里一样——为什么你不挣脱并逃到另一个更美好的世界去呢？或者你可以提出要求，我们帮助你得到解脱。这样做是要减轻你的痛苦。这也是听从教士的劝诫的虔诚的行为，因为教士代表上帝的意志。”

如果病人听从这些劝诫，他或者会绝食而死，或者吃点安眠药毫无痛苦地结束他悲惨的生命。但这必须是完全自愿的，而且，如果病人宁愿继续活着，所有人都会一如既往地悉心照料他。官方认可的安乐死被认为是一种光荣的死亡——但是如果你为了教士和议员都认为不够充分的理由而自杀，那么你就没有权利得到安葬或火化，并且你的尸体会被随意抛弃进水塘。

女子在十八岁之前不允许结婚——男子则还要等四年。任何男女在婚前私通都会受到严厉的处罚，而且以后永远没有资格结婚，除非他们得到市长的宽恕。在发生这种事情的家庭里，管事的男女户主也会蒙受耻辱，因为他们没有尽好自己的职责。乌托邦人对这种罪行处罚非常严厉，因为他们认为如果不认真防止婚前性行为，那么很少会有人愿意结婚——结婚意味着和另一半共同生活一辈子，并忍受婚姻生活中的各种麻烦。

当他们考虑结婚时，他们的做法在我们看来非常荒谬，但他们非常严肃的遵循这种做法。不管准新娘是未婚还是寡妇，都会全身裸露，由一位受人尊敬的已婚妇女带到准新郎的面前，同样，新郎也是全身赤裸，由一位适合的男伴带到新娘面前。当我们笑话这样的制度，认为这太愚蠢时，乌托邦人会立刻反过来笑话我们。

他们说：“让我们觉得太奇怪的是其他国家的愚蠢的做法。你在买一匹马时，这件事其实无关紧要，只是需要花点钱而已，你尚且谨慎小心。虽然这只动物几乎是赤裸的，但你仍要取下马鞍和所有挽具确定下面没有任何烂疮才肯付钱。但是在挑选妻子，一个不管怎么样都将陪伴你一生的人时，你却那么不仔细。你甚至连包装都懒得拆开。仅仅从几平方英寸大的脸来评价一个女子的全部，你能看到的就只是她的脸，然后就决定娶她——冒着当你看见真实的她时发现根本就不是你所喜欢的人的风险。如果你只注重美德那当然就不用担心了——但不是所有人都这么明智，而且就算是明智的男人有时也发现，结婚之后，一个美丽的身体可以是对一个美丽灵魂的最有效补充。那些包装确实能够轻易掩盖足以毁掉丈夫对妻子感情的丑陋，但这时候要分开已经来不及了。当然，如果妻子是在婚后才变丑的，丈夫就只能认命——但是人的确需要法律的保护以防在婚姻问题上受骗。”

根据他们的情况，这种预防是很有必要的，因为与他们的邻国不同的是，乌托邦人实行严格的一夫一妻制。对于大多数已婚夫妇而言，只有死亡才会导致他们分离，除非发生通奸行为或者有令对方无法忍受的恶劣行为，这种情况下受害的一方会得到议会的许可另行择偶——有过错的一方则会蒙受耻辱并被罚永远单身。但是如果妻子没有过失，只是身体状况恶化，丈夫不能以此为由离弃妻子。在一个人最需要安慰的时候将其抛弃是非常残忍的，乌托邦人认为，如果允许这种事情的发生，那么人到老年将没有任何安全感，因为年老不仅会导致许多疾病，且年老本身就是一种疾病。

可是，有时候夫妻双方因感情不和，在丈夫和妻子都找到能够使他们幸福的伴侣时，允许他们在双方一致同意的情况下离婚。但是这种情况需要获得特别批准，只有在经过议员和他们的妻子的严格调查之后才能获得批准。即使理由充分且经过了严格的调查，他们也很不愿意批准离婚，因为他们认为，没有什么比轻易离婚更不利于巩固婚姻关系。

通奸者要判苦役。假使双方都已经结婚，那么他们的受害者如果愿意的话可以获得批准离婚并相互结合，或者和自己选择的其他任何人结婚。但是，倘若受害者仍然爱着不值得他们爱的配偶，只要受害者愿意和充当奴隶的配偶一起干活，那么他们就可以继续维持婚姻关系。这种情况下，市长有时会被有罪一方的懊悔和无辜一方的忠贞所感动并让他们都重获自由。但是如果再犯，他将会被处死刑。

在其他罪行方面，法律并没有规定明确的处罚——议会根据每个案件的情况来处以适当的判决。除非是罪行严重到不得不由官方处理，以便于促进社会道德，一般情况下，丈夫有责任惩罚妻子，父母有责任惩罚孩子。对于重罪的处罚通常是充当奴隶。他们认为对于犯人来说，充当奴隶与判处死刑同样可怕，且把他们罚为奴隶比把他们立刻消灭更有利于社会，因为活着的劳力比死了的犯人更有社会价值，并能起到更长久遏制犯罪的作用。然而，如果罪犯胆敢反抗这样的处罚，且不服从任何形式的监狱惩罚，那么他们就会像野兽一般被杀死。那些接受惩罚的人的出路也不是没有任何希望。如果经过多年的艰苦劳作的驯服，他们能够表现出对自己的所作所为真心忏悔而不是为自己感到遗憾，那么或者通过市长的指令，或者全民公决，就可以减轻或完全取消对他们的惩罚。

企图诱奸会受到和实际诱奸同样的处罚。这同样适用于其他任何罪行——任何蓄意犯罪者在法律上都被认定为犯有该罪。乌托邦人认为，蓄意犯罪者并不是由于主观意愿而没有实现犯罪，因此，为何要因为他犯罪未遂而不加追究呢？

乌托邦人很喜欢弱智者，虽然侮辱他们被看作是不合礼貌的举止，但是人们可以从他们愚蠢的行为中获得乐趣。事实上，这被认为是对弱智者更加有益的，因为，如果你没有幽默细胞，欣赏不了他们的言行，那么你显然不适合观赏他们的表演。我的意思是，他们唯一有益的就是娱乐大众，如果你没有把他们当作一种娱乐，你就不可能友善对待他们。

否则你讥笑别人的丑陋或残疾，人们反而会讥笑你。因为如果你认为人们要因自己无能为力的事情受到责备的话，那么你自己就成为了一个十足的蠢人——因为虽然不好好保养天生的美貌被认为是非常懒散的，但是乌托邦人非常不赞同化妆。事实上，经验使乌托邦人发现，比起美丽的外表，丈夫更需要妻子贤淑端庄并对自己恭敬顺从。漂亮的脸蛋或许能够吸引一个男人，但是要得到他的心还需要良好的品性和温顺的脾气。

乌托邦的体制不仅阻止犯罪，而且还以公共荣誉来激励良好的品行。例如，他们在广场上给为社会作出突出贡献的伟人建立雕像，一方面纪念他们的丰功伟绩，另一方面通过对前人荣誉的景仰来激励后代更加奋发上进。但如果有人设法谋取公职，那么他将永远失去资格。乌托邦的社会关系总是和谐友好，因为官员的态度从不傲慢或令人畏惧。百姓通常称官员为“父”，而官员也确实尽到了父母官的职责。人人都尊敬他们，但没有人是被迫这样做的。甚至市长的衣着也极为普通，也没有任何特殊的头饰。唯一显示他是官员的标志是他携带的一束谷穗——就像主教总是拿着一只小蜡烛一样。

他们的法律很少，因为对于他们的社会制度来说，只需要很少的法律就足够了。实际上，他们对于其他国家的最大的抱怨就是，虽然他们已经有了种种法律以及释文，却永远都不够用。因为乌托邦人认为，用普通公民无法通读的冗长而又晦涩的法律条款来约束人们是极不公正的。而且，他们也没有操纵案情、曲解法律的律师。他们认为最好每个人为自己辩护，并直接向法官陈述他本要告知律师的事由。这样一来，问题就不易被掩盖，也更容易找出事实的真相——因为假如没人学律师那样满口谎言，法官就能运用他的聪明才智权衡案件的真相，帮助保护淳朴的人免受狡猾之人肆无忌惮的攻击。

这种制度在其他国家无法实行，因为他们有大量的复杂的法律要处理。但在乌托邦，人人都是法律专家，理由很简单，就像我前面说的，因为他们只有极少的法律，并且他们认为对法律最简洁的解释就是最正确的解释。他们认为法律的唯一目的就是提醒人们应尽的义务，因此，对法律的解释越深奥，法律的作用就越小，因为只有少数人才能理解——然而意思简洁而明了的法律人人都能一目了然。对普通民众来说，即对社会中人数最多且最需要启发的人来说，最好就不要制定法律，因为制定法律之后还要经过一系列巧妙的争辩之后才能得出对法律的解释——对于每天忙于生计的普通百姓来说，他们既没有时间也没有精力来做这样的研究。

由于乌托邦人拥有如此多的美德，许多邻国邀请他们前往担任政府官员，任期一年或五年。当然，这只能发生在人民能够自己当家作主的国家——但乌托邦早已帮助周边的大部分国家摆脱了独裁统治。当这些官员任职期满，他们载誉回国，然后会有其他乌托邦人接替他们的工作。这些国家的举措当然是非常明智的，因为一个国家的安宁完全取决于行政官的品质，而乌托邦人显然是最适合这项工作的。他们不可能收受贿赂徇私枉法，因为他们不久就会回国，金钱对他们来说毫无用处。再者由于他们也不熟悉当地居民，他们也不会受个人喜好影响而作出错误的决定。这些品质对于法官来说尤为重要，因为偏见和贪财是影响法庭公正的两大罪恶，一旦这两种罪恶控制了人的思想，他们就会摧毁公正，破坏社会秩序。

乌托邦人把那些请求他们派遣官员的国家称为“盟邦”，而那些他们曾经以其他形式帮助的国家称为“友邦”。其他国家频繁制定、破坏、又重订条约，但乌托邦人从不签订这样的条约。他们问道，条约有什么用处呢？人类本身不就已经联系在一起了吗？且如果人有意忽视这样的本质上的联系，那么他可能会重视形式上的承诺吗？他们持这种观点主要是因为，在他们这部分世界，国王们并不会谨慎遵守契约和协议。在欧洲，当然，尤其是在基督教盛行的地方，条约是神圣不可侵犯的，一方面因为国王贤明公正，另一方面大家都非常敬重教皇。众所周知，这些教皇不仅自己虔诚地履行自己的职责，而且要求其他所有的统治者无论如何都要遵守诺言，违抗者会受到教会严厉的处罚。显然，他们完全有理由认为，如果连所谓的“忠实信徒”都不信守条约，那是极其恶劣的。

然而在他们那部分世界，不论是社会风俗和道德伦理还是地理位置都与我们这里的世界完全相反的地方，条约根本没有效力。订约越是严肃庄重，毁约也就越快，他们只需找出措辞上的漏洞就能轻易撕毁条约。实际上，这些漏洞通常是故意加在原始条约中，这样一来，不管他们的承诺多么有约束力，他们总是能够设法逃避条约的约束，从而破坏条约，背信弃义。事实是，这种外交手段完全是一直欺诈。如果那些怂恿统治者使用这种欺骗伎俩并引以为傲的人，发现同样的伎俩出现在私人合同中，他们会第一个跳出来尖锐地、自以为是地指责这是亵渎神明、罪该万死的。这似乎意味着，诚实只是平民百姓的美德，远在王权的威严之下——或者说，至少有两种诚实。一种适用于普通民众，一匹蹒跚的驽马，套着牢固的拴绳以防它翻越任何栅栏。另一种，是属于国王的，那是一种比驽马高贵得多的动物，享有比驽马更多的自由——因为它可以做任何想做的事情。

总之，这就是那里国王们的所作所为，正如我说的，这大概就是为什么乌托邦人从不订立条约。也许如果他们住在欧洲的话可能会改变他们的想法——虽然事实上他们不赞成签订条约，但他们却严格遵守约定。他们说条约使得人们视彼此为天敌。住在同一座小山的两侧或同一条河两岸的人似乎就被割断了所有联系，使两个国家毁灭对方的企图正当化，除非有特别的条约禁止。而且即使有这样的条约，也不意味着他们能友好相处，如果条约起草者一时疏忽没有把相关规定纳入条约中，他们就仍会互相掠夺。而乌托邦人的观点恰恰相反。他们认为不应该把从没对你造成伤害的人视为敌人，人性本身就构成了一种条约，人类的善良能比条约更有效地团结在一起，情感比文字更有效。

谈到战争，乌托邦人非常讨厌战争。他们认为战争是不适合人类的活动，虽然人类比任何低等动物都更沉迷于战事。事实上，乌托邦人几乎是世界上唯一不把战争中的任何事情看成荣耀的人。当然，乌托邦的男男女女都要定期参加军事训练，以防一旦需要打仗时无法作战。但他们不会轻易交战，除非需要自卫、击退友邦的侵略者、或者解放独裁统治的受害者——他们这么做是出于人道主义精神，仅仅因为同情他们。然而，乌托邦不但为友邦的自卫战争提供军事援助，也参加反击侵略的讨伐战争。这通常都要事先征得乌托邦人的同意，在他们觉得开战的理由充足，而提出的索赔遭到拒绝，且战争完全由乌托邦人控制的条件下才参战。他们认为，充足的开战理由不仅仅包括军事掠夺。他们甚至采取更强有力的行动来保护在外国受到不公正待遇商人的利益，这些不公正或者由于不公正的法律，或者由于对公正法律的故意曲解。

这就是前不久他们与柏林兰之间的战争的起因。乌托邦人给予格罗迪人军事援助，原因是一些格罗迪商人在柏林兰受到某种法律欺骗——乌托邦人大概这么认为。不论谁对谁错，结果引发了一场大战，由于周边各国的介入，加剧了原本的冲突所带来的怨恨。到战事结束时，一些强国被削弱，其他国家也损失惨重。至于柏林兰人，经历一系列灾难后，他们终于投降了。乌托邦人没有从中获得任何战利品——他们的动机自始至终都是公正无私的——但是柏林兰人沦为了格罗迪人的奴隶，过去格罗迪人的实力根本无法与柏林兰人相提并论。

如你所见，乌托邦人是如何很快就为他们的朋友所受的伤害进行报复的，哪怕只是涉及金钱的问题。但他们对自己所受的伤害却更加容忍。如果乌托邦商人被骗去了货物，但是没有受到人身伤害，那么他们采取的最强硬的行动也只是与该国停止贸易往来，直到他们得到补偿为止。他们这么做不是因为他们更不关心本国人民的利益——只是其他国家的人民更易受到欺骗的伤害，因为那意味着他们损失的是他们自己的私有财产，而乌托邦人在同样的情况下什么个人损失也没有，损失由国家承担。此外，丢失的货物都是国内需求过剩的物资，否则的话他们是绝不会出口的。所以没有人会为这点损失感到难过——而且，他们认为为了一些对任何一个乌托邦人的生命或生活毫无影响的损失去进行报复而杀害许多生命是非常残忍的。但如果致使他们的公民身体残废或丧命，不管是因为外国政府还是因为外国个人，他们的立场就完全不同了。他们一旦通过外交渠道获得这种事故的消息，便会立即宣战。任何形式的让步都不可能息事宁人，除非对方交出为该事件负责的罪犯——这种情况下，罪犯会被处以死刑或被贬为奴隶。

他们不喜欢沾满血腥的胜利——事实上他们觉得那是非常可耻的，因为他们认为花过高的代价去购买任何东西都是很愚蠢的，不论这样东西有多么贵重。他们真正引以为豪的是用智慧战胜敌人。他们用胜利游行来庆祝这样的胜利，并树立胜利纪念碑，为英雄行为记功。你瞧，他们认为了不起的人就是要以人类特有的方式取得胜利，即运用智慧的力量取胜。他们说任何动物都可以靠身体去搏斗——熊、狮子、野猪、狼、狗都能用身体对付敌人，而且这些野兽大多数比人类更加强壮更加凶猛——但是人类的理性和智慧使人类比野兽更高级。

他们发动战争只是为了达到用和平手段无法达到的目的——或者，既然非作战不可，他们就要严厉处罚侵犯者，使任何人不敢再犯。他们用速战速决来达到这些目的——但是一切以自身安全第一，国家声望第二为原则。一经宣战，他们通过特工人员在敌人境内一些显眼的地方同时张贴大量公告。这些公告上盖有乌托邦政府的公章，对杀死敌国国王者有重赏。他们对杀死公告名单中其他人员也提供了次等但也很可观的大笔奖金，因为他们是仅次于国王的反乌托邦政策的主要支持者。活捉这些人的奖金是杀死他们的一倍——若是被捕的人员反过来对付自己的伙伴，乌托邦也向他们提供同样丰厚的奖金，并给他们自由。

这样做的直接结果就是名单里提到的每个人都变得草木皆兵，他们互相猜疑，互不信任。他们长期处在恐惧状态中，这完全是事出有因的——因为听说所有的敌人，包括国王自己也被身边最信任的人出卖。事实上，有钱能使鬼推磨，而乌托邦人准备的金钱是没有限数的。考虑到反水者的风险，乌托邦人会谨慎地给予他们相应的利益作为补偿。所以，除了大量的黄金之外，乌托邦人还允诺在安全友好的邻邦给予价值不菲的房产——且乌托邦人向来信守承诺。

这种贿赂买通敌人的方法通常被认为卑鄙而残忍的，但乌托邦人认为这是值得夸耀的。他们认为能够不费一兵一卒而解决这样一场大战是非常明智的，且牺牲少数有罪之人来拯救数以千计的无辜生命也是最为仁慈的。他们为所有可能战死沙场的士兵着想，即考虑自己这一方，也考虑对方——因为他们既同情本国的人民，也同样同情敌方的人民。他们认识到如果不是被他们的统治者的疯狂所迫，他们是绝不会投入战争的。

如果这种方法失败，乌托邦人就会通过鼓动国王的兄弟或其他王亲贵族觊觎王位而使敌人内部产生不和。如果内部不和有消失的迹象，他们就翻出某些陈年旧账，国王们从不缺乏此类劣迹，进而引发一些邻国的敌意。他们承诺在战争中对倒戈者给予支持，并提供充足的金钱和少许人力——因为他们彼此非常珍爱，不愿意牺牲任何一个乌托邦公民，即使用一个公民去换敌国的国王，他们也不干。但他们更乐意把黄金白银拿出来，因为储存金银就是为了应战，且他们知道即使他们把金银都花光也丝毫不会影响他们的生活水平。此外，除了国内的资金外，他们还拥有大量国外资产，因为，正如我上面所说，很多国家都欠他们债。

因此，乌托邦的大多数战争都是由雇佣兵去打。他们从世界各地招募雇佣兵，特别是从一个叫维纳利亚的地方，这是个离乌托邦东面五百英里的地方。维纳利亚人非常野蛮而又凶残——他们喜欢他们生长的原始森林和险峻的山地。他们身强体壮，耐热耐寒且不怕身体上的劳苦。他们完全不知道快乐为何物，从来不会耕作，且对衣着和住房也同样随意。除了寻找战事之外，他们多以打猎和偷窃为生。事实上，他们似乎天生合适打仗。他们总是寻求打仗的机会，当他们找到了机会，只要提供微薄报酬，他们就成千上万的去为任何一个需要士兵的国家服务。因为杀戮是他们唯一懂得的谋生方法。

他们对雇主忠心耿耿，但不能保证他们会持续多久。他们加入你第二天就可能加入你的敌人一方，只要对方出更高的佣金，假如给得价钱更高一点，再过一天他们又会回来。在许多战争中，你都会发现双方的士兵中有许多都是维纳利亚人。因此你能想象到会发生什么样的事情。同一个家庭的两个成员应征在同一军队。他们忽而是最要好的朋友——忽而又互相敌对并像死敌一样对峙。他们忘记所有的血缘亲情和友谊并拼命互相残杀。他们互相消灭的唯一动机就是不同的国王付给他们的一点点金钱——金钱对他们来说非常重要，因此一天多给半便士就足以使他们倒戈相向。但虽然他们很快便贪婪成性，却没得到半点好处，因为他们把流血杀生挣来的钱立刻投入堕落肮脏的生活。

这些人愿意为乌托邦对抗世界上任何国家，因为世上再没有谁愿意付这么多钱给他们。你瞧，乌托邦人既善于雇用好人，也热衷于发掘并利用坏人。所以必要时他们就用丰厚的赏金来引诱维纳利亚人去从事疯狂的事情，去做这样的事情的人多数都再也没命回来索要他们的酬劳。但那些完成任务的人都能领取到全部酬金，这样他们会觉得值得因而将来会再次冒险。因为乌托邦人不在乎有多少维纳利亚人为他们送命。他们说，要是他们能够将那些肮脏的糟粕从地球上完全清除掉，他们就能给人类带来一个很好的转变。

乌托邦的第二人力来源于他们为维护其利益而作战的国家。其次就是其他友邦，最后是乌托邦自己的公民，并从自己的公民中选出一位经过考验的有能力者指挥联合军队。他们还在指挥官身边安排另外两人，在指挥官一切安好时，他们没有什么特殊职责。但如果指挥官被杀或被俘，这两人中之一就继任指挥官的职位——且，如果情况需要，另一个人再接替。这就可以在战场发生偶然变化，即使将军遇到什么情况，都能确保不会使整个军队陷入无组织的混乱状态。

乌托邦分遣队是由各个城市的志愿者组成的——因为没有人会被招募到国外去服役。他们认为胆怯的人不仅不可能成为好士兵，还可能削弱身边同伴的士气。但是，如果有入侵，只要身体强健，这些胆怯的人也会被编入海军在可靠的人员身边，或者安排他们在城墙上服役，这样他们就没有机会逃跑。当他们真的与敌人交锋，他们碍于公众舆论，加上无路可逃，通常会战胜自己的恐惧并在绝境中像英雄一样战斗。

但是没有人会被强迫去海外参战，同样，妻子如果愿意跟随丈夫到前线，也不会被迫待在家中。相反，这样的事是受到鼓励和赞扬的。这些妻子会立即被安排在她们在战场上的丈夫身边，孩子和其他亲戚也都会安排在他身边。他们认为，那些有最强烈本能互相帮助的人会紧密团结在一起并能够渡过难关。如果丈夫回来失去了妻子，或妻子回来失去了丈夫，又或是孩子回来失去了父母，都会是极大的耻辱。这意味着一旦上了战场，如果敌人有意负隅顽抗，他们就要战斗到底。只要能够用雇佣军作战，乌托邦人就尽量避免本国公民参战，但如果最终被迫战斗，他们的勇猛也不亚于他们之前的谨慎。

他们不是一开战就猛烈战斗，但是渐渐地，随着战事的发展，他们会变得越来越坚决，宁死也寸土不让。他们知道不必为家人的生计担心，也不用为孩子的未来担忧——这两项担忧往往会瓦解战士的斗志——这使得他们斗志高昂，志在必胜。他们接受的军事训练也大大增加了他们的信心。最后，从小受他们的教育和社会环境的影响所禀受的坚定信念也增强了他们的勇气。这确保了他们会珍惜生命，不会轻率地牺牲自己，但应该放弃生命时也不会苟且偷生。

在战事激烈时，会有一群经过精心选拔并发誓团结一致的青年设法消灭敌军首领。他们不断尝试各种方法干掉他——正面攻击，埋伏突袭，远程射击，近身搏斗。他们从远处冲向他不停地以楔形队形攻击，在点上的人不断更换，这样就会不断有新人来替代精疲力竭的人。这样一来，对方的首领不是被杀就是被捕——除非他能逃跑保命。

如果乌托邦人打了胜仗，他们不会大肆屠杀。他们宁可俘虏败兵也不会残杀逃兵。他们还定下了这样的规则，除非他们至少有一列队伍保有战斗队形，否则绝不追击。他们在一方面非常严格，假如在援军到达之前他们没能打胜仗，他们宁可让整个敌军都逃脱也不会开先例为追击而打乱队列。你知道，他们仍然记得自己多次用过的策略。每当乌托邦的主力军被击败，敌军得意扬扬地四处追赶掉队散兵时，这时候整个战局就会被事先埋伏好的少数乌托邦战士所扭转。他们寻找机会对四散的敌军突然袭击，由于敌军这时以为自己是安全的，所以毫无防备。因此，很多次胜利都是从敌人手中强夺过来的，从而反败为胜。

很难说是他们的攻击策略巧妙，还是他们的防御策略更巧妙。你可能以为他们要撤退，但这却是他们最后才考虑的事——当他们真正要撤退时，你可能想都没有想到他们会这么做。当他们觉得兵力严重不足或地势对他们不利时，他们会在夜间悄无声息地撤退或用其他方法迷惑敌军。不然他们就在白天撤军，但撤退时，他们秩序井然，且保持着完美的队列，在撤退时攻击他们和在行进时攻击他们一样危险。

他们的战营总是防御森严，用又深又宽的壕沟来加强防御，用壕沟里挖出的土从内侧筑起壁垒。他们不会用奴隶来做这项工作，而是士兵自己来做，军队中除了少数在壁垒前站岗以防突发状况的哨兵之外，所有的士兵共同完成。由于人手充足，他们高效完成如此巨大的防御工程，速度之快令人难以置信。

他们的盔甲非常的坚固，足以提供充分的保护，但是又适合身体的各种活动。这种盔甲甚至还能穿着游泳——事实上他们从军事训练起始期就接受了身着盔甲游泳的训练。他们所使用的远程武器是箭，骑兵和步兵都是训练有素，挽弓有力，射箭精准的好手。打近身战时，他们不用刀剑，而是用战斧，因为这种战斧沉重而又锋利，用来砍杀和刺杀都同样具有杀伤力。他们还发明和制造了具有独创性的机械武器，且在使用之前绝对保密——否则如果这些武器可能被看作笑话而降低了使用效果。在研发这些设备时，他们特别考虑设备携带方便和易于操作。

他们一旦签订了休战协议，无论别人如何煽动，也从不破坏协议。他们从不蹂躏敌国的领土，或烧毁他们土地上的谷物——因为他们把这些谷物视为对自己有益的事物，所以他们尽力确保这些谷物不被他们的骑兵或步兵践踏。他们从不伤害手无寸铁的民众，除非他是间谍。他们对任何投降的城市都加以保护，即使是他们攻占的城市，也不洗劫。他们只处死那些反对投降的头目，而剩下的守卫则贬为奴隶。对所有的民众则毫发不动。如果得知任何人曾建议投降，他们就会将被判死刑或贬为奴隶的人的财产分一部分给这些人。其余的就赠送给盟军——因为乌托邦没有任何一个人分取战利品。

战争结束后，他们不要求使他们破费的友邦支付费用，而是要求战败国来支付。他们要求支付一部分现金，留作下一次战争的储备，一部分索要敌国境内具有自由保有权的不动产。因此他们在很多不同的国家都获得了财产，由此获得的收入，由各种来源逐渐组成的收入已经多达每季度三十二万七千英镑。他们派出一些乌托邦公民到这些国家去充当收租人，但实际上是去过豪华的生活并成为当地的显贵。但仍有充足的资金充盈国库，除非他们愿借给所在的国家，他们经常借给这些国家，在他们自己需要用钱的时候——即使这样的情况下他们也很少全部要回。他们将这些财产中的一部分送给那些曾经被他们劝服去做我之前提过的实施冒险之举的人。

如果有哪个国王想交战，企图侵占乌托邦的领土，他们会派出大量军力将他拦截在境外——因为如果可以，他们从不在自己的土地上开战，而且不管在任何情况下，他们都不会允许盟军进驻本岛。

最后，我想给你们说说他们的宗教思想。岛上有几种不同的宗教，事实上，每个城镇的宗教都不同。有人崇拜日神，有人崇拜月神，还有人崇拜其他各种星辰。有人不仅把一些伟大的或优秀的先贤奉为神明，甚至尊为至高无上的神。然而，绝大多数人的观念更加理智，他们认为只有某一个单一的神，这个神是未知的、永恒的、无限的、奥妙无穷的、人类智慧无法理解的，他以一种威力而不是以物质的形式存在于整个宇宙之中。他们称这种力量为“万物之父”。他们将万物的起源与结束、生长、发展和演变都归功于他。除了他，乌托邦人不承认任何形式的神明。

在这一点上，诚然，所有不同的教派都意见一致——即只有一个至高无上的神，他是宇宙的创造者和主宰者，且用乌托邦的语言中他们一致称它为“密特拉”（Mythras）。他们所不一致的就是密特拉是谁。有人说是这个，有些人又说是那个——但所有人都坚称自己的至高无上的神明就是大自然，所有的民族都承认它的伟大力量是万事万物的唯一起源。然而，乌托邦人在所有的低等信仰上有渐行渐远的趋势，并一致接受了最合理的一种信仰。且毫无疑问，若不是人们用迷信来解释厄运，其他信仰本来早就消失了，当有人考虑更换信仰时遭到厄运，他们不认为这是巧合，而把这当作是遭到天谴——仿佛是被放弃的神明在惩罚他们的不忠。

但当我们给他们讲述基督，基督的教义，他的品行，他的奇迹，以及同样令人惊叹的殉道者的奉献，他们甘愿流血牺牲，使得许多国家皈依基督教，你想象不到使他们皈依基督教竟也如此容易。也许他们下意识地受到了某些神秘灵感的感召，又或许是基督教和他们自己的宗教原则颇为相似——虽然我应该想到他们是知道基督规定他的门徒共同生活的故事，且这种生活方式在那些最虔诚的基督教国家仍在实行，这使他们受到了很大影响。无论如何，不管作何解释，很多乌托邦人接受了我们的宗教信仰，并接受了洗礼。

可惜我们四个人中没有一个是教士——是的，只有我们四个人幸存——其他两人已经死去。所以，虽然他们已经履行了其他所有的宗教仪式，但我们的皈依者还未能接受只有教士才能主持的圣礼。但他们已经了解了有关教士的事宜，并希望由他们来实行圣礼，这比世界上任何事情都急迫。事实上，眼下他们正在热烈讨论在未派来基督教主教来主持仪式的情况下，是否可以从他们中间选出一个人任命为教士。看来他们肯定要推选出一名候选人来担任这项职务，虽然在我们离开之前他们还没有选出来。

当然，有许多乌托邦人拒绝接受基督教，但即使这样，他们并不阻止别人接受这一信仰，也不会侵犯已经皈依基督的人——我在当地的时候，却有一名我们公理会的成员因此陷入了麻烦。他刚接受洗礼，尽管我们劝诫过他，他仍公开发表有关基督教义的演说，他的狂热超过了谨慎。最后他情绪太过激动，不但声称基督教是最好的宗教，甚至还谴责其他宗教。他不断高声咆哮，说其他宗教都是邪恶的迷信，而信仰这些宗教的人是亵渎神明的怪物，将永远在地狱中受火刑。由于他多次这样做，最后终于被捕并遭到控告，控告理由不是亵渎神明，而是制造骚乱扰乱和平。他被证明有罪并处以流放——因为乌托邦最古老的法律原则之一就是宗教自由。

这条原则要追溯到当年诺曼人征服英国的时候。那时一直为宗教争吵不休，且各个冲突的教派无法联合起来保卫他们的国家。乌托普得知他们这样之后，认识到他之所以能够征服他们所有人的原因所在。所以他取得胜利之后就立刻制定了法律，规定每个人都能够自由信仰他喜欢的宗教，也可以规劝别人皈依自己的宗教，但是要求温和礼貌的方式通过合理的劝说使其皈依。如果他劝说失败，绝不允许对其他的宗教进行尖刻的攻击，也不能使用暴力或谩骂他人。在宗教问题上争斗过于激烈的人，通常会受到流放或贬为奴隶的处罚。

乌托普制定这样的法律，不仅为了维护和平，防止无休止的争辩和不可调和的斗争将和平破坏殆尽，而且还因为他认为这对宗教本身也是有利的。他不断言哪种信条是正确的。显然他认为或许上帝使不同的人信仰不同的事物，因为上帝希望人们以不同的方式崇拜他。但他非常确信，强迫人人接受自己的信条是非常愚蠢又傲慢的。但他明显非常确定，即使只有一种宗教是真理，其他宗教都没有什么意思，真理最终会靠自身的力量战胜一切——只要能用温和理性的方式来讨论问题。但如果是由暴力解决问题，即使是最好最神圣的宗教也会沦为最愚蠢的迷信，就像谷物容易生长过旺于灌木和荆棘之中——因为最坏的人往往总是最顽固不化的。

因此乌托普将信仰选择作为一个尚未解决的问题，让人民根据自己的意志决定自己的信仰——除了他严格而又庄重地禁止他们的人民相信任何违背人尊严的事物，例如相信灵魂随肉体消亡的信条，和宇宙是无目的运行且不受神意志支配的信条。这就是为什么他们确信人死之后会有因果报应。在他们看来，任何持不同观点的人都将丧失作为人的资格，因为他将自己不朽的灵魂降低到和动物的躯体同一水平。他们更不把这种人看作是乌托邦的公民。他们说这样的人对乌托邦的生活方式毫不在乎——只是他们不敢这样说。理所当然地，如果一个人除了法律对任何事物都无所忌惮，且对死后也没有任何期盼，他就会为了满足自己的私欲逃避或践踏国家的法律。所以任何怀有这样的信条的人都不允许获得任何公众荣誉，担任任何公职或为任何公共机关服务。事实上，这样的人通常都被视为极其卑劣的。

但这些人不管怎样都不会受到处罚，因为没有人会因为信仰受到处罚。他们也不会被威胁隐瞒自己的观点，因为乌托邦人完全不能容忍虚伪，他们认为虚伪就等同于欺骗。无可否认，任何人争辩维护自己的信仰都是违法的，但也只是在公共场合才违法。但是在与教士或其他严肃人物的私下讨论中允许甚至积极鼓励他为自己的观点申辩，因为大家坚信，这种谬见最终要为理性让步。

甚至有些乌托邦人——实际上有不少人——远远偏离了唯物主义，走向了另一个极端。当然，没有法律禁止他们，因为他们的观点也有一定的道理，且这些人本身也都非常正派。这些人认为动物也有不朽的灵魂，虽然动物的灵魂比人类的灵魂要低级得多，且注定只能得到比人类更低等的幸福。几乎人人都深信，人类在另一个世界会得到无尽的幸福，虽然他们总是为伤病感到遗憾，但他们从不哀悼死亡——除非死者显然非常不安和不愿意离开人世。他们认为这是非常不祥之兆。似乎暗示着这个人的灵魂意识到了自己的罪恶，且因预感到即将到来的惩罚而沮丧——所以对死亡感到恐惧。此外，他们认为如果一个人不是欣然从命听从上帝的召唤，而是极不情愿地被迫来到上帝面前，上帝未必会乐意见到他。所以，他们害怕见到这样的死亡，并在悲伤中默默地举行葬礼。他们只是说“愿上帝宽恕他的灵魂，原谅他的软弱”，然后他们就埋葬他的尸体。

但是当有人在高高兴兴而又乐观的气氛中死去，没有人会为他哀悼。他们在他的葬礼上欢快地歌唱，并满怀爱意地将他的灵魂交托给上帝。最后，更多的是怀着敬意而不是悲伤，他们将尸体火化，并在死者的坟前立碑，在碑上刻上墓志铭。然后他们回到家后，讲述死者的品质和事迹，但他们最乐于谈论的还是他临死前的怡然从容的精神状态。他们认为，以这种方式纪念死者良好品行，不仅是鼓励生者效仿其美德的最好的方法，也是死者最乐于接受的敬意——因为人们谈论死者时，死者就与他们同在，虽然肉眼看不见他。毕竟，享受天堂之乐的灵魂意味着拥有绝对的行动自由，且任何有感情的人都不会不想在死后回来看望他的好友，如果他在生前与他们有过真挚的友谊。反之，乌托邦人认为一个善良的人友爱的能力犹如他身上其他美好的品质一样，在死后不会消失反而会增强。所以，乌托邦人认为死者会自由自在地存在于生者当中，目睹生者的一言一行。其实乌托邦人几乎认为死者是守护天使，这使得他们在处理问题时更具信心。而且，由于觉得他们的祖先在身边，他们也就不敢私下做任何亏心事。

他们不关心预兆、占卜，或在其他国家相当盛行的任何迷信活动。事实上他们把这些迷信当笑话看待。但他们非常崇拜那些不是由自然原因引起的奇迹，因为他们将这些奇迹看作上帝显灵和能力的证明。他们说乌托邦常有这样的奇迹发生。甚至，在危急关头，举国上下都会祈求发生奇迹，且他们的信念如此强烈，有时还真有求必应。

大部分乌托邦人觉得通过研究自然世界，赞美上帝的杰作，就能够取悦上帝。但一大部分人由于宗教的引导，他们并不追求知识。他们对科学不感兴趣——他们只是没有工夫去研究这些事，因为他们认为要在死后获得幸福就必须用一辈子去行善。他们有的照顾老弱病残，而其他人有的修路，有的清理沟渠，有的改造桥梁，有的挖除杂草砂石，有的砍树劈柴，或者将柴粮等物资运送到城镇去。总之，他们做事像仆人一样卖力，且工作比奴隶还要更加辛苦，不仅为公家干活是这样，给私人干活也是这样。他们欣然接受所有粗活、脏活和各种苦差事，一般人对这些活都避之不及，或者觉得过于劳累，或者因为厌恶这些工作，或者觉得根本无法完成。因此他们不停地劳作，让别人享受清闲——而他们却不以此居功。他们从不贬低别人的生活方式或夸耀自己的生活方式。因此他们越是像奴隶一般劳作，就越受到人们的尊敬。

这类人分为两派，其中一派是独身主义。他们都是绝对的禁欲主义者，不仅戒除性行为，还戒除肉食，且在某些情况下戒除所有的动物性食品。他们放弃所有的生活乐趣，因为他们认为那是有罪的，而只向往来世。为了来世的快乐，他们辛苦流汗，日夜劳作——但这样的来世即将到来的希望使得他们生活得热忱而又积极。另一派人，虽然同样热衷于辛勤劳作，但他们赞成婚姻，因为他们不轻视婚姻带来的安乐。且他们认为生殖繁育是对自然也是对国家应尽的责任。他们不反对享乐，只要不影响工作就行。在这一原则上，他们大量的吃肉，因为他们认为吃肉能使他们更有力气干辛苦的工作。乌托邦人认为这类人更加睿智，而另一类人则更加虔诚。当然，如果第一派人以理性为由为他们的行为辩护，他们只会遭到嘲笑。但既然他们承认他们是出于宗教的动机而不是理性使然，乌托邦人则会对他们充满敬意——因为乌托邦人总是小心翼翼，从不在宗教问题上妄下论断。这一派人在他们的语言中被称为考帕森（Cowparson），可粗略译为笃信宗教的世俗同胞。

乌托邦人的教士都是极其虔诚的，这意味着他们中只有极少数的人——通常每个城镇十三个，或每个教会一个。但在战时，这十三名教士中的七名要随军出征，而由另外七名教士暂时代替他们的职位。出征的牧师回来后，就恢复了原来职位，而临时教士就任主教的侍从——因为原来十三名教士中就有一名任这一职务——直到原任在职主教身故他们才能一个一个的继任空缺职位。

教士是由全民选举出来的。就像所有的公职一样，选举采取无记名投票的形式，以防结党营私，选举胜出的候选人会由他的同僚授予圣职。教士的职责是主持教会事务、组织宗教活动、监察社会道德。被教会法庭传唤或因行为恶劣被教士训斥被看作是奇耻大辱。当然，对罪行真正的镇压和惩罚是市长和其他政府机构的职责。教士只是进行劝诫和警告——虽然他们可以将屡犯开除教籍，几乎没有什么惩罚比这让人害怕。你瞧，被开除教籍的人不仅颜面尽失，内心也会受到害怕圣神复仇的折磨。他的人身安全也会受到威胁，因为除非他能尽快使教士相信他已经悔改，否则将以不虔诚的罪名被议会逮捕并受到惩罚。

教士还负责教育儿童和青少年，这种教育不仅注重知识的培养，同样也注重道德的培养。他们尽量确保在孩子易受影响的阶段向他们传输正确的观点——这种观点最有利于维护他们的社会结构。如果这些观念能够在儿童时期被完全接受，那么这些观念将会伴随他们一生，从而极大地促进社会安定，没有什么比错误的观点引发的道德缺陷更加严重威胁社会安定。

男教士允许结婚——因为没有什么能够阻止女性成为教士，虽然很少有女性当选这个职务，且只有年长的寡妇才有资格。事实上，教士的妻子是全国最优秀的女性，因为没有什么公众人物比教士更受人尊敬。人们如此尊敬教士，以至于即使教士犯了罪，他也可能不会被控告。人们只是将他交由上帝和他自己的良心来裁决，因为，乌托邦人认为，不论教士做了什么，都不应由人类逮捕他，因为他已经将自己献给上帝了。乌托邦人发现这项规则很容易遵守，因为教士人数很少，且都是经过非常慎重才选出来的。毕竟，一个从优秀的候选人当中选拔出来的人，且他所任命的职位也是完全因为他高尚的道德品质，这样的人会突然堕落腐化是不太可能的。即使我们不得不接受这样的可能性——人性是如此的不可预测，极少数毫无实权的人几乎不能对社会构成任何严重危害。他们减少教士的数量，以免由于享有这份荣誉的人数泛滥而降低他们任职的崇高声望——尤其是如他们所说，要物色很多适合这个职位的人并非易事，因为这个职位要求有高尚道德而不是有普通修养就行。

乌托邦教士在国外的声望和在国内一样高。我想从战场上发生的事中能够找到这样的例证和原因。当战争正在进行，教士跪在不远处，身披法衣，伸出双手朝天。他们首先祈求和平，然后祈求在不流血的情况下乌托邦能取得胜利——双方都不流血的情况下。当乌托邦军队占了上风，教士就会立刻赶到战场阻止任何滥杀无辜的行为。如果教士出现在战场，敌军只要向他呼救就能保住性命，如果他能触摸到教士飘扬的法衣，不仅能够保住性命，还能使他的财产也免受战争摧毁。这使得教士在各个国家都赢得了尊重，且获具有真正的威严，他们往往既能够保护本国的士兵又能保护敌国的士兵。有时，当乌托邦士兵全线溃退，而敌军又紧追不舍，要对他们进行屠杀和洗劫时，教士介入就避免一场杀戮，他将战士分离开来，从而得以签署公正的和约。所有的国家，且即使是最野蛮最残暴的民族都将乌托邦的教士视为神圣而不可侵犯的。

乌托邦在每月和每年的第一天和最后一天定为宗教节日——顺便说一下，他们的日历是根据太阳年，划分阴历月。在他们的语言中他们将每月的第一天称为多格德，每月的最后一天称为特德斯——换句话说，就是开始的节日和结束的节日。

他们的教堂最令人印象深刻，不仅仅因为它们建得如此美轮美奂，还因为雄伟壮观。你知道，由于教堂并不多，他们必需能够容纳许多人才行。但是，它们光线不足，他们告诉我这并不是建筑失误，而是有意为之。因为教士认为太多的光线会分散人们的注意力，昏暗的光线能够使人集中精力并促进虔诚。乌托邦不止一种宗教，虽然他们的方式各不相同，但目标却是一致的，即崇拜神明。因此他们的教堂内没有与各种宗教相冲突的事物。任何独特的宗教仪式都在家中举行，而公共场合的礼拜也井然有序，绝不会与各个宗教相抵触。

在这一原则下，他们的教堂中不设神像，因此人人都能根据自己最喜欢的宗教，随意将其想象成他所选择的任何形态。他们也没有对神有什么特殊的称呼。只是称之为密特拉，一个人们普遍称呼神明的称谓，不论是什么神。同样，没有什么祈祷文会损害教会中某些人的特殊信仰。

在结束的节日，他们整日斋戒，夜晚他们聚集在教堂，感谢神让他们幸运度过这一年或这一个月。第二天，即开始的节日，他们清早聚集在教堂，祈祷在新的一年或新的月份里能幸福繁荣。但是在结束的节日，他们赶赴教堂之前，在家中，妻子会跪在丈夫面前，孩子会跪在父母面前，为自己所有的疏忽和过错忏悔并祈求原谅。这样一来，就能够消除弥漫在家庭中小小的怨恨，这样，人人都能带着绝对纯净的心灵参加祭礼。因为心中带着烦闷参加祭礼被认为是亵渎神明的。所以，任何人如果明显对别人感到愤怒或怨恨，在参加祭礼之前必须和那人言归于好，并使自己不愉快的情绪得到净化，以免立即遭到严厉的惩罚。

他们进入教堂后，男人转向右边，女人转向左边，座位都安排得井然有序，每家每户的男性都坐在他们的父亲前面，而母亲也坐在女子的后面。这样就确保了在家管束子女的家长在公共场合也能监督子女的行为。他们也特别注意，年轻人必须和年长的坐在一起——因为孩子们待在一起定会嬉戏打闹，但这时应该是他们对神敬畏的时刻，即使不是唯一的时机，也是激发他们良好德行的最佳时机。

他们从不宰杀动物来献祭，因为他们认为，仁慈的上帝不会喜欢看到杀戮和流血的。他们说上帝给了万物生命，是因为上帝有好生之德。但他们供奉一些烧祭品——焚香或其他芳香物品，并点燃许多蜡烛。他们当然很清楚，神并不需要这些香烛，但他们认为这种献祭方式并无害处，且他们觉得这些芳香和烛光以及其他仪式能够不可思议地提高人的思想境界，使他们更加虔诚膜拜神明。

人们身着白衣参加圣会，而教士则穿着彩色的法衣，做工细致，设计精美，但是由廉价的布料制作——既不是金线织成，也没有镶嵌宝石，是用各种鸟羽装饰。另一方面，这些法衣作为艺术品的价值远远超过了世界上最值钱的材料。此外，这些羽毛编织成象征着神圣真理的特殊图案，且教士对这些象形文字的意义作详细的解说，因为他们要让人们想起上帝对他们的恩泽，以及他们对上帝和彼此的职责。

身着这样法衣的教士从圣堂出来时，所有人都恭敬地跪在地上，整个教堂鸦雀无声。这种气氛令人敬畏，人们似乎能够感觉到神明显灵。不一会儿，教士指示他们起立。然后他们就伴随着乐器演奏的音乐唱起赞美诗，他们的乐器与我们的大不相同。大部分乐器的旋律比我们的更加悦耳，虽然有些乐器无法与欧洲的乐器相提并论。但是在某一点上，毫无疑问他们远胜过我们。他们所有的音乐，不论是声乐还是乐器，都很好表达出自然的情感。演奏出的音乐都能很好适应现场气氛，无论是祈祷还是庆祝，激动还是平静，悲伤还是愤怒，它们的旋律都能恰如其分地表达出适当的情感。因而能够深深打动听众的心灵，使人们的内心受到极大鼓舞。

仪式以教士和教众一起朗诵祈祷文而结束。祈祷的经文措辞使得一起朗诵的每一个人都能将其应用到自己的身上。祈祷经文大致是这样：

神啊，你是我的创造者，我的主宰，是一切美好事物的源泉。感谢神的恩泽，尤其感谢神让我生在世上最幸福的国度，并信仰最虔诚的宗教。如果是我弄错了，如果还有其他更好的宗教或社会制度是神更加赞许的，请求神让我知道，因为我愿意跟随神的引导。但如果我们的制度的确是最好的，我所信仰的宗教也是最虔诚的，那么请让我对它们忠贞不移，并让其他所有人也过和我一样的生活，拥有同样的信仰——除非现存各种不同的信仰时神难以捉摸的意志。请求神让我轻松的离世，向神皈依。我不敢奢求这样的解脱来得早还是晚。但如果是神的旨意，我宁愿以最痛苦的方式解脱以便早日向神皈依，也不愿过最快乐的世俗生活而离神如此遥远。

念完这些祈祷文之后，他们再次跪拜片刻，之后才起身走开用餐。这一天剩余的时间就用于娱乐和军事训练。

好了，我已经力求准确地向你们描述了乌托邦理想国了。在我看来，它不仅是世界上最好的国家，而且是唯一有资格被称为理想国的国度。在别的国家，虽然人们总是谈论公共利益，但所有人关心的都只是个人利益。在乌托邦，不存在私有财产，人们都认真履行公共义务。而这两种情形都合情合理。在其他“共和国”，几乎人人都知道，如果人不为自己打算，他就会活活饿死，无论他的国家是多么繁荣。因此他会将自己的私人利益凌驾于国家利益之上，也就是放在别人的利益之上。但是在乌托邦，一切都是公共所有，只要公共仓库充盈，就没有人会担心缺少什么。人人都能得到公平的分配，因而从来都没有穷人或乞丐。人人都一无所有，但人人又都很富裕——因为有什么财富能比得上愉快、平静的心灵和无忧无虑的生活？不被衣食之忧所困扰，也不被妻子的苦苦哀求所烦扰，不怕儿子会贫困，不用为女儿的嫁妆发愁，乌托邦人有绝对的把握，他、他的妻子、他的孩子、他的孙子、他的曾孙、他的玄孙，以及无穷无尽的后代都能过上丰衣足食、幸福无忧的生活。人们另外还想到，那些上了年纪因而丧失劳动能力的人也应受到和劳动者同样的待遇。

现在，有人敢将乌托邦的公平制度和其他国家所谓的公平作个比较吗？——如果我能看到一丝一毫的公正和公平就真是活见鬼了。这算什么公正呢？贵族、金匠或高利贷者要么无所事事，要么做些毫无必要的事，对这种人的懒惰和无益之功却报以豪华奢侈的生活。而像驽马一样不停地辛勤工作的劳动者、车夫、木匠、农场工人，他们从事如此重要的工作，假使他们罢工，用不了一年，任何国家都会停止运转——他们又是什么境遇呢？他们食不果腹，过着悲惨的生活，甚至连牛马都不如。然而，至少牛马还不用工作这么长时间，吃的也还不错，味道也更可口，也不用为未来担心。实际上，他们不仅现在不得不一无所获地劳累受苦，也不禁为受贫困潦倒的老年而发愁——因为他们的日薪连一天的开支都无法维持，更谈不上存钱养老了。

在所谓的贵族、金匠这些游手好闲或只会从事奢侈和娱乐之事的人身上浪费大量金钱，而对社会存在和发展不可或缺的农场工人、矿工、劳动者、车夫或木匠却没有这样的待遇，这样的社会有何公平和感恩可言？当这些人又老又病，穷困潦倒时，这种忘恩负义简直达到了极点。在利用完他们的大好青春之后，社会却忘记他们不眠不休的服务，对他们所作的重要贡献的回报就是任由他们悲惨死去。不仅如此，富人还要剥削穷人微薄的收入，不仅用私下欺诈的方式，还利用公共法令巧取豪夺。似乎为社会贡献最多的人就理所应当得到最少的回报，他们甚至更加恶劣，还制定法律把不公平冠以公平之名。

事实上，我在细想当今世界上所有盛行的社会制度时，我敢断言，我所见到的都是富人在管理社会的名义下牟取私利的阴谋。他们想出各种诡计和托词，首先是保存自己的不义之财，然后就用最廉价的工钱榨取穷人的劳动。一旦富人决定这些诡计和托词应该正式得到社会的认可——包括穷人和富人——这些诡计和托词就成了法律。因此，一些少数不择手段的人在贪得无厌的欲望的驱使下将本足以满足整个社会需求的物资占为己有。而这些人又能比乌托邦人幸福多少呢？在那里，随着金钱和对钱的欲望同时消失，解决了多少社会问题，又根除了多少罪恶啊！因为，显然金钱终结意味着每日的惩罚都无法阻止的所有罪行的终结：欺诈、偷盗、抢劫、争吵、暴乱、骚乱、叛乱、凶杀、谋反，以及巫术。且随着金钱的消亡，人们的恐惧、不安、焦虑、劳累过度，以及不眠之夜都会随之消失。咳，甚至连贫困，这个似乎只有金钱才能解决的问题，也会立即随金钱的终止而消失。

让我把这一点解释得更清楚一些。回想收成最差的一年，成千上万的人死于饥荒。那么，我敢打赌如果你在歉收的年末调查所有富人的谷仓，你会发现那里有足够挽救所有因营养不良或疾病而失去的生命的粮食，也能防止人们受天气和土壤影响而受罪。如果不是金钱这个该死的东西，人人都能丰衣足食。这个伟大的发明本来是为了使我们更容易获得食物，但实际上恰恰是金钱妨碍了食物的获得。

我敢肯定，连富人也一定意识到了这一点，也认识到与其占有太多，不如知足常乐——与其被巨大的财富所包围，不如一起从危险地带撤退。同样毫无疑问，不管是自身利益，还是救世主基督的威严——基督是如此明智，他知道什么是对我们最有利的，基督又是如此仁慈，任何事情他都会劝诫我们——如果不是因为狂妄这个万恶之源，基督早就应该引导全世界采用乌托邦的制度了。因为狂妄衡量成功的标准不是自己得到了什么，而是其他人得不到什么。狂妄甚至不愿意踏入天堂，如果她觉得天堂没有可以任她凌辱和使唤的可怜虫——如果没有谁的痛苦能够衬托她的幸福，或如果炫耀她的财富不能使别人的贫困更难以忍受。狂妄，就像凶恶的毒蛇盘绕在人们心头——或者，我们可以说，犹如一条紧拽着国家这艘船的大鱼？——它总是把我们往后拽，阻碍我们向更美好的生活进发。

但由于这样的错误在人性中已经扎根太深，所以不易根除，我很高兴看到至少有一个国家致力于建立我希望全世界都能够采取的制度。乌托邦的生活方式不仅为文明社会奠定了幸福的基础，而且很有可能能够永远持续下去。他们消除了野心、政治冲突和其他类似罪恶的根源。所以没有发生内部纠纷的危险，这曾经摧毁了许多无法征服的城市。只要国内团结一致并管理健全，不论邻国国王多么嫉妒，他们也无法动摇或破坏乌托邦政权。他们过去曾多次来犯，但终究都败退了。

拉斐尔在为我们讲述这一切时，我心中不断产生许多异议。这个国家的法律和风俗，在许多情况下对我来说都荒谬至极。更何况他们的军事战术、宗教和礼拜仪式，他们整个社会的基础即没有资金流通的共产主义，尤为荒谬。单凭这一点就意味着高贵的终结，进而是尊严、显赫以及权威尽失，这些都是任何国家真正引以为荣的。

然而，我看得出拉斐尔说了这么多已经累了，而我也不是很确定他是否能容忍任何反对意见——尤其是我记得他曾经讽刺过那些如果不对他人的观点吹毛求疵就生怕被人当作傻瓜的人。所以我很客气地评价了乌托邦的制度，并感谢了他有趣的谈话——之后我挽着他的胳膊带他一起去晚餐，我告诉他：

“好的，我会好好考虑这个问题，或许以后我们还能再见，到时候还能进行更深入的探讨。”

我当然希望有朝一日这能够实现。同时，虽然他具有渊博的学识且见多识广，但我不能同意他所说的一切。但我坦率地承认，乌托邦共和国的许多特征——我希望欧洲也能采用——可是我很难指望这能够实现。

More's Letter to Peter Gilles

My dear Peter Gilles,

I feel almost ashamed to send you this little book about the Utopian Republic, for I've kept you waiting for nearly a year, and you doubtless expected to get it within six weeks. You knew that in this work I didn't have the problem of finding my own subject-matter and puzzling out a suitable form—all I had to do was repeat what Raphael told us. There was no need to bother very much about the wording, since his style wasn't particularly polished—the whole thing was improvised on the spur of the moment, and, as you know, his Latin isn't quite as good as his Greek. So the closer I could get to his simple, off-hand way of expressing himself, the closer I'd be to the truth, which in this case is all I'm worrying about, and all I ought to worry about.

Yes, Peter, I know. So much of it was ready made, that there was practically nothing left for me to do. Mind you, in any other circumstances the creation and organization of a thing like this would have demanded a good deal of time and thought—even from a reasonably intelligent and cultivated person. And if the style had had to be graceful as well as accurate, no amount of time and thought would have enabled me to do it. As it was, I was relieved of all such headaches. My job was simply to write down what I'd heard, which was really perfectly easy—but my other commitments have left me less than no time to get this perfectly easy job done. I've been kept hard at work in the law courts, either at the Bar or on the Bench, either in civil or in criminal cases. Then there's always someone that has to be visited, either on business, or as a matter of courtesy. I'm out practically all day, dealing with other people—the rest of the day I spend with my family—so there's no time left for me, that is, for my writing.

You see, when I come home, I've got to talk to my wife, have a chat with my children, and discuss things with my servants. I count this as one of my commitments, because it's absolutely necessary, if I'm not to be a stranger in my own home. Besides, one should always try to be nice to the people one lives with, whether one has chosen their company deliberately, or merely been thrown into it by chance or family-relationship—that is, as nice as one can without spoiling them, or turning servants into masters.

Thus the days, the months, the years slip by. You may ask, when do I write then? Well, so far I haven't mentioned sleep, or meals—which many people allow to consume as much time as sleep itself—and in fact the only time I ever get to myself is what I steal from sleep and meals. There isn't very much of it, so my progress has been slow—but there has at least been some, so I've finally finished Utopia, and I'm sending it to you, my dear Peter, in the hope that you will read it, and tell me if I've left anything out. I feel fairly confident on that score—for I only wish my scholarship and intelligence were up to the standard of my memory—but not quite confident enough to assume that nothing could have slipped my mind.

As you know, my young assistant, John Clement, was with us at the time. I never let him miss any conversation that might have some educational value, for he has already begun to show such promise in Latin and Greek that I expect great things of him one day. Well, he has made me feel very doubtful about one point. As far as I can recall, Raphael told us that the bridge across the river Nowater at Aircastle was five hundred yards long, but John wants me to reduce this number by two hundred, for he says the river wasn't more than three hundred yards wide at that point. Will you please search your memory for the correct figure? If you agree with him, I'll take your word for it, and assume that I've made a mistake. But if you've completely forgotten, I'll let my figure stand, for that's how I seem to remember it. You see, I'm extremely anxious to get my facts right, and, when in doubt, any lies that I tell will be quite unintentional, for I'd much rather be thought honest than clever.

However, the simplest solution would be for you to ask Raphael himself, either by word of mouth or by letter—in fact you must do that anyway, because of another little problem which has cropped up. I don't know whose fault it was, mine, yours, or Raphael's, but we never thought of asking, and he never thought of telling us whereabouts in the New World Utopia is. I'd gladly give what little money I possess to repair the omission. For one thing, it makes me feel rather a fool, after all I've written about the island, not to know what sea it's in. For another, there are one or two people in England who want to go there. In particular, there's a very pious theologian, who's desperately keen to visit Utopia, not in a spirit of idle curiosity, but so that he can foster the growth of Christianity, now that it's been successfully introduced into that country. As he wishes to do it officially, he has decided to get himself sent out there by the Pope, and actually created Bishop of Utopia. He's not deterred by any scruples about begging for preferment. He thinks that sort of thing is perfectly all right if it's done, not for the sake of profit or prestige, but purely out of zeal.

So, Peter, will you please arrange to see Raphael, if you conveniently can, or else write to him, and make sure that my work contains the whole truth and nothing but the truth? Perhaps it would be best for you to show him the book itself, for he's the person best qualified to correct any mistakes, and he can't very well do so, unless he reads the thing right through. Besides, in that way you'll be able to find out how he reacts to the idea of my writing up the results of his researches. For if he's planning to write them up himself, he'd probably rather I didn't—and I certainly shouldn't want to give Utopia premature publicity, so that his story lost the charm of novelty.

To tell you the truth, though, I still haven't made up my mind whether I shall publish it at all. Tastes differ so widely, and some people are so humourless, so uncharitable, and so absurdly wrong-headed, that one would probably do far better to relax and enjoy life than worry oneself to death trying to instruct or entertain a public which will only despise one's efforts, or at least feel no gratitude for them. Most readers know nothing about literature—many regard it with contempt. Lowbrows find everything heavy going that isn't completely lowbrow. Highbrows reject everything as vulgar that isn't a mass of archaisms. Some only like the classics, others only their own works. Some are so grimly serious that they disapprove of all humour, others so half-witted that they can't stand wit. Some are so literal-minded that the slightest hint of irony affects them as water affects a sufferer from hydrophobia. Others come to different conclusions every time they stand up or sit down. Then there's the alcoholic school of critics, who sit in public houses, pronouncing ex cathedra verdicts of condemnation, just as they think fit. They seize upon your publications, as a wrestler seizes upon his opponent's hair, and use them to drag you down, while they themselves remain quite invulnerable, because their barren pates are completely bald—so there's nothing for you to get hold of.

Besides, some readers are so ungrateful that, even if they enjoy a book immensely, they don't feel any affection for the author. They're like rude guests who after a splendid dinner-party go home stuffed with food, without saying a word of thanks to their host. So much for the wisdom of preparing a feast of reason at one's own expense for a public with such fastidious and unpredictable tastes, and with such a profound sense of gratitude!

But do, as I say, get in touch with Raphael. I can think about the other question later—though really it's too late to start being sensible now, when I've gone to all the trouble of writing the book. So if he has no objection, whether I publish it or not will depend on what my friends, and especially what you advise.

Best wishes, my dearest Peter Gilles, to you and your charming wife. And please go on liking me as much as ever—because I like you even more than ever.

Yours sincerely,

THOMAS MORE

Gilles's Letter to Busleiden

Antwerp

1 November 1516

My dear Busleiden,

The other day a great friend of yours, Thomas More —who is, I'm sure you'll agree, one of the glories of our age—sent me the enclosed account of Utopia. At present very few people know about this island, but everyone should want to, for it's like Plato's Republic, only better —especially as it's described by such a talented author. He sets it all so vividly before one's eyes that by reading his words I seem to get an even clearer picture of it than I did while Raphael Nonsenso's voice was actually sounding in my ears—for I was with More when the conversation took place. And yet Raphael spoke extraordinarily well. He obviously wasn't retailing somebody else's story, but describing his own experiences in a place where he'd lived for quite a long time. Personally, I think he must have seen even more of the world than Ulysses, and I doubt if there has been anyone like him for at least eight hundred years. He made us feel that Vespucci had seen absolutely nothing!

The man also appeared to have a special talent for exposition—though I suppose we can always describe what we've seen more effectively than what we've heard. But when I consider More's quasi-pictorial treatment of the same theme, I sometimes get the impression that I'm actually living in Utopia. In fact, I honestly believe there's more to be seen in his account of the island than Raphael himself can have seen during all those five years that he spent there. One comes across so many wonderful things on every page, that I hardly know what to admire first or most—the remarkable accuracy of his memory, which could reproduce an immensely long speech practically word for word—his cleverness in immediately grasping the actual and potential causes, hitherto largely unknown, of every social evil—or the force and fluency of his style, his ability to deal with such a variety of topics in such correct and muscular Latin—especially as he's distracted by so many official and domestic responsibilities. But all this will seem less surprising to a fine scholar like you. Besides, you already know him intimately, and are quite familiar with the prodigious, if not positively superhuman power of his intellect.

I can't think of anything to add to what he has written—except that I've attached four lines of verse in the Utopian language, which Nonsenso happened to show me after More had gone, together with the Utopian alphabet. I've also added a few marginal notes. By the way, More's a bit worried because he doesn't know the exact position of the island. As a matter of fact Raphael did mention it, but only very briefly and incidentally, as though he meant to return to the question later—and, for some unknown reason, we were both fated to miss it. You see, just as Raphael was touching on the subject, a servant came up to More and whispered something in his ear. And although this made me listen with even greater attention, at the critical moment one of his colleagues started coughing rather loudly—I suppose he'd caught cold on the boat—so that the rest of Raphael's sentence was completely inaudible. However, I shan't rest until I've cleared up that point too, and can tell you exactly where the island is, latitude and all. That is, if our friend Raphael is still safe and sound, for I've heard several different stories about him. Some people say that he has died somewhere on his travels. Others that he has gone back to his own country. Others again that he has returned to Utopia, partly because he felt nostalgic about it, and partly because he couldn't stand the way Europeans behaved.

You may wonder why no reference to Utopia appears in any geographical work, but this problem has been very neatly solved by Raphael himself. He says it's quite possible that the ancients knew of the island under another name, or else that they never heard of it at all—for nowadays countries are always being discovered which were never mentioned in the old geography books. However, I need no arguments to prove my point, when I can appeal to the authority of a man like More.

I understand and respect the modesty that makes him hesitate to publish. Personally, though, I think it's the sort of work that should on no account be suppressed for long, but should be put into circulation as quickly as possible, preferably with a letter from you to recommend it to the world—because you have a special insight into More's genius, and who could be better qualified to introduce sound ideas to the public than one who has spent many years in the public service and earned the highest praise for his wisdom and integrity?

With all good wishes to a great patron of scholarship, who is also among the glories of this age,

Yours sincerely,

PETER GILLES

Book One

There was recently a rather serious difference of opinion between that great expert in the art of government, His Invincible Majesty, King Henry the Eighth of England, and His Serene Highness, Prince Charles of Castile. His Majesty sent me to Flanders to discuss and settle the matter, along with my friend Cuthbert Tunstall, an excellent person who has since been appointed Master of the Rolls, much to everyone's satisfaction. Of his learning and moral character I shall say nothing—not because I am afraid of seeming prejudiced in his favour, but because they are too remarkable for me to describe adequately, and too well known to need describing at all. I have no wish to labour the obvious.

We were met at Bruges, as previously arranged, by the envoys from Castile, who were all men of great distinction. Their nominal leader was the Mayor of Bruges, and a splendid fellow he was; but most of the thinking and talking was done by the Provost of Cassel, George de Theimsecke. This man was a born speaker, as well as a highly trained one. He was also a legal expert, and both by temperament and by long experience a first-rate negotiator. After one or two meetings there were still some points on which we had failed to agree, so they said goodbye to us for a few days and set off for Brussels, to consult their royal oracle. In the meantime I went to Antwerp on business of my own.

While I was there, I had several frequent visitors, but the one I liked best was a young native of Antwerp called Peter Gilles. He is much respected by his own people, and holds an important post in that town; but he fully deserves promotion to the highest post of all, for I do not know which impressed me more, his intellectual or his moral qualities. Certainly he is a very fine person, as well as a very fine scholar. He is scrupulously fair to everyone, but towards his friends he shows so much genuine kindness, loyalty, and affection, that he must be almost unique in his all-round capacity for friendship. He is unusually modest, utterly sincere, and has a shrewd simplicity all his own. He is also a delightful talker, who can be witty without hurting anyone's feelings. I was longing to get back to England and see my wife and children, as I had been away for over four months; but my homesickness was to large extent relieved by the pleasure of his company and the charm of his conversation.

One day I had been to a service at the Cathedral of Notre Dame, a magnificent building which is always packed with people. I was just starting back to my hotel when I happened to see Peter Gilles talking to an elderly foreigner with a sunburnt face, a long beard, and a cloak slung carelessly over one shoulder. From his complexion and costume I judged him to be a sailor. At this point Peter caught sight of me. He immediately came up and said good morning, then before I had time to reply, drew me a little further away.

'Do you see that man over there?' he asked, indicating the one he had been talking to. 'I was just bringing him along to visit you.'

'If he's a friend of yours,' I said, 'I'll be very glad to see him.'

'When you hear the sort of person he is,' said Peter, 'you'll be glad to see him anyway—for there's not a man alive today who can tell you so many stories about strange countries and their inhabitants as he can. I know what a passion you have for that kind of thing.'

'Then I didn't guess too far wrong,' I remarked. 'The moment I saw him, I thought he must be a sailor.'

'In that case you made a big mistake,' he replied. 'I mean, he's not a sailor of the Palinurus type. He's really more like Ulysses, or even Plato. You see, our friend Raphael—for that's his name, Raphael Nonsenso—is quite a scholar. He knows a fair amount of Latin and a tremendous lot of Greek. He's concentrated on Greek, because he's mainly interested in philosophy, and he found that there's nothing important on that subject written in Latin, apart from some bits of Seneca and Cicero. He wanted to see the world, so he left his brothers to manage his property in Portugal—that's where he comes from—and joined up with Amerigo Vespucci. You know those Four Voyages of his that everyone's reading about? Well, Raphael was his constant companion during the last three, except that he didn't come back with him from the final voyage. Instead, he practically forced Amerigo to let him be one of the twenty-four men who were left behind in that fort. So he stayed out there, to indulge his taste for travel, which was all he really cared about. He didn't mind where he eventually died, for he had two favourite quotations, "The unburied dead are covered by the sky" and "You can get to heaven from anywhere"—an attitude which, but for the grace of God, might have led to serious trouble. Anyway, when Vespucci had gone, Raphael did a lot of exploring with five other members of the garrison. Finally, by an amazing stroke of luck, they turned up in Ceylon. From there he made his way to Calicut, where he was fortunate enough to find some Portuguese ships, and so, quite unexpectedly, got a passage home.'

'Well, thank you very much,' I said. 'I'll certainly enjoy talking to a man like that. It's most kind of you to give me a chance of doing so.'

I then walked up to Raphael and shook hands with him. After making a few stock remarks, as people generally do when first introduced, we adjourned to the garden of my hotel, where we sat down on a bench covered with a layer of turf, and began to talk more freely.

First of all Raphael told us what happened to him and the other men in the fort, from the point where Vespucci left them. By polite and friendly behaviour they gradually started ingratiating themselves with the local inhabitants. Soon relations were not merely peaceful but positively affectionate. They got on particularly well with a certain king, whose name and nationality have slipped my memory. He most generously provided Raphael and his five fellow-explorers with food and money for their journeys, which involved the use of boats as well as carriages. He also supplied a most reliable guide, who was told to put them in touch with various other kings, to whom they were given letters of introduction. Thus after travelling for many days they came to some large towns and densely populated areas, with quite a high standard of political organization.

Apparently, at the equator, and throughout most of the torrid zone, you find vast deserts parched by perpetual heat. Everything looks grim and desolate. There are no signs of cultivation, and no animal life, except for snakes and wild beasts, or equally wild and dangerous human beings. But, if you go on a bit further, things gradually improve. The climate becomes less extreme, the earth grows green and pleasant, human beings and animals are not so fierce. Finally, you come to people living in towns and cities, who are constantly engaged in trade, both by land and by sea, not only with one another or with their immediate neighbours, but even with quite distant countries.

'This gave me the chance,' said Raphael, 'of travelling about all over the place, for whenever I found a ship just setting sail I asked if my friends and I might go on board, and they were always glad to let us. The first ships we saw were flat-bottomed, with sails made of papyrus leaves stitched together, or else of wicker-work, or in some cases of leather. But the ones we came across later had sharp keels and canvas sails, and were generally just like ours. The sailors out there have a good knowledge of winds and tides, but I made myself extraordinarily popular with them by explaining the use of the magnetic compass. They'd never heard of it before, and for that reason had always been rather frightened of the sea, and seldom risked going on it except during the summer. But now they put such faith in their compasses that they think nothing of winter voyages—although this new sense of security is purely subjective. In fact their overconfidence threatens to convert an apparently useful invention into a source of disaster.'

It would take too long to repeat everything he told us about each place. Besides, that is not the purpose of this book. I may conceivably do so in another one, emphasizing the most instructive parts of his story, such as the sensible arrangements that he noticed in various civilized communities. These were the points on which we questioned him most closely, and he enlarged most willingly. We did not ask him if he had seen any monsters, for monsters have ceased to be news. There is never any shortage of horrible creatures who prey on human beings, snatch away their food, or devour whole populations; but examples of wise social planning are not so easy to find.

Of course, he saw much to condemn in the New World, but he also discovered several regulations which suggested possible methods of reforming European society. These, I say, will have to be dealt with later. My present plan is merely to repeat what he said about the laws and customs of Utopia.

I must start by recording the conversation which led up to the first mention of that republic. After shrewdly pointing out the mistakes that have been made on both sides of the globe—and there are certainly plenty of them—Raphael went on to discuss the more sensible features of Old and New World legislation. He seemed to have the facts about every single country at his fingertips—as though he had spent a lifetime wherever he had stopped for a night. Peter Gilles was particularly impressed.

PETER: My dear Raphael, I can't think why you don't enter the service of some king or other. I'm sure any king would jump at the chance of employing you. With your knowledge and experience, you'd be just the man to supply not only entertainment, but also instructive precedents and useful advice. At the same time you could be looking after your own interests, and being a great help to all your friends and relations.

RAPHAEL: I'm not really worried about them. I feel I've done my duty by them already. Most people hang on to their property until they're too old and ill to do so any longer—and even then they relinquish it with a very ill grace. But I shared out mine among my friends and relations when I was still young and healthy. I think they should be satisfied with that. They can hardly expect me to go a stage further, and become a king's slave for their benefit.

PETER: God forbid! Service, not servitude, was what I suggested.

RAPHAEL: A few letters don't make all that difference.

PETER: Well, call it what you like, I still think it's your best method of helping other people, both individually and collectively, and also of making life pleasanter for yourself.

RAPHAEL: How can I do that by acting against all my instincts? At present I live exactly as I please, which is more, I suspect, than the vast majority of court officials can say. Besides, kings have quite enough people competing for their friendship already. It won't be any serious hardship for them to do without me, and a handful of others like me.

MORE: My dear Raphael, you're obviously not interested in money or power, and I couldn't respect you more if you were the greatest king on earth. But surely it would be quite in keeping with this admirably philosophical attitude if you could bring yourself, even at the cost of some personal inconvenience, to apply your talents and energies to public affairs? Now the most effective way of doing so would be to gain the confidence of some great king or other, and give him, as I know you would, really good advice. For every king is a sort of fountain, from which a constant shower of benefits or injuries rains down upon the whole population. And you've got so much theoretical knowledge, and so much practical experience, that either of them alone would be enough to make you an ideal member of any privy council.

RAPHAEL: You're quite mistaken, my dear More, first about me and then about the job itself. I'm not so highly qualified as you seem to think, and, even if I were, I still shouldn't do the slightest good to the community by giving myself a lot of extra work. To start with, most kings are more interested in the science of war—which I don't know anything about, and don't want to—than in useful peacetime techniques. They're far more anxious, by hook or by crook, to acquire new kingdoms than to govern their existing ones properly. Besides, privy councillors are either too wise to need, or too conceited to take advice from anyone else—though of course they're always prepared to suck up to the king's special favourites by agreeing with the silliest things they say. After all, it's a natural instinct to be charmed by one's own productions. That's why raven chicks are such a delight to their parents, and mother apes find their babies exquisitely beautiful.

So there you have a group of people who are deeply prejudiced against everyone else's ideas, or at any rate prefer their own. Suppose, in such company, you suggest a policy that you've seen adopted elsewhere, or for which you can quote a historical precedent, what will happen? They'll behave as though their professional reputations were at stake, and they'd look fools for the rest of their lives if they couldn't raise some objection to your proposal. Failing all else, their last resort will be: 'This was good enough for our ancestors, and who are we to question their wisdom?' Then they'll settle back in their chairs, with an air of having said the last word on the subject—as if it would be a major disaster for anyone to be caught being wiser than his ancestors! And yet we're quite prepared to reverse their most sensible decisions. It's only the less intelligent ones that we cling on to like grim death. I've come across this curious mixture of conceit, stupidity, and stubbornness in several different places. On one occasion I even met it in England.

MORE: Really? Have you been to my country too, then?

RAPHAEL: Certainly I have. I was there for several months, soon after that disastrous civil war which began with a revolution in the west country, and ended with a ghastly massacre of the rebels. During my stay, I received a lot of kindness from the Most Reverend John Morton, the Archbishop of Canterbury. He was also a Cardinal, and at that time Lord Chancellor of England. I must tell you about him, Peter—for I can't tell More anything he doesn't know already. He was a person that one respected just as much for his wisdom and moral character as for his great eminence. He was of average height, without a trace of a stoop, although he was fairly old. He had the sort of face that inspires reverence rather than fear. He was quite easy to get on with, though always serious and dignified. Admittedly he was rather inclined to be rude to people who asked him for jobs, but he meant no harm by it. He only did it to test their intelligence and presence of mind, for he found these qualities very congenial, so long as they were used with discretion, and considered them most valuable in public life. He was a polished and effective speaker, with a thorough knowledge of the law. He also had a quite remarkable intellect, and a phenomenal memory—two natural gifts which he'd further developed by training and practice.

Apparently the King had great confidence in his judgement, and at the time of my visit the whole country seemed to depend on him. This was hardly surprising, since he'd been rushed straight from the university to Court, when he was not much more than a boy, and had spent the rest of his life in the public service, learning wisdom the hard way, by having to cope with a long series of crises. And what one learns like that isn't easily forgotten.

I once happened to be dining with the Cardinal when a certain English lawyer was there. I forgot how the subject came up, but he was speaking with great enthusiasm about the stern measures that were then being taken against thieves.

'We're hanging them all over the place,' he said, 'I've seen as many as twenty on a single gallows. And that's what I find so odd. Considering how few of them get away with it, why are we still plagued with so many robbers?'

'What's odd about it?' I asked—for I never hesitated to speak freely in front of the Cardinal. 'This method of dealing with thieves is both unjust and socially undesirable. As a punishment it's too severe, and as a deterrent it's quite ineffective. Petty larceny isn't bad enough to deserve the death penalty, and no penalty on earth will stop people from stealing, if it's their only way of getting food. In this respect you English, like most other nations, remind me of incompetent schoolmasters, who prefer caning their pupils to teaching them. Instead of inflicting these horrible punishments, it would be far more to the point to provide everyone with some means of livelihood, so that nobody's under the frightful necessity of becoming first a thief and then a corpse.'

'There's adequate provision for that already,' replied the lawyer. 'There are plenty of trades open to them. There's always work on the land. They could easily earn an honest living if they wanted to, but they deliberately choose to be criminals.'

'You can't get out of it like that,' I said. 'Let's ignore, for the sake of argument, the case of the disabled soldier, who has lost a limb in the service of King and Country, either at home or abroad—perhaps in that battle with the Cornish rebels, or perhaps during the fighting in France, not so long ago. When he comes home, he finds he's physically incapable of practising his former trade, and too old to learn a new one. But as I say, let's forget about him, since war is only an intermittent phenomenon. Let's stick to the type of thing that happens every day.

'Well, first of all there are lots of noblemen who live like drones on the labour of other people, in other words, of their tenants, and keep bleeding them white by constantly raising their rents. For that's their only idea of practical economy—otherwise they'd soon be ruined by their extravagance. But not content with remaining idle themselves, they take round with them vast numbers of equally idle retainers, who have never been taught any method of earning their living. The moment their master dies, or they themselves fall ill, they're promptly given the sack—for these noblemen are far more sympathetic towards idleness than illness, and their heirs often can't afford to keep up such large establishments. Now a sacked retainer is apt to get violently hungry, if he doesn't resort to violence. For what's the alternative? He can, of course, wander around until his clothes and his body are both worn out, and he's nothing but a mass of rags and sores. But in that state no gentleman will condescend to employ him, and no farmer can risk doing so—for who could be less likely to serve a poor man faithfully, sweating away with mattock and hoe for a beggarly wage and a barely adequate diet, than a man who has been brought up in the lap of luxury, and is used to swaggering about in military uniform, looking down his nose at everyone else in the neighbourhood?'

'But that's exactly the kind of person we need to encourage,' retorted the lawyer. 'In wartime he forms the backbone of the army, simply because he has more spirit and self-respect than an ordinary tradesman or farmhand.'

'You might as well say,' I answered, 'that for purposes of war you have to encourage theft. Well, you'll certainly never run short of thieves, so long as you have people like that about. And, of course, you're perfectly right—thieves do make quite efficient soldiers, and soldiers make quite enterprising thieves. The two professions have a good deal in common. However, the trouble is not confined to England, although you've got it pretty badly. It's practically a world-wide epidemic. France, for instance, is suffering from an even more virulent form of it. There the whole country is overrun even in peacetime—if you can call it that—by mercenaries who have been brought in for much the same reasons as you gave for supporting idle retainers. You see, the experts decided, in the interests of public safety, that they must have a powerful standing army, consisting mostly of veterans—for they put so little faith in raw recruits that they deliberately start wars to give their soldiers practice, and make them cut throats "just to keep their hands in", as Sallust rather nicely puts it.

'So France has learnt by bitter experience how dangerous it is to keep these savage pets, but there are plenty of similar object-lessons in the history of Rome, Carthage, Syria, and many other countries. Again and again standing armies have seized some opportunity of overthrowing the government that employed them, devastating its territory, and destroying its towns. And yet it's quite unnecessary. That's obvious enough from the fact that for all their intensive military training the French can't often claim to have beaten your wartime conscripts—I won't put it more strongly than that, for fear of seeming to flatter present company.

'Besides, it's not generally thought that either of the types you mentioned, the tradesman in town or the ignorant farmhand in the country, is actually so very frightened of the retainers in question—unless his physical strength isn't equal to his courage, or his spirit has been broken by privations at home. The fact is that though these retainers start off with powerful physiques—for no gentleman would stoop to corrupt an inferior specimen—they soon get soft and flabby by sitting around doing nothing, or nothing that a woman couldn't do. So there's really not much risk of their losing all their manhood, if they were taught useful trades and made to work like men. In any case I don't see how it can possibly be in the public interest to prepare for a war, which you needn't have unless you want to, by maintaining innumerable disturbers of the peace—when peace is so infinitely more important.

'But that's not the only thing that compels people to steal. There are other factors at work which must, I think, be peculiar to your country.'

'And what are they?' asked the Cardinal.

'Sheep,' I told him. 'These placid creatures, which used to require so little food, have now apparently developed a raging appetite, and turned into man-eaters. Fields, houses, towns, everything goes down their throats. To put it more plainly, in those parts of the kingdom where the finest, and so the most expensive wool is produced, the nobles and gentlemen, not to mention several saintly abbots, have grown dissatisfied with the income that their predecessors got out of their estates. They're no longer content to lead lazy, comfortable lives, which do no good to society—they must actively do it harm, by enclosing all the land they can for pasture, and leaving none for cultivation. They're even tearing down houses and demolishing whole towns—except, of course, for the churches, which they preserve for use as sheepfolds. As though they didn't waste enough of your soil already on their coverts and game-preserves, these kind souls have started destroying all traces of human habitation, and turning every scrap of farmland into a wilderness.

'So what happens? Each greedy individual preys on his native land like a malignant growth, absorbing field after field, and enclosing thousands of acres with a single fence. Result—hundreds of farmers are evicted. They're either cheated or bullied into giving up their property, or systematically ill-treated until they're finally forced to sell. Whichever way it's done, out the poor creatures have to go, men and women, husbands and wives, widows and orphans, mothers and tiny children, together with all their employees—whose great numbers are not a sign of wealth, but simply of the fact that you can't run a farm without plenty of manpower. Out they have to go from the homes that they know so well, and they can't find anywhere else to live. Their whole stock of furniture wouldn't fetch much of a price, even if they could afford to wait for a suitable offer. But they can't, so they get very little indeed for it. By the time they've been wandering around for a bit, this little is all used up, and then what can they do but steal—and be very properly hanged? Of course, they can always become tramps and beggars, but even then they're liable to be arrested as vagrants, and put in prison for being idle—when nobody will give them a job, however much they want one. For farm-work is what they're used to, and where there's no arable land, there's no farm-work to be done. After all, it only takes one shepherd or cowherd to graze animals over an area that would need any amount of labour to make it fit for corn production.

'For the same reason, corn is much dearer in many districts. The price of wool has also risen so steeply that your poorer weavers simply can't afford to buy it, which means a lot more people thrown out of work. This is partly due to an epidemic of the rot, which destroyed vast numbers of sheep just after the conversion of arable to pasture land began. It almost looked like a judgement on the landowners for their greed—except that they ought to have caught it instead of the sheep.

'Not that prices would fall, however many sheep there were, for the sheep market has become, if not strictly a monopoly—for that implies only one seller—then at least an oligopoly. I mean it's almost entirely under the control of a few rich men, who don't need to sell unless they feel like it, and never do feel like it until they can get the price they want. This also accounts for the equally high prices of other types of livestock, especially in view of the shortage of breeders caused by the demolition of farms, and the general decline of agriculture. For the rich men I'm talking about never bother to breed either sheep or cattle themselves. They merely buy scraggy specimens cheap from someone else, fatten them up on their own pastures, and resell them at a large profit. I imagine that's why the full effects of the situation have not yet been felt. So far they've only inflated prices in the areas where they sell, but, if they keep transferring animals from other districts faster than they can be replaced, stocks in the buying areas too will gradually be depleted, until eventually there'll be an acute shortage everywhere.

'Thus a few greedy people have converted one of England's greatest natural advantages into a national disaster. For it's the high price of food that makes employers turn off so many of their servants—which inevitably means turning them into beggars or thieves. And theft comes easier to a man of spirit.

'To make matters worse, this wretched poverty is most incongruously linked with expensive tastes. Servants, tradesmen, even farm-labourers, in fact all classes of society are recklessly extravagant about clothes and food. Then think how many brothels there are, including those that go under the names of wine-taverns or alehouses. Think of the demoralizing games people play—dice, cards, backgammon, tennis, bowls, quoits—what are they but quick methods of wasting a man's money, and sending him straight off to become a thief?

'Get rid of these pernicious practices. Make a law that anyone responsible for demolishing a farm or a country town must either rebuild it himself or else hand over the land to someone who's willing to do so. Stop the rich from cornering markets and establishing virtual monopolies. Reduce the number of people who are kept doing nothing. Revive agriculture and the wool industry, so that there's plenty of honest, useful work for the great army of unemployed—by which I mean not only existing thieves, but tramps and idle servants who are bound to become thieves eventually. Until you put these things right, you're not entitled to boast of the justice meted out to thieves, for it's a justice more specious than real or socially desirable. You allow these people to be brought up in the worst possible way, and systematically corrupted from their earliest years. Finally, when they grow up and commit the crimes that they were obviously destined to commit, ever since they were children, you start punishing them. In other words, you create thieves, and then punish them for stealing!'

Long before I'd finished, the lawyer was ready with his answer. He was evidently one of those people whose method of argument consists in repeating what you've said, rather than replying to it—as though having a good memory were all that mattered.

'That was a very fine effort,' he said, 'especially for a foreigner whose information is bound to be second-hand, and therefore inaccurate—as I'll very briefly demonstrate. I'll begin by running through the points you've made. Then I'll show where you've gone wrong through your ignorance of local conditions. And finally I'll refute all your arguments. Proceeding in that order, I think you've made four—'

'Just a moment,' interrupted the Cardinal. 'After such an introduction, your reply seems unlikely to be as brief as you suggest. So don't bother to produce it now—keep it fresh for your next meeting. Why not make it tomorrow, if you're both free then? Meanwhile, my dear Raphael, I'd very much like to hear just why you object to capital punishment for theft, and what penalty you think would be more in the public interest. For even you, I take it, feel that stealing should be stopped. And since it goes on merrily in spite of the death penalty, what power on earth could stop it, what possible deterrent could be effective, if the fear of death were removed? Surely any reduction of sentence would be interpreted as a positive invitation to crime?'

'Your Grace,' I said, 'it seems to me quite unjust to take a man's life because he's taken some money. To my mind no amount of property is equivalent to a human life. If it's argued that the punishment is not for taking the money, but for breaking the law and violating justice, isn't this conception of absolute justice absolutely unjust? One really can't approve of a régime so dictatorial that the slightest disobedience is punishable by death, nor of a legal code based on the Stoic paradox that all offences are equal—so that there's no distinction in law between theft and murder, though in equity the two things are so completely different.

'God said, "Thou shalt not kill" —does the theft of a little money make it quite all right for us to do so? If it's said that this commandment applies only to illegal killing, what's to prevent human beings from similarly agreeing among themselves to legalize certain types of rape, adultery, or perjury? Considering that God has forbidden us even to kill ourselves, can we really believe that purely human arrangements for the regulation of mutual slaughter are enough, without any divine authority, to exempt executioners from the sixth commandment? Isn't that rather like saying that this particular commandment has no more validity than human laws allow it?—in which case the principle can be extended indefinitely, until in all spheres of life human beings decide just how far God's commandments may conveniently be observed.

'Under the law of Moses—which was harsh enough in all conscience, being designed for slaves, and rebellious ones at that—thieves were not hanged, but merely fined. We can hardly suppose that the new dispensation, which expresses God's fatherly kindness towards His children, allows us more scope than the old for being cruel to one another.

'Well, those are my objections on moral grounds. From a practical point of view, surely it's obvious that to punish thieves and murderers in precisely the same way is not only absurd but also highly dangerous for the public. If a thief knows that a conviction for murder will get him into no more trouble than a conviction for theft, he's naturally impelled to kill the person that he'd otherwise merely have robbed. It's no worse for him if he's caught, and it gives him a better chance of not being caught, and of concealing the crime altogether by eliminating the only witness. So in our efforts to terrorize thieves we're actually encouraging them to murder innocent people.

'Now for the usual question—what punishment would be better? I'd have found it much harder to answer, if you'd asked me what would be worse. Well, why should we doubt the value of a system which those expert administrators, the Romans, found satisfactory for so long? They, as we know, sentenced people convicted of major crimes to penal servitude for life in mines or stone quarries.

'However, the best arrangement I know is one I came across while travelling through Persia, in a district generally known as Tallstoria. The Tallstorians form quite a large and well-organized community, which is completely autonomous, except for having to pay taxes to the King of Persia. As they're a long way from the sea, practically encircled by mountains, and content to live on the produce of their own soil, which is extremely fertile, they have little contact with foreigners. They've never had any wish to increase their territory, which is secured against external aggression both by the mountains and by the protection-money that they pay to the Great King. This means that they're exempt from military service, so they're able to live in comfort, if not in luxury, and be happy, if not exactly famous or glorious—for, apart from their immediate neighbours, I doubt if anyone has ever heard of them.

'Well, in Tallstoria a convicted thief has to return what he's stolen to its owner, not, as in most other countries, to the King—who according to the Tallstorians has just about as much right to it as the thief himself. If the stolen goods are no longer in his possession, their value is deducted from his own property, the rest of which is handed over intact to his wife and children. He himself is sentenced to hard labour. Except in cases of robbery with violence, he's not put in prison or made to wear fetters, but left quite free and employed on public works. If he downs tools or goes slow, they don't slow him down still more by loading him with chains—they accelerate his movements with a whip. If he works hard, he's not treated at all badly. He has to answer a roll-call every evening, and he's locked up for the night—but otherwise, apart from having to work very long hours, he has a perfectly comfortable life.

'The food, for instance, is quite reasonable. It's provided at the public expense, since convicts work as servants of the public. The procedure for raising the money varies from place to place. In some districts it's collected from voluntary contributions. This sounds an unreliable method, but in practice it brings in more than any other, for the people there are extraordinarily kind-hearted. Elsewhere, certain public revenues are set aside for the purpose, or a special poll-tax is levied. There are also some places where, instead of being employed on public works, convicts are hired out to private enterprise. Anyone needing their services goes to the market-place and engages them by the day, at a rather lower wage than he would pay for free labour. He's also allowed to whip them if they don't work hard enough. This system ensures that they're never out of work, their meals are provided for them, and each convict makes a daily contribution to public funds.

'They all wear clothes of a special colour, which nobody else wears. Their heads aren't actually shaved, but the hair is clipped short just above the ears, and a tiny piece is cut off one of them. Their friends are allowed to give them food and drink, and clothes of the regulation colour, but it's a capital crime for anyone to give them money, or for them to accept it. So it is for free men to accept money on any pretext from slaves—as convicts are usually called—or for slaves to touch any kind of weapon.

'Each slave is given a badge to show which district he belongs to, and it's a capital crime to take one's badge off, to be seen outside one's own district, or to speak to a slave from another district. As for running away, it's just as risky to plan it as to do it. The penalty for being accessory to any such plan is death for a slave, and slavery for a free man—whereas by betraying an escape-project you can earn a reward in cash, if you're a free man, or your freedom, if you're a slave. In either case the informer receives a pardon for his part in the plot, on the principle that it must always be safer to abandon a criminal undertaking than to go ahead with it.

'Well, that's how the system works, and it's obviously most convenient and humane. It comes down heavily on crime, but it saves the lives of criminals, treating them in such a way that they're forced to become good citizens, and spend the rest of their lives making up for the harm they've done in the past.

'In fact there's so little risk of their relapsing into their old habits, that they're generally regarded as the safest possible guides for long-distance travellers, who employ them in relays, one for each district they pass through. You see, slaves have no facilities for highway-robbery. They're not allowed to carry weapons. If money is found on them, it proves that they've committed a crime. If they're caught, punishment is automatic, and they haven't the slightest hope of not being caught—for how can you make an unobtrusive getaway when your clothes are quite different from ordinary people's, unless you decamp in the nude?—and even then your ear will betray you.

'There's still, of course, a theoretical risk that they might start a conspiracy to overthrow the government. But how could the slaves of any one district hope to organize such a large-scale operation, without first sounding and stirring up the slaves in several other districts? And that's physically impossible. They're not even allowed to meet them, or talk to them, or say good morning to them, let alone conspire with them. Besides, can you imagine anyone cheerfully letting the other slaves of his district into a secret which would be so dangerous for them to keep, and so very profitable for them to betray? On the other hand, every slave has some hope of recovering his freedom, simply by doing what he's told and giving the authorities reason to believe that he'll go straight in future—since a certain number of slaves are released every year for good conduct.'

I then added that I didn't see why this system shouldn't be adopted in England. It would produce far better results than the so-called 'justice' that the lawyer had praised so highly.

At this our learned friend—I mean the lawyer—shook his head.

'Such a system,' he announced, with a smile of contempt, 'could never be adopted in England, without serious danger to the country.'

That was all he said—and practically everyone else agreed with him.

Then the Cardinal gave his opinion.

'It's hard to predict,' he said, 'without giving it a trial, whether it would work or not. But suppose the King were to postpone the execution of death sentences for an experimental period—having first abolished all rights of asylum. If the results were good, we'd be justified in making the arrangement permanent. If not, the original sentences could still be carried out, with quite as much benefit to society, and quite as much justice, as if they were carried out now. In the meantime no great harm could have been done. As a matter of fact, I don't think it would be at all a bad idea to treat vagrants in the same way. We're always making laws about them, but so far nothing has had the slightest effect.'

This, from the Cardinal, was enough to make everyone wildly in favour of an idea which nobody had taken seriously when I produced it. They were particularly keen on the bit about vagrants, since that was his own contribution.

Perhaps I ought to leave out the next part of the conversation, which was not wholly serious. But I don't think I shall, because it was perfectly harmless, and had a certain relevance to the point at issue. Among those present was a professional diner-out, who wanted you to think that he was merely acting the fool but played the part almost too convincingly. His efforts to raise a laugh were usually so feeble that one tended to laugh at him rather than with him. But occasionally he'd come out with something rather good, thus restoring one's faith in the proverb, 'If at first you don't succeed, try, try, try again.' Well, somebody gave him his cue by remarking that the Cardinal and I between us had solved the problem of thieves and vagrants, so it only remained to decide on appropriate state action to deal with poor people who were either too old or too ill to earn their living.

'Just leave it to me,' said this gentleman. 'I'll tell you exactly what to do. The fact is, I'm desperately anxious to get that sort of person out of my sight. I've suffered so often from demands for money in that whining sing-song of theirs—a form of music which has never charmed a penny out of me. What always happens is this—either I don't feel like giving them anything, or else I do, but I can't, because I haven't got anything to give. So now they're learning not to waste their energy. When they see me walking past, they just let me walk past, without saying a word. They know I might as well be a priest, for all the help I'll be to them. Well, I propose a law for the compulsory enrolment of beggars in Benedictine monasteries, the males to become lay brethren—that's the technical term for monks—and the females to become nuns.'

The Cardinal smiled, and jokingly agreed. So did all the others, with perfectly straight faces. The only exception was a certain friar, who'd apparently studied theology. Normally a grimly serious type of person, he was so delighted by these digs at priests and monks that he too started trying to be funny.

'Ah, but you won't get rid of beggars quite so easily,' he said. 'What are you going to do about us mendicant friars?'

'Why, that's already taken care of,' replied the wag. 'Don't you remember the Cardinal's splendid regulation for the control and useful employment of tramps?'

Everyone glanced at the Cardinal, to see how he was taking it, and, as he showed no signs of disapproval, the remark was greeted with applause—except by the friar. He, not very surprisingly, reacted to this cold douche of satire by losing his temper and becoming downright abusive. He called the man every rude name he could think of, including a son of Belial, and wound up with some fearful curses out of Holy Scripture.

At this point the clown started clowning in real earnest. He obviously felt in his element.

'My dear friar,' he began, 'you mustn't get so angry. You know what it says in the Bible, "Ye shall possess your souls in patience".'

'I'm not angry, damn you!' shouted the friar—those were his very words. 'Or if I am, I've every right to be. "Be ye angry, and sin not", that's what it says in the Psalms.'

The Cardinal gently suggested that he should try to keep his temper.

'My temper, sir?' he repeated. 'There's nothing wrong with my temper. It's righteous zeal that makes me say these things, the sort of righteous zeal that inspired the saints. Hence the words of the Psalmist, "The zeal of thy house hath eaten me up", or of the hymn that we sing in church:

They who mocked the great Elisha,

As he mounted up to Bethel,

By a baldhead's zeal was punished.

And I dare say this filthy sneering idiot may find the same thing happening to him.'

'I'm sure your feelings do you great credit,' said the Cardinal, 'but I wonder if your behaviour wouldn't be even more saintly—it would certainly be wiser—if you refrained from making a fool of yourself by arguing with a fool.'

'No, sir,' retorted the friar, 'it would not be wiser, for who could be wiser than Solomon? And Solomon says, "Answer a fool according to his folly"—which is precisely what I'm doing. I'm showing him the bottomless pit that he's liable to fall into, if he isn't very careful. In Elisha's case, it was forty-two mockers against only one baldhead, and yet his zeal was enough to punish them. So how much worse it's going to be for this man here—a single mocker against all the friars in Christendom, a very high proportion of whom are bald! Besides, we have a Papal Bull expressly forbidding anyone to mock us, on pain of excommunication.'

Seeing that the thing would go on indefinitely, the Cardinal gave the wit a sign to withdraw, and tactfully changed the subject. A few minutes later he got up and dismissed us, as he had to interview some people who'd applied to him for help.

Well, my dear More, I'm afraid I've subjected you to a very long lecture. Only you really did ask for it—and you listened so attentively that I felt you wouldn't want me to leave anything out. Anyway, the conversation seemed worth repeating, if only in general outline, so as to give you some idea of the way these people think. You see, everything I said was treated with contempt, until it appeared that the Cardinal was not against it—and then they were immediately all for it. In their efforts to flatter him, they were even prepared to applaud, and almost take seriously the suggestions made by a hanger-on of his, simply because the great man laughingly approved of them. So you can guess how much notice people would take of me and my advice at Court!

MORE: My dear Raphael, I enjoyed every word of it. There's so much wit and wisdom in everything you say. Besides, it all carried me back, not merely to England, but in a sense to my own boyhood—it recalled such pleasant memories of the Cardinal, in whose household I was brought up. I liked you from the start, my dear Raphael, but you've no idea how much your warm tribute to his memory has increased my feeling for you. But I still can't help thinking that if you could only overcome your aversion to court life, your advice would be extremely useful to the public. Which means that it's your positive duty, as a good man, to give it. You know what your friend Plato says—that a happy state of society will never be achieved, until philosophers are kings, or kings take to studying philosophy. Well, just think how infinitely remote that happy state must remain, if philosophers won't even condescend to give kings a word of advice!

RAPHAEL: Oh, philosophers aren't as bad as all that. They'd be only too glad to offer advice—in fact many of them have done so already in their published works—if only people in power would listen to them. And that's doubtless what Plato meant. He realized that kings are too deeply infected with wrong ideas in childhood to take any philosopher's advice, unless they become philosophers themselves—as he learned by experience with Dionysius. What do you suppose would happen if I started telling a king to make sensible laws, or trying to expel the deadly germs of bad ones from his mind? I'd be promptly thrown out, or merely treated as a figure of fun.

For instance, just imagine me in France, at a top-secret meeting of the Cabinet. The King himself is in the chair, and round the table sit all his expert advisers, earnestly discussing ways and means of solving the following problems: how can His Majesty keep a grip on Milan, and get Naples back into his clutches? How can he conquer Venice, and complete the subjection of Italy? How can he then establish control over Flanders, Brabant, and finally the whole of Burgundy?—not to mention all the other countries that he has already invaded in his dreams.

One gentleman proposes a pact with the Venetians, to remain in force for just so long as the King shall find convenient. He should take them into his confidence, and even allow them a certain amount of the plunder—he can always demand it back later, when he has got what he wants. Another gentleman recommends the employment of German mercenaries, and a third is in favour of greasing the palms of the Swiss. A fourth advises His Majesty to propitiate the Holy Roman Empire with a sacrifice of gold. A fifth thinks it might be wise for him to improve relations with the King of Aragon, and as a peace-offering hand over the kingdom of Navarre—which doesn't belong to him anyway. Meanwhile a sixth is proposing that the Prince of Castile should be enticed into the French camp by promises of a marriage alliance, and that some of his courtiers should be paid a regular salary for their support.

And now for the knottiest problem of all—what's to be done about the English? Well, obviously the first step is to arrange a peace-conference, and conclude a solemn treaty of alliance which means absolutely nothing. In other words, call them friends, but regard them as potential enemies. The Scotch must therefore be kept standing by, ready to start an invasion at a moment's notice, in case the English make the slightest move. It might also be as well to offer secret encouragement—under the terms of the treaty it can't be done openly—to some exiled English nobleman with pretensions to the throne. This would give His Majesty an extra hold over the King of England, whom he otherwise wouldn't trust an inch.

At this point, while all these mighty forces are being set in motion, and all these worthy gentlemen are producing rival plans of campaign, up gets little Raphael, and proposes a complete reversal of policy. I advise the King to forget about Italy and stay at home. I tell him that France is already almost too big for one man to govern properly, so he really needn't worry about acquiring extra territory.

I then refer to an incident in the history of Nolandia, a country just south-east of Utopia. On the strength of some ancient marriage, the King of Nolandia thought he had a hereditary claim to another kingdom, so his people started a war to get it for him. Eventually they won, only to find that the kingdom in question was quite as much trouble to keep as it had been to acquire. There were constant threats of internal rebellion and external aggression. They were always having to fight either for their new subjects or against them. They never got a chance to demobilize, and in the meantime they were being ruined. All their money was going out of the country, and men were losing their lives to pay for someone else's petty ambition. Conditions at home were no safer than they'd been during the war, which had lowered moral standards, by encouraging people to kill and steal. There was no respect whatever for the law, because the King's attention was divided between the two kingdoms, so that he couldn't concentrate properly on either.

Seeing that this hopeless situation would continue indefinitely, if they didn't do something about it, the Nolandians finally decided on a course of action, which was to ask the King, quite politely, which kingdom he wanted to keep.

'You can't keep them both,' they explained, 'because there are too many of us to be governed by half a king. Why, even if we were a lot of mules, it would be a full-time job looking after us!'

So that exemplary monarch was forced to hand over the new kingdom to a friend of his—who was very soon thrown out—and make do with the old one.

I also remind the French King that even if he does start all these wars and create chaos in all these different countries, he's still quite liable to find in the end that he has ruined himself and destroyed his people for nothing. I therefore advise him to concentrate on the kingdom that his ancestors handed down to him, and make it as beautiful and as prosperous as he can, to love his own subjects and deserve their love, to live among them and govern them kindly, and to give up all ideas of territorial expansion, because he has got more than enough to deal with already.

Now tell me, my dear More, how do you think he'll react to my advice?

MORE: Not terribly well, I must admit.

RAPHAEL: Now let's imagine another situation. Suppose some king's financial advisers are discussing how to increase his capital. One suggests raising the value of the currency when the King has to pay money out, and lowering it abnormally when payments are due to him. This will have the effect of increasing his receipts, and reducing the cost of meeting his liabilities. A second suggests that the King should pretend to start a war. This will give him an excuse for levying extra taxes. Then, at his own convenience, he can solemnly make peace, while posing, for the benefit of the lower orders, as a kind ruler who can't bear the thought of bloodshed. A third reminds him of some moth-eaten old law, which has long been obsolete—which everybody breaks, because nobody's aware of its existence—and urges him to collect the fines so incurred. It will greatly redound to his credit, in a moral as well as a financial sense—for the operation will be carried out under the cloak of justice. A fourth advises him to introduce legislation imposing heavy fines for certain offences, preferably of the most anti-social type. He can then sell exemption from such laws to anyone who finds them inconvenient. This will ensure his popularity with the general public, while providing a double source of revenue—for first he'll get the fines collected from profiteers who fall into his trap, and secondly he'll get the money paid for special dispensations. Of course, the price of these will vary in proportion to the King's moral character. The higher his principles, the more reluctant he'll be to let anyone act against the public interest—so the more a dispensation will cost.

A fifth recommends him to get some hold over the judges, so that they'll always give a verdict in his favour. He should also invite them to the Palace, and consult them about his legal position. He may be quite obviously in the wrong, but one of the judges is sure to discover a loophole which will serve to defeat justice. Whatever motives he may have for doing so—a passion for contradiction, a dislike of the obvious, or a simple wish to please—the result will be the same. Soon every judge will be voicing a different opinion, a perfectly clear case will begin to seem controversial, and the plainest facts will be questioned. This will give the King a splendid chance of interpreting the law to his own advantage. Everyone else will agree, from either fear or politeness, and eventually this interpretation will be boldly pronounced from the Bench. After all, there are so many ways of justifying a verdict for the Crown. One can either appeal to equity, or to the letter of the law; or to some perversion of its meaning, or in the last resort to a principle which carries more weight with conscientious judges than any law on earth—the 'indisputable royal prerogative'.

There's unanimous support for the doctrine of Crassus, that you can never have enough money, if you've got an army to maintain. It's also generally agreed that a King can do no wrong, however much he may want to, because everything belongs to him, including every human being in the country, and private property does not exist, except in so far as he's kind enough not to seize it. He should always reduce such provisional private property to a minimum, since his safety depends on preventing his subjects from having too much wealth or freedom. These things make people less willing to put up with injustice and oppression, whereas poverty and privation make them dull and submissive, and stifle the noble spirit of rebellion.

At this point I get up again, and say that it would be most unwise as well as most immoral for the King to do any of these things, because his prestige and security depend less on his own than on his subjects' wealth.

'Why do you suppose they made you king in the first place?' I ask him. 'Not for your benefit, but for theirs. They meant you to devote your energies to making their lives more comfortable, and protecting them from injustice. So your job is to see that they're all right, not that you are—just as a shepherd's job, strictly speaking, is to feed his sheep, not himself. As for the theory that peace is best preserved by keeping the people poor, it's completely contradicted by the facts. Beggars are far the most quarrelsome section of the community. Who is more likely to start a revolution than a man who's discontented with his present living conditions? Who could have a stronger impulse to turn everything upside down in the hope of personal profit, than a man who'd got nothing to lose?

'No, if a king is so hated or despised by his subjects that he can't keep them in order unless he reduces them to beggary by violence, extortion, and confiscation, he'd far better abdicate. Such methods of staying in power may preserve the title, but they destroy the majesty of a king. There's nothing majestic about ruling a nation of beggars—true majesty consists in governing the rich and prosperous. That's what that admirable character Fabricius meant when he said he'd rather govern rich men than be one. Certainly a man who enjoys a life of luxury while everyone else is moaning and groaning round him can hardly be called a king—he's more like a gaoler.

'In short, it's a pretty poor doctor who can't cure one disease without giving you another, and a king who can't suppress crime without lowering standards of living should admit that he just doesn't know how to govern free men. He should start by suppressing one of his own vices—either his pride or his laziness, for those are the faults most liable to make a king hated or despised. He should live on his own resources, without being a nuisance to others. He should adapt his expenditure to his income. He should prevent crime by sound administration rather than allow it to develop and then start punishing it. He should hesitate to enforce any law which has long been disregarded—especially if people have got on perfectly well without it. And he should never invent a crime as an excuse for imposing a fine—no private person would be allowed to do anything so dishonest.'

I then proceed to tell them about a system they have in Happiland, a country not far from Utopia. There the King has to swear a solemn oath at his coronation that he'll never keep more than a thousand pounds of gold in his treasury, or an equivalent amount of silver. Apparently the system was started by an excellent king of theirs, who cared more about his country's welfare than his own. He thought it would prevent the accumulation of royal wealth on such a scale as to cause national poverty, and chose that particular figure because he reckoned it would be enough to suppress a revolution or repel an invasion, but not enough to inspire a king with thoughts of foreign conquest. That was his main idea, but not his only one. He also hoped this arrangement would ensure that there was always enough money in circulation for ordinary purposes of exchange, and that the King would have no motive for raising money unfairly, since he wouldn't be allowed to keep any capital in excess of the statutory limit. Now there you have the type of king who's feared by bad men and loved by good ones—but if I said things like that to people who were quite determined to take the opposite view, do you think they'd listen to me?

MORE: Of course they wouldn't, and I can't say I'd blame them. Frankly, I don't see the point of saying things like that, or of giving advice that you know they'll never accept. What possible good could it do? How can they be expected to take in a totally unfamiliar line of thought, which goes against all their deepest prejudices? That sort of thing is quite fun in a friendly conversation, but at a Cabinet meeting, where major decisions of policy have to be made, such philosophizing would be completely out of place.

RAPHAEL: That's exactly what I was saying—there's no room at Court for philosophy.

MORE: There's certainly no room for the academic variety, which says what it thinks irrespective of circumstances. But there is a more civilized form of philosophy which knows the dramatic context, so to speak, tries to fit in with it, and plays an appropriate part in the current performance. That's the sort you should go in for. Otherwise it would be like interrupting some comedy by Plautus, in which a lot of slaves were fooling about, by rushing on to the stage dressed up as a philosopher, and spouting a bit of that scene in the Octavia where Seneca is arguing with Nero. Surely it would be better to keep your mouth shut altogether than to turn the thing into a tragicomedy by interpolating lines from a different play? For, even if your contribution were an improvement on what had gone before, the effect would be so incongruous that you'd ruin the whole show. No, do the best you can to make the present production a success—don't spoil the entire play just because you happen to think of another one that you'd enjoy rather more.

The same rule applies to politics and life at Court. If you can't completely eradicate wrong ideas, or deal with inveterate vices as effectively as you could wish, that's no reason for turning your back on public life altogether. You wouldn't abandon ship in a storm just because you couldn't control the winds.

On the other hand, it's no use attempting to put across entirely new ideas, which will obviously carry no weight with people who are prejudiced against them. You must go to work indirectly. You must handle everything as tactfully as you can, and what you can't put right you must try to make as little wrong as possible. For things will never be perfect, until human beings are perfect—which I don't expect them to be for quite a number of years!

RAPHAEL: The only advantage of that method would be that I mightn't find it quite so maddening as making a real effort to cure other people's madness. But if I'm to speak the truth, I'll have to say the sort of things that you object to. I don't know whether it's right for a philosopher to tell lies, but it's certainly not my way. Besides, though they might be annoyed by what I said, I don't see why it should be thought so fantastically out of the ordinary. It's not as if I'd recommended the system operated in Plato's imaginary Republic, or in Utopia today. Now that, while undoubtedly better than ours, might well strike them as rather odd, because it's based on communal ownership instead of private property.

Of course they wouldn't like my proposals. Having set their hearts on a certain course of action, they'd naturally resent being shown the dangers that lay ahead, and told to give the whole thing up. But apart from that, what did I say that couldn't or shouldn't be said in any company? If we're never to say anything that might be thought unconventional, for fear of its sounding ridiculous, we'll have to hush up, even in a Christian country, practically everything that Christ taught. But that was the last thing He wanted. Didn't He tell His disciples that everything He had whispered in their ears should be proclaimed on the housetops? And most of His teaching is far more at variance with modern conventions than anything I suggested, except in so far as His doctrines have been modified by ingenious preachers—doubtless on your recommendation!

'We'll never get human behaviour in line with Christian ethics,' these gentlemen must have argued, 'so let's adapt Christian ethics to human behaviour. Then at least there'll be some connection between them.'

But I can't see what good they've done. They've merely enabled people to sin with a clear conscience—and that's about all I could do at a Cabinet meeting. For I'd either have to vote against my colleagues, which would be equivalent to not voting at all, or else I'd have to vote with them, in which case, like Micio in Terence, I'd be 'aiding and abetting insanity'.

As for working indirectly, and when things can't be put right, handling them so tactfully that they're as little wrong as possible, I don't quite see what that means. At Court you can't keep your opinions to yourself, or merely connive at other people's crimes. You have to give open support to deplorable policies, and subscribe to utterly monstrous resolutions. If you don't show enough enthusiasm for a bad law, you'll be taken for a spy or even a traitor. Besides, what chance have you got of doing any good, when you're working with colleagues like that? You'll never reform them—they're far more likely to corrupt you, however admirable a character you are. By associating with them you'll either lose your own integrity, or else have it used to conceal their folly and wickedness. So much for the practical results of your indirect method!

There's a delightful image in Plato, which explains why a sensible person is right to steer clear of politics. He sees everyone else rushing into the street and getting soaked in the pouring rain. He can't persuade them to go indoors and keep dry. He knows if he went out too, he'd merely get equally wet. So he just stays indoors himself, and, as he can't do anything about other people's stupidity, comforts himself with the thought: 'Well, I'm all right, anyway.'

Though, to tell you the truth, my dear More, I don't see how you can ever get any real justice or prosperity, so long as there's private property, and everything's judged in terms of money—unless you consider it just for the worst sort of people to have the best living conditions, or unless you're prepared to call a country prosperous, in which all the wealth is owned by a tiny minority—who aren't entirely happy even so, while everyone else is simply miserable.

In fact, when I think of the fair and sensible arrangements in Utopia, where things are run so efficiently with so few laws, and recognition of individual merit is combined with equal prosperity for all—when I compare Utopia with a great many capitalist countries which are always making new regulations, but could never be called well-regulated, where dozens of laws are passed every day, and yet there are still not enough to ensure that one can either earn, or keep, or safely identify one's so-called private property—or why such an endless succession of never-ending lawsuits?—when I consider all this, I feel much more sympathy with Plato, and much less surprise at his refusal to legislate for a city that rejected egalitarian principles. It was evidently quite obvious to a powerful intellect like his that the one essential condition for a healthy society was equal distribution of goods—which I suspect is impossible under capitalism. For, when everyone's entitled to get as much for himself as he can, all available property, however much there is of it, is bound to fall into the hands of a small minority, which means that everyone else is poor. And wealth will tend to vary in inverse proportion to merit. The rich will be greedy, unscrupulous, and totally useless characters, while the poor will be simple, unassuming people whose daily work is far more profitable to the community than it is to them.

In other words, I'm quite convinced that you'll never get a fair distribution of goods, or a satisfactory organization of human life, until you abolish private property altogether. So long as it exists, the vast majority of the human race, and the vastly superior part of it, will inevitably go on labouring under a burden of poverty, hardship, and worry. I don't say that the burden can't be reduced, but you'll never take it right off their shoulders. You might, of course, set a statutory limit to the amount of money or land that any one person is allowed to possess. You might, by suitable legislation, maintain a balance of power between the King and his subjects. You might make it illegal to buy, or even to apply for a public appointment, and unnecessary for a state official to spend any money of his own—otherwise he's liable to recoup his losses by fraud and extortion, and wealth, rather than wisdom, becomes the essential qualification for such posts. Laws of that type would certainly relieve the symptoms, just as a chronic invalid gets some benefit from constant medical attention. But there's no hope of a cure, so long as private property continues. If you try to treat an outbreak in one part of the body politic, you merely exacerbate the symptoms elsewhere. What's medicine for some people is poison for others—because you can never pay Paul without robbing Peter.

MORE: I disagree. I don't believe you'd ever have a reasonable standard of living under a communist system. There'd always tend to be shortages, because nobody would work hard enough. In the absence of a profit motive, everyone would become lazy, and rely on everyone else to do the work for him. Then, when things really got short, the inevitable result would be a series of murders and riots, since nobody would have any legal method of protecting the products of his own labour—especially as there wouldn't be any respect for authority, or I don't see how there could be, in a classless society.

RAPHAEL: You're bound to take that view, for you simply can't imagine what it would be like—not accurately, at any rate. But if you'd been with me in Utopia, and seen it all for yourself, as I did—I lived there for more than five years, you know, and the only reason why I ever left was that I wanted to tell people about the New World—you'd be the first to admit that you'd never seen a country so well organized.

PETER: I must say, I find it hard to believe that things are so much better organized in the New World than in the Old. I should think we're just as intelligent as they are, and our civilization is older. It therefore embodies the fruits of long experience, by which I mean all the schemes that we've worked out for making life more comfortable—not to mention several chance discoveries, which could never have been achieved by deliberate planning.

RAPHAEL: You'd be more qualified to judge the age of their civilization, if you'd read their history books. If these are to be trusted, there were towns in the New World before human life had even begun in the Old. As for what you say about intelligence and chance discoveries, there's no reason to suppose we have a monopoly of either. We may or may not be more intelligent than they are, but I'm quite sure they leave us far behind in their capacity for concentration and hard work. According to their records, they'd had no contact whatsoever with Trans-equatorials, as they call us, until we landed there—except on one occasion, twelve hundred years ago, when a ship was driven off its course in a storm, and wrecked on the coast of Utopia. A few survivors managed to swim ashore, including some Romans and Egyptians, who settled there for good.

Now, this will give you some idea what good use they make of their opportunities. There wasn't a single useful technique practised anywhere in the Roman Empire that they didn't either learn from these survivors, or else work out for themselves, once they'd been given the first clue. They got all that from just one contact with our hemisphere. But if, by any similar accident, a Utopian has ever found his way over here, we've completely forgotten about it, as I dare say people will soon forget that I was ever there. On the strength of our first meeting, they immediately adopted all the best ideas that Europe has produced—but I doubt if we'd be quite so quick to take over any of their arrangements which are better than ours. And that's the main reason, I think, why although they've got no more intelligence or natural resources than we have, they're so much ahead of us politically and economically.

MORE: In that case, my dear Raphael, for goodness' sake tell us some more about the island in question. Don't try to be too concise—give us a detailed account of it from every point of view, geographical, sociological, political, legal—in fact, tell us everything you think we'd like to know, which means everything we don't know already.

RAPHAEL: There's nothing I'd enjoy more, for it's all quite fresh in my memory. But it'll take some time, you understand.

MORE: All right, let's go in to lunch straight away. Then we'll have the whole afternoon at our disposal.

RAPHAEL: Let's do just that.

So we went indoors and had lunch. After the meal we returned to the same spot, sat down on the same bench, and told the servants we were not to be disturbed. Then Peter Gilles and I asked Raphael to keep his promise. Seeing that we really meant it, he took a few moments to collect his thoughts, and then began as follows:

Book Two

RAPHAEL: Well, the island is broadest in the middle, where it measures about two hundred miles across. It's never much narrower than that, except towards the very ends, which gradually taper away and curve right round, just as if they'd been drawn with a pair of compasses, until they almost form a circle five hundred miles in circumference. So you can picture the island as a sort of crescent, with its tips divided by a strait approximately eleven miles wide. Through this the sea flows in, and then spreads out into an enormous lake—though it really looks more like a vast standing pool, for, as it's completely protected from the wind by the surrounding land, the water never gets rough. Thus practically the whole interior of the island serves as a harbour, and boats can sail across it in all directions, which is very useful for everyone.

The harbour mouth is alarmingly full of rocks and shoals. One of these rocks presents no danger to shipping, for it rises high out of the water, almost in the middle of the gap, and has a tower built on it, which is permanently garrisoned. But the other rocks are deadly, because you can't see them. Only the Utopians know where the safe channels are, so without a Utopian pilot it's practically impossible for a foreign ship to enter the harbour. It would be risky enough even for the local inhabitants, if it weren't for certain landmarks erected on the shore—and by simply shifting these landmarks they could lure any number of enemy warships to destruction. Of course, there are plenty of harbours on the other side of the island, but they're all so well fortified, either naturally or artificially, that a handful of men could easily prevent a huge invading force from landing at any of them.

They say, though, and one can actually see for oneself, that Utopia was originally not an island but a peninsula. However, it was conquered by somebody called Utopos, who gave it its present name—it used to be called Sansculottia—and was also responsible for transforming a pack of ignorant savages into what is now, perhaps, the most civilized nation in the world. The moment he landed and got control of the country, he immediately had a channel cut through the fifteen-mile isthmus connecting Utopia with the mainland, so that the sea could flow all round it. Fearing it might cause resentment if he made the local inhabitants do all the work, he put his whole army on the job as well. With this colossal labour force, he got it done incredibly quickly, to the great surprise and terror of the people on the mainland, who'd begun by making fun of the whole idea.

There are fifty-four splendid big towns on the island, all with the same language, laws, customs, and institutions. They're all built on the same plan, and, so far as the sites will allow, they all look exactly alike. The minimum distance between towns is twenty-four miles, and the maximum, no more than a day's walk.

Each town sends three of its older and more experienced citizens to an annual meeting at Aircastle, to discuss the general affairs of the island. Aircastle is regarded as the capital, because of its central position, which makes it easy to get at from every part of the country. The distribution of land is so arranged that the territory of each town stretches for at least twenty miles in every direction, and in one direction much farther—that is, where the distance between towns reaches its maximum. No town has the slightest wish to extend its boundaries, for they don't regard their land as property but as soil that they've got to cultivate.

At regular intervals all over the countryside there are houses supplied with agricultural equipment, and town dwellers take it in turns to go and live in them. Each house accommodates at least forty adults, plus two slaves who are permanently attached to it, and is run by a reliable, elderly married couple, under the supervision of a District Controller, who's responsible for thirty such houses. Each year twenty people from each house go back to town, having done two years in the country, and are replaced by twenty others. These new recruits are then taught farming by the ones who've had a year on the land already, and so know more about the job. Twelve months later the trainees become the instructors, and so on. This system reduces the risk of food shortages, which might occur if the whole agricultural population were equally inexperienced.

Two years is the normal period of work on the land, so that no one's forced to rough it for too long, but those who enjoy country life—and many people do—can get special permission to stay there longer. Landworkers are responsible for cultivating the soil, raising livestock, felling timber, and transporting it to the towns, either by land or sea, whichever is more convenient. They breed vast numbers of chickens by a most extraordinary method. Instead of leaving the hens to sit on the eggs, they hatch out dozens at a time by applying a steady heat to them—with the result that, when the chicks come out of the shells, they regard the poultryman as their mother, and follow him everywhere!

They keep very few horses, and no really tame ones, as they only use them for riding practice. Ploughing and pulling carts is done by oxen. Admittedly they can't go as fast as horses, but the Utopians say they're tougher and subject to fewer diseases. They're also less trouble and less expensive to feed, and, when they're finally past work, they're still useful as meat.

Corn is used solely for making bread, for they drink no beer, only wine, cider, perry, or water—sometimes by itself, but often flavoured with honey or liquorice, which are both very plentiful. The authorities of each town work out very accurately the annual food consumption of their whole area, but they always grow corn and breed livestock far in excess of their own requirements, so that they've plenty to spare for their neighbours.

Any necessary equipment which is not available in the country is got from one's home town—for there's a holiday once a month, when most people go there. You simply ask an official for what you want, and he hands it over, without any sort of payment.

Just before harvest-time District Controllers notify the urban authorities how much extra labour they'll need. So exactly that number of harvesters turns up punctually on the right day, and, if the weather's good, gets the whole job done in something like twenty-four hours.

But I must tell you some more about the towns. Well, when you've seen one of them, you've seen them all, for they're as nearly identical as local conditions will permit. So I'll just give you one example—it doesn't much matter which. However, the obvious choice is Aircastle, for the fact that Parliament meets there gives it a special importance, and it's the one I know best, having lived there for five years.

Aircastle is built on a gently sloping hill-side, and its ground-plan is practically square. It stretches from just below the top of the hill to the River Nowater, two miles away, and extends for two miles and a bit along the river-bank.

The source of the Nowater is quite a small spring eighty miles further inland, but it's joined by several tributaries, two of them pretty big ones, so by the time it gets to Aircastle it's already more than fifty yards wide. It then keeps on growing wider, until it reaches the sea sixty miles away. Right up to the town, and for several miles beyond it, there are strong tidal currents which change direction every six hours. At high tide the sea comes thirty miles inland, filling the whole river-bed and forcing the river back. The water turns brackish for some distance further up-stream, but after that the taste of salt gradually disappears, and the water which flows past Aircastle is absolutely fresh. At low tide the river chases the sea back, and continues pure and uncontaminated practically all the way to the coast.

The town is connected with the other bank of the river by a splendid arched bridge, with stone piers—not just wooden ones. That's at the landward end, so that ships can have unobstructed access to one whole side of the town. There's also another river, not very big, but delightfully calm and peaceful. It gushes out of the hill on which Aircastle is built, and flows down through the middle of it to join the Nowater. The fountain-head is just outside the town, but they've brought it within the circuit of the city wall, so that in case of invasion the enemy couldn't either cut off, divert, or poison their water supply. From that point water is run off to the lower districts of the town through a system of brickwork pipes. Where this method won't work, they have huge cisterns to collect rainwater—which serves the purpose equally well.

The town is surrounded by a thick, high wall, with towers and blockhouses at frequent intervals. On three sides of it there's also a moat, which contains no water, but is very broad and deep, and obstructed by a thornbush entanglement. On the fourth side the river serves as a moat. The streets are well designed, both for traffic and for protection against the wind. The buildings are far from unimpressive, for they take the form of terraces, facing one another and running the whole length of the street. The fronts of the houses are separated by a twenty-foot carriageway. Behind them is a large garden, also as long as the street itself, and completely enclosed by the backs of other streets. Each house has a front door leading into the street, and a back door into the garden. In both cases they're double swing-doors, which open at a touch, and close automatically behind you. So anyone can go in and out—for there's no such thing as private property. The houses themselves are allocated by lot, and changed round every ten years.

They're extremely fond of these gardens, in which they grow fruit, including grapes, as well as grass and flowers. They keep them in wonderful condition—in fact, I've never seen anything to beat them for beauty or fertility. The people of Aircastle are keen gardeners not only because they enjoy it, but because there are interstreet competitions for the best-kept garden. Certainly it would be hard to find any feature of the town more calculated to give pleasure and profit to the community—which makes me think that gardening must have been one of the founder's special interests.

By the founder I mean Utopos himself, who is said to have designed the whole layout of the town right from the start. However, he left posterity to embellish it and add the finishing touches, which he realized would take more than a single lifetime. According to their historical records, which cover a period of 1,760 years from the Conquest, and have always been most carefully written up, the original houses were merely small huts or cottages, built hurriedly with the first timber that came to hand. The walls were plastered with mud, the roofs ridged and thatched. But nowadays every house is an imposing three-storey structure. The walls are faced with flint or some other hard stone, or else with bricks, and lined with roughcast. The sloping roofs have been raised to the horizontal, and covered with a special sort of concrete which costs next to nothing, but is better than lead for resisting bad weather conditions, and is also fireproof. They keep out draughts by glazing the windows—oh yes, they use a great deal of glass there—or sometimes by fitting screens of fine linen treated with clear oil or amber, which has the effect of making it more transparent and also more airtight.

Now for their system of local government. The population is divided into groups of thirty households, each of which elects an official called a Styward every year. Styward is the Old Utopian title—the modern one is District Controller. For every ten Stywards and the households they represent there is a Bencheater, or Senior District Controller.

Each town has two hundred Stywards, who are responsible for electing the Mayor. They do it by secret ballot, after solemnly swearing to vote for the man that they consider best qualified. He has to be one of four candidates nominated by the whole electorate—for each quarter of the town chooses its own candidate and submits his name to the Council of Bencheaters. The Mayor remains in office for life, unless he's suspected of wanting to establish a dictatorship. Bencheaters are elected annually, but they're not normally changed. All other municipal appointments are for one year only.

Every three days, or more often if necessary, the Bencheaters have a meeting with the Mayor, at which they discuss public affairs, and promptly settle any private disputes—though these are very rare. They always invite two Stywards, a different pair each day, to attend their meetings, and there's a rule that no question affecting the general public may be finally decided until it has been debated for three days. It's a capital crime to discuss such questions anywhere except in the Council or the Assembly. Apparently this is to discourage the Mayor and Bencheaters from plotting to override the people's wishes and change the constitution. For the same reason any major issue is referred to the Assembly of Stywards, who explain it to all their households, talk it over among themselves, and then report their views to the Council. Occasionally the matter is referred to Parliament.

There's also a rule in the Council that no resolution can be debated on the day that it's first proposed. All discussion is postponed until the next well-attended meeting. Otherwise someone's liable to say the first thing that comes into his head, and then start thinking up arguments to justify what he has said, instead of trying to decide what's best for the community. That type of person is quite prepared to sacrifice the public to his own prestige, just because, absurd as it may sound, he's ashamed to admit that his first idea might have been wrong—when his first idea should have been to think before he spoke.

And now for their working conditions. Well, there's one job they all do, irrespective of sex, and that's farming. It's part of every child's education. They learn the principles of agriculture at school, and they're taken for regular outings into the fields near the town, where they not only watch farm-work being done, but also do some themselves, as a form of exercise.

Besides farming which, as I say, is everybody's job, each person is taught a special trade of his own. He may be trained to process wool or flax, or he may become a stonemason, a blacksmith, or a carpenter. Those are the only trades that employ any considerable quantity of labour. They have no tailors or dressmakers, since everyone on the island wears the same sort of clothes—except that they vary slightly according to sex and marital status—and the fashion never changes. These clothes are quite pleasant to look at, they allow free movement of the limbs, they're equally suitable for hot and cold weather—and the great thing is, they're all home-made. So everybody learns one of the other trades I mentioned, and by everybody I mean the women as well as the men—though the weaker sex are given the lighter jobs, like spinning and weaving, while the men do the heavier ones.

Most children are brought up to do the same work as their parents, since they tend to have a natural feeling for it. But if a child fancies some other trade, he's adopted into a family that practises it. Of course, great care is taken, not only by the father, but also by the local authorities, to see that the foster-father is a decent, respectable type. When you've learned one trade properly, you can, if you like, get permission to learn another—and when you're an expert in both, you can practise whichever you prefer, unless the other one is more essential to the public.

The chief business of the Stywards—in fact, practically their only business—is to see that nobody sits around doing nothing, but that everyone gets on with his job. They don't wear people out, though, by keeping them hard at work from early morning till late at night, like cart-horses. That's just slavery—and yet that's what life is like for the working classes nearly everywhere else in the world. In Utopia they have a six-hour working day—three hours in the morning, then lunch—then a two-hour break—then three more hours in the afternoon, followed by supper. They go to bed at 8 p.m., and sleep for eight hours. All the rest of the twenty-four they're free to do what they like—not to waste their time in idleness or self-indulgence, but to make good use of it in some congenial activity. Most people spend these free periods on further education, for there are public lectures first thing every morning. Attendance is quite voluntary, except for those picked out for academic training, but men and women of all classes go crowding in to hear them—I mean, different people go to different lectures, just as the spirit moves them. However, there's nothing to stop you from spending this extra time on your trade, if you want to. Lots of people do, if they haven't the capacity for intellectual work, and are much admired for such public-spirited behaviour.

After supper they have an hour's recreation, either in the gardens or in the communal dining-halls, according to the time of year. Some people practise music, others just talk. They've never heard of anything so silly and demoralizing as dice, but they have two games rather like chess. The first is a sort of arithmetical contest, in which certain numbers 'take' others. The second is a pitched battle between virtues and vices, which illustrates most ingeniously how vices tend to conflict with one another, but to combine against virtues. It also shows which vices are opposed to which virtues, how much strength vices can muster for a direct assault, what indirect tactics they employ, what help virtues need to overcome vices, what are the best methods of evading their attacks, and what ultimately determines the victory of one side or the other.

But here's a point that requires special attention, or you're liable to get the wrong idea. Since they only work a six-hour day, you may think there must be a shortage of essential goods. On the contrary, those six hours are enough, and more than enough to produce plenty of everything that's needed for a comfortable life. And you'll understand why it is, if you reckon up how large a proportion of the population in other countries is totally unemployed. First you have practically all the women—that gives you nearly fifty per cent for a start. And in countries where the women do work, the men tend to lounge about instead. Then there are all the priests, and members of so-called religious orders—how much work do they do? Add all the rich, especially the landowners, popularly known as nobles and gentlemen. Include their domestic staffs—I mean those gangs of armed ruffians that I mentioned before. Finally, throw in all the beggars who are perfectly hale and hearty, but pretend to be ill as an excuse for being lazy. When you've counted them up, you'll be surprised to find how few people actually produce what the human race consumes.

And now just think how few of these few people are doing essential work—for where money is the only standard of value, there are bound to be dozens of unnecessary trades carried on, which merely supply luxury goods or entertainment. Why, even if the existing labour force were distributed among the few trades really needed to make life reasonably comfortable, there'd be so much over-production that prices would fall too low for the workers to earn a living. Whereas, if you took all those engaged in non-essential trades, and all who are too lazy to work—each of whom consumes twice as much of the products of other people's labour as any of the producers themselves—if you put the whole lot of them on to something useful, you'd soon see how few hours' work a day would be amply sufficient to supply all the necessities and comforts of life—to which you might add all real and natural forms of pleasure.

But in Utopia the facts speak for themselves. There, out of all the able-bodied men and women who live in a town, or in the country round it, five hundred at the most are exempted from ordinary work. This includes the Stywards, who, though legally exempt, go on working voluntarily to set a good example. It also includes those who are permanently relieved of other duties so that they can concentrate on their studies. This privilege is only granted on the recommendation of the priests, confirmed by the Stywards in a secret ballot—and, if such a student produces disappointing results, he's sent back to the working class. On the other hand, it's not at all unusual for a manual worker to study so hard in his spare time, and make such good progress, that he's excused from practising his trade, and promoted to the intelligentsia.

This is the class from which the diplomats, priests, Bencheaters, and, of course, mayors are recruited. The old-fashioned word for a mayor, by the way, is Barzanes, though nowadays he's usually called a Nopeople. As hardly any other member of the population is either unemployed or non-productively employed, you can guess how much good work they get done in a few hours. Their labour problem is also reduced by the fact that they tackle essential jobs with more economy of effort than we do. For instance, the reason why the building trade usually absorbs so much labour is that people put up houses which their improvident heirs allow to tumble down. So the next generation has to start building all over again, which costs infinitely more than it would have cost to keep the original houses standing. In fact, what often happens is this: A builds a very expensive house, which then fails to satisfy B's fastidious taste. B therefore neglects it so badly that it's soon in ruins, and builds himself an equally expensive house elsewhere. But in Utopia, where everything's under state control, houses are very seldom built on entirely new sites, and repairs are carried out immediately they become necessary, if not before. Thus they achieve maximum durability with the minimum of labour, which means that builders sometimes have practically nothing to do. On such occasions they're sent home to saw up planks and get stones ready squared, so that if they do have to build anything it can go up all the faster.

Then think how much labour they save on clothes. Their working clothes are just loose-fitting leather overalls, which last for at least seven years. When they go about in public, they cover these rough garments with a sort of cloak, which is always the same colour—the natural colour of wool. Thus not only is their consumption of woollen fabric the lowest in the world, but so are their production costs for this material. Linen is even easier to produce, and therefore more often used—but, as long as the linen is white and the wool is clean, they don't care how fine or coarse the thread is. So whereas in other countries you won't find anyone satisfied with less than five or six suits and as many silk shirts, while dressy types want over ten of each, your Utopian is content with a single piece of clothing every two years. For why should he want more? They wouldn't make him any warmer—or any better looking.

With everybody doing useful work, and with such work reduced to a minimum, they build up such large reserves of everything that from time to time they can release a huge labour force to mend any roads which are in bad condition. And quite often, if there's nothing of that sort to be done, the authorities announce a shorter working day. They never force people to work unnecessarily, for the main purpose of their whole economy is to give each person as much time free from physical drudgery as the needs of the community will allow, so that he can cultivate his mind—which they regard as the secret of a happy life.

Now I'd better explain their social arrangements—how society is organized, how they behave towards one another, how goods are distributed, and so on. Well, the smallest social unit is the household, which is virtually synonymous with the family. When a girl grows up and gets married, she joins her husband's household, but the boys of each generation stay at home, under the control of their oldest male relative—unless he becomes senile, in which case the next oldest takes over.

Each town consists of six thousand households, not counting the country ones, and to keep the population fairly steady there's a law that no household shall contain less than ten or more than sixteen adults—as they can't very well fix a figure for children. This law is observed by simply moving supernumerary adults to smaller households. If the town as a whole gets too full, the surplus population is transferred to a town that's comparatively empty. If the whole island becomes over-populated, they tell off a certain number of people from each town to go and start a colony at the nearest point on the mainland where there's a large area that hasn't been cultivated by the local inhabitants. Such colonies are governed by the Utopians, but the natives are allowed to join in if they want to. When this happens, natives and colonists soon combine to form a single community with a single way of life, to the great advantage of both parties—for, under Utopian management, land which used to be thought incapable of producing anything for one lot of people produces plenty for two.

If the natives won't do what they're told, they're expelled from the area marked out for annexation. If they try to resist, the Utopians declare war—for they consider war perfectly justifiable, when one country denies another its natural right to derive nourishment from any soil which the original owners are not using themselves, but are merely holding on to as a worthless piece of property.

Should any town become so depopulated that it can't be brought up to strength by transfers from elsewhere on the island, without reducing the population of some other town below the prescribed minimum—a thing which is said to have happened only twice in their history, each time as the result of a violent epidemic—they recall colonists to fill the gap, on the principle that it's better to lose a colony than to weaken any part of Utopia itself.

But let's get back to their social organization. Each household, as I said, comes under the authority of the oldest male. Wives are subordinate to their husbands, children to their parents, and younger people generally to their elders. Every town is divided into four districts of equal size, each with its own shopping centre in the middle of it. There the products of every household are collected in warehouses, and then distributed according to type among various shops. When the head of a household needs anything for himself or his family, he just goes to one of these shops and asks for it. And whatever he asks for, he's allowed to take away without any sort of payment, either in money or in kind. After all, why shouldn't he? There's more than enough of everything to go round, so there's no risk of his asking for more than he needs—for why should anyone want to start hoarding, when he knows he'll never have to go short of anything? No living creature is naturally greedy, except from fear of want—or in the case of human beings, from vanity, the notion that you're better than people if you can display more superfluous property than they can. But there's no scope for that sort of thing in Utopia.

These shopping centres include provision markets, to which they take meat and fish, as well as bread, fruit and vegetables. But there are special places outside the town where all blood and dirt are first washed off in running water. The slaughtering of livestock and cleaning of carcasses are done by slaves. They don't let ordinary people get used to cutting up animals, because they think it tends to destroy one's natural feelings of humanity. It's also forbidden to bring anything dirty or unhygienic inside the town, for fear of polluting the atmosphere and so causing disease.

Every so often, as you walk down a street, you come to a large building, which has a special name of its own. That's where the Styward lives, and where his thirty households—fifteen from one direction and fifteen from the other—have their meals. The caterers for such dining-halls go off at a certain time each day to the provision market, where they report the number of people registered with them, and draw the appropriate rations.

But hospital patients get first priority—oh yes, there are four hospitals in the suburbs, just outside the walls. Each of them is about the size of a small town. The idea of this is to prevent overcrowding, and facilitate the isolation of infectious cases. These hospitals are so well run, and so well supplied with all types of medical equipment, the nurses are so sympathetic and conscientious, and there are so many experienced doctors constantly available, that, though nobody's forced to go there, practically everyone would rather be ill in hospital than at home.

However, once the caterers for the hospital have got what the doctors have ordered, all the best food that's left is divided equally among the dining-halls—that is, in proportion to the number registered at each—except that certain people receive preferential treatment, such as the Mayor, the Bishop, Bencheaters, and diplomats. The same applies to foreigners—not that there often are any; but, when there are, they're provided with special furnished accommodation.

At lunch-time and supper-time a bugle is blown, and the whole Sty assembles in the dining-hall—except for anyone who's in hospital or ill at home. However, you're quite at liberty to take food home from the market, once the dining-halls have been supplied, for everyone knows you wouldn't do it unless you had to. I mean, no one likes eating at home, although there's no rule against it. For one thing, it's considered rather bad form. For another, it seems silly to go to all the trouble of preparing an inferior meal, when there's an absolutely delicious one waiting for you at the dining-hall just down the street.

In these dining-halls all the rough and dirty work is done by slaves, but the actual business of preparing and cooking the food, and planning the menus, is left entirely to the women of the household on duty—for a different household is responsible for providing the meals every day. The rest of the adults sit at three tables or more, according to their numbers, with the men against the wall and the women on the outside—so that if they suddenly feel sick, as pregnant women do from time to time, they can get up without disturbing anyone else, and retire to the nursery.

By the nursery I mean a room reserved for nursing mothers and their babies, where there's always a good fire and plenty of clean water. There are also plenty of cots, so that mothers can either put their babies to bed, or, if they like, undress them and let them play in front of the fire. Babies are always breast-fed by their mothers, except when death or illness makes this impossible, in which case the Styward's wife takes immediate steps to find a wet-nurse. This presents no problem, for any woman who's in a position to do so will be only too glad to volunteer for the job. You see, such acts of mercy are universally admired, and the child itself will always regard her as its real mother.

The nursery is also the place where the under-fives have their meals. The other children, that is, all boys and girls who aren't old enough to be married, wait at table in the dining-room, or if they're too young for that, just stand there and keep absolutely quiet. In neither case do they have a separate meal-time—they're fed from the tables of the grown-ups.

The place of honour is the centre of the high table, which is on a platform across the end of the hall, and so commands a view of the whole company. Here sit the Styward and his wife, with two of the oldest residents—for the seating is always arranged in groups of four. If there happens to be a church in the Sty, the priest and his wife automatically take precedence, and sit with the Styward. On either side of them are four younger people, then four more older ones, and so on right round the hall. In other words, you sit with your contemporaries, but you're also made to mix with a different age group. The theory of this, I'm told, is that respect for the older generation tends to discourage bad behaviour among the younger ones—since everything they say or do is bound to be noticed by the people sitting just beside them.

When they're handing out food, they don't work straight along the table from one end to the other. They start by giving the best helpings to the older groups, whose places are clearly marked, and then serve equal portions to the others. However, if there's not enough of some particular delicacy to go round, the older ones share their helpings, as they think fit, with their neighbours. Thus the privilege of age is duly respected—but everyone gets just as much in the end.

Lunch and supper begin with a piece of improving literature read aloud—but they keep it quite short, so that nobody gets bored. Then the older people start discussing serious problems, but not in a humourless or depressing way. Nor do they monopolize the conversation throughout the meal. On the contrary, they enjoy listening to the young ones, and deliberately draw them out, so that they can gauge each person's character and intelligence, as they betray themselves in a relaxed, informal atmosphere.

Lunch is pretty short, because work comes after it, but over supper they rather spread themselves, since it's followed by a whole night's sleep, which they consider more conducive to sound digestion. During supper they always have music, and the meal ends with a great variety of sweets and fruit. They also burn incense, and spray the hall with scent. In fact, they do everything they can to make people enjoy themselves—for they're rather inclined to believe that all harmless pleasures are perfectly legitimate.

Well, that's what life is like in the towns. In the country, because of the greater distances involved, everyone eats at home. Of course, they have just as good food as they'd have in town—for they're the ones who produce what the town-dwellers eat.

Now about travel facilities. If you want to visit friends in some other town, or would simply like to see the town itself, you can easily get permission to go there, unless you're urgently needed at home, by applying to your Styward and your Bencheater. You'll be sent with a party of people travelling on a group passport, signed by the Mayor, which says when you've got to be back. You'll be offered some sort of vehicle, with a slave to drive the oxen and look after them—but, unless there are women in the party, most people find this more trouble than it's worth, and prefer to do without. You needn't take any luggage, for wherever you go you'll be equally at home, and able to get everything you want. If you stay in any place for more than twenty-four hours, you'll be expected to carry on with your ordinary work—and be welcomed with open arms by the other people who do it there.

If you're caught without a passport outside your own district, you're brought home in disgrace, and severely punished as a deserter. For a second offence the punishment is slavery. However, if you feel the urge to go wandering about the countryside near the town, there's nothing to stop your doing so, provided your father gives his permission, and your wife doesn't object. Of course, you won't be able to get a meal anywhere, until you've done either a morning's or an afternoon's work there—but, apart from that, you're free to go wherever you like within the territory of your own town, and you're just as useful a member of society as if you'd stayed at home.

You see how it is—wherever you are, you always have to work. There's never any excuse for idleness. There are also no wine-taverns, no ale-houses, no brothels, no opportunities for seduction, no secret meeting-places. Everyone has his eye on you, so you're practically forced to get on with your job, and make some proper use of your spare time.

Under such a system, there's bound to be plenty of everything, and, as everything is divided equally among the entire population, there obviously can't be any poor people or beggars. Each town, you remember, sends three representatives to the annual Lietalk, or Parliament, at Aircastle. There they collect details of the year's production, and as soon as it's clear which products are plentiful in each area, and which are in short supply, they arrange for a series of transfers to equalize distribution. These transfers are one-way transactions, requiring nothing in return—but in practice the free gifts that Town A makes to Town B are balanced by the free gifts that it receives from Town C. So the whole island is like one big household.

When they've made adequate provision for their own needs—which they don't consider they've done, until their reserves are big enough to last them for a year, no matter what happens during the next twelve months—the remainder is exported. Such exports include vast quantities of corn, honey, wool, flax, timber, scarlet and purple cloth, rawhide, wax, tallow, leather, and livestock. One seventh of their total exports to any country go as a free gift to the poor—the rest they sell at reasonable prices. This foreign trade not only pays for essential imports—which normally means just iron—but also brings in a great deal of money. In fact, over a long period they've built up incredibly large reserves of gold and silver. So nowadays they don't much care whether they sell for cash or on credit, and nearly all their trade is of the second kind. However, when giving credit, they're not content with private securities, but insist on having a legal contract signed, sealed, and delivered by the local authority of the importing area. When payment becomes due, this authority collects the money from the individuals concerned, puts it in the public funds, and enjoys the use of it until such time as the Utopians call it in—which they practically never do, for they think it unfair to deprive other people of anything that's useful to them, if one doesn't need it oneself.

However, if they find it necessary to lend part of this capital to another country, then they do ask for it back—and so they do in wartime, for war is the one thing they have in mind when accumulating all that wealth. You see, it's meant to protect them in the event of any major crisis or emergency. Its chief function is to provide colossal rates of pay for foreign mercenaries—whose lives they risk more willingly than their own. They're also well aware that even enemies can be bribed, if you offer them enough, to betray one another or start fighting among themselves. And that's the only reason why they keep such huge stocks of precious metals. Not that they regard them as precious. In fact, I hardly like to tell you how they do regard them, for fear you shouldn't believe me—a fear which seems all the more reasonable when I think how difficult I'd have found it to believe myself, if I hadn't seen it with my own eyes. For things always sound incredible if they're remote from one's own habits of thought. Still, I suppose it's rather illogical to be surprised at the way they use silver and gold, considering how different all their other customs are from ours. I'm thinking particularly of the fact that they don't use money themselves, but merely keep it for use in an emergency which may or may not arise.

In the meantime silver and gold, the raw materials of money, get no more respect from anyone than their intrinsic value deserves—which is obviously far less than that of iron. Without iron human life is simply impossible, just as it is without fire or water—but we could easily do without silver and gold, if it weren't for the idiotic concept of scarcity-value. And yet kind Mother Nature has deliberately placed all her greatest blessings, like earth, air, and water, right under our noses, and tucked away out of sight the things that are no use to us.

Now if they locked these metals up in a strong-room, the man in the street might get some silly idea into his head—you know what a talent he has for that kind of thing—that the Mayor and the Bencheaters were cheating him, and somehow making a profit out of the stuff. It could, of course, be converted into ornamental bowls or other objets d'art. But then people would grow so fond of them that, if they ever had to melt them down and pay soldiers with them, it would be a terrible wrench.

To get around these difficulties, they've devised a system which, while perfectly consistent with their other conventions, is diametrically opposed to ours—especially to the way we treasure up gold. So you'll probably think it incredible, until you've actually seen it for yourselves. According to this system, plates and drinking-vessels, though beautifully designed, are made of quite cheap stuff like glass or earthenware. But silver and gold are the normal materials, in private houses as well as communal dining-halls, for the humblest items of domestic equipment, such as chamber-pots. They also use chains and fetters of solid gold to immobilize slaves, and anyone who commits a really shameful crime is forced to go about with gold rings on his ears and fingers, a gold necklace round his neck, and a crown of gold on his head. In fact they do everything they can to bring these metals into contempt. This means that if they suddenly had to part with all the gold and silver they possess—a fate which in any other country would be thought equivalent to having one's guts torn out—nobody in Utopia would care two hoots.

It's much the same with jewels. There are pearls to be found on the beaches, diamonds and garnets on certain types of rock—but they never bother to look for them. However, if they happen to come across one, they pick it up and polish it for some toddler to wear. At first, children are terribly proud of such jewellery—until they're old enough to register that it's only worn in the nursery. Then, without any prompting from their parents, but purely as a matter of self-respect, they give it up—just as our children grow out of things like dolls, and conkers, and lucky charms. This curious convention is liable to cause some equally curious reactions, as I realized most vividly in the case of the Flatulentine diplomats.

These diplomats visited Aircastle while I was there, and, as they were coming to discuss a matter of great importance, each town had sent its three Members of Parliament to meet them. Now all foreign diplomats who'd been there before had come from places just across the channel, and were therefore quite familiar with Utopian ideas. They knew it was a country where expensive clothes were not admired, silk was despised, and gold was a dirty word, so they'd dressed as simply as they could for the occasion. But these Flatulentines lived too far away to have had much contact with the Utopians. All they knew was that everyone in Utopia wore the same sort of clothes, and pretty crude ones at that—presumably because they'd nothing better to wear. So they adopted a policy more arrogant than diplomatic, which was to array themselves in positively godlike splendour, and dazzle the wretched Utopians with their magnificence.

When the legation arrived, it consisted of only three men, but these were escorted by a hundred retainers, all wearing multi-coloured clothes, mostly made of silk. As for the great men themselves—for they were great men in their own country—they wore cloth of gold, with great gold chains round their necks, gold ear-rings dangling from their ears, and gold rings on their fingers. Their very hats were festooned with glittering ropes of pearls and other jewels. In fact they were fully equipped with all the things used in Utopia for punishing slaves, humiliating criminals, or amusing small children.

Well, I wouldn't have missed it for anything. There were these three gentlemen, looking terribly pleased with themselves, as they compared their own appearance with that of the local inhabitants—for of course the streets were packed with people. And there was the actual effect that they were producing—so very unexpected and disappointing. You see, from the Utopians' point of view—apart from a few who'd had occasion to go abroad—all that splendour was merely degrading. So they reserved their most respectful greeting for the least distinguished members of the party, and completely ignored the diplomats themselves, assuming from their gold chains that they must be slaves.

Oh, but you should have seen the faces of the older children, who'd grown out of things like pearls and jewels, when they saw the ones on the envoys' hats. They kept nudging their mothers and whispering:

'I say, Mother, just look at that great baby! Fancy wearing jewellery at his age!'

To which the mother would reply, very seriously:

'Sh, dear! I imagine he must be a clown attached to the embassy.'

The gold chains also came in for a lot of criticism.

'I don't think much of that chain,' someone would say. 'It's so thin, the slave could easily break it. Besides, it's far too loose. He could wriggle out of it any time he liked, and run off scot-free!'

But when they'd been there for a day or two, the Flatulentines began to realize the situation. They saw that gold was plentiful, and held extremely cheap—in fact despised as heartily as they themselves admired it. They also noticed that a single runaway slave carried more silver and gold on his person than the three of them put together. So eventually they stopped trying to show off, and, feeling rather ashamed of themselves, abandoned all the finery that they'd been so proud of—especially after a few friendly talks with their hosts, which gave them some insight into local conventions and attitudes. For instance, the Utopians fail to understand why anyone should be so fascinated by the dull gleam of a tiny bit of stone, when he has all the stars in the sky to look at—or how anyone can be silly enough to think himself better than other people, because his clothes are made of finer woollen thread than theirs. After all, those fine clothes were once worn by a sheep, and they never turned it into anything better than a sheep.

Nor can they understand why a totally useless substance like gold should now, all over the world, be considered far more important than human beings, who gave it such value as it has, purely for their own convenience. The result is that a man with about as much mental agility as a lump of lead or a block of wood, a man whose utter stupidity is paralleled only by his immorality, can have lots of good, intelligent people at his beck and call, just because he happens to possess a large pile of gold coins. And if by some freak of fortune or trick of the law—two equally effective methods of turning things upside down—the said coins were suddenly transferred to the most worthless member of his domestic staff, you'd soon see the present owner trotting after his money, like an extra piece of currency, and becoming his own servant's servant. But what puzzles and disgusts the Utopians even more is the idiotic way some people have of practically worshipping a rich man, not because they owe him money or are otherwise in his power, but simply because he's rich—although they know perfectly well that he's far too mean to let a single penny come their way, so long as he's alive to stop it.

They get these ideas partly from being brought up under a social system which is directly opposed to that type of nonsense, and partly from their reading and education. Admittedly, no one's allowed to become a full-time student, except for the very few in each town who appear as children to possess unusual gifts, outstanding intelligence, and a special aptitude for academic research. But every child receives a primary education, and most men and women go on educating themselves all their lives during those free periods that I told you about. Everything's taught in their own language, for it has quite a rich vocabulary. It's also quite pleasant to listen to, and extremely expressive. People are beginning to speak it all over that part of the world—though always in a more or less debased form.

Until we arrived, they didn't even know the name of any famous European philosopher. And yet they'd discovered much the same principles, in music, logic, arithmetic, and geometry, as those early authorities of ours. But though in most things they're on a par with the Ancients, they're no match for the Moderns when it comes to logic. For instance, they've still failed to invent a single one of those rules about Restrictions, Amplifications, and Suppositions which have been so cleverly worked out in A Short Introduction to Logic, for all our schoolboys to learn by heart. And so far from being equal to investigating Second Intentions, they're even blind to the existence of that notorious Universal, M A N. Now he, as you know, is a pretty conspicuous figure, bigger than any giant you ever heard of—but, though we pointed him out quite clearly, none of them could see him.

On the other hand they're great experts in astronomy, and have invented several ingenious instruments for determining the precise positions and movements of the sun and moon, and of all other heavenly bodies visible in their hemisphere. But as for astrology—friendships and quarrels between the planets, fortune-telling by the stars, and all the rest of that humbug—they've never even dreamt of such a thing.

They've learnt by long experience to recognize the signs of approaching rain, wind, and other changes in the weather. But if you asked them to explain the theory of such phenomena, or to say why the sea is salt, or what causes tides, or to give a general account of the origin and nature of the universe, you'd get various different answers. Some of them would be in line with the views of our ancient philosophers. However, as these weren't always unanimous, you won't be surprised to hear that the Utopians have produced some entirely new theories of their own, which aren't wholly consistent with one another either.

In ethics they discuss the same problems as we do. Having distinguished between three types of 'good', psychological, physiological, and environmental, they proceed to ask whether the term is strictly applicable to all of them, or only to the first. They also argue about such things as virtue and pleasure. But their chief subject of dispute is the nature of human happiness—on what factor or factors does it depend? Here they seem rather too much inclined to take a hedonistic view, for according to them human happiness consists largely or wholly in pleasure. Surprisingly enough, they defend this self-indulgent doctrine by arguments drawn from religion—a thing normally associated with a more serious view of life, if not with gloomy asceticism. You see, in all their discussions of happiness they invoke certain religious principles to supplement the operations of reason, which they think otherwise ill-equipped to identify true happiness.

The first principle is that every soul is immortal, and was created by a kind God, Who meant it to be happy. The second is that we shall be rewarded or punished in the next world for our good or bad behaviour in this one. Although these are religious principles, the Utopians find rational grounds for accepting them. For suppose you didn't accept them? In that case, they say, any fool could tell you what you ought to do. You should go all out for your own pleasure, irrespective of right and wrong. You'd merely have to make sure that minor pleasures didn't interfere with major ones, and avoid the type of pleasure that has painful after-effects. For what's the sense of struggling to be virtuous, denying yourself the pleasant things of life, and deliberately making yourself uncomfortable, if there's nothing you hope to gain by it? And what can you hope to gain by it, if you receive no compensation after death for a thoroughly unpleasant, that is, a thoroughly miserable life?

Not that they identify happiness with every type of pleasure—only with the higher ones. Nor do they identify it with virtue—unless they belong to a quite different school of thought. According to the normal view, happiness is the summum bonum towards which we're naturally impelled by virtue—which in their definition means following one's natural impulses, as God meant us to do. But this includes obeying the instinct to be reasonable in our likes and dislikes. And reason also teaches us, first to love and reverence Almighty God, to Whom we owe our existence and our potentiality for happiness, and secondly to get through life as comfortably and cheerfully as we can, and help all other members of our species to do so too.

The fact is, even the sternest ascetic tends to be slightly inconsistent in his condemnation of pleasure. He may sentence you to a life of hard labour, inadequate sleep, and general discomfort, but he'll also tell you to do your best to ease the pains and privations of others. He'll regard all such attempts to improve the human situation as laudable acts of humanity—for obviously nothing could be more humane, or more natural for a human being, than to relieve other people's sufferings, put an end to their miseries, and restore their joie de vivre, that is, their capacity for pleasure. So why shouldn't it be equally natural to do the same thing for oneself?

Either it's a bad thing to enjoy life, in other words, to experience pleasure—in which case you shouldn't help anyone to do it, but should try to save the whole human race from such a frightful fate—or else, if it's good for other people, and you're not only allowed, but positively obliged to make it possible for them, why shouldn't charity begin at home? After all, you've a duty to yourself as well as to your neighbour, and, if Nature says you must be kind to others, she can't turn round the next moment and say you must be cruel to yourself. The Utopians therefore regard the enjoyment of life—that is, pleasure—as the natural object of all human efforts, and natural, as they define it, is synonymous with virtuous. However, Nature also wants us to help one another to enjoy life, for the very good reason that no human being has a monopoly of her affections. She's equally anxious for the welfare of every member of the species. So of course she tells us to make quite sure that we don't pursue our own interests at the expense of other people's.

On this principle they think it right to keep one's promises in private life, and also to obey public laws for regulating the distribution of 'goods'—by which I mean the raw materials of pleasure—provided such laws have been properly made by a wise ruler, or passed by common consent of a whole population, which has not been subjected to any form of violence or deception. Within these limits they say it's sensible to consult one's own interests, and a moral duty to consult those of the community as well. It's wrong to deprive someone else of a pleasure so that you can enjoy one yourself, but to deprive yourself of a pleasure so that you can add to someone else's enjoyment is an act of humanity by which you always gain more than you lose. For one thing, such benefits are usually repaid in kind. For another, the mere sense of having done somebody a kindness, and so earned his affection and good will, produces a spiritual satisfaction which far outweighs the loss of a physical one. And lastly—a belief that comes easily to a religious mind—God will reward us for such small sacrifices of momentary pleasure, by giving us an eternity of perfect joy. Thus they argue that, in the final analysis, pleasure is the ultimate happiness which all human beings have in view, even when they're acting most virtuously.

Pleasure they define as any state or activity, physical or mental, which is naturally enjoyable. The operative word is naturally. According to them, we're impelled by reason as well as an instinct to enjoy ourselves in any natural way which doesn't hurt other people, interfere with greater pleasures, or cause unpleasant after-effects. But human beings have entered into an idiotic conspiracy to call some things enjoyable which are naturally nothing of the kind—as though facts were as easily changed as definitions. Now the Utopians believe that, so far from contributing to happiness, this type of thing makes happiness impossible—because, once you get used to it, you lose all capacity for real pleasure, and are merely obsessed by illusory forms of it. Very often these have nothing pleasant about them at all—in fact, most of them are thoroughly disagreeable. But they appeal so strongly to perverted tastes that they come to be reckoned not only among the major pleasures of life, but even among the chief reasons for living.

In the category of illusory pleasure-addicts they include the kind of person I mentioned before, who thinks himself better than other people because he's better dressed than they are. Actually he's just as wrong about his clothes as he is about himself. From a practical point of view, why is it better to be dressed in fine woollen thread than in coarse? But he's got it into his head that fine thread is naturally superior, and that wearing it somehow increases his own value. So he feels entitled to far more respect than he'd ever dare to hope for, if he were less expensively dressed, and is most indignant if he fails to get it.

Talking of respect, isn't it equally idiotic to attach such importance to a lot of empty gestures which do nobody any good? For what real pleasure can you get out of the sight of a bared head or a bent knee? Will it cure the rheumatism in your own knee, or make you any less weak in the head? Of course, the great believers in this type of artificial pleasure are those who pride themselves on their 'nobility'. Nowadays that merely means that they happen to belong to a family which has been rich for several generations, preferably in landed property. And yet they feel every bit as 'noble' even if they've failed to inherit any of the said property, or if they have inherited it and then frittered it all away.

Then there's another type of person I mentioned before, who has a passion for jewels, and feels practically superhuman if he manages to get hold of a rare one, especially if it's a kind that's considered particularly precious in his country and period—for the value of such things varies according to where and when you live. But he's so terrified of being taken in by appearances that he refuses to buy any jewel until he's stripped off all the gold and inspected it in the nude. And even then he won't buy it without a solemn assurance and a written guarantee from the jeweller that the stone is genuine. But my dear sir, why shouldn't a fake give you just as much pleasure, if you can't, with your own eyes, distinguish it from a real one? It makes no difference to you whether it's genuine or not—any more than it would to a blind man!

And now, what about those people who accumulate superfluous wealth, for no better purpose than to enjoy looking at it? Is their pleasure a real one, or merely a form of delusion? The opposite type of psychopath buries his gold, so that he'll never be able to use it, and may never even see it again. In fact, he deliberately loses it in his anxiety not to lose it—for what can you call it but lost, when it's put back into the earth, where it's no good to him, or probably to anyone else? And yet he's tremendously happy when he's got it stowed away. Now, apparently, he can stop worrying. But suppose the money is stolen, and ten years later he dies without ever knowing it has gone. Then for a whole ten years he has managed to survive his loss, and during that period what difference has it made to him whether the money was there or not? It was just as little use to him either way.

Among stupid pleasures they include not only gambling—a form of idiocy that they've heard about but never practised—but also hunting and hawking. What on earth is the fun, they ask, of throwing dice on to a table? Besides, you've done it so often that, even if there was some fun in it at first, you must surely be sick of it by now. How can you possibly enjoy listening to anything so disagreeable as the barking and howling of dogs? And why is it more amusing to watch a dog chasing a hare than to watch one dog chasing another? In each case the essential activity is running—if running is what amuses you. But if it's really the thought of being in at the death, and seeing an animal torn to pieces before your eyes, wouldn't pity be a more appropriate reaction to the sight of a weak, timid, harmless little creature like a hare being devoured by something so much stronger and fiercer?

So the Utopians consider hunting below the dignity of free men, and leave it entirely to butchers, who are, as I told you, slaves. In their view hunting is the vilest department of butchery, compared with which all the others are relatively useful and honourable. An ordinary butcher slaughters livestock far more sparingly, and only because he has to, whereas a hunter kills and mutilates poor little creatures purely for his own amusement. They say you won't find that type of blood-lust even among animals, unless they're particularly savage by nature, or have become so by constantly being used for this cruel sport.

There are hundreds of things like that, which are generally regarded as pleasures, but everyone in Utopia is quite convinced that they've got nothing to do with real pleasure, because there's nothing naturally enjoyable about them. Nor is this conviction at all shaken by the argument that most people do actually enjoy them, which would seem to indicate an appreciable pleasure-content. They say this is a purely subjective reaction caused by bad habits, which can make a person prefer unpleasant things to pleasant ones, just as pregnant women sometimes lose their sense of taste, and find suet or turpentine more delicious than honey. But however much one's judgement may be impaired by habit or ill health, the nature of pleasure, as of everything else, remains unchanged.

Real pleasures they divide into two categories, mental and physical. Mental pleasures include the satisfaction that one gets from understanding something, or from contemplating truth. They also include the memory of a well-spent life, and the confident expectation of good things to come. Physical pleasures are subdivided into two types. First there are those which fill the whole organism with a conscious sense of enjoyment. This may be the result of replacing physical substances which have been burnt up by the natural heat of the body, as when we eat or drink. Or else it may be caused by the discharge of some excess, as in excretion, sexual intercourse, or any relief of irritation by rubbing or scratching. However, there are also pleasures which satisfy no organic need, and relieve no previous discomfort. They merely act, in a mysterious but quite unmistakable way, directly on our senses, and monopolize their reactions. Such is the pleasure of music.

Their second type of physical pleasure arises from the calm and regular functioning of the body—that is, from a state of health undisturbed by any minor ailments. In the absence of mental discomfort, this gives one a good feeling, even without the help of external pleasures. Of course, it's less ostentatious, and forces itself less violently on one's attention than the cruder delights of eating and drinking, but even so it's often considered the greatest pleasure in life. Practically everyone in Utopia would agree that it's a very important one, because it's the basis of all the others. It's enough by itself to make you enjoy life, and unless you have it, no other pleasure is possible. However, mere freedom from pain, without positive health, they would call not pleasure but anaesthesia.

Some thinkers used to maintain that a uniformly tranquil state of health couldn't properly be termed a pleasure since its presence could only be detected by contrast with its opposite—oh yes, they went very thoroughly into the whole question. But that theory was exploded long ago, and nowadays nearly everybody subscribes to the view that health is most definitely a pleasure. The argument goes like this—illness involves pain, which is the direct opposite of pleasure, and illness is the direct opposite of health, therefore health involves pleasure. They don't think it matters whether you say that illness is or merely involves pain. Either way it comes to the same thing. Similarly, whether health is a pleasure, or merely produces pleasure as inevitably as fire produces heat, it's equally logical to assume that where you have an uninterrupted state of health you cannot fail to have pleasure.

Besides, they say, when we eat something, what really happens is this. Our failing health starts fighting off the attacks of hunger, using the food as an ally. Gradually it begins to prevail, and, in this very process of winning back its normal strength, experiences the sense of enjoyment which we find so refreshing. Now, if health enjoys the actual battle, why shouldn't it also enjoy the victory? Or are we to suppose that when it has finally managed to regain its former vigour—the one thing that it has been fighting for all this time—it promptly falls into a coma, and fails to notice or take advantage of its success? As for the idea that one isn't conscious of health except through its opposite, they say that's quite untrue. Everyone's perfectly aware of feeling well, unless he's asleep or actually feeling ill. Even the most insensitive and apathetic sort of person will admit that it's delightful to be healthy—and what is delight, but a synonym for pleasure?

They're particularly fond of mental pleasures, which they consider of primary importance, and attribute mostly to good behaviour and a clear conscience. Their favourite physical pleasure is health. Of course, they believe in enjoying food, drink, and so forth, but purely in the interests of health, for they don't regard such things as very pleasant in themselves—only as methods of resisting the stealthy onset of disease. A sensible person, they say, prefers keeping well to taking medicine, and would rather feel cheerful than have people trying to comfort him. On the same principle it's better not to need this type of pleasure than to become addicted to it. For, if you think that sort of thing will make you happy, you'll have to admit that your idea of perfect felicity would be a life consisting entirely of hunger, thirst, itching, eating, drinking, rubbing, and scratching—which would obviously be most unpleasant as well as quite disgusting. Undoubtedly these pleasures should come right at the bottom of the list, because they're so impure. For instance, the pleasure of eating is invariably diluted with the pain of hunger, and not in equal proportions either—for the pain is both more intense and more prolonged. It starts before the pleasure, and doesn't stop until the pleasure has stopped too.

So they don't think much of pleasures like that, except in so far as they're necessary. But they enjoy them all the same, and feel most grateful to Mother Nature for encouraging her children to do things that have to be done so often, by making them so attractive. For just think how dreary life would be, if those chronic ailments, hunger and thirst, could only be cured by foul-tasting medicines, like the rarer types of disease!

They attach great value to special natural gifts such as beauty, strength, and agility. They're also keen on the pleasures of sight, hearing, and smell, which are peculiar to human beings—for no other species admires the beauty of the world, enjoys any sort of scent, except as a method of locating food, or can tell the difference between a harmony and a discord. They say these things give a sort of relish to life.

However, in all such matters they observe the rule that minor pleasures mustn't interfere with major ones, and that pleasure mustn't cause pain—which they think is bound to happen, if the pleasure is immoral. But they'd never dream of despising their own beauty, overtaxing their strength, converting their agility into inertia, ruining their physique by going without food, damaging their health, or spurning any other of Nature's gifts, unless they were doing it for the benefit of other people or of society, in the hope of receiving some greater pleasure from God in return. For they think it's quite absurd to torment oneself in the name of an unreal virtue, which does nobody any good, or in order to steel oneself against disasters which may never occur. They say such behaviour is merely self-destructive, and shows a most ungrateful attitude towards Nature—as if one refused all her favours, because one couldn't bear the thought of being indebted to her for anything.

Well, that's their ethical theory, and short of some divine revelation, they doubt if the human mind is capable of devising a better one. We've no time to discuss whether it's right or wrong—nor is it really necessary, for all I undertook was to describe their way of life, not to defend it.

But one thing I'm quite sure of. Whatever you may think of their doctrines, you won't find a more prosperous country or a more splendid lot of people anywhere on earth. Physically, they're very active, full of energy, and stronger than their height would suggest—though you couldn't call them exactly short. Their land isn't always very fertile, and their climate's not too good, but by a well-balanced diet they build up their resistance to bad weather conditions, and by careful cultivation they correct the deficiencies of the soil. The result is that they've beaten all records for the production of corn and livestock, their expectation of life is the highest in the world, and their disease-rate the lowest. Thus, by scientific methods, they've done wonders with a country that's naturally rather barren. Not that their talents are confined to ordinary farming. You'll also find them uprooting whole forests and replanting them elsewhere, not to increase the yield, but to facilitate the transport of timber, by bringing it nearer to the sea, or to a river, or to a town—for it's not so easy to carry timber long distances by roads as corn. The people themselves are friendly and intelligent, with a good sense of humour. Though fond of relaxation, they're capable of hard physical work when necessary. Otherwise they don't much care for it—but they never get tired of using their brains.

When I told them about Greek literature and philosophy—for I didn't think there was anything in Latin that they'd like very much—they became extraordinarily anxious to study the original texts, under my tuition. So I started giving them lessons, at first merely because I didn't like to refuse, rather than from any hope of getting good results. But I soon realized that with such hardworking pupils my own efforts wouldn't be wasted. They had so little difficulty with the letters and pronunciation, learned things so quickly by heart and repeated them so accurately, that I'd have thought it quite miraculous, if I hadn't known that everyone who'd volunteered for the course, and got permission from the Council to join it, was a mature scholar of outstanding intelligence. So in less than three years they knew the language perfectly, and, apart from corruptions in the text, there was nothing to stop them from reading straight through any good author.

My own guess is that Greek somehow came naturally to them, and that's why they found it so easy to learn. You see, I can't help thinking they must be of Greek extraction, since their language, though otherwise more like Persian, contains some traces of Greek in place-names and official titles. I presented them with several Greek texts—for when I started out on the fourth voyage I didn't intend to come back for a very long time, if at all, so, instead of packing a lot of things to sell, I took on board a pretty large trunk full of books. I gave them most of Plato, even more of Aristotle, and Theophrastus's work on botany—but this, I'm sorry to say, was in rather poor condition, as I'd carelessly left it lying around while we were at sea, and a monkey had got hold of it. He'd amused himself by playfully ripping out odd pages here and there, and tearing them to pieces. The only grammar I could let them have was the one by Lascaris, for I hadn't brought my Theodorus with me, and their only dictionaries are those of Hesychius and Dioscorides. They've also got Plutarch, who is their favourite author, and Lucian, whom they find delightfully entertaining. The poets are represented by Aristophanes, Homer, and Euripides—oh yes, and Sophocles—in the miniature Aldine edition, and the historians by Thucydides and Herodotus, not to mention Herodianus.

My friend Tommy Rot had also brought some medical text-books with him, a few short works by Hippocrates, and Galen's Handbook. The Utopians think very highly of them, for, though nobody in the world needs medicine less than they do, nobody has more respect for it. They consider it one of the most interesting and important departments of science—and, as they see it, the scientific investigation of nature is not only a most enjoyable process, but also the best possible method of pleasing the Creator. For they assume that He has the normal reactions of an artist. Having put the marvellous system of the universe on show for human beings to look at—since no other species is capable of taking it in—He must prefer the type of person who examines it carefully, and really admires His work, to the type that just ignores it and like the lower animals remains quite unimpressed by the whole astonishing spectacle.

By applying their trained intelligence to scientific research, they've become amazingly good at inventing things that are useful in everyday life. Two inventions, however, they owe to us—though even there much of the credit should go to them. For the moment we showed them some books that Aldus had printed, and talked a bit about printing and paper-making—we couldn't explain them properly, as none of us knew much about either process—they immediately made a shrewd guess how the things were done. Up till then they'd only produced skin, bark, or papyrus manuscripts, but now they instantly started to manufacture paper, and print from type. At first they weren't too successful, but after repeated experiments they soon mastered both techniques so thoroughly that, if it weren't for the shortage of original texts, they could have all the Greek books they wanted. As it is, they have only the works I mentioned, but of these they've already printed and published several thousand copies.

They welcome foreign tourists with open arms, if they've any special talents to recommend them, or have done a lot of travelling and know about many different countries. That's why they were so glad to see us, for they love hearing what goes on in other parts of the world. But traders don't often call there, for apart from gold and silver, which most traders would rather take home with them, the Utopians import nothing but iron. As for their own export trade, they prefer to deliver things themselves than have people come and fetch them, as this gives them more experience of the outside world, and more practice in navigation.

By the way, the slaves that I've occasionally referred to are not, as you might imagine, non-combatant prisoners-of-war, slaves by birth, or purchases from foreign slave markets. They're either Utopian convicts or, much more often, condemned criminals from other countries, who are acquired in large numbers, sometimes for a small payment, but usually for nothing. Both types of slaves are kept hard at work in chaingangs, though Utopians are treated worse than foreigners. The idea is that it's all the more deplorable if a person who has had the advantage of a first-rate education and a thoroughly moral upbringing still insists on becoming a criminal—so the punishment should be all the more severe.

Another type of slave is the working-class foreigner who, rather than live in wretched poverty at home, volunteers for slavery in Utopia. Such people are treated with respect, and with almost as much kindness as Utopian citizens, except that they're made to work harder, because they're used to it. If they want to leave the country, which doesn't often happen, they're perfectly free to do so, and receive a small gratuity.

As I told you, when people are ill, they're looked after most sympathetically, and given everything in the way of medicine or special food that could possibly assist their recovery. In the case of permanent invalids, the nurses try to make them feel better by sitting and talking to them, and do all they can to relieve their symptoms. But if, besides being incurable, the disease also causes constant excruciating pain, some priests and government officials visit the person concerned, and say something like this:

'Let's face it, you'll never be able to live a normal life. You're just a nuisance to other people and a burden to yourself—in fact you're really leading a sort of posthumous existence. So why go on feeding germs? Since your life's a misery to you, why hesitate to die? You're imprisoned in a torture-chamber—why don't you break out and escape to a better world? Or say the word, and we'll arrange for your release. It's only common sense to cut your losses. It's also an act of piety to take the advice of a priest, because he speaks for God.'

If the patient finds these arguments convincing, he either starves himself to death, or is given a soporific and put painlessly out of his misery. But this is strictly voluntary, and, if he prefers to stay alive, everyone will go on treating him as kindly as ever. Officially sanctioned euthanasia is regarded as an honourable death—but if you commit suicide for reasons which the priests and the Bencheaters do not consider adequate, you forfeit all rights to either burial or cremation, and your body is just thrown unceremoniously into a pond.

Girls aren't allowed to marry until they're eighteen—boys have to wait four years longer. Any boy or girl convicted of premarital intercourse is severely punished, and permanently disqualified from marrying, unless this sentence is remitted by the Mayor. The man and woman in charge of the household in which it happens are also publicly disgraced, for not doing their jobs properly. The Utopians are particularly strict about that kind of thing, because they think very few people would want to get married—which means spending one's whole life with the same person, and putting up with all the inconveniences that this involves—if they weren't carefully prevented from having any sexual intercourse otherwise.

When they're thinking of getting married, they do something that seemed to us quite absurd, though they take it very seriously. The prospective bride, no matter whether she's a spinster or a widow, is exhibited stark naked to the prospective bridegroom by a respectable married woman, and a suitable male chaperon shows the bridegroom naked to the bride. When we implied by our laughter that we thought it a silly system, they promptly turned the joke against us.

'What we find so odd,' they said, 'is the silly way these things are arranged in other parts of the world. When you're buying a horse, and there's nothing at stake but a small sum of money, you take every possible precaution. The animal's practically naked already, but you firmly refuse to buy until you've whipped off the saddle and all the rest of the harness, to make sure there aren't any sores underneath. But when you're choosing a wife, an article that for better or worse has got to last you a lifetime, you're unbelievably careless. You don't even bother to take it out of its wrappings. You judge the whole woman from a few square inches of face, which is all you can see of her, and then proceed to marry her—at the risk of finding her most disagreeable, when you see what she's really like. No doubt you needn't worry, if moral character is the only thing that interests you—but we're not all as wise as that, and even those who are sometimes find, when they get married, that a beautiful body can be quite a useful addition to a beautiful soul. Certainly those wrappings may easily conceal enough ugliness to destroy a husband's feelings for his wife, when it's too late for a physical separation. Of course, if she turns ugly after the wedding, he must just resign himself to his fate—but one does need some legal protection against marriage under false pretences!'

In their case, some such precautions are particularly necessary, since unlike all their neighbours they're strictly monogamous. Most married couples are parted only by death, except in the case of adultery or intolerably bad behaviour, when the innocent party may get permission from the Council to marry someone else—the guilty party is disgraced, and condemned to celibacy for life. But in no circumstances can a man divorce his wife simply because, through no fault of her own, she has deteriorated physically. Quite apart from the cruelty of deserting a person at the very time when she most needs sympathy, they think that, if this sort of thing were allowed, there'd be no security whatever for old age, which not only brings many diseases with it, but is really a disease in itself.

Occasionally, though, divorce by mutual consent is allowed on grounds of incompatibility, when both husband and wife have found alternative partners that seem likely to make them happier. But this requires special permission, which can only be got after a thorough investigation by the Bencheaters and their wives. Even then they're rather reluctant to give it, for they think there's nothing less calculated to strengthen the marriage tie than the prospect of easy divorce.

Adulterers are sentenced to penal servitude of the most unpleasant type. If both offenders are married, their injured partners may, if they like, obtain a divorce and marry one another, or anyone else they choose. But if they continue to love their undeserving mates, they're allowed to stay married to them, provided they're willing to share their working conditions. In such cases the Mayor is sometimes so touched by the guilty party's remorse and the innocent party's loyalty that he lets them both go free. But a second conviction means capital punishment.

Otherwise there are no fixed penalties prescribed by law—the Council decides in each case what sentence is appropriate. Husbands are responsible for punishing their wives, and parents for punishing their children, unless the offence is so serious that it has to be dealt with by the authorities, in the interests of public morality. The normal penalty for any major crime is slavery. They say it's just as unpleasant for the criminals as capital punishment, and more useful to society than getting rid of them right away, since live workers are more valuable than dead ones, and have a more prolonged deterrent effect. However, if convicts prove recalcitrant under this treatment, and don't respond to any sort of prison discipline, they're just slaughtered like wild beasts. But the prospects of those who accept the situation aren't absolutely hopeless. If, after being tamed by years of hardship, they show signs of feeling really sorry, not merely for themselves, but for what they've done, their sentence is either reduced or cancelled altogether, sometimes at the discretion of the Mayor, and sometimes by a general plebiscite.

Attempted seduction is punished no less severely than actual seduction. The same applies to every other type of offence—anyone who deliberately tries to commit a crime is legally assumed to have committed it. It's no fault of his, they argue, that he didn't bring it off, so why give him credit for his failure?

They're extremely fond of people who are mentally deficient and, though it's considered very bad form to insult them, it's quite in order to find their silly behaviour amusing. In fact, it's thought better for them that you should, for, if you haven't enough sense of humour to see anything funny about the things they say and do, you're obviously not the right person to look after them. I mean, if you don't value them even as a source of entertainment, which is the only thing they're good for, you won't treat them kindly enough.

But if you start laughing at anyone who's ugly or deformed everyone will start laughing at you. You'll have made an awful fool of yourself by implying that people are to blame for things they can't help—for, although one's thought very lazy if one doesn't try to preserve one's natural beauty, the Utopians strongly disapprove of make-up. Actually, they've found by experience that what husbands look for in their wives is not so much physical beauty, as modesty and a respectful attitude towards themselves. A pretty face may be enough to catch a man, but it takes character and good nature to hold him.

The Utopian system includes not only deterrents from crime, but also incentives to good behaviour in the form of public honours. For instance, they put up statues in the market-place of people who've distinguished themselves by outstanding services to the community, partly to commemorate their achievements, and partly to spur on future generations to greater efforts, by reminding them of the glory of their ancestors. But anyone who deliberately tries to get himself elected to a public office is permanently disqualified from holding one. Social relations are uniformly friendly, for officials are never pompous or intimidating in their manner. They're normally addressed as 'Father', and that's how they behave. Everyone treats them with proper respect, but nobody's forced to do so. Even the Mayor himself wears perfectly ordinary clothes, without any special headdress. His only badge of office is a bunch of corn that he carries—just as a Bishop carries a taper.

They have very few laws, because, with their social system, very few laws are required. Indeed, one of their great complaints against other countries is that, although they've already got books and books of laws and interpretations of laws, they never seem to have enough. For, according to the Utopians, it's quite unjust for anyone to be bound by a legal code which is too long for an ordinary person to read right through, or too difficult for him to understand. What's more, they have no barristers to be over-ingenious about individual cases and points of law. They think it better for each man to plead his own cause, and tell the judge the same story as he'd otherwise tell his lawyer. Under such conditions, the point at issue is less likely to be obscured, and it's easier to get at the truth—for, if nobody's telling the sort of lies that one learns from lawyers, the judge can apply all his shrewdness to weighing the facts of the case, and protecting simple-minded characters against the unscrupulous attacks of clever ones.

This arrangement wouldn't work very well in other countries, because there's such a mass of complicated legislation to deal with. But in Utopia everyone's a legal expert, for the simple reason that there are, as I said, very few laws, and the crudest interpretation is always assumed to be the right one. They say the only purpose of a law is to remind people what they ought to do, so the more ingenious the interpretation, the less effective the law, since proportionately fewer people will understand it—whereas the simple and obvious meaning stares everyone in the face. From the point of view of the lower orders, who form the largest section of the community, and are most in need of such reminders, you might just as well not make a law at all, as make one and then interpret it in a sense that can only be established after a lot of clever argument—for the ordinary person who's busy earning his living hasn't either the time or the mental capacity for that type of research.

Because of their many good qualities, the Utopians are asked by several of their neighbours to supply them with government officials, some on an annual and some on a quinquennial basis. Of course, this only happens where the people are free to make their own decisions—but the Utopians liberated most of the countries round them from dictatorships long ago. When their tour of duty expires, these officials are repatriated with every mark of honour and esteem, and replaced by other Utopians. It's certainly a very wise move on the part of the countries concerned, for the welfare of a state depends entirely on the quality of its administrators, and the Utopians are obviously ideal for the job. They can't be bribed to do anything dishonest, as they'll soon be going home, where money is no use to them. And as they don't know any of the local inhabitants, they're never tempted by private likes or dislikes to make a wrong decision. These qualifications are particularly important for a judge, because personal prejudice and financial greed are the two great evils that threaten courts of law, and once they get the upper hand they immediately hamstring society, by destroying all justice.

When the Utopians talk about their 'allies' they mean these countries which they supply with administrators. 'Friendly powers' are countries that they've helped in any other way. But they never make any actual treaties of the kind that are so constantly being made, broken, and renewed by other nations. What, they ask, is the good of a treaty? Aren't all human beings natural allies already? And if a person's prepared to ignore a fundamental bond like that, is he likely to pay much attention to a mere form of words? They take this view mainly because, in their part of the world, kings aren't very scrupulous about observing pacts and agreements. In Europe, of course, especially the Christian parts of it, treaties are universally regarded as sacred and inviolate, partly because our kings are so good and just themselves, and partly because they're so much in awe of the Popes. They, as we know, not only discharge their own obligations most religiously, but command all other rulers to keep their promises whatever happens, and administer stern pastoral rebukes to any who fail to do so. They evidently think, quite rightly, that it looks extremely bad for the so-called 'faithful' to break faith in such matters.

But in their part of the world, which is diametrically opposed to ours, no less in a social and moral than in a geographical sense, you can't rely on treaties at all. The more solemnly they're made, the sooner they're violated, by the simple process of discovering some loophole in the wording. Indeed, such loopholes are often incorporated deliberately in the original text, so that, no matter how binding one's commitments appear to be, one can always wriggle out of them, thus breaking both treaty and faith simultaneously. The fact is, such diplomacy is downright dishonest. If the very people who pride themselves on suggesting such tricks to their rulers found the same sort of thing going on in connection with a private contract, they'd be the first to denounce it, in shrill, self-righteous tones, as sacrilegious and criminal. The implication seems to be that honesty is a low plebeian virtue, far beneath the dignity of royalty—or at least that there are two kinds of honesty. One is suitable for ordinary people, a plodding hack which is kept securely tethered, so that it can't go leaping any fences. The other, reserved for kings, is a far nobler animal which enjoys far greater freedom—for it's allowed to do exactly what it likes.

Anyway, that's how kings behave out there, and that, as I was saying, is presumably why the Utopians make no treaties. Perhaps if they lived in Europe they'd change their minds—though actually they disapprove of treaties on principle, however scrupulously they're observed. They say treaties make people regard one another as natural enemies. The mere fact of living on different sides of a small hill or river is supposed to sever all ties of humanity, and justify two nations in trying to destroy each other, unless there's a special treaty to forbid it. And even if there is such a treaty, it still doesn't mean that they're friends, for they always retain the right to rob one another, in so far as the drafters of the treaty have carelessly failed to include enough provisions to the contrary. The Utopians take precisely the opposite view. They think no one should be regarded as an enemy who hasn't done you any harm. Human nature constitutes a treaty in itself, and human beings are far more effectively united by kindness than by contracts, by feelings than by words.

And that brings us to the subject of war. Well, fighting is a thing they absolutely loathe. They say it's a quite subhuman form of activity, although human beings are more addicted to it than any of the lower animals. In fact, the Utopians are practically the only people on earth who fail to see anything glorious in war. Of course, both sexes are given military training at regular intervals, so that they won't be incapable of fighting if they ever have to do it. But they hardly ever go to war, except in self-defence, to repel invaders from friendly territory, or to liberate the victims of dictatorship—which they do in a spirit of humanity, just because they feel sorry for them. However, they give military support to 'friendly powers', not only in defensive wars, but also in attempts to make reprisals for acts of aggression. This is always on condition that they're consulted well in advance, that they think the casus belli adequate, that compensation has been demanded and refused, and that the control of operations is left entirely to them. Their idea of an adequate casus belli includes more than robbery by force of arms. They take even stronger action to protect the rights of traders who are subjected to any kind of legal injustice in foreign countries, either as a result of unfair laws, or of fair ones deliberately misinterpreted.

That's how the war with Blindland started, a little before our time. The Utopians gave military aid to the Cloudians, because some Cloudian businessmen operating in Blindland had been the victims of some sort of legal fraud—or so the Utopians thought. Whether they were right or wrong, the result was a major war, for the bitterness of the original conflict was stepped up by the intervention of all the surrounding countries. By the time it was over, the strength of several great powers had been shattered, and others had sustained crippling losses. As for the Blindlanders, after a series of disasters they finally had to give in. The Utopians got nothing out of it—their motives were quite disinterested throughout—but the Blindlanders became the slaves of the Cloudians, who in the old days had been no match for them at all.

So you see how quick the Utopians are to avenge injuries done to their friends, even in money matters. But they're far more tolerant of injuries done to themselves. If a Utopian trader is cheated out of his goods, but suffers no physical injury, the strongest action they take is to suspend trade relations with the country concerned, until they receive compensation. Not that they care less about their own people—it's just that members of other nations are far more vulnerable to fraud, since it means the loss of their own private property, whereas a Utopian in similar circumstances loses nothing whatever. The loss is borne by the state. Besides, any goods lost are surplus to home requirements, or they'd never have been exported. So nobody feels any the worse for it—and they think it would be cruel to kill large numbers of people in revenge for something which hasn't made the slightest difference to the life or the livelihood of a single Utopian. But they take a very different line if one of their citizens is physically disabled or killed, either by a foreign government or by an individual foreigner. The moment they get news of such an incident through diplomatic channels, they immediately declare war. No form of appeasement has any effect, except the surrender of the people responsible—in which case they're sentenced to death or slavery.

They don't like bloody victories—in fact they feel ashamed of them, for they consider it stupid to pay too high a price for anything, however valuable it is. What they're really proud of is outwitting the enemy. They celebrate any success of this kind by a triumphal procession, and by putting up a trophy, as for some feat of heroism. You see, their idea of quitting themselves like men is to achieve victory by means of something which only man possesses, that is, by the power of the intellect. They say any animal can fight with its body—bears, lions, boars, wolves, dogs can all do it, and most of them are stronger and fiercer than we are—but what raises us above them is our reason and intelligence.

Their one aim in wartime is to get what they've previously failed to get by peaceful means—or, if that's out of the question, to punish the offenders so severely that nobody will ever dare to do such a thing again. They make for these objectives by the shortest possible route—but always on the principle of safety first, and national prestige second. So the moment war's declared they arrange through secret agents for lots of posters to go up simultaneously at all points on enemy territory where they're most likely to be seen. These posters carry the official seal of the Utopian government, and offer a huge reward for killing the enemy king. They also offer smaller, but still very considerable sums for killing certain individuals, whose names appear on a list, and who are presumed to be the chief supporters, after the king, of anti-Utopian policies. The reward for bringing such people in alive is twice as much as for killing them—and they themselves are offered the same amount of money, plus a free pardon, for turning against their own associates.

The immediate result is that everyone mentioned on the list becomes suspicious of everything in human shape. They all stop trusting one another, and stop being trustworthy. They live in a constant state of terror, which is perfectly justified—for it's often been known to happen that all of them, including the king himself, are betrayed by the very person that they pinned most faith on. The fact is, people will do anything for money, and there's no limit to the amount of money that the Utopians are prepared to give. Bearing in mind the risks that they're inviting each traitor to run, they're very careful to offer him compensating advantages. So, in addition to vast quantities of gold, they also promise him the freehold of a valuable estate in safe and friendly territory—and such promises they invariably keep.

This system of making take-over bids for the enemy is generally considered mean and cruel, but the Utopians are very proud of it. They say it's extremely sensible to dispose of major wars like this without fighting a single battle, and also most humane to save thousands of innocent lives at the cost of a few guilty ones. They're thinking of all the soldiers who would have been killed in action, on one side or the other—for they feel almost as much sympathy for the mass of the enemy population as they do for their own. They realize that these people would never have started a war if they hadn't been forced into it by the insanity of their rulers.

If this method fails, they sow and foster the seeds of discord among their enemies, by encouraging the king's brother or some other member of the aristocracy to aspire to the throne. If internal dissension shows signs of flagging, they inflame hostility in some adjacent country by digging up one of those ancient claims that kings are always so well provided with. They promise to support the claimant's war effort, and do it by supplying plenty of money and very little manpower—for they're much too fond of one another to be willing to sacrifice a single Utopian citizen, even in exchange for the enemy king himself. But they're perfectly happy to hand out silver and gold, because that's all they keep it for, and they know it won't make any difference to their standard of living if they spend the whole lot. Besides, quite apart from their capital at home, they possess vast foreign assets, for, as I explained before, a great many countries owe them money.

So most of their fighting is done by mercenaries. They recruit them from all over the world, but especially from a place called Venalia, which is about five hundred miles to the east of Utopia. The Venalians are extremely primitive and savage—like the wild forests and rugged mountains among which they grow up. They're very tough, and can stand any amount of heat, cold, and physical hardship. They've no idea of enjoying themselves, never do any farming, and are equally careless about their clothes and their houses. Apart from looking after cattle, they live mostly by hunting and stealing. In fact, they seem naturally designed for nothing but war. They're always looking for a war to fight in, and when they succeed in finding one they go rushing off in their thousands to offer their services cheap to anyone who needs soldiers. For taking lives is the only method they know of earning a living.

They fight for their employers with great loyalty and zeal, but won't guarantee how long they'll continue to do so. They join you on the understanding that they'll join your enemy tomorrow, if he'll pay them better, and be back with you the day after that, if you'll give them a little bit more. There aren't many wars in which you won't find that most of the soldiers on each side are Venalians. So you can imagine the sort of thing that's always happening. Two members of a family enlist in the same army. For a while they're the best of friends—the next moment they're on opposite sides, and going for one another like deadly enemies. All ties of blood and friendship are forgotten, and they're busy cutting each other's throats. And yet their only motive for mutual destruction is the fact that different kings are paying them small sums of money—and money means such a lot to them that an extra halfpenny a day is quite enough to make them change sides. But although they yield so quickly to the temptations of avarice, they get nothing out of it, for what they earn by bloodshed they immediately spend on debauchery of the most squalid type.

These people will fight for the Utopians against any nation in the world, because no one else is prepared to pay them so much. You see, the Utopians are just as anxious to find wicked men to exploit as good men to employ. So when necessary they tempt Venalians with lavish promises to engage in desperate enterprises, from which most of them never come back to claim their earnings. But those who do are always paid in full, so that they'll think it worth while to take similar risks in future. For the Utopians don't care how many Venalians they send to their deaths. They say, if only they could wipe the filthy scum off the face of the earth completely, they'd be doing the human race a very good turn.

Their second source of manpower is the nation for whose benefit they've gone to war. Next come contingents supplied by other friendly powers, and last of all their own citizens, from whom they choose a man of proved ability to command the combined forces. They also keep two others standing by, who have no particular duties so long as the general is all right. But if he's killed or taken prisoner, one of them inherits his command—and, if necessary, the other takes over from him. This is to allow for the changing fortunes of war, and ensure that the whole army won't become disorganized, no matter what happens to the general.

The Utopian contingent is made up of volunteers from every town—for no one is conscripted for military service abroad. They feel that nervous people are not only unlikely to make good soldiers, but also apt to lower the morale of those around them. However, in case of invasion, able-bodied men of this type are either drafted into the navy, to serve alongside more reliable personnel, or posted at intervals on some city wall, where they've no chance of running away. When they actually come face to face with the enemy, respect for public opinion, combined with the fact that there's simply no escape, usually overcomes their fear, and in the last resort they often fight like heroes.

But nobody's forced to fight overseas, and similarly no wife is forced to stay at home, if she'd rather go with her husband to the front. On the contrary, that sort of thing is much encouraged and admired. Any such wife is stationed immediately beside her husband on the battlefield, along with his children and the rest of his relations. The idea is that those who have the strongest natural instinct to help one another should be enabled to do so, by being kept as close together as possible. It's a terrible disgrace for a husband to come back without his wife, or a wife without her husband, or a child without its parents. This means that once their forces are engaged, they go on fighting to the bitter end—that is, if the enemy is prepared to stick it out. So long as they're able to wage war by proxy, the Utopians do everything they can to keep out of action, but when they're finally compelled to fight their courage is fully equal to their previous caution.

They don't fly into a fury at the first attack, but gradually, as time goes on, they grow more and more determined, until they'd rather die than yield an inch. They know there's no need to worry about food for their families, or about their children's future—two sources of anxiety that usually tend to undermine a soldier's morale—and this gives them a lofty contempt for the very idea of defeat. Their confidence is also increased by their military training. And finally they're fortified by the sound principles which they absorbed in childhood, both from their education and from their social environment. These ensure that they value life too much to throw it recklessly away, but not enough to cling on to it in a mean and cowardly manner, when it's their duty to give it up.

When the battle is at its height, a group of specially selected young men, who have sworn to stick together, try to knock out the enemy general. They keep hammering away at him by every possible method—frontal attacks, ambushes, long-range archery, hand-to-hand combat. They bear down on him in a long, unbroken wedge-formation, the point of which is constantly renewed as tired men are replaced by fresh ones. As a result, the general is nearly always killed or taken prisoner—unless he saves his skin by running away.

If the Utopians win a battle, they don't go in for any massacres. Once they've got the enemy on the run they prefer capturing to killing. They also make it a rule never to start off in pursuit, unless they can keep at least one line of troops drawn up in battle formation. They're so strict about this that, if they fail to win a battle until their rearguard goes into action, they're prepared to let the whole enemy army escape rather than establish a precedent for breaking ranks in order to pursue it. You see, they never forget a trick that they've played several times themselves. On each of these occasions the main Utopian army had been totally defeated, and the enemies were triumphantly chasing stragglers about in all directions. At this point the entire outcome of the battle was reversed by a handful of Utopians who'd been stationed in reserve. Watching for their opportunity, they suddenly counter-attacked the scattered enemy troops, who were taking no precautions, because they thought they were safe. Thus certain victory was wrested from the enemy's grasp, and the vanquished became the victors.

It's hard to say which are more cunning, their offensive or their defensive tactics. You may think they're going to retire, when it's the last thing they have in mind—and when they've really decided to do so, you'd never think it to look at them. If they feel seriously outnumbered or handicapped by the terrain, they decamp during the night without a sound, or find some other method of deluding the enemy. Or else they withdraw in daylight, but do it so gradually, and preserve such perfect formation, that they're just as dangerous to attack while retreating as while advancing.

They're always careful to fortify their camp with a very deep, broad trench, throwing the earth from inside to form a rampart. For this job they don't rely on slave labour. The soldiers do it themselves, which means every soldier in the army, except for a few armed sentries who are posted in front of the rampart to watch out for emergencies. With so many hands at work, they can get a large area effectively fortified in an incredibly short time.

Their armour is strong enough to give adequate protection, but yields to every movement of the body. It doesn't even interfere with swimming—in fact they practise swimming in armour from a very early stage of their military training. Their long-range weapons are arrows, which cavalry as well as infantry learn to discharge with great force and accuracy. For close combat they use not swords but battle-axes, which because of their weight and sharpness are equally deadly for slashing or for stabbing. They also invent and manufacture most ingenious mechanical weapons, which are carefully kept out of sight until it's time to put them into action—otherwise such things are liable to be treated as a joke, and are therefore less effective. In designing this type of apparatus they concentrate particularly on making it mobile and easy to operate.

Once they've signed an armistice, they never break it, however much they've provoked. They never devastate enemy territory, or burn corn growing on it—for they regard such corn as being grown for their own benefit, so they do all they can to ensure that it's not trampled down either by their cavalry or by their infantry. They never hurt an unarmed man, unless he's a spy. They give protection to any town that surrenders, and even if they have to take it by storm they still don't loot it. They merely kill those responsible for its failure to surrender, and enslave the rest of the garrison. The whole civilian population remains untouched. Anyone known to have spoken in favour of surrender is given part of the property left by those condemned to death or slavery. The residue is presented to the allied forces—for nobody in Utopia gets any share of the spoil.

When the war's over, they send in the bill, not to the friendly powers for whose sake the expenses were incurred, but to the defeated enemy. They demand to be paid partly in cash, which is put aside for use in future wars, and partly in freeholds of valuable estates on enemy territory. Thus they've acquired property in many different countries, and the resultant income, built up gradually from various sources, has now reached the equivalent of more than £327,000 per annum. To each of these countries they send out Utopian citizens, nominally to act as rent-collectors, but actually to live there in grand style and play the part of distinguished local residents. Still, there's plenty of money left over to pay into the Exchequer, unless they prefer to lend it to the country concerned, which they often do, until such time as they actually need it themselves—and even then they very seldom call in the whole amount. Some of these estates they make over to individuals whom they've persuaded to take the sort of risks that I mentioned before.

If any king goes to war with them and prepares to invade their territory, they send off a large force to intercept him before he reaches the frontier—for they never fight on their own soil if they can help it, and in no circumstances will they allow allied troops to set foot on the island itself.

Finally, let me tell you about their religious ideas. There are several different religions on the island, and indeed in each town. There are sun-worshippers, moon-worshippers, and worshippers of various other planets. There are people who regard some great or good man of the past not merely as a god, but as the supreme god. However, the vast majority take the much more sensible view that there is a single divine power, unknown, eternal, infinite, inexplicable, and quite beyond the grasp of the human mind, diffused throughout this universe of ours, not as a physical substance, but as an active force. This power they call 'The Parent'. They give Him credit for everything that happens to everything, for all beginnings and ends, all growth, development, and change. Nor do they recognize any other form of deity.

On this point, indeed, all the different sects agree—that there is one Supreme Being, Who is responsible for the creation and management of the universe, and they all use the same Utopian word to describe Him: Mythras. What they disagree about is, who Mythras is. Some say one thing, some another—but everyone claims that his Supreme Being is identical with Nature, that tremendous power which is internationally acknowledged to be the sole cause of everything. However, people are gradually tending to drift away from all these inferior creeds, and to unite in adopting what seems to be the most reasonable religion. And doubtless the others would have died out long ago if it weren't for the superstitious tendency to interpret any bad luck, when one's thinking of changing one's religion, not as a coincidence, but as a judgement from heaven—as though the discarded god were punishing one's disloyalty.

But when we told them about Christ, His teaching, His character, His miracles, and the no less miraculous devotion of all the martyrs who, by voluntarily shedding their blood, converted so many nations to the Christian faith, you've no idea how easy it was to convert them too. Perhaps they were unconsciously influenced by some divine inspiration, or perhaps it was because Christianity seemed so very like their own principal religion—though I should imagine they were also considerably affected by the information that Christ prescribed of His own disciples a communist way of life, which is still practised today in all the most truly Christian communities. Anyway, whatever the explanation, quite a lot of Utopians adopted our religion, and were baptized.

Unfortunately none of us four was a priest—yes, there were only four of us left—the other two had died. So though they've been admitted to all the other rites of the Church, our converts haven't yet received the sacraments that only priests can administer. But they understand about them, and want them more than anything on earth. In fact, just now they're busy discussing whether it would be in order for one of them to be ordained priest, without sending for a Christian bishop to perform the ceremony. And it certainly looked as if they were going to choose a candidate for the job, though they hadn't actually done so by the time I left.

Of course, many Utopians refuse to accept Christianity, but even they make no attempt to discourage other people from adopting it, or to attack those who do—though there was one member of our congregation who got into trouble while I was there. Immediately after his baptism, in spite of all our advice to the contrary, this man started giving public lectures on the Christian faith, in which he showed rather more zeal than discretion. Eventually he got so worked up that, not content with asserting the superiority of our religion, he went so far as to condemn all others. He kept shouting at the top of his voice that they were all vile superstitions, and that all who believed in them were monsters of impiety, destined to be punished in hell-fire for ever. When he'd been going on like this for some time, he was arrested and charged, not with blasphemy, but with disturbance of the peace. He was duly convicted and sentenced to exile—for one of the most ancient principles of their constitution is religious toleration.

This principle dates right back to the time of the Conquest. Up till then there'd been constant quarrels about religion, and the various warring sects had refused to cooperate in the defence of their country. When Utopos heard how they'd behaved, he realized that this was why he'd been able to conquer the whole lot of them. So immediately after his victory he made a law, by which everyone was free to practise what religion he liked, and to try and convert other people to his own faith, provided he did it quietly and politely, by rational argument. But, if he failed to convince them, he was not allowed to make bitter attacks on other religions, nor to employ violence or personal abuse. The normal penalty for being too aggressive in religious controversy is either exile or slavery.

Utopos made this law, not only to preserve the peace, which he saw being completely destroyed by endless disputes and implacable feuds, but also because he thought it was in the best interests of religion itself. He didn't presume to say which creed was right. Apparently he considered it possible that God made different people believe different things, because He wanted to be worshipped in many different ways. But he was evidently quite certain that it was stupid and arrogant to bully everyone else into adopting one's own particular creed. It seemed to him perfectly obvious that, even if there was only one true religion, and all the rest were nonsense, truth would eventually prevail of its own accord—as long as the matter was discussed calmly and reasonably. But if it was decided by force of arms, the best and most spiritual type of religion would go down before the silliest forms of superstition, just as corn is liable to be overgrown by thorns and brambles—for the worst people are always the most obstinate.

So he left the choice of creed an open question, to be decided by the individual according to his own ideas—except that he strictly and solemnly forbade his people to believe anything so incompatible with human dignity as the doctrine that the soul dies with the body, and the universe functions aimlessly, without any controlling providence. That's why they feel so sure that there must be rewards and punishments after death. Anyone who thinks differently has, in their view, forfeited his right to be classed as a human being, by degrading his immortal soul to the level of an animal's body. Still less do they regard him as a Utopian citizen. They say a person like that doesn't really care a damn for the Utopian way of life—only he's too frightened to say so. For it stands to reason, if you're not afraid of anything but prosecution, and have no hopes of anything after you're dead, you'll always be trying to evade or break the laws of your country, in order to gain your own private ends. So nobody who subscribes to this doctrine is allowed to receive any public honour, hold any public appointment, or work in any public service. In fact such people are generally regarded as utterly contemptible.

They're not punished in any way, though, for no one is held responsible for what he believes. Nor are they terrorized into concealing their views, because Utopians simply can't stand hypocrisy, which they consider practically equivalent to fraud. Admittedly, it's illegal for any such person to argue in defence of his beliefs, but that's only in public. In private discussions with priests or other serious-minded characters, he's not merely allowed but positively encouraged to do so, for everyone's convinced that this type of delusion will eventually yield to reason.

Indeed there are some Utopians—quite a lot of them actually—who, so far from being materialists, go to the opposite extreme. Of course, there's no law against them, for they have a certain amount of reason on their side, and are quite decent characters in themselves. These people believe that animals have immortal souls too, though much inferior to ours, and designed for happiness on a lower plane. As for the infinite happiness in store for human beings, practically everyone feels so sure of it that, although they always mourn for an illness, they never mourn for a death—unless the person in question was obviously uneasy and unwilling to let go of life. This they regard as a very bad sign. It seems to suggest that the soul is conscious of its own guilt, and has gloomy forebodings of punishment to come—hence its terror of dying. Besides, they doubt if God will be at all pleased to see someone who, instead of running gladly to answer His summons, has to be dragged into His presence by force. So they shudder to see a death of this type, and perform the funeral rites in sorrowful silence. They merely say, 'God have mercy on his soul, and forgive his weaknesses.' Then they bury the body.

But when a person dies in a cheerful and optimistic mood, nobody mourns for him. They sing for joy at his funeral, and lovingly commend his soul to God. Finally, more in a spirit of reverence than of grief, they cremate the body, and mark the spot by a column engraved with an epitaph. Then they go home and discuss the dead man's character and career, and there's nothing in his life that they dwell on with such pleasure as the happy state of mind in which he left it. This method of recalling his good qualities is thought the best way of encouraging similar virtues in the living, and also of pleasing the dead—for the subject of these discussions is believed to be present at them, though invisible to human eyes. After all, perfect happiness implies complete freedom of movement, and no one with any feeling would stop wanting to see his friends when he died, if they'd been really fond of one another while he was alive. On the contrary, the Utopians assume that a good man's capacity for affection, like every other good thing about him, is increased rather than diminished by death. So they believe that the dead mix freely with the living, and observe everything they say and do. In fact they regard them almost as guardian angels, and this gives them greater confidence in tackling all their problems. Also, the sense of their ancestors' presence discourages any bad behaviour in private.

They pay no attention to omens, fortune-telling, or any of the superstitious practices that are taken so seriously in other countries. In fact they treat them as a joke. But they have a great respect for miracles which aren't attributable to natural causes, because they see them as evidence of God's presence and power. They say such miracles often happen there. Indeed at moments of crisis the whole country prays for a miracle, and their faith is so great that the prayer is sometimes answered.

Most Utopians feel they can please God merely by studying the natural world, and praising Him for it. But quite a lot of them are led by their religion to neglect the pursuit of knowledge. They're not interested in science—they simply have no time for that sort of thing, since they believe that the only way to earn happiness after death is to spend one's life doing good works. Some of them look after invalids, while others mend roads, clean out ditches, repair bridges, dig up turf, sand, or stone, cut down and saw up trees, or cart such things as timber and corn into the towns. In short, they behave like servants, and work harder than slaves, not only for the community, but also for private individuals. They cheerfully undertake all the rough, dirty, and difficult jobs that the average person fights shy of, either because of the physical effort involved, or just because he dislikes them, or despairs of ever getting them done. Thus they create leisure for other people by working ceaselessly themselves—and yet they take no credit for it. They never find fault with other ways of life, or boast about their own. So the more they make slaves of themselves, the more everybody respects them.

They're divided into two sects, of which one believes in celibacy. Its members are total abstainers, not only from sexual intercourse, but also from meat, and in some cases from every form of animal food. They renounce all the pleasures of this life, which they regard as sinful, and yearn only for the life to come. This they try to earn by the sweat of their brows, and by going without sleep—but the hope of reaching it any day now keeps them lively and cheerful. The other sect, though equally keen on hard work, approves of marriage, on the grounds that its comforts are not to be despised, and that procreation is a duty which one owes both to nature and to one's country. They have no objection to pleasure, so long as it doesn't interfere with work. On that principle they eat a lot of meat, because they think it enables them to work harder. They're generally considered more sensible than the others, though the others are thought more devout. Of course, if the members of the first sect tried to justify their behaviour on logical grounds, they'd merely be laughed at. But as they admit that their motives are religious rather than rational, they're regarded with great reverence—for Utopians are always extremely careful to avoid rash judgements in the matter of religion. People who belong to this sect are known in their own language as Cowparsons which may be roughly translated, Lay Brethren.

All their priests are exceptionally pious, which means that there are very few of them—normally thirteen per town, or one per church. But in wartime seven of the thirteen go off with the troops, and seven more priests are ordained as temporary substitutes. When the army chaplains return, they get back their old livings, and the extra priests remain on the staff of the Bishop—for one of the thirteen is given this status—until they succeed, one by one, to vacancies created by the death of the original incumbents.

Priests are elected by the whole community. The election is by secret ballot, as it is for all public appointments, to prevent the formation of pressure groups, and the successful candidates are then ordained by their colleagues. Priests are responsible for conducting services, organizing religions, and supervising morals. It's considered very shameful to be had up before an ecclesiastical court, or even reprimanded by a priest for bad behaviour. Of course, the actual suppression and punishment of crime is the job of the Mayor and other public officials. Priests merely give advice and warning—though they can also excommunicate persistent offenders, and there's hardly any punishment that people fear more. You see, a person who has been excommunicated is not only completely disgraced and racked with fears of divine vengeance. His physical security is threatened too, for, unless he can very soon convince the priests that he's a reformed character, he's arrested and punished by the Council for impiety.

Priests are also responsible for the education of children and adolescents, in which quite as much stress is laid on moral as on academic training. They do their utmost to ensure that, while children are still at an impressionable age, they're given the right ideas about things—the sort of ideas best calculated to preserve the structure of their society. If thoroughly absorbed in childhood, these ideas will persist throughout adult life, and so contribute greatly to the safety of the state, which is never seriously threatened except by moral defects arising from wrong ideas.

Male priests are allowed to marry—for there's nothing to stop a woman from becoming a priest, although women aren't often chosen for the job, and only elderly widows are eligible. As a matter of fact, clergymen's wives form the cream of Utopian society, for no public figure is respected more than a priest. So much so that, even if a priest commits a crime, he's not liable to prosecution. They just leave him to God and his own conscience, since, no matter what he has done, they don't think it right for any human being to lay hands on a man who has been dedicated as a special offering to God. They find this rule quite easy to keep, because priests represent such a tiny minority, and because they're so carefully chosen. After all, it's not really very likely that a man who has come out top of a list of excellent candidates, and who owes his appointment entirely to his moral character, should suddenly become vicious and corrupt. And even if we must accept that possibility—human nature being so very unpredictable—a mere handful of people without any executive power can hardly constitute a serious danger to the community. They keep the numbers down, in order not to lower the present high prestige of the priesthood, by making the honour less of a rarity—especially as they say it's hard to find many people suitable for a profession which demands considerably more than average virtues.

The reputation of Utopian priests is just as good abroad as it is at home. The evidence and, I think, the reason for this may be found in what happens on the battlefield. While the fighting is in progress, the priests kneel a short way off, wearing their holy vestments, and hold up their hands to heaven. They pray first for peace, and then for a bloodless victory—bloodless on both sides. As soon as their own troops start getting the best of it, the priests hurry on to the battlefield and stop all unnecessary violence. Once they appear on the scene, an enemy soldier can save his life simply by calling out to them, and, if he can manage to touch their flowing robes, his property too is safe from any sort of war damage. This earns them so much respect in every country, and gives them so much genuine authority, that they've often been able to protect their own soldiers quite as effectively as they normally protect the enemy's. Sometimes, at desperate moments when the Utopian forces were in full retreat, and their enemies were rushing after them, intent on killing and looting, the intervention of the priests has been known to prevent a massacre, part the combatants, and bring about the conclusion of a peace on equal terms. For the person of a Utopian priest is universally regarded as sacred and inviolable even among the most savage and barbarous nations.

They have religious festivals on the first and last days of each month, and also of each year—their calendar, by the way, is based on the solar year, divided into lunar months. These first days are called Dogdates in their language, and the last ones Turndates—in other words, Beginning Feasts and Ending Feasts.

Their churches look most impressive, not only because they're so beautifully built, but also because of their size. You see, as there are so few of them, they have to be capable of holding vast numbers of people. However, they're all rather dark, which is not, I'm told, a mistake on the part of the architects, but a matter of policy. The priests think that too much light tends to distract one's attention, whereas a sort of twilight helps one to collect one's thoughts, and intensifies religious feeling. Now this doesn't take the same form with everyone, though all its varieties lead by different routes, as it were, to the same destination: the worship of the Divine Being. For that reason, there's nothing to be seen or heard in their churches which can't equally well be applied to all religions. Any ceremonies which are peculiar to individual sects are performed privately at home, and public services are so arranged as not to detract in any way from these private ones.

On the same principle, their churches contain no visual representations of God, so that everyone's left free to imagine Him in whatever shape he chooses, according to which religion he thinks the best. Nor is God addressed by any special names there. He is simply called Mythras, a general term used by everybody to designate the Supreme Being, whoever He may be. Similarly, no prayers are said in which each member of the congregation cannot join without prejudice to his own particular creed.

At Ending Feasts they fast all day, and go to church in the evening, to thank God for bringing them safely to the end of the year or month in question. Next day, which is of course a Beginning Feast, they meet at church in the morning to pray for happiness and prosperity during the year or month which has just begun. But before going to church at an Ending Feast, wives kneel down at home before their husbands, and children before their parents, to confess all their sins of omission and commission, and ask to be forgiven. This gets rid of any little grudges that may have clouded the domestic atmosphere, so that everyone can attend divine service with an absolutely clear mind. To do so when one is feeling upset is thought positively blasphemous. For that reason, anyone who's conscious of feeling anger or resentment towards another person stays away from church until he's made it up, and purged himself of these unpleasant emotions, for fear of being promptly and severely punished otherwise.

As they enter the church, the men turn to the right and the women to the left, and the seating is so arranged that the males of each household are in front of the house-father, and the house-mother acts as a rearguard for the females. This ensures that everyone's conduct in public is watched by those who are responsible for his discipline at home. Here too they take great care to see that a young person always sits next to an older one—for if children are left to themselves they're apt to waste their time in church playing childish games, when they ought above all to be developing a sense of religious awe, the strongest, if not the only incentive to good behaviour.

They never sacrifice any animals, for they can't imagine a merciful God enjoying slaughter and bloodshed. They say God gave His creatures life, because He wanted them to live. But they do make certain burnt offerings—of incense and other aromatic substances, and of innumerable candles. Of course they realize that such things are no use to the Divine Being, but they see no harm in them as a form of tribute, and feel that these scents and lights and other elements of ritual somehow raise people's thoughts, and make them more eager to worship God.

The congregation is dressed in white, and the priest wears multi-coloured vestments, magnificent in workmanship and design, but made of quite cheap materials—for instead of being woven with gold thread, or encrusted with rare jewels, they're merely decorated with the feathers of various birds. On the other hand, their value as works of art is far greater than that of the richest material in the world. Besides, the feathers are arranged in special patterns which are said to symbolize certain divine truths, and the priests are careful to teach the meaning of these hieroglyphics, since they serve to remind worshippers of God's favours towards them, of their duty towards Him in return, and of their duty towards one another.

The moment the priest appears from the sanctuary wearing these vestments, everyone bows down to the ground in reverence, and there is deep silence throughout the building. The effect is so awe-inspiring that one almost seems to feel a divine presence. After a few minutes the priest gives a sign for the congregation to stand up. Then they sing hymns of praise to God, accompanied by musical instruments, which are generally quite different from anything to be seen in our part of the world. Most of these have a much sweeter tone than ours, though some of them simply won't bear comparison with European instruments. But in one respect they're undoubtedly far ahead of us. All their music, both vocal and instrumental, is wonderfully expressive of natural feelings. The sound is so well adapted to the sense that whether the theme is prayer or rejoicing, agitation or calm, sorrow or anger, the melodic line exactly represents the appropriate emotion. It therefore enters deeply into the hearer's consciousness, and has an extraordinarily stimulating effect.

The service ends with a set form of prayer repeated by both priests and congregation. It's worded in such a way that, while they're all saying it together, each person can apply it to himself. It goes something like this:

O God, I acknowledge Thee to be my creator, my governor, and the source of all good things. I thank Thee for all Thy blessings, but especially for letting me live in the happiest possible society, and practise what I hope is the truest religion. If I am wrong, and if some other religion or social system would be better and more acceptable to Thee, I pray Thee in Thy goodness to let me know it, for I am ready to follow wherever Thou shalt lead me. But if our system is indeed the best, and my religion the truest, then keep me faithful to both of them, and bring the rest of humanity to adopt the same way of life, and the same religious faith—unless the present variety of creeds is part of Thy inscrutable purpose. Grant me an easy death, when Thou takest me to Thyself. I do not presume to suggest whether it should be late or soon. But if it is Thy will, I would much rather come to Thee by a most painful death, than be kept too long away from Thee by the most pleasant of earthly lives.

After saying this prayer, they again bow down to the ground for a few moments, and then get up and go off to lunch. The rest of the day is spent in recreation and military training.

Well, that's the most accurate account I can give you of the Utopian Republic. To my mind, it's not only the best country in the world, but the only one that has any right to call itself a republic. Elsewhere, people are always talking about the public interest, but all they really care about is private property. In Utopia, where there's no private property, people take their duty to the public seriously. And both attitudes are perfectly reasonable. In other 'republics' practically everyone knows that, if he doesn't look out for himself, he'll starve to death, however prosperous his country may be. He's therefore compelled to give his own interests priority over those of the public; that is, of other people. But in Utopia, where everything's under public ownership, no one has any fear of going short, as long as the public storehouses are full. Everyone gets a fair share, so there are never any poor men or beggars. Nobody owns anything, but everyone is rich—for what greater wealth can there be than cheerfulness, peace of mind, and freedom from anxiety? Instead of being worried about his food supply, upset by the plaintive demands of his wife, afraid of poverty for his son, and baffled by the problem of finding a dowry for his daughter, the Utopian can feel absolutely sure that he, his wife, his children, his grand-children, his great-grandchildren, his great-great-grandchildren, and as long a line of descendants as the proudest peer could wish to look forward to, will always have enough to eat and enough to make them happy. There's also the further point that those who are too old to work are just as well provided for as those who are still working.

Now, will anyone venture to compare these fair arrangements in Utopia with the so-called justice of other countries?—in which I'm damned if I can see the slightest trace of justice or fairness. For what sort of justice do you call this? People like aristocrats, goldsmiths, or money-lenders, who either do no work at all, or do work that's really not essential, are rewarded for their laziness or their unnecessary activities by a splendid life of luxury. But labourers, coachmen, carpenters, and farmhands, who never stop working like cart-horses, at jobs so essential that, if they did stop working, they'd bring any country to a standstill within twelve months—what happens to them? They get so little to eat, and have such a wretched time, that they'd be almost better off if they were cart-horses. Then, at least, they wouldn't work quite such long hours, their food wouldn't be very much worse, they'd enjoy it more, and they'd have no fears for the future. As it is, they're not only ground down by unrewarding toil in the present, but also worried to death by the prospect of a poverty-stricken old age—since their daily wages aren't enough to support them for one day, let alone leave anything over to be saved up for when they're old.

Can you see any fairness or gratitude in a social system which lavishes such great rewards on so-called noblemen, goldsmiths, and people like that, who are either totally unproductive or merely employed in producing luxury goods or entertainment, but makes no such kind provision for farm-hands, coal-heavers, labourers, carters, or carpenters, without whom society couldn't exist at all? And the climax of ingratitude comes when they're old and ill and completely destitute. Having taken advantage of them throughout the best years of their lives, society now forgets all the sleepless hours they've spent in its service, and repays them for all the vital work they've done, by letting them die in misery. What's more, the wretched earnings of the poor are daily whittled away by the rich, not only through private dishonesty, but through public legislation. As if it weren't unjust enough already that the man who contributes most to society should get the least in return, they make it even worse, and then arrange for injustice to be legally described as justice.

In fact, when I consider any social system that prevails in the modern world, I can't, so help me God, see it as anything but a conspiracy of the rich to advance their own interests under the pretext of organizing society. They think up all sorts of tricks and dodges, first for keeping safe their ill-gotten gains, and then for exploiting the poor by buying their labour as cheaply as possible. Once the rich have decided that these tricks and dodges shall be officially recognized by society—which includes the poor as well as the rich—they acquire the force of law. Thus an unscrupulous minority is led by its insatiable greed to monopolize what would have been enough to supply the needs of the whole population. And yet how much happier even these people would be in Utopia! There, with the simultaneous abolition of money and the passion for money, how many other social problems have been solved, how many crimes eradicated! For obviously the end of money means the end of all those types of criminal behaviour which daily punishments are powerless to check: fraud, theft, burglary, brawls, riots, disputes, rebellion, murder, treason, and black magic. And the moment money goes, you can also say good-bye to fear, tension, anxiety, overwork, and sleepless nights. Why, even poverty itself, the one problem that has always seemed to need money for its solution, would promptly disappear if money ceased to exist.

Let me try to make this point clearer. Just think back to one of the years when the harvest was bad, and thousands of people died of starvation. Well, I bet if you'd inspected every rich man's barn at the end of that lean period you'd have found enough corn to have saved all the lives that were lost through malnutrition and disease, and prevented anyone from suffering any ill effects whatever from the meanness of the weather and the soil. Everyone could so easily get enough to eat, if it weren't for that blessed nuisance, money. There you have a brilliant invention which was designed to make food more readily available. Actually it's the only thing that makes it unobtainable.

I'm sure that even the rich are well aware of all this, and realize how much better it would be to have everything one needed, than lots of things one didn't need—to be evacuated altogether from the danger area, than to dig oneself in behind a barricade of enormous wealth. And I've no doubt that either self-interest, or the authority of our Saviour Christ—Who was far too wise not to know what was best for us, and far too kind to recommend anything else—would have led the whole world to adopt the Utopian system long ago, if it weren't for that beastly root of all evils, pride. For pride's criterion of prosperity is not what you've got yourself, but what other people haven't got. Pride would refuse to set foot in paradise, if she thought there'd be no under-privileged classes there to gloat over and order about—nobody whose misery could serve as a foil to her own happiness, or whose poverty she could make harder to bear, by flaunting her own riches. Pride, like a hellish serpent gliding through human hearts—or, shall we say, like a sucking-fish that clings to the ship of state?—is always dragging us back, and obstructing our progress towards a better way of life.

But as this fault is too deeply ingrained in human nature to be easily eradicated, I'm glad that at least one country has managed to develop a system which I'd like to see universally adopted. The Utopian way of life provides not only the happiest basis for a civilized community, but also one which, in all human probability, will last for ever. They've eliminated the root-causes of ambition, political conflict, and everything like that. There's therefore no danger of internal dissension, the one thing that has destroyed so many impregnable towns. And as long as there's unity and sound administration at home, no matter how envious neighbouring kings may feel, they'll never be able to shake, let alone to shatter, the power of Utopia. They've tried to do so often enough in the past, but have always been beaten back.

While Raphael was telling us all this, I kept thinking of various objections. The laws and customs of that country seemed to me in many cases perfectly ridiculous. Quite apart from such things as their military tactics, religions, and forms of worship, there was the grand absurdity on which their whole society was based, communism minus money. Now this in itself would mean the end of the aristocracy, and consequently of all dignity, splendour, and majesty, which are generally supposed to be the real glories of any nation.

However, I could see that he was tired after talking so much, and I was not quite sure how tolerant he would be of any opinion that contradicted his own—especially when I remembered his sarcastic reference to the sort of person who is afraid of looking a fool if he cannot pick holes in other people's ideas. So I just made some polite remarks about the Utopian system, and thanked him for his interesting talk—after which I took his arm and led him in to supper, saying:

'Well, I must think it over. Then perhaps we can meet again and discuss it at greater length.'

I certainly hope we shall, some day. In the meantime I cannot agree with everything that he said, for all his undoubted learning and experience. But I freely admit that there are many features of the Utopian Republic which I should like—though I hardly expect—to see adopted in Europe.

导读

让-雅克·卢梭（Jean-Jacques Rousseau，1712—1778），法国著名的思想家、哲学家、政治家、教育家、文学家与音乐家，是欧洲启蒙运动的代表人物之一。卢梭出生于日内瓦一个清贫的家庭，自幼便多遭磨砺，不过爱好读书，涉猎广泛。三十岁时，卢梭移居巴黎，并相继结识了狄德罗（Denis Diderot，1713—1784）等“百科全书派”的代表人物，甚至应邀参与了《百科全书》的撰写工作。之后的两篇论文《论科学与艺术》和《论人类不平等的起源和基础》，使他在法国名声大噪，而《社会契约论》与《爱弥儿》的相继出版则更是把他推上了时代的风口浪尖。

卢梭是一个有着极其复杂性格的人，那种偏执、好斗、敏感、脆弱的性格要素使他渐渐成为一个不被大众认可的人，他甚至还深深得罪了曾经的好友们，如“百科全书派”一众人物与思想泰斗伏尔泰（Voltaire，1694—1778）等，同时，他“主权在民”的政治理念又与自然与法国当局的统治所不调和。所以在群起的声讨之中，卢梭开始了晚年颠沛流离、异常艰辛的流亡生涯，直到七十年代才被允许重回法国。1778年，时年六十六岁的卢梭在孤独与交困中走完了自己复杂的一生。法国大革命结束之后，卢梭被移葬先贤祠，这也是对他不凡成就的最高肯定。

卢梭完全称得上是一位“百科全书”式的人物。《社会契约论》的民权思想是“法国大革命”与“北美殖民地的独立运动”的奠基之石，《爱弥儿》中描绘的“性善论”教育系统在教育史上掀起了一场革命，猛烈讴歌爱情的小说《新爱洛伊斯》成为欧洲一时纸贵的文学读物，《忏悔录》开天辟地的自传式文体，他还为《百科全书》撰写音乐部分……

在卢梭生平活跃的十八世纪欧洲，“文艺复兴”运动种下的“人文主义”精神已然开花结果，中世纪神学彻底走下神坛，科学逐渐成为真理，人性的意义变得不言自明。在此基础上，以“理性”为基础概念的“启蒙运动”接连登场，社会上已更早地酝酿出一种“自由”与“平等”的氛围。法国，作为欧洲的中心，作为这股社会思潮的中心，更是人心思变、群情激昂，成为所有热爱自由的人心向往之的伟大国家。而卢梭亦是如此，自中年移居法国之后，不断探索、发现、升华，终于在1762年出版《社会契约论》这一部政治思想的集大成之作。

《社会契约论》是卢梭政治思想的代表作，处处体现着以社会契约精神为核心的民权思想，自问世以来即受到普罗大众的追捧，不仅点燃了之后轰轰烈烈的“法国大革命”之火，更鼓舞了世界各地人民对自由与民主的不懈追求，尤以北美殖民地独立运动为代表。书中首章首句“人生而自由，却无处不受枷锁的束缚”成为跨越时代的名言金句，一语道破契约社会的本质秩序。书中“主权在民”的思想为现代民主制度奠基。原作共四卷，第一卷论述了社会结构和社会契约，第二卷论述了主权及其权利，第三卷论述了政府及其运作方式，第四卷讨论了几种社会组织。“伟大的思想”系列收录《社会契约论》一书，希望读者能从中一窥卢梭伟大的政治思想。

“社会契约”的概念其实古已有之，而其中又以霍布斯（Thomas Hobbes，1588—1679）与洛克（John Locke，1632—1704）等两位英国政治家的理论为代表，不过卢梭的思想则与二位前辈不尽相同。卢梭认为人人生而自由平等，人们通过平等地放弃天然自由，转而获取平等的契约自由，这些订立的契约的集合便是国家的组成。人民才是国家的主人，而政府只是人民意志的执行者而已。当政府站在人民意志的对立面时，人民有权通过起义的方式推翻它。

如果说现代民权思想是一棵参天巨树，世人皆生活在其福荫之下，那社会契约精神则是孕育这棵巨树的良土，由卢梭等先贤精心栽种，再经过世世代代无数先人的不懈奋斗与努力，血泪汗水的挥洒浇灌，终于茁壮而成，不容撼动。品读《社会契约论》，我们不仅能体会到缜密的思维方式，也能如临其境般置身于那段热血的岁月。民智如何走向开化，我们所处的现代契约社会从何处发端，又将去往何方，这一系列的问题，读者皆可从本书中找到满意的答案。

柴尔

第一卷

我写本文的意图是想思考，从人的现实情况与法律的可能情况来看，在政治社会中是否存在什么合法又可靠的政权法则。为探究这一目的，我必须始终努力将权利容许什么与利益规定什么结合起来，这样，正义与功利不致有所分歧。

我一开始并不试图证明主题的重要性。或许人们会问，我是一位君主还是一名立法者，从而要论述政治？我要回答：都不是。实际上，这正是我要讨论政治的理由。我若是一位君主或是一名立法者，就不应该在谈论本该做什么的问题上浪费时间，而应该当好我的君主或立法者，否则就保持沉默。

既然我生来是一个自由国家的公民，是主权国家的一员，无论我的呼声对公共事务的影响多么微弱，我所拥有的对公共事务的选举权赋予我研究它们的责任。无论何时，细想到各种政权，我就会欣喜地发现，我的研究总能给予我热爱自己国家政权的新理由。

第一章　第一卷的主题

人生而自由，却无处不受枷锁的束缚。那些自认为可以主宰他人的人，反而成为他人的奴隶。这种从主人到奴隶的角色转换是如何发生的呢？我不得而知。我们又如何能够使这种转换合法化呢？我相信我能够解答这个问题。

如果我只是考虑强权以及强权的种种后果，我会说：“只要一个人被迫顺从他人，并且顺从了，那么这个人做得对；但是，一旦他能够挣脱枷锁，并且挣脱了，那么他做得更对。既然一个人以与被剥夺自由一样的权利重新获得自由，那么要么他有权寻回自由，要么当初人们无权剥夺他的自由。”然而，社会秩序是一种神圣的权利，是其他所有权利的基础。同时，由于它不是一种源于自然的权利，它必然建立在各种约定的基础之上。问题是要确定那些约定都是什么。可是，在切入这个问题之前，我必须对迄今为止我所谈的东西加以证实。

第二章　论原始社会

在所有社会中，最古老的、唯一自然的社会是家庭。然而，只有孩子们为了自身的生存需要父亲养育时，他们才倚赖于父亲。一旦没有了这种需要，父子关系就此了结。一旦孩子从对父亲的顺从中解脱出来，一旦父亲从对孩子的负担中解脱出来，双方都同样重获独立。假如他们继续保持父子关系，那么，这种情况就不再是一种自然的状态，而是他们自愿的选择，而家庭本身只是依靠契约得以维持。

这种共有的自由是人性的一种产物。人类的首要法则是维护自身的生存；人的首要关怀对象是自己。而人一旦到了具有理智的年龄，可以自行判断保存自我的最佳手段，那么他也就成了自己的主人。

因此，家庭或许可以被视为政治社会的原始模式：国家领袖是父亲的形象，人民就是孩子的形象，而所有生来自由平等的人，只有当他们在放弃自由中看到好处时，才会放弃其自由。唯一不同的是，在家庭中，父亲对孩子的爱从他给予他们的关心中得到回报，而在一个统治者对其臣民没有如此感情的国家里，统治者对发号施令的乐趣必然取代其对子民的爱。

格劳秀斯引用奴隶制度的例子并否认，一切人类政府都是为了被统治者的利益而建立的。他另具一格的推理方法总是为建立人权提供佐证。人们还可以采取另一种更能自圆其说的方法，但也不见得对暴君就更为有利。

因而，按格劳秀斯的说法，究竟是人类属于一百个人，还是这一百个人附属于人类，这是难以预测的，尽管在整本书中他似乎更倾向于前一种见解，而这也正是霍布斯的看法。这些作者向我们表明，人类就像被分成各种类别的牛群，每一支牛群都有一个首领，首领保护牛群只是因为想吃掉它们。

正如牧羊人的品性优于羊群的品性一样，那些人类的牧羊人——他们的统治者——的品性也优于人民的品性。据菲洛记载，卡里古拉皇帝就是这样类推的，并得出这样的结论：国王都是神明，或者说，人民都是畜牲。

卡里古拉的推理与霍布斯及格劳秀斯的推理相吻合。的确，亚里士多德在他们之前就曾说过，既然一些人生来是奴隶，而一些人生来是主人，那么，人根本不是生而平等的。

亚里士多德是对的，可他把结果误认为原因。任何在奴隶制下出生的人都为奴隶制而生——这话说得再贴切不过了。枷锁之下的奴隶失去了一切，甚至也失去了摆脱枷锁的渴望。他们热衷于被奴役，就像尤利西斯的伙伴们热衷于禽兽一般的生活一样。[1]因此，如果说有天生的奴隶，那只是因为世上早已有违背天性的奴隶。强权造就了第一批奴隶，而他们的懦弱使他们永世为奴。

我不曾谈论过亚当王或挪亚皇，也就是瓜分世界的三大君主之父，尽管有人以为在他们身上也能看出像萨士林儿子那样的行为。我希望读者会对这种谦逊的态度心存感激，因为既然我是那些或许排行老大的君主之一的直系，或许还是长房的后代，谁知如果考证起族谱来，我就不会发现自己是全人类合法的国王呢？不管怎样，没有人能否认亚当是世界之王，就像鲁滨逊是荒岛的主人一样——因为他是岛上唯一的居民。而这样一个帝国的巨大优势在于，君主能安享王位宝座，没有必要担心叛乱、战争或阴谋篡权。

第三章　论最强者的权利

最强者决非强大到足以自始至终做主人，除非他能将强力转化为权利，将顺从转化为义务。由此就得出了“最强者的权利”，这种权利听起来有些嘲讽，实际上已作为一种原则确定下来。但是，我们不需要让人解释一下这个名词吗？强力不过是一种物理力量，我不明白，强力的影响能够产生什么样的道德。屈服于强力是一种必要的行为，而不是一种意志的行为，它充其量只是一种谨慎的行为。在何种意义上它才算是一种义务呢？

我们不妨假设，这种所谓的权利是存在的。我认为，这种权利只能招致无法解释的混乱，因为一旦强力变成权利，因果关系便会倒置，而每一种强力都能征服另一种强力，那么前者继承了属于被征服者的权利。要是人们不服从却又不会受到惩罚，其不服从的行为就变得合法了。既然最强者始终是对的，那么唯一的问题就是如何成为最强者。可是，这种随强力的终止而消失的权利，又是怎样一种权利呢？假设强力驱使人们服从，那就没有必要根据义务而服从了，而假设强力不驱使人们服从，他们也就不再有服从的义务了。因而，“权利”一词并没有给强力增添什么东西；它在此毫无意义。

服从权力。如果这意味着屈服于强力的话，这条箴言虽好，却属多余；我想它绝不会遭到违背。我承认一切权力都来自上帝；可一切疾病也是上帝的旨意。那就意味着我们不能请医生看病吗？如果我在森林边上被一个强盗抢劫的话，强盗的勒索迫使我交出钱包。可假如我能以某种方式设法保住钱包而不让强盗抢走，那我从良心上依然得被迫交出钱包吧？毕竟，强盗手中的手枪无疑也是一种权力。

那么，确实必须承认的是，强力并不构成权利，而人们对合法的权力才有服从的义务。因而，仍然要回到我初始的问题上来。

第四章　论奴隶制

既然没人对自己的伙伴行使什么自然的权力，既然强力独自不赋予人们什么权利，人们当中的一切合法权力必然要建立在约定的基础上。

格劳秀斯说过：“如果一个个体能转让其自由而成为主人的奴隶，那么整个民族为什么就不能转让其自由而成为国王的随从呢？”在这一评论中，有不少模棱两可的词需要加以解释。可就将我们自己的目光限制在“转让”这个问题上吧。转让是给予或出卖的意思。一个成为别人奴隶的人并没有给予自己什么，他出卖自己至少是为了个人的生存。那么，整个民族出卖自己又为了什么呢？国王远不能供养他的臣民，反而只能从臣民那里获得他自身的生活供养。按照拉伯雷的说法，要供养国王付出的不是一星半点。那么，臣民就应该为君主而献身，同时以国王接受其财产为条件吗？假设是这样，我就看不出他们还剩什么了。

有人会说，专制者向他的臣民保证国内安宁。这很好，可如果他的野心所引起的战争、他的难以餍足的贪求、他统治下的恶毒与羞辱，这一切对人们的迫害更有甚于人们内部的纠纷的话，那么人们从这里又得到什么呢？如果这份安宁对人民而言是一种苦难，人们在这里又得到什么呢？在地牢中会有安宁，可是那样的安宁足以使人们感到舒适吗？希腊人虽在独眼巨人的魔窟里安宁而居，可他们正等着被吃掉。

说一个人只讲奉献而不求任何回报，这是荒唐可笑、不可思议的。只因为如此行事的人都不理智，这样的行为便不合法理、毫无价值。说整个民族有过同样的行为，就等于幻想出一个疯癫之国，而疯癫是不能形成权利的。

纵然每个人能够转让自己，他也无法转让其孩子，因为他们生来是人，是自由的。他们的自由属于他们。除了他们自己，没人有权剥夺他们的自由。在他们到了具有理智的年龄之前，他们的父亲可以以他们的名义，为了保护他们及其幸福而制定某些规则，可是却不能彻底无条件地出卖他们的自由，因为这种天赋权利总是与自然目标相矛盾的，它超出了父权的范围。因此，唯有在每一新生代能够接受或拒绝的情况下，专制的政府才是合法的，在这种情况下，这样的政府才不会专制。

放弃自由等于放弃作为人的特性——人的权利甚至是义务。对于放弃一切的人是无法给予补偿的。实际上，这种放弃与人性相悖，因为如果你剥夺了意志的一切自由，你就使一个人的行为失去一切道德上的意义。最终，任何规定一方绝对权威、规定另一方绝对服从的约定，都是无效且自相矛盾的。有权请求一切的人并不承担任何义务，这不是很明白的吗？难道这种既不等价又无交换的唯一条件，其本身不就包含着这种行为的无效性吗？我的奴隶有什么权利来反对我？假设他所拥有的一切都属于我，他的权利就是我的权利，那么，自己反对自己的权利，简直就是一派胡言。

格劳秀斯和其他人声称，他们从战争中引出了这种所谓的奴役权的另一个起源。他们认为，胜利者拥有杀死失败者的权利，而失败者可以用自由换取生命的延续——这种约定更为合法，因为这对双方都是有利的。

可是，这种所谓的杀死失败者的权利显然无法从战争状态中取得。唯独由于这一原因，生活在其原始独立条件下的人缺乏足够定期的交流，其结果不是和平状态就是战争状态，因而人们并非自然成为仇敌。正是对事情的冲突而不是人们之间的争论，才引发战争，而形成战争状态并不出自纯粹的个人关系，而只是出自所有权关系。一个人与另一个人之间的私人战争，既不存在于一个没有固定财产的自然状态之中，也不存在于一个一切都置于法律权威下的社会状态之中。

个人之间的斗殴、决斗或小冲突无法构建任何一种状态。至于法兰西国王路易九世的法令所允许的那些私人战争，以及上帝的和平所中止的那些战争，都不过是封建政权的滥用——如果曾有过这样一种体制的话，这是一种不合理的体制，它不但违背了自然之法，也违背了一切健全的政权。

那么，战争不是人与人之间的关系，而是国与国之间的关系。在战争中，每个个体并不以人的身份，甚至也不以公民的身份，[2]而只以士兵的身份参战，他们偶然地成为敌人，他们这时并不作为国家的成员，而只作为国家的保卫者。总而言之，一国只能把另一国而非国人当作敌人，因为在具有不同内在性质的东西之间不存在真正的关系。

这一原则既符合一切时代所制定的法则，也符合一切文明民族的恒定惯例。宣战与其说是对臣民发出警告，倒不如说是对政权发出警告。假如外国人——不论他是一位君主、一个个体，还是一整个民族——抢劫、杀害或扣押另一个君主的臣民却没有向该君主宣战的话，他就不是敌人，而是强盗。即使在战争当中，要是一个正义的君主掠夺了敌人领土上所能掠夺的公众财产，他仍然要尊重臣民及其个人的财产，也要尊重自己的权利所依据的原则。既然战争的目标是征服敌对国，当士兵全副武装时，他们就有权杀死敌对国的守军。一旦放下武器向对方投降，他们就既不是敌对国的敌人，也不是敌对国的工具，他们只是再一次成为普通人，而敌对国再也无权夺去他们的生命。有时不杀死一兵一卒也可摧毁一个国家。战争不会产生不为目的所需的权利。这些原则既不是格劳秀斯的发明创造，也不是诗人笔下的凭空杜撰，它们源自事物的本性，建立在理性的基础之上。

征服权除了有最强者的法则之外，就没有什么其他基础。假设战争并不赋予征服者屠杀被征服者的人民的任何权利，那么这种他所不具有的权利，就不能用来证明奴役是正当的。只有当无法奴役敌人时，人们才有权杀死他们的敌人，这样，奴役权就不可能出自杀害权。让被征服者以其自由换取胜利者不法索取的生命，因而这是一场不公正的交易。将生死权建立在奴役权基础上、将奴役权建立在生死权基础上的争论，是一场恶性循环的争论。

甚至假设存在这种可怕的屠杀权，那么战争的奴役，或被征服的民族不再有义务服从主人，除非他被迫服从主人。胜利者夺取受害者生命的等价物后，对受害者没有施恩。胜利者是以剥削受害者的方式，而不是以无利的方式消灭受害者。因此，胜利者与失败者之间的战争在继续，除以武力在失败者身上获得权力之外，胜利者决不能获取更多的权力。胜利者与失败者的相互关系是战争的结果，而战争权的使用意味着和平条约的不复存在。约定确实已经制定了，可那种约定完全终止不了战争，而是预示着战争的继续。

因而，不管我们怎样看待这一问题，奴役权是不存在的。之所以不存在，不仅是因为其无法被证实，而且也是因为其荒谬、无任何意义。“奴役”与“权利”这两个词相互矛盾，相互排斥。不论是人与人之间，还是人与整个民族之间，说：“我特此与你签订契约，该契约完全由你付出代价而完全有利于我，只要我高兴，我就遵守契约，而只要我高兴，你必须遵守契约。”这样的话岂不荒唐可笑。

第五章　论我们总该追溯到原始契约

即使我要承认迄今为止我反驳过的一切，可专制的斗士总不会有什么好结果。征服一大批人与统治一个社会之间将始终存在天壤之别。如果一个人接二连三地奴役许多单一的个体，不管数目有多大，在这里我只看到主人与奴隶，而根本看不到人民与其统治者。或许就存在一个集合体的关系，但肯定不是一个联合体的关系，因为他们既没有共同的利益，也不属于同一个政体。即使这样的一个人奴役了全球一半的人，他仍然只是一个个体，而他那总与他人截然不同的利益，只不过是个人利益而已。当他死去时，他所留下的帝国会分崩离析，就像一棵橡树被大火燃得精光，化为一堆灰烬一样。

格劳秀斯说过：“一个民族可以将自身交给国王。”因此，依格劳秀斯的说法，在将自己奉献给国王之前，一个民族就是一个民族。这种奉献本身就是一种公民行为。它预示着公众的深思熟虑。因此，在考虑一个民族选择国王的行为之前，我们应该仔细审视一下民族之所以成为一个民族的行为，因为那种后者的行为必然先于前者，而这才是社会的真正基础。

实际上，如果不存在更早的约定的话，除非选举一致通过，不然，怎么会存在少数服从多数的义务呢？希望得到一个主人的一百人有什么权利代表不希望得到一个主人的十人投票呢？多数投票法本身以约定为依据，它意味着至少有一次全体一致的情况。

第六章　论社会公约

我设想人们达到这样一种状态：自然状态下，阻碍人们维持现状的力量已超过了每个个体在该状态下用以自保的力量。如果不改变其生存模式的话，那么原有状态将无法持续，人类必将消亡。

既然人们无法形成新的势力，那只好将那些早已存在的势力联合起来，并加以控制。他们能够保存自己的唯一方法是，在一个强大到足以克服任何抵抗的集体中联合起个体的力量，并在单一动力的驱动下朝着一个目标一致行动。

各种势力的联合只有依靠个体联合才能产生，但是，因为每个人自身的力量和自由又是其生存的首要手段，要是他自己不去冒险，不愿忽视对自己所应有的关怀，他又怎么能融合他人的力量呢？根据我现有的主题，这一难题可以用以下这句话来表达：

“如何找到一种以一切集体力量保护个人及其利益的联合方式，以这种方式，每个个体在与他人联合时，除听从自己外，无需服从他人，依旧可以像以前那样自由自在？”这是社会契约所要解决的根本问题。

该契约的条款按行为的性质规定得如此严密，哪怕微小的修改都可能使其变得空洞无效。它们就是这样确定的，虽然可能从未在形式上加以说明，但是无论在哪里它们都是相同的，无论在哪里都是被默许认可的。这个社会公约一旦遇到破坏，每个人就会重新获得其原有权利，而在恢复其自然自由的同时，又会失去其用自然自由换来的公民自由。

这些关于联合的条款可以简化为一句话，即每个联合者自身及他对整个集体的权利的全盘转让。首先，由于每个个体完全交出自己，所以对大众来说条件都是一样的，正因为对于每个人的条件都相同，所以在没有个人利益的情况下，就不会有人想让这种条件成为别人的负担。

其次，既然这种转让是无保留的，联合体会尽可能完美无缺，而每个联合者就不会有什么要求了。因为假设个体保留了某些权利，个体与公众之间将缺乏更高的裁判权威，每个个体从某种意义上说便可以自行作出判断，因而很快就会要求在一切事务中自行作出判断。这样一来，自然状态就会继续下去，而联合体不可避免地变成暴政或是空话。

最后，既然每个人都把自己交给了大众，就等于没把自己交给任何人。既然从任何一种联合里，人们都可以获得与自己让渡给他人的同等的权利，那么他就重新获取其所失去的每样东西的等价物，并且在讨价还价之中，获取更多的权力以保存其所拥有的东西。

那么，如果从社会公约中删除一切不太重要的东西，我们就会发现社会公约可以简化为如下词句：“我们每个人在公意的最高指示下，将其个体及其一切力量都投入到集体中，并且作为一个整体，我们接纳作为整体不可分割的一部分的每一个成员。”

紧接着，这种联合行为产生一个道德的与集体的共同体，以代替每个契约方的个人，该共同体由众多像与会的选举人那样的成员组成。通过这样的相同行为，共同体获得其团结且普遍的自我、生活和意志。因而，由所有其他人联合产生的公共人格过去被称为城市，[3]而现在被认为是共和国或政体。在被动情况下，它被称为国家；在主动情况下，它就是主权者；和自己的同类相比，它就是政权。至于联合者，他们集体被称为人民，而其中的个体作为主权权威的参与者，可称之为公民，也可称他们为臣民，因为他们己处于国家法律制度的管辖之下。不过，这些词汇常常混淆不清，每个词都可能被误解为另一个词。重要的是，在以确切的含义使用这些词时，要知道如何辨别它们。

第七章　论主权者

这一法则表明，联合行动包括社会与个体之间的相互规约，其结果是，在与自己制定的契约中，每个人都会发现自己承担着双重义务，第一，与个体相比，作为主权者主体的一员；第二，与主权者相比，作为国家公民的一员。但是在这里，民法上的准则却不适用，民法上写道：每个人并不受与自己的规约的约束，因为在对自己尽责和对个体作为整体一部分所涉及的某事尽责之间，存在着巨大的差别。

我必须补充说明的是，一次公众决策可能把一项义务强加给服从于主权者的臣民，由于两方面的原因每个人都能被理解，而相反的是，如此的决策并不可能把一项义务强加给主权者本身。由此，这必然违背了为主权者服务的政体的真正本性，因为主权者为自身制定其不能违反的法律。只有以唯一相同的关系来考虑，主权者才处在与自己订约的个人地位，这表明，既不存在也不可能存在任何把人民共同体捆绑起来作为一个主体的基本法，甚至是社会契约本身，也不可能做到这一点。这并不意味着，只要不违背该契约，整个主体就可以与其他国家订约，因为相对于国外势力而言，该政体只是一个简单的实体、个体而已。

不过，既然政体或主权者将其存在只归于契约的神圣性，那么甚至在与外国势力制定的条约中，它也不能让自己承担任何损害这一初始行为的义务，例如，它无法将自己的一部分转让或呈送给另一个主权者。违背自己赖以生存的法令，必将自我毁灭。巧妇难为无米之炊啊。

因而，民众一联合起来就成为一个集体，要是不进攻这个集体，就没有人能够伤害到集体中的任何一员。要不是每个成员都受到攻击，仍然不太可能伤害到整体。因而，义务与自我利益同样强制契约双方互相援助。而同样的这些人应试图在这双重关系中，将与此相关的一切利益结合起来。

现在，由于主权者完全由构成主权者的个体组成，所以主权者没有也不能有任何对立于个体利益的利益。于是，主权者没有必要向臣民作种种保证，因为一个主体希望伤害其所有的成员，这是不可能的，而我们之后会看到，主体不能伤害任何一个特定的成员。主权者，正因为他是主权者，便永远是他应有的样子。

但是，这并非臣民与主权者之间关系的真实写照。不管他们的共同利益如何，除非主权者能找到确保臣民忠诚的方法，否则臣民都不愿意受其所负责任的约束，除非他们保证其忠诚的方法。

因为作为人的每个个体，都可能有个人意志，而这一意志对立或有别于他作为公民所具有的公意。他的个人利益可以大声呼吁，其呼声大大有别于公众利益的呼声。他绝对自然独立的生命，可能使他将其所要归于公共事业的东西，既看作无偿奉献，也看作损失，不过这种损失与他的沉重付出相比，不那么令人痛苦。试想一下，那个创建国家的非自然人只是一个虚构的实体（既然他不是一个人），他可能试图享受各种权利，而又不想对臣民尽什么义务。这种不公正的滋生势必引发政体的毁灭。

由此，为了使社会公约不至于成为一个空洞的法则，社会公约就要在约定中默示——给予所有其他人以强力——任何拒绝服从公意的人都将由全体迫使其这样做，这除了必须迫使其获得自由之外，没有任何其他意思，因为这是在让每个公民献身国家时，保证他免于一切人身依附的必要条件，正是这一条件，才使政治机器设计成型，并使其正常运转，而政治机器本身将合法性赋予公民契约。没有这一条件，如此的契约肯定是荒唐可笑、专制残暴、易于被严重滥用的。

第八章　论公民社会

在从自然状态到公民社会的发展历程中，人类发生了惊人的变化。公民社会将作为行为准则的正义置于本能的位置，赋予其行为以其前所未有的道德品质。只有到那时，当义务的呼声已经取代了生理的冲动，权利取代了欲望，至今只想到自己的人才会发现自己被迫根据他人准则去行事，去求教自己的理智，而不去研究自我倾向。在公民社会中，虽然一个人转让了一些属于自然状态的利益，可是他却能获得更大利益作为回报。他的才能得到锻炼和发展，其思想得到拓展，其情操变得高尚，其整体精神得到提升，其结果是，如果在多种情况下滥用新的条件不会将自己降低到比出发点更糟糕的地步，他应该经常祈佑幸福的时光。这幸福的时光已使其脱离自然状态，也使其从一头愚笨的、受限制的畜牲变成了有智力的动物，乃至变成了人。

假定我们起草一份资产负债表，以便可以很容易地比较赢亏。对任何诱导他及其可获取的东西来说，一个人在社会契约中所亏损的东西是他的自然自由与绝对权利。他在社会契约中赢得的东西，是公民的自由及其所有物的财产权。如果想避免犯厚此薄彼的错误，我们必须清楚区分仅以个人力量为界限的自然自由，以及受限于公意的公民自由；我们还必须区分仅建立在强力或“最先占有权”基础上的享有权，以及必须倚赖法定所有权的财产权。

我还得补充一点，一个与公民社会往来的人，应该获得道德自由，唯有道德自由才能使其成为自己的主人，因为奴隶制只受肉欲支配，而服从为自己制定的法律才是自由。然而，就这一主题我已经说过好多次，而“自由”一词的哲学含义并不是本主题所要论述的。

第九章　论财产权

集体的每个成员，在集体存在的瞬间就将当时情况下存在的自我——他自己及其所有资产，包括一切动产——交给了这个集体。这并不是说，这样一来，享有权在转手过程中改变其性质，变成主权者掌握的财产权。更准确地说，由于国家的资产与个体的那些资产比要大得无以言状，所以个人财产虽然不再合理合法——可不管怎样，在陌生人的眼里，公共财产其实比个人财产更安全，也更不可变更。因为在面对国家的公民时，国家变成了他们全部动产的主人，这有赖于社会契约，这是由于社会契约在国家内部充当所有其他权利的基础，面对其他国家时，本国只有源自个体的“最先占有权”。

“最先占有权”尽管比“最强者的权利”更为真实，可是直到创立了财产权才变成一种真正的权利。每个人对自己所需要的东西都拥有自然权利。但是，使一个人变成某一财产的所有者的积极行为，却把他排除在别的一切事物之外。他一旦得到自己的份额，必然将自己局限于那一份财产，也就更没有权利违背集体了。因而，我们明白，在自然状态下脆弱的“最先占有权”，在政治社会中却迫使每个公民尊重它。这种权利让人们意识到，属于别人的东西并不比属于他自己的东西来得少。

作为一条普遍的法则，为了证明对任何一块土地的最先占有权是正当的，我们必须满足下列条件：第一，土地必须尚未被任何其他人占有；第二，所有权者仅仅拥有他为生存所需要的土地；第三，他不是通过游手好闲的方式，而是通过实实在在耕地的方式取得享有权——这是在缺乏法定所有权时需要别人尊重的所有权的唯一标志。

的确可以说，试图把“最先占有权”变成人们的需要，并能操作得起来，这使其内涵得到最大限度地延伸。一个人真的能够避免给权利设定限制条件吗？一个人两脚踏上一片共用的土地，便马上声称这块土地归自己所有，这就足够了吗？以强力不让别人接近一会儿，以便剥夺他人永久的回归权，这就足够了吗？一个人或一个民族又怎么能够掠夺广袤的土地，拒其他民族于门外，除非是罪犯的霸占——由于这种行为劫掠了其余人的住所及自然给予他们共有的一切，那就足够了吗？当努涅斯·德·巴尔波亚站在海岸上，以卡斯提王权的名义占有了南太平洋和整个南美洲的时候，那就足以剥夺一切居住者，把世上所有的君主排除在外吗？假如是这样的话，这些仪式不断上演，枉然无益。天主教皇要是没离开皇室，可能会拥有全世界，除非后来帝国所在地区已属于别的君主。

我们会明白，私人土地被统一连片时，是怎样变成公共土地的；我们也会明白，主权者权利从臣民扩大到他们所占有的土地时，是怎样既涵盖财产权又涉及人的。这使那些土地所有者都变得更加依赖别人，然后把自己的实力变成了忠于他人的保证。古代君王似乎没有看到这一好处，因为他们自称波斯人或斯基泰人或马其顿人时，好像认为自己宁可是人们的统治者，而不是国家的主人。当今的君主更精明地称自己为法国国王，或西班牙国王，或英国国王等，他们以这种方式占有国土，那么也就拥有了国土上的居民。

社会契约所具有的唯一特点是：集体在接受个体动产，远非剥夺个体的财产。相反，集体只是保证个体对财产的合法享有权，这就将侵占变成了有效的权利，将享有变成了合法所有权。因此，每个所有者都被认为是公共财产的托管人，其权利就必须得到国家每个其他公民的尊重，并且受到集体力量的保护以抵御异乡人的侵犯。通过对公众有利并对他们更有利的让与，人们就已经获取了一切，可以说是他们已放弃的一切——这一似是而非的论点，很容易通过区分主权者所拥有的权利和所有者对这一财产所拥有的权利加以解释，这一点可从下文了解。

还可能发生这样的事，人们在一无所有时，就已经开始联合了，在扩大土地并使其大到足以分给其所有者之后，他们开始共享土地，或者在他们中间交替地分配土地，不是平等分配就是由主权者决定按份额分配。不管所得物以什么方式安排，任何个体对自己财产的所有权都必须从属于集体对一切财产的所有权，因为要是没有了这一权利，就失去了社会契约的约束力，也失去了行使主权的有效力量。

我将以一种可作为整个社会制度基础的观点结束本章——第一卷：换句话说，社会公约决不可能破坏自然平等，恰恰相反，它将用一种道德上的合法平等代替自然可能强加给人的任何物质上的不平等，其结果是，不管在人力和智力方面如何不平等，人们依靠契约和权利都会变得平等。[4]

第二卷

第一章　论主权是不可转让的

迄今已建立的种种原则的首要也是最重大的结果在于，唯有公意才能按照已创建的国家想获得共同利益的目标来指导国家的各种力量。因为如果个人利益之间的冲突已使必要的公民社会得以建立的话，那些相同利益之间的和谐一致就会使公民社会的建立成为可能。正是那些不同利益的共同点才产生这种社会联系。假如没有了与个体利益相一致的契合点，那么可以想象，社会就不可能存在。因此社会就是必须在这共同利益的基础上进行治理。

那么我的论点是，主权不外乎公意的运作，因而决不能转让。主权者只是一个集体存在，因而不能由任何其他人代表，而只能由本人代表——权力可以由他人代表，意志却不能由他人代表。

实际上，个意与公意在某些点上相互一致不是不可能的，但至少这种一致不可能连续持久。因为个意本质上倾向于偏私，而公意则倾向于平等。甚至更不可思议的是，在个意与公意之间的和谐一致可以有保证，即使如此，这种保证还要一直继续下去，因为如此持久的和谐一致往往是碰巧产生的，而不是人为的结果。主权者可能会说：“我现在想要的正是这个人想要的，或者至少是他说他想要的。”但是，没有一位主权者会说：“这个人明天想要的，也是我想要的。”因为一个人希望在未来受到束缚，这是荒谬可笑的，而且说一个人希望同意与其利益相悖的观点，这是自相矛盾的。如果一个民族只是唯命是从，那么这个民族会因为这样的承诺而解体。因为一旦有了一位主人，就不再有主权，原有政体因而消亡。

这并不是说，如果主权者有反对的自由却没有这么做，领袖的命令也不能算是公意。在这种情况下，人民的沉默可视为人民的同意。这一点将在下文详细阐述。

第二章　论主权是不可分割的

正如主权是不可转让的，同样的道理，主权也是不可分割的，因为意志要么是公意，[5]要么不是。主权不是民族主体的意志，只是一部分人的意志。在前者中，主权宣布意志是主权国家与宪法法律的行为；而在后者中，主权宣布意志只是特定意志的表达，或者说是管理机构的行为，它充其量不过是一道法令。

然而，我们那些无法对主权原则分类的政治理论家们，将主权原则按其意图来分类。他们将主权原则分为权力与意志，即将其分为行政权与立法权，征税权、司法权与战争权，内政权与外交权。我们的理论家们时而将这些东西混为一谈，时而将它们割裂开来。他们把主权者变成一只空想的动物、一件用破布缝制的拼缀物，更确切地说，仿佛他们是用几个人的肢体来凑成一个人体的样子——其中一个人有眼，一个人有腿，而另一人则只有脚。据说，日本的江湖郎中可以当着旁观者把一个小孩切开，将身体的不同部位抛向空中，然后让这个小孩落下来，结果每一部位都有生命。这或多或少是我们的政治理论家玩弄的戏法——总之，他们用一种只配在露天市场上耍弄的手法肢解社会主体之后，再将碎片拼凑在一起。

这一错误出自没有形成主权者权威的正确概念，也出自仅仅把权威的派生产物误认为权威本身的各个部分。例如，宣战与媾和都被认为是主权行为，它们实际上并不是主权行为，因为这些行为都不构成法律，而只是法律的应用、决定该法律如何加以解释的特定行为——我给附在“法律”这个词上的思想下完定义之后，这一切就显而易见了。

如果我们以同样的方式仔细考察关于主权其他假定的分类法，我们应该会发现，无论何时我们认为主权被分类，我们都搞错了，因为被认为是主权的那一部分权利，实际上现已被证实只是从属于主权，预示着主权付诸实施的最高意志的存在。

当到了法律理论家该运用自己的原则来分别确定君主和人民的权利时，这种缺乏确切性的情况已大大模糊了他们自己所下的那些结论。读过格劳秀斯第一部作品中的第一卷第三、四章的读者都会明白，这位渊博的学者及其译者巴贝拉克是怎样陷入他们自己的诡辩论中的，他们担心不是说得太多就是说得太少（根据他们的偏见），也担心违背了他们需要调和的各种利益。格劳秀斯，一个在法兰西的流亡者，对自己的国家心怀不满，逃离本国，想追随路易十三，将自己的书献给路易十三，所以他不遗余力地剥夺各民族的一切权利，并千方百计地将那些权利奉献给君主。这肯定非常合巴贝拉克的胃口，巴贝拉克将自己翻译的格劳秀斯的译著献给英国国王乔治一世。然而，不幸的是，詹姆斯二世的被逐——巴贝拉克称之为一次“逊位”——迫使他把话说得明显有所保留、含糊其辞、模棱两可，以免暗示威廉三世是一个篡夺者。如果这两个作家采用了正确的原则，他们的所有困难就都烟消云散，他们的论点也就一致了。但可悲可叹的是，他们本该说出真理，并且只追随公民。真理不会给他们带来财富，而公民也不是授予他们大使、教授头衔和给之高薪厚俸的人。

第三章　论公意是否会出错

由我所论证的论题可见，公意总是正义的，并且总是趋向于公共利益。但这并不表明，公民的讨论总是有同样的正确性。我们总想得到对我们有利的东西，可我们总是辨别不出对我们有利的东西。人民决不会腐败，可他们常常误入歧途。而只有在这时，人民似乎愿意要不好的东西。

众意（一切个体想要的东西）与公意之间常常存在极大的差异。公意只研究公共利益，而众意则研究个人利益——确实只不过是个体欲望的总和。但是，如果我们从这些相同的意志中去掉互相抵销的加减数，那么剩下的总数依然是公意。[6]

当公民能够充分了解情况并展开讨论，而公民彼此之间有没有任何勾结时，许许多多的小分歧往往会产生公意，所作出的决策总会是正确的。但是，如果以牺牲大集体为代价而形成小团体，则每个小团体的意志对自己的成员来说成了公意，而对国家来说却成了个意。那么，我们可能会说，投票数不再与人数相等，而是与现有的组群相等了。分歧变少，结果是产生更少的公意。最终，当其中一个小团体变得很大，大到能够超过其余的小团体，其结果不再是许多小分歧的总和，而是只有一个唯一的分歧。到那时，就不存在公意，而那占上风的意见不过是个意而已。

因而，为了公意能够得到清楚的表达，国家中不应该存在各种派系，而每个公民应该只为自己做决定，这是绝对必要的[7]——这便是伟大的利库尔戈斯那独一无二的发明。可如果存在着各种派系，那就成倍增加它们的数量，并像梭伦、努玛和塞尔维乌斯所做的那样，防止它们中出现不平等。这些是能确保公意始终得到启迪、人们不会误入歧途的唯一预防措施。

第四章　论主权者权力的限度

如果国家或城邦，只是一个道德人格——由成员联盟构成其生命，如果它最担忧的东西是其生存，那它就需要具有普遍的强制力，以便以对整体最有利的方式推动并应对每一部分。正如大自然给予每个人以支配自己四肢的绝对力量一样，社会公约赋予政体以支配其所有成员的绝对权力。正是这相同的权力，在公意的指引下，才有了像我所说的主权的名称。

然而，除公众之外，我们还得考虑构成公众的个人，个人的生命和自由自然独立于公众之外。由此，我们必须清楚地区分公民与主权者各自的权利，[8]而且还必须将公民作为臣民所应尽的义务与他们作为人所应享受的自然权利区别开来。

我们承认，每个人可按社会公约转让其与集体有关的权力、动产和自由的；可还必须承认的是，唯有主权者才是上述关系的裁断者。

无论公民能够为国家作出什么样的贡献，只要主权者要求，他就应该去做；而主权者不能将对集体不必要的任何负担强加给臣民。事实上，主权者甚至不能有这样的意图，这与其说是依照凡事必有因的自然法则，倒不如说是依照推理的法则。

将我们与社会团体联结在一起的之所以是义务，只是因为它们是相互的。鉴于其性质如此，一个人在尽义务的过程中，要是不能同时为自己工作，就无法为其他人工作。公意总是正当合法的，所有人常常希望获得各自的幸福，只是大众将“各自”一词用在自己身上，在投票中都想着自己，这怎么可能呢？这表明，权利的平等及平等所产生公正的概念得自于每个人对自己的偏爱，因此也得自于同样的人性。这还表明，公意若要成为真正的公意，就必须在其目的和在其性质上都是普遍的。公意应该从公众为了公意延伸到公意适用于公众。当对准任何特别限定的目标时，公意就会失去其自然的公正——因为在判断陌生事物时，我们没有任何真正的公正原则来引导我们。

实际上，无论何时，在我们处理一件特定的事情或权利，且其未能按照事先的公约得到解决时，事情就会变得有争议。这是一种个人利益和公共利益针锋相对的冲突，我既看不到需要遵循的法律，也看不到作出裁判的仲裁者。这在如此有赖于公意决策的争论中，显得荒唐可笑，因为得出的结论只能有利于其中一方，而对另一方而言则认为这是一种不相同、不公平的，在如此情况下有失公正而犯过失的意志。于是，正如个意无法代表公意，如果公意试图处理个体情况的话，也将改变其性质，它也就不能再作为公意对任何人或任何事作出裁决了。例如，雅典人在任命或罢免其领导人时，授荣誉予一个人，而惩罚另一个人，并且按照许多特别的规定，不加选择地行使行政的一切职能，那么，此时雅典人不再使明白无误的东西变成公意，不再像主权者那样做事，反而像行政官那样做事。所有这一切似乎与通常接受的观念并不一致，但是，请给我时间来详细说明我自己的观点。

从我迄今为止所说的来看，公意产生其公意性，与其说源自人们的选票数目，倒不如说源自人们结合在一起的共同利益——因为公意是一项制度，在这一制度下，每个人都必须服从他所施加给别人的相同条件。利益与正义之间这值得赞美的和谐一致性给予了社会讨论以公正性，但这种公正性在讨论个体事件时会立刻消失，因为不存在一种能够将判决方和争论方各自的判决结合统一起来的共同利益。

无论以哪种方式看待这件事，我们始终都要回到同样的结论：社会公约在公民中建立起平等，因为他们遵从相同的条件，也都必须享有相同的权利。因此，按照契约的性质，主权者的每一个行为，即公意的每一次真实的行动，同样约束或有利于所有公民，结果是主权者只认识到民族的整体，而不区分构成民族的任何成员之间的差异。那么，什么东西真正称得上是主权行为呢？它并不是高贵者与低贱者之间的契约，而是主体与其每个成员之间的契约。它是一种合法的契约，因为它的基础是社会契约；它是一份公正的契约，因为它对公众而言是共用的；它是一份有益的契约，因为除了共同利益外它别无所求；它也是一份持久的契约，因为它得到武力和最高权力的保障。只要臣民履行这样的契约，他们就不是顺从任何人而是顺从自己的意志。而要问主权者和公民的各自权利延伸多远，那就等于问这两类人共同履约的程度如何，也就是问每个人对全体及全体对每个人履约的程度如何。

由此可见，很显然，主权者的权力事实上是完全绝对的、神圣不可侵犯的，但它并不超越也不能超越公共契约的限制。因而，每个人都可以随心处置这些契约留给他的财富和自由。由此推断，主权者绝对没有将负担厚此薄彼地强加给臣民的权利，因为一旦发生这种情况，事情就会变成个人的事，主权者的权利对此不再奏效。

一旦承认这些差异，要断言个体会按照社会契约作出什么真正的放弃，明显变得不真实。的确，由于这种契约，他们发觉自己处在一种比以前更为优越的处境中。为谋取利益，他们用了不确定且不稳定的生命来交换更美好更安全的生命，而不是进行转让；他们用了自然的独立交换自由，也交换为享有自己的安全却伤害他人的权力；他们用了其可被战胜的权力交换社会联盟使其不可战胜的权利。他们抵押给国家的真正生命始终受到国家的保护；甚至当他们冒着生命危险保卫国家时，除了归还他们从国家那儿接受的东西外，还做了什么呢？除了他们不再经常做的事之外，在面临更大的危险时，在每个人不可避免地处在战争、冒生命危险保卫任何为维护生命而服务于自己的自然状态中，还做了什么呢？确实，所有人现在都必须在万一需要时为自己的国家而战，但是，至少每个人不再为自己而战。为了保障安全，我们只需要冒着在没有这种保障时每个人所必须独自面对的危险中的一部分，这难道不算是某种受益吗？

第五章　论生死权

有人会问，无权掌控自己生命的个体，怎么能将他们不曾拥有的权利转让给主权者？这个问题看起来似乎难以解答，只因为问题提得很糟糕。每个人都有权冒生命危险以保存生命。你听说过一个跳出窗口逃避火灾的人犯有自杀罪吗？一个人上船时知道有危险而死于暴风雨，能以此认定他自杀吗？

社会契约的目的是维护契约方。不论哪一方，想要达到目的，就要有手段，而这种手段与一定的危险，乃至一定的牺牲是分不开的。无论谁想要以别人的生命代价来保全自己的性命，就必须在必要时为别人献身。现在作为公民，个人不再自行判断法律要求他冒的是哪种危险。而当君主对他说：“你应该死，这对国家来说是有利的。”那么，他应该死，因为正是这样的条件让他得以安全生活至今，而且，他的生命不再是自然的赠物，而是国家给予他的一种有条件的礼物。

判处罪犯死刑可以用相同的方式来看待：正是为了避免自己成为杀人事件的被害人，如果一个人本身成了杀人犯，他才同意去死。在社会契约中一个人只会想到保住性命，而决不会想舍弃性命。我们绝不认为，任何契约方会从开始就设想自己被绞杀。

此外，每个罪犯都会触犯社会法律，按其行为被判为叛乱者、叛国者。他违反了国家法律，便不再是国家的一员。甚至于，他对国家发动战争。在这种情况下，国家存亡与其个人生存是不相容的，要么国亡，要么人死。而当这个罪人被处死时，他与其说是公民，倒不如说是敌人。审判和判决证明并且宣布他违反了社会契约，结果他再也不是这个国家的一员了。既然他接受了这样的成员资格，就其公民身份而言，就应该将其作为社会公约的违犯者驱逐出境，或者将其作为众矢之的处死。这样的敌人不是一个虚构的人，而是一个活生生的人，因此，战争权使杀人变得合法。

可有人会说，谴责一个罪犯是个体的行为。这我同意。接下来，这样的行为并不从属于主权者，谴责罪犯是主权者可赋予却不可自行运用的一项权利。我的所有想法都融会在一起，但我无法一下子描述清楚。

此外，频繁的惩罚是政权软弱或涣散的标志。不存在一个坏到一无是处的人。人不该被处以死刑，即使是以儆效尤，也不该如此。如果他对社会不构成危险，就应该放他一条生路。

至于赦免或免除一个法律判定有罪且法官已宣判的罪犯刑罚的权利，这只属于凌驾于法官和法律之上的那种人，即主权者。可即使是的话，这种权利也并非十分清晰，并且极少付诸实施。在一个管理良好的国家，极少有人受处罚，这不是因为有许多的赦免，而是因为极少有罪犯：而在一个日渐衰落的国家，大量犯罪的涌现才确保了罪犯不受惩罚。在古罗马共和国的统治下，元老院和执政官绝对都不想赦免罪犯，古罗马人也是如此，尽管他们有时取消了自己的判决。经常性的赦免标志着犯罪将很快不需要赦免，任何人都能明白那必然导致的结果。然而，我能感觉到我的心正在低语，并且正在阻止我下笔。让我们把对这些问题的讨论留给那些从不犯错因而无需赦免的公正的人吧！

第六章　论法律

我们已按社会公约赋予政体以生命和存在，而现在按立法赋予政体以运动和意志却成了问题，因为联合形成政体所依据的原始行为并不决定其为保存自身所要做的事。

事物的美好和井然有序皆源于其真正的本性，而与人类契约无关。一切的正义都来自那唯一的源泉——神，如果我们知道如何从这高贵的源泉中获取正义的话，我们就既不需要政权也不需要法律了。毋庸置疑，存在一种完全出自理性的普遍正义，但要认可那种正义，它就必须是互惠的。从人性上说，由于缺少自然的制裁，自然正义的法则便不适用于人间。其实，这样的法则只益于恶劣的人，却伤害了正直的人，因为正义的人尊重法则，而其他人却不以尊重法则作为回报。于是，就必须有契约和明确的法律，以此将权利和义务相结合，并将正义引向其目标。在一切事物都处于公共的自然状态下，我对那些我未曾许诺过的人并没有什么亏欠，并且我认识到，对我没用的那些东西只属于别人。但是，在一切权利依法而定的公民社会中，就不再是那样了。

然而，究竟什么是法律呢？如果我们根据形而上学的观点简单地给法律下定义的话，我们就会继续谈论下去，却无法理解。即使我们能说出自然法则是什么，也仍旧无法理解国家法。

我已说过，公意不可能涉及任何特定的目标，因为这样的特定目标不是在国家之内，就是在国家之外。如果它是在国家之外，那么，一种与其无关的意志对其而言就不是公意；如果它是在国家之内，那么它将构成自然的一部分。因而，整体与部分就形成了一种关系，这其中包含两个独立的存在，一个是部分，一个是除掉这一部分后的整体。可是，除掉这一部分后的整体不再是一个整体，于是，只要这种关系存在的话，就没有整体而只有两个不平等的部分。由此可见，其中一方的意志从不是另一方的公意。

但是，当全体人民为全体人民制定规则时，就只考虑自身。而如果有什么关系出现的话，这种关系则存在于一种观点下的整体和另一种观点下的整体之间，全体不存在分裂。在此，制定规则就像制定规则的意志一样，是普遍的。这就是我称之为法律的行为。

当我说法律的对象总是普遍的时候，我的意思是，法律只考虑全体臣民及所有抽象行为，可它并不考虑任何个人或任何特定的行为。因而，法律可以规定应该存在有特权，但不可能指名将特权赋予某一个人；法律可以给公民划分多个等级，甚至确定各个等级的准入资格，但不可能指名把某某人列入某个等级之中；法律可以创建一个王室政权，并安排一个世袭继承人，但不可能选举一个君主或指定一个王室家庭——总之，涉及个体的职能并不在立法权的范畴之列。

根据这一观点，立刻就能发现，我们再也不用问由谁来制定法律，因为法律是公意行为；再也不用问君主是否可以凌驾于法律之上，因为君主只是国家的一部分；再也不用问法律是否可以是非正义的，因为没有人对自己是非正义的；再也不用问我们如何能做到既自由自在又受法律约束，因为法律不过是我们自己意愿的记录。

我们还能发现，既然法律将意志的普遍性与立法范畴的普遍性统一起来，任何人，不管是谁，依据自己的权力所要求的任何东西都不是法律，甚至主权者本身就某一特定目标所指令的东西也不是一条法律，而是一道法令，它不是主权的行为，而是政权的行为。

因此，我称任何有法可依的国家为“共和”，不论其宪法形式如何，因为只有到那时，公共利益才能得以统治，并且只有到那时，公共利益才是真实存在的东西。所有合法政府都是“共和的”。[9]我下面会解释政权是什么。

实际上，法律只是公民社会赖以存在的条件。既然人人都得服从法律，他们就应该是法律的制定者。制定社会规则的权利只属于构成社会的那些人；但是，他们如何运用法律呢？法律靠的是公共契约，还是突发的灵感？政体拥有一个宣布其意志的机构吗？谁将赋予法律以必要阐明条例和提前宣布条例的远见卓识呢？法律将如何在必要时宣布条例呢？一大群盲人常常不知想要什么，因为他们很少知道什么东西对其有用，他们怎么会独自承担像立法制度那样宏大而艰难的事业呢？人们自己总是很想得到好东西，可他们自己并非总能辨认出好东西。公意总是正当合法的，可引导公意的判断并非总是明智的。必须促使公意看事物的本质，而且有时也要看事物的表象；还必须为其指明所探索的美好之路，以便抵御个体欲望的诱惑；还必须赋予其对地点和时间的感知，以便其在眼前切实优势和未来隐患间加以权衡。个体看到好东西却拒绝了它，公众期望好东西却又看不到它。两者都同样需要加以引导。必须强迫个体使其意志服从其理性，必须教会公众识别其所期许的东西。这样的公众启迪将在社会团体中使理解与意志结合起来，使各个部分达到完美协调，使整体提升至拥有最大力量。为此，我们需要立法者。

第七章　论立法者

为了寻求最适合国家的社会法则，需要有一个能理解人之七情六欲但本身无欲无求的高明智者。这个智者与我们的天性无关，却又对其了如指掌；他的幸福并不依赖于我们的幸福，然而他始终致力于为我们谋求福祉，且愿意在长久的时间里平静等待一份不知何日才会授予他的荣耀。他总是在年轻时劳动而在年老时享受劳动的果实。[10]人类总得需要神明给予其法律。

为了给公民或国王下定义，柏拉图曾在他的对话录《政治家》中，从哲学角度应用了与卡里古拉从经验主义角度所应用的相同推理。如果说伟大的君主很少出现是事实的话，一个伟大立法者的出现又该有多稀罕呢？毕竟，君主只需遵循立法者提供的模式即可。立法者是发明机器的工程师；而君主只不过是启动并操作机器的机械师。孟德斯鸠说过：在政治社会诞生之时，规范种种制度的是共和国领袖，而后来，造就共和国领袖的是种种制度。

无论是谁在建立民族的艰巨事业上冒险，要我们说，都必须准备改变人类的本性，将每个自身彻底完整而孤独的个体改变为更大整体的一部分，到那时，从某种意义上说，同样的个体会从这个整体得到自己的生命与存在。国家的缔造者必须削弱人的组织以强化国家，并用道德上的集体存在取代我们大家从自然那儿得到的物质上的独立存在。总之，每个人都必然要被剥夺去自己的权力，并被赋予对他来说是外部的、而在没有别人的帮助下却无法使用的种种权力。人们的自然权力越是接近灭绝或消灭，社会制度就越是强大和完美，因此，当每个公民若不与别人合作就绝对一事无成，且整体所获取的权力等于或大于个体中每个人的自然权力的总和时，我们便可以说，法律的制定已经达到尽善尽美的程度。

在一个国家里，立法者从各方面看都是非同寻常的存在。非同寻常既是指他的天赋，也是指他肩负着的、既非行政者也非主权者的职责。这种赋予共和国以宪法的职责在这宪法中却不占一席之地。这是一项与帝权无关的、特别的、超然的职责，因为，正如指挥人的人没必要掌握法律一样，掌握法律的人也没必要指挥人。否则，当法律成了立法者感情的产物，不公正的判决便会层出不穷，并不可避免地损害立法者之事业的神圣性。

在利库尔戈斯为自己的国家制定法律时，他是以放弃自己君主之位的方式开始这项工作的。将制定城市法框架的任务授予异乡人原是大多数希腊城市的惯例。意大利现代的共和国往往仿效这个惯例。日内瓦共和国也是这样做的，并且发觉这种做法挺管用。[11]古罗马早在其最繁荣的年代便已显现暴政死灰复燃的迹象，而它后来的覆灭只有一个原因，那就是立法权和主权的合二为一。

然而，即使是古罗马的十大行政官，他们本身也从未以自己的权力霸占立法权。他们曾对公民说：“我们对你们提出的东西，未经你们同意，都不可能成为法律。能制定出确保人民幸福之法律的，只有古罗马人自己。”

正是由于这个原因，制定法律的人既没必要也不应该拥有立法权，而且就算人民心甘情愿，也绝不可以任由他们将这一权利拱手相让，因为按照基本的契约，能约束个体的只有公意，如果没有举行公民的自由投票、让个体发表意见，个意与公意的相互一致便无法确保——这一点我已经说过，但它值得我重复论述。

于是，在立法者的工作中我们发现两件看起来似乎互相矛盾的事情——超越人权的任务及其不存在的行政权力。

还有一道难题值得一提。由于有成千上万个无法译成大众化习语的概念，那些坚持用自己的语言对凡夫俗子说话的圣人，肯定不为人所明白。一些普遍的观点及其生僻的用意同样超越了普通人群所理解的范围；在一些人眼里，只有为他们的利益服务的政策才是好的政策，他们很难明白，优秀的法律对人施加的种种限制能带来益处。对一个刚建立起来的民族而言，若要求人人理解英明的政治原理，并遵守治国要领的基本法则，那就必须将因果倒置；也就是说，必须让作为社会制度产物的社会精神反过来支配制度的建设；而人也应该在法律出现之前就自发将自己变成法律的遵守者。出于以上这些原因，立法者既不能使用权力，也不能展开辩论，所以必须求助于另一制度的权威——不用暴力就能强迫他人、不用规劝就能说服他人的人。

正是这样，历史上各国的缔造者才不得不求助于神的调和，并将他们自己的智慧归功于神，因为只有当民众像顺从自然法则那样顺从国家的法律、认为人与城邦出自于同一造物主之手的时候，他们才能真正出于自己的意愿听人发话，并温顺地接受公众幸福必须被束缚的现实。

立法者就是使用了这样高妙的技巧，借神的嘴巴将自己的决策传达下去，并且不让普通民众察觉其中的原理，这样一来，神权便驱动了那些不相信由人制定的审慎决策的人。[12]但是，有一点要注意，不是人人都能让神开口说话，或是假扮神之旨意的解释者来获取民众的信任的。立法者必须彰显其灵魂之伟大，并证明自己的存在有如奇迹，因此有资格肩负使命。任何人都能用一些粗劣的手段来装神弄鬼、显示自己的与众不同，比如雕刻石碑、贿赂一名预言者、声称秘密接触过神学、训练一只小鸟在自己的耳边窃窃私语等。可以想象得出，一个会做这种事情的人，可能会聚集起一群蠢人，但他永远也创建不了一个帝国，那些不入流的小把戏只会随他一起消亡。毫无价值的伎俩也许能成为暂时的纽带，但只有智慧才能维系永久的联盟。至今仍流行的希伯来法律，以及以实玛利的后代使用的、统治了半个世界多达千年的的法律，现今依然显示出最初的制定者的伟大。即使傲慢的哲学家和目中无人的派别认为他们不过是走运的骗子，真正的政治家也能看得出谁拥有那只伟大之手，以及隐藏在千秋功业后面的强大智慧。

然而，通过以上的论述，我们并不能得出与瓦波顿一样的结论：宗教和政治都有着同样的目的。我们只能说，在国家成立之时，宗教充当了政治的工具。

第八章　论人民

正像建筑师初次安装建筑测量仪，以检验地面能否承载重量那样，明智的立法者一开始并不是制定对自己有利的法律，而是判定那些对法律感兴趣的人是否能支持法律。这样的推理导致柏拉图拒绝为阿卡迪亚人或塞伦人提供法律，因为他很清楚，那些富人无法容忍平等。克里特岛也提供了一个好法律和坏民众的例子，米洛斯人本身的恶习不改，即便引进法律也是无益。

这个世界已见证过成百上千个灿烂辉煌的民族，它们基本都没接受过好法律，甚至那些据说接受过好法律的民族，也可能只是在其历史上有过短暂的法治时期。民族[13]就像人一样，只有在其青年时期是可教的；随着年龄的增长，民族就变得积习难改。一旦习惯形成了，偏见根深蒂固，改造民族便成了危险而无果的事业；人们非但不会自发地消灭民族内的邪恶，还会全力阻碍他人来揭露自己的缺点，就像愚蠢胆怯的病人一看见医生就发抖那样。

我并不否认，正如某些痛苦搅乱人们的思想并消除人们对往事的记忆一样，在民族中也有某些重大的暴力事件或革命会对公民产生影响。不过，疾病只会使人遗忘，而历史留下的是清晰的恐惧感。在遭内战毁灭后，民族可以说是在一片废墟中再生，跨过了存亡之关隘，重新获得青春的活力。利库尔戈斯时代斯巴达人的经历是如此；塔尔昆之后古罗马的经历是如此；在近代世界驱逐专制君主之后，荷兰和瑞士的经历也是如此。

可是，这样的事件并不寻常：它们都是需要由国家特别机构加以解释的例外情况。这种情况不可能第二次在同样的民族身上发生，因为虽然一个民族在仍未开化时可以使自己自由，但当这个民族的成员筋疲力尽时，它就无力抗争了。到那时，骚乱会导致覆灭，而且连革命也不能挽救这个民族的命运，其结果是锁链一旦被打破，民族就土崩瓦解、不复存在；之后，其所需要的便是一个主人，而不是一个解放者了。自由的人儿，请你们记住这句格言：自由可以获得，但决不可以重新获得。

民族与人一样，若要使其服从法律，必须等到成熟期；民族的成熟是不易被察觉的；一些事情做得太快，结果反而夭折。而且不同民族之间也有差别；有的民族从一开始就懂得约束自己，而有的民族即使延续千年也依然桀骜不驯。俄国人永远不会成为归顺的臣民，因为这个民族在还未成熟的时候就受到了强制性的统治。彼得大帝有模仿者的才能，但没有真正创造性的天资。他所做的一些事情是好的，可大多数时候他会误入歧途。他明白，他的人民尚未开化，可他并不明白自己的人民尚未为政权做好准备：在本应适当指导臣民的阶段，他却试图让他们文明起来。他努力将他们变成德国人或英国人，而不是变成俄国人。他敦促他们脱胎换骨，而不是以自然的方式成长。法国的家庭教师也是这样，这就是为什么他们训练出来的学生在童年时展露才华，成年后却大失风彩。俄罗斯帝国想征服欧洲，却反被征服。鞑靼人——俄罗斯帝国的邻居和臣民——则成为俄罗斯帝国乃至更广疆域的主人。依我之见，这场革命必将到来，欧洲所有国王都在齐心协力做工作以加快这一进程。

第九章　论人民（续）

自然已给一个发育健全的人设定了身高范围，出了这范围他不是巨人就是矮子。同样，国家体制若要达到最佳状态，也必须在规模上有所限制，这一规模既不能大到不好治理，也不能小到无法维护自身。一个政体有其力量的上限，通常来说，随着政体扩张，这一极限会愈来愈可望而不可及。而社会关系就如同皮筋，拉得越长，越容易松弛。所以，若是以面积与实力所成的比例为标准，那么小国往往强于大国。

成百上千次的思考应该能证明这一结论的准确性。第一，大国幅员辽阔，偏远地区的行政工作不能顺畅进行，这就像物体放在杠杆长的那一端，就得花更大力气去抬动一样。由于领土扩张，政府在治理方面的任务也更加繁重了。每个城镇的居民都要为他们自己的管理机构支付运行费用；城镇所属的每个区同样设有政府，费用还是居民来出；到了省里，又有更高一级的管理机构，然后是再上面的政府、总督府或总督辖区。越是往上，民众越是得掏更多的钱来支付管理成本，而国家最高行政机构的花费更是成为了每个人必须肩负的重担。如此大量、层层叠叠的费用使得臣民精疲力竭。而且，这种分级的管理结构远没有达到其治理目的，相反，如果只有一个行政机构，民众的生活会轻松不少。事实上，庞大的管理体系消耗了太多资金，以至于几乎没有剩余的公共税收能用来应急，一旦有状况发生，国家便会在崩溃的边缘摇摇欲坠。

这还没完。在实施法律、避免骚乱、纠正恶习、防止偏远居民区发生暴动等方面，有问题的不仅仅是软弱无比、反应迟钝的政府，还有无动于衷的人民。他们对素未谋面的政府官员、疆域辽阔的祖国、千千万万形同陌路的同胞缺乏更多的热情。相同的法律并不适用于许多不同的省份，因为它们有着各自的风俗习惯和千差万别的气候，形式划一的管理是行不通的。然而，各地偏偏又处在相同的统治之下，若是施行不同的法律，只会在相互往来的民族中产生曲解，造成混淆；在这种情况下，若是不同族群混居并通婚，他们甚至会搞不清楚自己是否有权继承遗产。当众多对彼此毫无了解的人通过一个单一的最高管理机构聚集在同一地方，人才就会被埋没，德行就会被忽视，恶行也将得不到惩罚。政府官员事务繁多，自顾不暇，在小事上很少亲力亲为，因此，实际上在处理国家政务的是那些普通职员们。同时，官员们逃避职责或滥用权力也是必然现象，一个政府为了维护基本的权威，往往得想尽一切办法监督这些官员，不管他们身在多么偏远的地方。如果做到了这些，政府便再没有什么余力去关心公民的幸福快乐了，而且若是受到攻击，它也毫无自我防御的能力。这个因其建制过于庞大而与国家规模不符的政府，将会在其自身的重压下崩溃，乃至灭亡。

另一方面，假如一个国家要有势力的话，它就必须为自己打下扎实的基础，以便能抵抗其必受的种种打击，并且能进行延续自身之存在的种种活动，因为所有民族都会产生一种离心力，凭着这种离心力，它们不断磨擦、互相抗击，都试图以牺牲邻国为代价，像笛卡儿的旋涡一样扩张自己的势力。因而，弱者总是处在被吞食的危险境地。的确，没有哪个民族能妥善地保护好自己，除非它与其他民族达成一种势均力敌的平衡。

这就向我们表明，扩张和收缩都自有其意义；实际上，要准确判断两者混合的比例、使国家顺风顺水地发展下去，其中的政治智慧不可小觑。一般地说，扩张是外部的、相对的，而收缩是内部的、绝对的，因此后者的意义更为重大。强健的组织是一个国家所期待的第一样东西，因为这种出自好政体的势力，比起大片领土所产生的资源更加可靠。

人们可能会补充说，已存在这样的国家，其政治结构要求它必须把征服作为国家体制的一部分；对它们来说，不停地扩张领土实属维护自身的无奈之举。或许，它们的人民也会暗中庆幸，毕竟国家的强大正是仰仗了征服的必要性。可是，这种必要性本身就是一个预兆，揭示了这些国家的最终命运——繁荣过后，便是崩塌。

第十章　论人民（再续）

衡量一个政体有两种方式，一是按其领土的广阔程度，二是按其人口的数量；如果国家想达到最佳规模的话，在这两个方面之间必须存在一定的平衡。公民创造国家，而土地滋养公民；因此，这种均衡要求国家以足够的土地养育人民，而人民的数量又刚好能为土地所承受。正是在这种均衡之中，已知数量的人口得以产生最大限度的力量，因为如果拥有太多的土地，治理便成了沉重负担，国家的劳动力不足，且无力消耗过量的产品，这样很快就会引来别国的侵略；而另一方面，如果拥有的土地太少，国家便不得不依靠从邻国进口的东西来维持生存，这又必然发展成进攻别国的理由。任何须在商业与战争之间抉择的民族，实质上都是虚弱的；它不但依赖其邻国，还要靠运气来撑过难关，因此终究只能在动荡不安的局势中短暂存在。它不是去征服别国、结束自己的困境，就是被别国征服然后消亡。要么弱小到毫无威胁，要么强大到战无不胜，只有这两种手段能让它保全自己的自由。

由于物产的性质、气候的影响，由于不同地方的不同特征以及土地肥沃程度的差异，还由于居住在不同区域的人——有些鱼米之乡的居民格外节俭，也有些荒蛮之地的居民生活优渥——存在性格上的差异，一个国家无法在其国土面积和居民数量之间确定一个应有的、数学上的确切比例。并且，我们还应该将妇女的生育能力的强弱、不同土地的特点和宜居程度、立法者希望其制度能吸引的移民数量考虑在内。由此可见，立法者必须根据其预见而非所见作出决策，计算出与其说是现有人口的数量，不如说是人口必须自然达到的数量。最后，意外事件会导致数量众多的特殊情况，要求或允许少数人生活在似乎不必要的大面积的土地上。比如，耕作型山区农村——森林地和牧场——不需要太多的劳动力，由于那里的妇女通常拥有比平原妇女更强的生育能力，且陡峭山坡仅留下平地边缘角落能用来种植植物，这个地区的居民确实需要更广阔的土地。与此相反的是海边的情况，在那儿，人们会聚集在一个狭小的区域，甚至聚集在几乎贫瘠的沙石地当中，因为捕鱼可以弥补当地农业生产的诸多不足，且密集的聚落帮助人们更好地抵抗海盗；此外，他们还更易于以殖民的办法来减轻小面积国土的人口负担。

然而，还有一个创建民族的条件，即人们必须享有和平与富足。这一条件是其他条件所无法替代的，没有了它，所有的其余条件都归于无效。这是因为，一个处在形成时期的国家期就像一个正在列阵的军团，抵抗力最弱，也最容易被摧毁。这段酝酿的时间危机四伏，比国家局势陷入混乱还要糟糕，因为此时每个人只考虑自身的处境，而不是共同的危险。如果在这紧要关头爆发一场战争，或是发生饥荒和騷乱的话，国家将不可避免地走向灭亡。

诚然，许多政体都是在这样的混乱中成功建立起来的，但是随后，这些政体自身却成了国家覆灭的原因。一个要颠覆国家的篡夺者，总是会选择在多事之秋利用民众的普遍恐慌来制定他们在冷静时决不愿意接受的法律。立法者之事业有别于暴君之事业的最明确的特点之一就是：为民族制定宪法的时机。

那么，哪些民族适合接受法律呢？我的回答是：一个已经与现有的某种联盟、利益或习俗紧密联系在一起，但还未正式被严密法律所束缚的民族：一个没有根深蒂固的风俗习惯或迷信的民族：一个不惧怕突然的入侵、不参与邻国的纷争也不畏惧任何邻国、能获得一国支援去抵抗另一国的民族；一个让内部每个成员都能为大家所知，且不强迫任何成员过度劳动民族：一个不依靠别国，也不被别国依靠的民族；[14]一个既不富裕也不贫穷，恰好能维持自己生存的民族；最后，一个将古代民族的凝聚力与现代民族的可塑性结合起来的民族。使立法者工作变得如此之难的，与其说是必须创建的东西，不如说是必须摧毁的东西；而使其成功变得如此稀罕的，则是自然之简单朴素与社会产生的需求的不相容性。把所有这些条件融为一体是有困难的。这就是为何体制完备又能生存下来的国家少之又少。

在欧洲还有一个适合接受法律的国家，它就是科西嘉岛。为了重获和捍卫其自由，这个无畏的民族展现出了无与伦比的英勇和忠诚，他们理应得到一些智者的指导，学习如何维护并延续这份自由。我有一个预感：这个小岛总有一天将让欧洲为之震动。

第十一章　论不同的法律制度

如果我们要问，那个造福全体人民、应该成为每种法律制度目标的最好的结果究竟是什么，我们会发现它有两个主要方面：自由与平等：之所以自由，是因为但凡个体不独立，国家主体的力量就会被大幅削弱；之所以平等，是因为它对自由的实现来说必不可少。

我已经解释过什么是公民自由；至于平等，这个词的意思绝不是说所有人都应拥有完全等量的权力与财富，而是说，权力不该成为任何暴力，而只有凭公正的权威与法律才能加以行使，同时，在财富方面，既不能让一个公民富得足以买下另一个公民，也不能让一个公民穷得被迫出卖自己。这反过来表明，地位较高者必须在财富和权力上有所节制，而地位较低者必须在贪婪和私欲上有所节制。[15]

有人会说，这样的平等完全是一个虚构的理论，它事实上并不存在。可就算恶习不可避免，难道我们不该至少尝试去抑制它吗？正因为环境的力量总是趋于破坏平等，我们才应该一如既往地用立法的力量去维护平等。

然而，一切制度的普遍目标必须在各国加以修正来满足当地的条件、适应相关民族的特性。正是根据这样的要素，一个国家才必须给每个民族制定专门的体制，这种体制在本质上或许不是最好的，但对那个采用它的国家来说应当是最好的。例如，你的国家土地贫瘠、一片荒芜吗？或者它的领土对居民来说太小了吗？那么，这个国家可以重点发展工业和手工业，并用工业品来交换短缺的天然资源。另一方面，假定你的国家拥有富饶的平原和肥沃的坡地，但优质的土地上却没有足够的人口，那么最好的解决办法就是集中精力搞好农业，增加人口，同时尽量避免居民进行工艺活动，因为此类工作不但会减少农村人口，还会让仅有的那些居民向少数城市中心聚集。[16]你的国家拥有便于船只停靠的宽阔海岸吗？那么，若是大量造船、发展贸易和航海业，你的国家即便历史短暂，也能繁荣富强。如果你的国家运气没那么好，只有一条风急浪高、岩石嶙峋的海岸线，那么也不必强求，顺其自然、像原始人一样捕鱼为生即可。这样，你的生活将更平静，或许也将更好，而且你一定会觉得更加幸福。总之，除了那些为大家所共用的原则之外，每个民族都有其特殊的理由以自己的方式去接受这些原则，并且遵循适合自身的法律。因此，古代的希伯来人和近代的阿拉伯人把宗教当作主要目标，雅典人搞文学，迦太基人和提尔人搞贸易，罗得西亚人出海远航，斯巴达人打仗，而古罗马人注重公民道德建设。《论法的精神》一书的作者已经用几十个例子表明，立法者的艺术是怎样为各国的体制指明其各自的目标的。

要想国家的体制变得真正持久强大，就要对惯例和习俗进行仔细的考量，使自然与法律逐渐在各方面变得和谐。这时候，我们就可以说，法律不管维护、伴随和纠正何种事物，都是在遵循自然规律。然而，立法者也有可能搞错目标，建立与环境要求不一致的原则。当他的原则和环境背道而驰，比如一个倾向于奴役而另一个倾向于自由、一个倾向于财富而另一个倾向于人口增长、一个倾向于和平而另一个倾向于征战时，法律将不知不觉地被削弱，体制将退化，国家将一直处于动乱，直到被毁灭或改朝换代。到那时，不可征服的自然将重新建起自己的帝国。

第十二章　论法律的分类

为了使一切井然有序，也为了给公众带来最可行的法律形式，有各种各样需要考虑的关系。第一，整个政体对自身的作用，换句话说，就是整体与整体之间的关系，或主权者与国家之间的关系。而正如我们会看到的那样，这种大关系由是由许多两者之间的个体的小关系构成的。

制定这种关系的法律被称为政治法，也叫作基本法——只有那些明智的法律才担得起这个称号。因为，如果国家只有一种规范秩序的好办法，那么制定这一办法的民族理应遵守它。但是，如果已建立的秩序不太好，那么这种阻碍人们获得幸福的法律又有什么基本性可言呢？而且，在任何情况下，一个民族都应有修改法律的自由，哪怕那条法律已经十分完美。毕竟，一个人无论做什么事，就算他是要伤害自己，别人也无权干涉。这对民族来说也是如此。

第二种关系是政体成员之间的关系，或个体与整体之间的关系。个体之间的关系应尽可能受制约，而个体与整体之间的关系应尽可能广泛。这是为了让每个公民既完全独立于其他公民，又十分依赖共和国——既然只有国家权力才能使其成员变得自由，这一结果总是以同样的手段获得，民法正是源自这第二种关系。

我们可能会考虑到人与法之间的第三种关系，即不服从法律和处罚之间的关系。刑法的制定就是以这一点为基础的，不过，与其说刑法是一种特殊法律，不如说它是所有法律背后的准则。

在这三类法律之外还有最为重要的第四类。它既不是雕在大理石上，也不是刻在黄铜上，而是铭记在公民的心坎上。它是一种构成国家真正宪法的法律；它每天都在凝聚力量，当其他法律变得陈旧或衰退时，它便会提供新的动力，或直接取而代之；它在其制度精神的鼓舞下维护国家，不知不觉地以习惯势力代替官方势力。我所说的这第四类法律，正是道德、风俗以及信仰：这一特性虽不为我们的政治理论家所知，却是所有其他法律成功的必要条件；伟大的立法者正是对此特性给予着秘密关注，尽管他们似乎将自己局限于法律详尽的条款，但这些条款只不过是拱顶的拱架，立法者清楚地知道，发展更为缓慢的道德最终将成为国家毫不动摇的基石。

在那些不同类型的法律中，唯有构成政体形式的政治法才与我的主题相关。

第三卷

在讲不同政府形式之前，让我们先来明确政府这个词的具体意思，该词至今尚未得到很好的解释。

第一章　政府总论

我必须提醒读者，本章应当仔细阅读，因为对于那些不想全神贯注的人，我是没有办法讲明白的。

每一种自由的行为都有两个使其发生的原因，一个是道德——确定这一行为的意志，另一个是身体——实施行为的体力。当我们走向一个目标时，首先是要想好该走哪条路，然后就是得确保我们的双脚能带着我们走到那儿。当一个瘫痪病人决心要跑步时，当一个健康的人决心不走时，两者都会停留在他们所在的位置。政体具有相同的两个动力——并且我们能在意志和体力之间作出相同的区分：前者为立法权；后者为行政权。要是两者不相一致，在这政体中就没有什么事能够或者应该做成。

我们已经明白，立法权属于且只属于公民。另一方面，从以上（第二卷第四章和第六章）所制定的原则不难看出，行政权不可能像立法权和主权那样属于一般人，因为行政权只在处于法律范畴之外的特定行动中实施，而既然主权仅有制定法律的职能，那这些行动也就自然不属于主权的范畴。

这样一来，公众力量便需要靠一个代理人才能集中起来，并公意的指导下实施行动。这个代理人是国家与主权者之间沟通的手段，就像一个个体需要灵魂与肉体的结合才能完整一样，公众也需要代理人的牵线搭桥来发挥其应有的力量。这就是国家需要政府的原因之所在。某些时候，人们会因为分不清政府和主权者而产生误会，但其实对于主权者来说，政府扮演的完全是大臣一样的角色。

那么，什么是政府呢？政府就是臣民与主权者之间为了相互沟通建立起来的中间体，它的职责是行使法律，同时维护社会自由和政治自由。

这个主体的成员被称作行政官或国王，换句话说就是执政者，而整个主体又被冠以君主的名称。[17]因而，那些不承认人民服从统治者的行为是一种契约的理论家们是完全正确的。那种行为只不过是一种委任，也就是说，执政者只不过是被主权者雇佣、以其名义代行其权利罢了，而且主权者随时可以凭自己的意志限制、改变，然后再次赋予执政者这种权利。既然如此，这种权力的转让便与社会主体的性质不可兼容，而且也违背了社会联盟建立的初衷。

因此，我把“政府”或“最高行政”称作行政权的合法行使，而把“君主”或“行政官”称为负责管理机构的人或主体。

正是在政府中，我们才可能辨别出构成整体与整体之间、或主权者与国家之间相互关系的中间力量。这最后一个关系，可描述为一种几何意义上的连续，有着明确的两个端点，而政府的位置就是这个连续的中项。政府从主权者那儿接受其给予公民的敕令；如果想让国家处于完全平衡的状态，就必须对一切进行精确计算，最后得出一个等式——政府权力的二次方等于既是主权者、又是权力实施之对象的公民权力的二次方。

此外，这三个条件中的任何一个都不得被破坏，否则比例立刻会发生改变。不管是主权者试图统治、行政官试图立法还是臣民拒绝服从，秩序都将让位于混乱，权力和意志将停止步调一致的行动，解体的国家不是陷入专制政治，就是陷入无政府状态。最后，由于两个极端之间只有一个几何学平均值，所以一个国家也只能有一种好的政府形式；但是，许许多多的事件可能会改变一个国家内部的种种关系，在这个基础上，除了不同的民族可以拥有各不相同的好政府，同一个民族也可能在多个时期拥有不同形式的好政府。

为了设法解说可能存在于这两个极端之间的种种关系，我将以人口数量为例，因为这是一种不难表达的比率。

假设一个国家由一万个公民组成。在这里，主权者只能被共同视为主体，而每个成员作为臣民必然被视为个体。因而，主权者与臣民的比率就是一万比一，那就是说，国家中每个成员只有万分之一的主权份额，尽管他自己是完全从属于主权者的。现在，假设这个民族的人口增加到十万。每个臣民的地位并没有改变，因为每个人与其他人一道平等地支撑起整个法律体系，而作为主权者，人们的投票份额减少到十万分之一，结果就是，一个人在法律制定方面的影响力也按比例骤减了。因而，当主权者与臣民的比率随公民数量而增大时，臣民依然还是单一的个体。由此可见，国家越扩大，自由就越减小。

当说到比率增加时，我是以一作为标准的。这样，数学意义上的比率越大，现实中的比率就越小，因为在前者中，根据数量考虑的比率是用商数来衡量的，而在后者中，根据相等考虑的比率是用相似值来衡量的。

个意与公意，即人们的道德与法律之间的比率越小，需要使用的压制力就越大。因此，要想维持一个好的政府，就应该让其力量与人口数量同步增长。

在人口比率中，既然国家的扩大意味着为官员提供更多的诱惑，以及更多滥用手中权力的机会，那么当政府管理公民的权力增大时，主权者也需要有更大的权力来制约政府。我在此所说的并非绝对权力，而是国家不同成分的相对权力。

由这种双重关系可见，主权者、君主和公民之间的几何连续并不是一个任意的概念，而是政体性质的必然结果。由此还可见，既然公民在两个极端之间作为一而存在，那么每当连续的平方发生增减，连续本身同样会增减。中间项——即政府——也就随之改变。这就表明，不存在唯一绝对的政府形式，有多少大小不同的国家，就有多少不同类型的政府。

如果有人会对这种体系不以为然，并说：按照我的思路，想要建立一个好政府，即找到这个几何连续的中项，只需算出人口数的平方根即可。那么，我的回答是，我在此仅以数量为例；我所讲的比率不仅以人口数来衡量，而且更多地以无数原因并发产生的作用量来衡量；我得补充说明的是，虽然为了用三言两语表达自己的想法，我刚才借用过数学语言，但是我仍然意识到，数学的精确度完全表达不出精神层面的深刻考量。

包含政府在内的政体规模有多大，政府本身的规模就有多小。政府是一个被赋予某些功能的、像主权者那样积极却像国家那样被动的虚构人格，它可以再被细分为几种相似的关系，而新的比率由此产生。在每一种比率中，我们都可根据行政官的等级继续分析，直至我们取得唯一不可分割的中间项，也就是唯一的最高行政官为止，他可以被认为是分数数列和整数数列之间的“一”。

我们也可以不纠结这些复杂的概念，只把政府简单当作国家之内的一个新主体，它与公民和主权者都不相同，而且正好处于这两者的正中间。

这新旧两个主体之间存在着本质上的差异——国家就其本身而言是存在的，而政府只有借助主权者才能存在。因而，君主的统治意志是或应该只是公意或法律；他的权力仅仅是公共权力的集中体现。一旦他决心以自己的权威施行某些绝对不受约束的行为，整个主体就会开始涣散。最后，如果君主拥有了比主权者更积极的个意，而且他为了贯彻这一个意而利用了手中的公众权力，以至于让两个主权者同时存在——一个是权利上的，另一个是事实上的——那么，联系社会的纽带便会即刻消失，政体也会随之瓦解。

即便如此，为了让政府本身拥有一个真实的、有别于国家的确切存在形式，也为了使它的全部成员能步调一致地依照政府设立的初衷提供服务，它必须有一个特定的“自我”、一种所有成员共有的觉悟、一种力量、一种倾向于延续自身的意志。如此特定的存在形式就需要有大会、内阁会议、审议权和决定权、头衔和专属于君主的特权，而且对于那些担当艰难任务的行政官，君主要用自己的特权给予他们相应的尊贵地位。难的是找到一种方法，在整体中妥善安排这个附属性的整体，使政府在自我调整的时候，不对总的国家体制造成影响。只有这样，政府用以维持其生存的自身力量，才能与保障国家之存续的公众力量区别开来。总而言之，国家应该始终准备为了公民牺牲政府，而不是为了政府牺牲公民。

再者，即使政府这个人造主体是另一个相似人造主体的产物，且它仅仅具有一种模仿的、附属的存在形式，但这并不妨碍它能以或多或少的活力和或快或慢的速度自由行动。同样，它的健康程度也完全由自身决定。最后，虽然政府不会直接走上与其设定好的种种目标相悖的道路，但根据其被构建起来的方式，政府确实有可能在不同程度上偏离那些目标。

正是这些差异促成了应当存在于政府与国家主体之间的多样化的关系，且这些使国家本身发生变化的关系都遵照种种偶然的、特定的比率。因为，若不想让本质上最好的政府演变为最邪恶的政府，就必须让它与国家的关系保持在最优状态，从而弥补它所属政体的种种不足。

第二章　论不同政府形式的建制原则

既然我已经在国家与主权者之间做过区分，所以为了解释这些差异的一般原因，现在有必要在君主和政府之间也做一番区分。

行政官主体可能由或多或少的成员组成。我们已经知道，人口越是众多，人民的主权份额就越小。通过明显的类推，我们可以说，政府较之行政官也有同样的比率。

不论何时，政府的整体力量就是国家的力量，这一点是永远不会改变的；由此可见，政府为其成员消耗的力量越多，它用在全体公民身上的力量就越小。

所以行政官的数量越多，政府就显得越弱。由于这是一项基本原则，那就让我们努力把它弄得更清楚吧。

我们可在行政官个人身上辨别出三个本质上不同的意志。第一，他作为个体拥有的、只倾向于他个人利益的意志。第二，行政官的集体意志，这种意志只涉及君主的利益，可以被称为团体的意志，因为它与对政府来说是普遍的，而对包含政府在内的国家来说又是特殊的。第三，公民意志或主权者意志，这种意志不管是对作为整体的国家来说，还是对作为整体一部分的政府来说，都是普遍的。

在一个立法健全的体制中，个意或特殊意志是不该存在的，而政府自身的团体意志也应该处于非常次要的地位。这样一来，公意或主权者意志就永远起到主导作用，并且成为所有其他意志的唯一规范。

相反，在自然秩序中，这些不同的意志越是各行其道，他们就越是活跃。因此，公意始终是最软弱的，而团体意志排列第二，特殊意志名列第一；结果，在政府内部，每个成员首先是个人的自我，其次是行政官，最后才是公民。这一排序正好与社会秩序所要求的相反。

这一点成立之后，让我们假设政府被掌握在单一个体的手中。那时，特殊意志与团体意志将完美地结合在一起，而团体意志也从而得以被提升到尽可能高的程度。既然已知权力的行使取决于意志，而政府的绝对权力总是不变的，那么我们就可以得出一个结论，即最具活力的政府就是一个人的政府。

然而，如果我们将条件替换，使政府和立法权威相结合，使君主成为主权者，使每个公民成为行政官——结果就是，与公意合并的团体意志变得与公意一样不活跃，只剩下特殊意志去指挥整个权力。而这样一个始终被同一个绝对力量所掌控的政府，势必只能拥有最少的相对力量和活力。

这些关系是无可争议的，而其他的思考也可以进一步补充证据。例如，我们清楚，每个在政府机构内的行政官肯定比每个在国家主体内的公民活跃。因此，政府行为比主权者行为更容易受到特殊意志的影响，因为每个行政官基本上都肩负着政府的某种特有职能，而公民作为个体却并不承担主权的任何职能。此外，国家扩张得越大，其真正的力量就增加得越多，尽管这两种增长不成一个固定的比例。然而，如果成倍增长的不是国家面积，而是行政官的数量的话，政府便无法从中获得任何实际的力量，毕竟政府力量就是国家力量，这两者总是完全相等的。所以，在其绝对或真正力量不可能增加的情况下，政府的行政官越多，它的相对力量或相对活力就越是减少。

而且，毋庸置疑的是，公众事务的处理速度会随着负责人的增加而下降。庞大的机构过于谨慎，不爱碰运气，往往会错失许多机会；他们花大量的时间深思熟虑，反而使思考的结果一文不值。

我刚刚说过，行政官成倍增加，政府就会涣散。我之前也提到，人口数量越多，对人施加的约束力也必须相应增大。由此可见，行政官与政府的比率应该跟臣民与主权者的比率相反；换句话说，国家扩张得越大，政府越得缩小自身的规模，从而让行政官数量按人口的增加成比例地减少。

我得补充一点，我在此谈的是政府的相对力量，而不是其行为特性。因为，反过来讲，行政官人数越多，他们的团体意志就越接近公意，而在唯一的行政官行使职权的情况下，唯一的的团体意志就像我所说的那样，只是一种特殊意志。所以，在一方面有所失，在另一方面就有所得；立法者的艺术就在于懂得如何确定这样的一个点：让始终在比率上背道而驰的政府力量与政府意志按最有利于国家的比率结合起来。

第三章　论政府的分类

从上一章我们了解到，为何要按组成政府的成员数量来区分政府的各种类型或各种形式；本章将继续阐明政府的分类如何进行的问题。

首先，主权者可能将政府交到全体公民或绝大多数人手中，使得作为行政官的公民比普通公民更多。这种政府形式就是民主制。

此外，主权者可能将政权限制在少数人手中，这样，普通公民就比行政官更多：这种政府形式就是贵族制。

再次，主权者可能将整个政府集中在唯一的一个行政官手中，所有其他人都从他那儿得到权力。这第三种政府的形式最为普遍，被称作君主制或王室政府。

应当注意的是，所有这些形式，或者至少前两种形式都可以增强或减弱其程度；它们具有相当明显的伸缩性。民主制可能包括所有人，但其实只要有一半以上的人数它就能成立。而贵族制既可以包括多达一半的人，也可以局限于极少数人。即使是王室政府，在某种程度上也可能由人们分享。斯巴达按其宪法，通常有两个国王；而在维持统一的基础上，古罗马帝国以同时拥有过多达八个君主而闻名于世。因而，每一种政府形式总有与另一种政府形式重叠的地方。另外，很明确的一点是，政府虽然只有三种名称，但它实际上的形式却有许多种，就像国家拥有众多不同的公民一样。

再者，既然一个政府在某些方面能够将自己细分成几个独立的部分，并让这些部分以不同方式进行行政工作，那么这三种政府便可以结合起来，产生多个混合形式，而每种混合形式又可以与三种原有形式结合。

在每个历史朝代，人们都争论过这样一个问题：“什么是政府的最佳形式？”然而，他们不明白，每一种可能存在的形式在某种情况下都是最佳的，但在另一种情况下又会变成最坏的。

假设在每个特定的国家，最高行政官数量都应与跟公民人数成反比，那么我们就会得出以下结果：一般地说，民主政府适于小国；贵族政府适于不大不小的国家；君主政府则适于大国。这一法则可以直接从我们的定理中得出；可是，我们怎么去计算那些可能出现的例外情况呢？

第四章　论民主制

制定法律的人比任何其他人都清楚法律应该如何实施与解释。这样看来，不可能有比行政权与立法权相结合更好的体制了；事实上，正是这种结合使政府的形式在某些方面变得不完善，因为本应该被分开的东西没有分开，而且，合为一体的君主与主权者只会造就一个徒有其表的政府。

让制定法律的人去执行法律，或者让公民共同体不关注普遍的观点而关注特殊的对象，都不是什么好事。在公共事务中，没有什么会比私利的影响更加危险了。立法者若追逐私利，就必将导致腐败，造成比政府滥用法律还要邪恶的后果。这种情况发生时，国家便会从自身的肌体内开始腐败，再进行改良也无济无事。一个从不滥用政府各种权力的民族，同样也不会滥用独立自主，而一个始终自我管理良好的民族，是无需由别人来管理的。

从严格意义上说，至今还未曾有过真正的民主制，而且将来也决不会有。管理人员比被管理人员还多，这是违背自然法则的。我们几乎无法想象所有人都永久地坐在大会席位上处理公务的情形，同时也很容易明白，我们不可能以此为目的成立委员会，除非连行政形式也一起改变。

我的确相信，人们可以制定这样一条原则：当政府的种种职能由若干委员会分别掌握时，那些拥有最少成员的委员会迟早会获得最大的权力。这不是出于别的原因，而是由调度事务的机制所导致的自然结果。

此外，民主形式的政府还需具备多少难以同时拥有的条件呢？第一，它必须要在一个非常小的国家，因此能迅速地将人们聚集在一起，而且使每个公民都很容易相互认识。第二，作风上要简朴，道德上要单纯，从而避免过多的事务和棘手的争论。第三，要竭力保持社会等级和财富的平等，若非如此，则权利和权威的平等也不会持久。第四，要尽量杜绝奢侈，因为奢侈要么是财富带来的结果，要么是人们视敛财为必要的动因。奢侈不但腐化富人，也腐化穷人；奢侈导致懒惰和虚荣之风盛行，也让一个国家失去所有公民，因为不管是拥有奴隶的人还是成为奴隶的人，全部都是观念的奴隶。

这就是为什么过去的一个著名作家主张将美德作为一个共和国的基本原则，因为没有美德，我前文所说的一切条件就不可能成立。然而，就算天才如这位伟大的作家，他也没能分辨一些必要的区别，因此常常犯错，有时还令人费解。他无法明白，既然主权者的权威放之四海而皆准，那么同样的原理在每个健全的国家就都应占有一席之地——当然，或多或少也要考虑到该国的政府形式。

我们可以补充说，没有一个政府会像民主政府或人民政府那样，极易发生内战和自相残杀的冲突，因为没有哪个政府会如此坚定有力地趋向于改朝换代，也没有哪个政府需要那么多的警惕性和勇气以维护其不变的状态。正是在这种体制而非其他的情况下，公民必须用力量和忠诚武装自身，并且于每天的生活中发自内心地反复重温一位善良的巴拉丁[18]在波兰议会上曾说过的话：“我愿自由而有危险，但不愿安宁而受奴役。”[19]

如果真的有一个天神之国，那它想必就是以民主的形式存在的。然而，如此完美的国家并不适合我们人类。

第五章　论贵族制

我们这里有两个截然不同的人造人格，即政府和主权者，所以也就有了两个公意，一个属于全体公民，另一个只属于行政官。因而，政府虽可随意制定其内部规章，但除非以主权者的名义，否则它决不能直接向公民传达意见。这一点我们必须牢记。

最初，社会都是由贵族治理的。家族的首领们组成小圈子商讨公共事务：年轻人则心甘情愿地服从经验的权威。因此，就有了宗师、长老、元老、长者等名称。北美洲的野蛮人现在仍然保留着这种治理方法，且卓有成效。

可是，当人为的的不平等渐渐胜过自然的不平等时，财富与权力[20]便显得比年龄更为重要了，因此，贵族社会开始实行选举。最后，决定一个家族显赫与否的是父辈遗留给子辈的权力和附带的财产，于是一些家族就有了世袭政权的资格；到那时，年仅二十的年轻人也能当元老了。

如此，就有了三种贵族制，即自然的、选举的和世袭的。第一种类型只适合原始社会，而第三种类型是所有贵族制中最糟糕的一种。第二种类型最好，并且代表了贵族制这个词的真正含义。

贵族制的好处，不仅在于它能将主权者与政府区别开，还在于它可以对行政官进行挑选。在公民政府中，所有公民生来都是行政官，而在贵族制国家，只有少数人能被选举[21]成为行政官，这一方法使得诚实、明智、经验以及所有其他受人喜爱并尊重的理由成为了优质政府的进一步保证。

此外，集会的安排也将变得更加容易，方便人们进行细致的商议，在处理事务时更加有序、恪尽职守；在外人看来，比起身世平凡、人微言轻的无名之辈，德高望重的元老更能维护国家的声誉。

总之，如果我们能确定，最英明的人会为大众利益而非为一己之利治理国家的话，那么由这样的人来统治大众就是最佳最自然的安排。同时，一味地增设机构毫无益处，我们也不该雇两万人来完成一百个出色的人就能圆满完成的任务。不过，必须注意到的是，这样一来，共同利益就会渐渐不再只按公意来引导国家力量了；更不可避免的趋向是，一部分权力的执行将脱离法律的管控。

若考虑与政府形式相适宜的状况，那么国家的面积就不必太小，公民也不必非得那么单纯、那么正直，以至于就像在理想的民主制社会一样，法律的实施可以完全遵照公意。同时，国家也没必要大到足以让四处分散的地方行政长官自立门户、侵占主权，从追求独立渐渐发展成各霸一方。

可是，如果说比起公民政府，贵族制更不在意人们普遍的美德的话，它对一些特定的美德却要求更高，比如让富人懂得节制、让穷人学会满足，因为严格的平等不但在这里无法实现，甚至在斯巴达也是见所未见的。

此外，如果政府的这种形式牵涉到一些财富上的不平等，那么好的做法应该是把公共事务委托给那些能全心全意投身于此的人，而不是像亚里士多德所主张的那样委托给富人。作出这样的选择是有必要的，因为那会时不时提醒人们：人的功绩比财富更有资格得到优先考虑。

第六章　论君主制

到目前为止，我们一直把君主看作是一个集体的、人造的人格，他与法律的力量融为一体，并在国家中扮演行政权的受托人的角色。现在，若是我们把这个人格换成一个自然的、真正的人，即只有这个人能够依法行使这种权利，那么他就可以被称为君主或国王。

这正好与其他管理机构相反。在其他机构，集体集中体现为一个个体，而君主制是让一个个体代表整个集体，所以，君主的精神统一性同时又是物质统一性，使得其他制度用法律难以聚拢的力量，在这里却能自然而然地聚拢起来。

由此，公民的意志、君主的意志、国家的公众力量、政府的个体权力，所有这些都听从同一个行为者的调遣，所有机器杠杆都掌握在同一个人手中，所有行为都指向同一个目标，不存在什么相互对抗的矛盾。面对这样一种体制，我们再也想象不出有什么别的形式能使一个国家以更少的努力获得更多的成果。阿基米德静静地坐在海岸上，却能毫不费力地发动一艘巨轮，这就是一位身居斗室而管理广阔疆域的君主的理想形象。他必然十分熟悉治国之道，所以即使自身不动，也能使国家的一切有序运转。

但是，如果说君主制是最为朝气蓬勃的一种政府，那么它同时也是最容易让特殊意志压倒其他所有意志的政府。诚然，在君主制国家，各方都在朝着同样的目标努力，可那个目标并不是公众的幸福。另一方面，就连行政权力本身也持续不断地为国家带来危害。

国王们都想尽可能地巩固自己的地位，而人们的声音从远处传来：若想高枕无忧，最好办法是使自己得到公民的爱戴。这是一条很好的箴言，甚至在某些方面还是一条千真万确的箴言。不幸的是，这条箴言总在宫廷里遭到嘲笑。建立在民众拥护基础上的权力无疑是最强大的权力，不过也是不稳固的、暂时的权力；君主们绝不会对此心满意足。再好的国王，都会想要一边为所欲为，一边稳坐一国之主的位子；一个政治说教者很可能会对国王说：既然公民的力量就是国王的力量，那么国王的最大利益就是使得民族繁荣昌盛、人丁兴旺、外敌不敢来犯。可是，国王们其实都非常明白，这并非事实。对他们的个人利益来说，首要的就是，人民应该软弱、不幸且永远无力反抗。我承认，如果国王拥有的是一群完全顺从于他的臣民，那么他的个人利益自然也就要求他使公民变得强大，因为这样一来，他便能将公民的力量作为自己的力量，从而对邻国施威；可既然这只是一种次要的、从属的利益，而且既然公民的强大与顺从不可兼得，君主们总是优先采纳更能带来直接利益的主张。这就是塞缪尔极力向希伯来人强调的东西，也是马基雅维利很清楚地证明过的东西——他表面上是在指导国王，实际上是给人民上了重要的一课。马基雅维利的《君王论》是一部为共和论者而写的指南。[22]

通过对一般比率的讨论，我们已经知道，君主制只适合大国，而且当我们检验君主制本身时，这一点也十分明显。公共行政人员的数量越多，君主与臣民的比率就减少得越多、越接近相等，乃至在民主制中达到一比一，即完全相等。而随着政府的收缩，这一比率会越来越大，且在政权掌握于唯一一人手里的情况下达到最大限度。到那时，君主与公民之间存在太大的差距，国家便缺少团结的纽带。要想形成纽带，就必须增加中间社会阶层，并以王公、大臣和贵族来填充。但是，这一切都不适合一个小国，因为它承受不了如此之多的社会阶级。

如果管好一个大国是有难度的，那要一个人单枪匹马管好大国就是难上加难了；每个人都知道，当一个国王找来许多副手治理国家时会发生什么情况。

一个使君主制始终不如共和制的关键而又不可避免的缺陷是，在共和国中，民众只会选择有知识、有能力的人来担任举足轻重的职位，而且这些人也会以相应的业绩来回报这份荣誉。相反，那些在君主制下加官进爵的人，几乎总是糊里糊涂的平庸之辈、身无长处的流氓和卑鄙的阴谋家，他们的小聪明只够让自己在宫廷里爬到高位，一旦履行起职务来，他们的无能便在公众面前暴露无遗。比起君主，公民更不经常在这样的选择中犯错。一个真正有才的人给王室当阁臣，几乎就像一个傻子在共和政府里当首相一样稀奇罕见。因此，如果在一个君主制国家中，碰巧有一位天生的明君出世，在一批糟糕到足以使巨轮倾覆的行政官中力挽狂澜、执掌事务之舵，那么每个人都会惊愕于他发展国家的能力，而他的统治也将在国史上开创一个新纪元。

君主制国家要想得到很好的治理，其领土大小和边界范围都应与统治者的才能成比例。征服一个国家比治理一个国家来得容易。一根手指在足够长的杠杆的帮助下可以撬动地球；可如果要一直撑住地球，一个人必须拥有一副大力神赫克里斯的肩膀。无论一个国家有多小，其君主的力量也几乎总是不足以顾及方方面面。而当两者地位颠倒，即国家对其统治者而言竟显得太小时，这个国家的治理肯定只会更差，因为这样一个统治者在高瞻远瞩时忽略了公民的利益；他过度使用自身强大能力给人民带来的不幸，可能比才能平平的统治者给人民带来的不幸还要多。同样，一个王国也需要根据各朝君主的能力来决定要扩张还是收缩。另一方面，共和国在选举元老院成员时已经基本确定了他们的水平，所以国家在面积上就不必再有变动，而行政机构的运转也可以保持顺畅。

一人掌权的政府最显而易见的缺点，就是缺乏继承者之间的连续性，而在另两种体制中却存在着一条持续不断的纽带。当国王驾崩时，新国王必定要继位；在下一个统治者人选得到确定之前，有一段危险的间歇，国家往往要经历一场狂风暴雨。而且，在这样一种体制下，除非全体公民都能保持超乎寻常的公正无私和团结一致，否则贿赂和腐化的现象必将出现。要让一个已经买下国家的人到头来既不把它转手卖掉，也不向弱者收回强者从他那儿勒索走的黄金，基本是不可能的。在这样一种行政机构的管理下，迟早一切都会成为贪污腐败的交易筹码，同时，比起动荡的政权空白期，人们在国王统治的和平时期反而会过得更糟糕。

为了避免这种邪恶的境况，人们都做了什么呢？其中一种做法是指定某些家族来世袭王位，并且设立继承秩序，以避免国王的驾崩引发任何争端——换句话说，为了避免王位争夺和新王继位带来的不利，明智的政体选择接受表面的和平，他们宁可冒着由小孩、怪胎或傻瓜来担任统治者的风险，也不愿意为了选出一位好国王而发生纠纷。他们没有意识到，在将自己置于种这两难境地时，这其实是在为一种非常小的可能性孤注一掷。小但尼斯的父亲因其不光彩的行为而责备他：“我给你树立过这样的榜样吗？”小但尼斯答道：“啊！可您的父亲不是国王啊。”这是一句多么精辟的话语。

当一个人生来就是要被培养成统治者时，他周围的一切都会来争相剥夺他的正义感与理性。我们听说过，年轻的统治者历经磨难是为了更好地掌握治国的艺术，但根据现实情况来看，这种教育对他们似乎并没有什么好处。相反，他们还不如将服从的艺术作为学习的起点。史上已知最伟大的国王，都不是接受了从小到大的教育才成为统治者的，因为统治是一门必须通过大量实践才能基本掌握的学问，而且比起发号施令，懂得顺从往往能帮助统治者更好地领悟其中的精髓。Nam utilissimus idem acbrevissimus bonarum malarumque rerum delectus, cogitare quid aut nolueris sub alio Principe aut volue-ris（因为区分好坏最有效最简便的方法是：如果当君主的不是自己而是别人，那就考虑一下自己想要什么，不想要什么）。[23]

这种缺乏连贯性的后果之一，便是王室政府的不稳定，这种政府时而由这个方针指导，时而由那个方针指导，一切都取决于在位国王或是替他执政的人们的个性。因此，这种政府无法长久地拥有一个固定的目标或连贯的政策，且这种不稳定的状况使得国家的准则和国家的方针也漂移不定。在其他政府形式中，由于统治者始终固定不变，这一缺陷便自然得以避免。因而，我们明白，如果通常在王室宫廷中有更多的狡诈，那么在元老院中就有更多的智慧，而共和国也能遵循更稳定、更有效的引导——这对每次管理层变革都意味着一次国家变革的君主制国家来说是不可能的——毕竟所有大臣和近乎所有国王都无一例外地要颠覆他们先辈的政策。

此外，这种缺乏连贯性还给保皇党政治思想家们常有的一种谬论提供了不实的依据，他们不仅把公民政府和家族政府作比较、把君主和一家之长作比较——我已经反驳过这种谬误——而且把治国的所有美德赋予一位国王，假定他已经是一位最优秀的统治者。若是这种假定成立，那么王室政府显然要比其他政府更优越，因为它无可争议是最强大的政府；要是它也有一个与公意相协调的团体意志的话，它必然也是最佳的政府。

可是，如果根据柏拉图的说法，一个天生的国王十分罕见的话，那天性与好运合二为一、使这样的人登基的可能性又有多大呢？而且，如果王室教育必然会腐化那些受教育者的话，我们又如何指望那些被培养出来的继任者会成为明君呢？

将王室政府与有一个好国王的政府混为一谈，这是故意自欺欺人。要了解政府的这种形式究竟是什么，人们必须把平庸或邪恶君主统治下的政府也考虑在内，因为这些君主若非本身就昏庸无道，那他们就只能是因为王位才变成了这个样子。

的确，我们的作家们都注意到了以上这些困难，但是困难从未使他们处于进退两难的尴尬境地。他们说，毫无怨言地去服从是一剂良药。神愤怒时强行把坏国王给了我们，于是，必须将其作为一次神的惩罚来忍受。这个观点无疑是有启发性的；不过，我想比起政治理论书，它更适和被用来布道。若一个医生许诺奇迹会发生，而他的全部医术就是教病人训练耐性，对这样的医生我们还有什么话可说呢？

我们大家都知道，当一个政府不好时，我们不得不容忍这样一个坏政府；真正的问题是，我们如何去寻找一个好政府。

第七章　论混合政府

严格地说，一种形式简单的政府是生存不下去的。一个国家元首必须有属下的行政官；一个公民政府必须有一个首脑。因而，在行政权力的分配中，总是存在着从较大到较小的等级——其中的差异就在于，有时少数服从多数，有时多数服从少数。

有时，还存在一个平等的划分，要么像英国政府一样，各个组成部分相互依赖，要么像波兰的情况那样，每部分的权力都是独立而不完善的。后者的形式不是很好，因为这样一来，非但政府内部无法团结，整个国家也缺乏联系的纽带。那么哪一种政府更好？是简单形式的政府还是混合形式的政府呢？这是一个政治理论家们争论已久的问题，也是一个我本人在早先探讨政府的所有形式时就给过答案的问题。

就其本身来说，简单形式的政府是最好的，因为它的简单就是优点。但是，当行政权不完全依附于立法权，即当君主与主权者的比率大于公民与君主的比率时，这种不平衡就必须通过划分政府来加以矫正。因为到那时，政府的各个部分依旧对臣民有足够的权威，但零散的结构将使政府不再有力量与主权者相抗衡。

同样的不利还可以通过设立居间的行政官来避免，这些行政官与整个政权分隔开来，只起到平衡这两种权力的作用，并为维护双方的权利而提供服务。那么，这样一种政府就不是混合的，而是调和的。

与此相反的不利也可以用类似的方法加以补救；当政府太涣散时，可设立一些委员会使之集中化。在前一种情况下，划分政府是为了将其削弱；而在目前所说的这种情况下，加强政府才是主要目的。这是所有民主制的惯用做法。简单形式的政府既有可能极端强大，也有可能极端弱小，而混合形式则可以让政府维持一种适中的强度。

第八章　论所有政府形式并非适合所有国家

自由并非每种社会思潮的产物，因此不是每个民族都能获得自由的。人们对孟德斯鸠的这一理论思考得越多，就越会觉得其中蕴含着真理。同时，人们越是想要反驳这个理论，就会为它提供越多新的证据。

在世界上的每个政府中，公众人格都是只消费、不生产的。那么，它从哪儿得到其所消费的物质呢？是从其成员的劳动中得到的。正是私人生产的过剩保证了大众衣食的供给。由此可见，只有当成员的劳动生产所得比其自身所需要的多，公民国家才能生存下去。

可是，这种过剩在世界上的每个国家不尽相同。在一些国家是相当过剩，而在另一些国家是中等过剩；在一些国家是没有过剩，而在另一些国家是亏空。过剩的比例取决于气候的适宜与否、不同土地对应的劳动种类、产品的性质、居民的力量、居民的消费水平以及其余各种各样的因素。

另外，并非所有政府都拥有相同的本性。一些政府比另一些政府更贪婪；它们之间的差异建立在以下的原则基础上——民众贡献的提供者和接受者之间的距离越远，造成的负担就越重。要衡量这种负担，不应看它的具体数量，而应该看它的回报最终落到生产者头上要经过多远的距离；如果这一流程运作得快捷且良好，那不管产出的要求是多是少，都没有关系；人们将一直富有，财政也将昌盛。相应地，就算人们给出得再少，若是一点回报都不返还给他们，那他们很快就会在不断的付出中将自己消耗殆尽；于是国家就永远富裕不起来，公民就永远赤贫。

这表明，公民与政府之间的距离越大，负税就变得越重，因此，人们的税金负担在民主社会最少，在贵族社会较多，而在君主国家则是三者中最多的。所以，君主制适宜于富国，贵族制适宜于那些富裕程度与领土大小适中的国家，而民主制则适宜于贫穷小国。

的确，人们思考得越多，对自由国与君主国之间存在差异的这个问题就认识得越深；在前者中，一切都为共同的利益所用；而在后者中，私人利益与公众利益则相互竞争，即一个要只能通过削弱另一个而增加。至于专制统治，它的目的从来不是使人民幸福，而是尽可能使他们过得悲惨，从而无力进行抗争。

于是，根据每个地区特有的自然因素，人们可以决定该地区所需要的政府形式；我们甚至还可以说出每个政府必须拥有什么样的居民。

有些地方一片荒芜，产出的物品抵偿不了所付出的劳动，所以人们不应该耕作，而应该放任不管，或者只让未开化的野人来居住。有些地方的生产所得只能勉强维持人们的生活，所以应该让缺乏教养的民族定居，因为政治社会不可能在那儿发展起来。有些地方条件尚可，适度的劳动就能换来过剩的产品，所以应该让崇尚自由的民族居住。有些地方环境优越，少量的劳动就能带来丰厚回报，所以应该实行君主制，以便君主的奢侈生活可以消费掉臣民过剩的产品——因为由政府来吸收这些多余产品总好过它们被私人用来浪费。我知道有例外的情况，不过这些例外本身就证实了这一规则，即它们迟早都会产生种种变革，使得事物回到自然的秩序。

我们应当始终把一般法则与无法预测其结果的特殊原因区别开来。纵然整个南方由共和党人居住，而整个北方由专制国家占据，我们也依然可以说一个法则是正确的，即根据气候条件，专制适宜于气候炎热的国家，野蛮适宜于气候寒冷的国家，优良的制度适宜于气候温和的地区。我意识到，人们虽然肯定这个一般法则，但它的应用却可能遭到质疑；有人会说，气候十分寒冷的国家也有非常肥沃的土地，而气候十分炎热的国家也有非常贫瘠的土地。不过，只有那些不从全面的比率看情况的人才会对这一问题无从下手。正如我曾说过的那样，人们必须考虑到生产、力量、消费等因素，然后问题便会迎刃而解。

假设有两块大小相同的土地，一块生产五份产品，另一块生产十份产品。如果前者的居民消费掉四份，后者的居民消费掉九份的话，一个过剩五分之一，另一个过剩十分之一。这两种过剩的比率与其产量的比率是相反的，其结果是，生产五份产品的土地所显示的过剩是生产十份产品土地的两倍。

但是，这个两倍指的仅仅是过剩比例，而不是产品数量。我相信，任何人都不敢把寒冷国家的生产能力等同于炎热国家的生产能力。不过，让我们暂且假设这是相等的吧：例如，让我们两两比较一下英国和西西里岛、波兰和埃及。再往南有非洲和印度；再往北就什么都没有了。为了达到产品的同等，不同国家在农业技术方面需要作出怎样的改变呢？在西西里岛，简单地耙一耙土壤就足够了，而在英国，要解决问题则需要付出多么大的努力啊！这就说明，需要更多人手才能获得一样多产品的地方，过剩必然更少。

除此之外，在炎热的国家，同样数量的人会消费更少的东西。炎热的气候要求人们变得饮食有度以保持健康——那些试图在炎热国家保持原有生活习惯的欧洲人都死于痢疾和胃病。沙尔丹说：“与亚洲人相比，我们是食肉动物，是狼。一些人把波斯人的饮食有度归因于他们国家耕种的土地较少；可相反，我认为，他们国家之所以在食品方面不够丰富，是因为居民需求量较少。如果他们的节俭[他继续]是由土地不足导致的，那么应该只有穷人才吃得很少；但实际上，他们每个人都是这样；人们发现，王国上上下下所有人都一样节俭，并没有哪个省份的人根据土地的肥沃程度吃得更多或更少。他们对自己的生活方式颇感自豪，并且说：人们只须看他们的气色就会明白，他们的生活方式比其他国家的优越得多。的确，波斯人的面色都干干净净，他们的皮肤精致、细嫩又光滑，而依附于他们的亚美尼亚人，生活习惯和欧洲人一样，他们的皮肤就粗糙而易于长斑，身体也肥胖笨拙。”

人们离赤道越近，生活就越节俭。他们几乎不吃肉；大米、玉米、蒸粗麦粉、小米和木薯是他们的日常食品。在印度，有好几百万人一天的饮食费用都不到一便士。而在欧洲本土，我们注意到，北欧人的胃口和南欧人的明显不同。德国人的一顿晚饭，可以让一个西班牙人吃上八天。在人们胃口比较大的国家，消费也更加奢侈。在英国，奢侈表现为在餐桌上堆满各种肉食；而在意大利，人们只要有糖和鲜花就心满意足了。

服装的奢侈显示出同样的差异。在季节变化又快又明显的国家，人们拥有更为简单而优质的衣服；在人们穿衣只考虑外表的国家，人们更注重衣服的款式而非实用性，且衣服本身也成了一种奢侈品。在那不勒斯，你天天都会看到人们身穿绣金外套而不穿长统袜沿着普斯里普漫步。那儿的建筑也是同样的风格；当人们不必担心气候问题时，他们就会注重建筑的宏伟壮丽。在巴黎或在伦敦，人们首先想居住得温暖舒适。在马德里，人们拥有华丽的会客室，但房子的整体质量却不怎么样，窗户都是关不上的，而卧室也像是耗子洞一般。

在炎热的国家，食物更加充足、种类丰富——这是第三种差异，它对第二种差异不能不产生影响。在意大利，人们为何吃很多的蔬菜呢？因为人们认为蔬菜好，有营养，且味道极其可口。而在法国，人们觉得蔬菜除了含水份外，根本就没有营养，在餐桌上算不了什么东西；即便如此，在蔬菜种植方面，法国人开垦的土地、耗费的其实并不比意大利人少。试验表明，巴巴利的小麦能产出更多面粉，因此优于法国的小麦；而法国的小麦又比北欧的小麦产量高。由此可以得出这样的结论：从赤道到地球极点，其间的各个地区都可以观察到类似的差异。产出同等数量的农产品，得到的食物却更少，这岂不是一个实实在在的劣势吗？

我可能得在所有这些思考中补上另一点。这一点源自这些思考，并且对它们也有所加强：炎热的国家比寒冷的国家需要更少的居民，但其物资却可以养活更多人——这就产生了有利于专制的双倍剩余。同样的人口，分布在越广阔的地区，叛乱就越困难，因为他们无法迅速秘密地集中起来，而政府总能轻而易举地看出这种企图，并且切断他们的交通。另一方面，越多人挤在一块，政府就越不容易侵占主权；民众首领在私人房间里商讨事务，就像政务院里的君主一样安全，而公共广场上的人群集结速度之快，堪比兵营里的部队。因而，广袤的领土有利于专制政府运筹于千里之外。在作为支点的防守战略据点的援助下，根据杠杆作用的原则，其势力因距离而增加。[24]

恰恰相反，公民的力量只有当集中起来时才是有效的；当公民的力量分散时，它就大幅衰减，正如撒在地上的火药只能一粒一粒地点燃。因而，人口少的国家最适合暴政，就像野生动物只有在沙漠里才可称王。

第九章　论好政府的标志

因此，如果有谁提问，在绝对条件下什么是最好的政府，人们便无法给出答案，因为这个问题是不确定的；或者，我们也可以说，一个民族的绝对地位与相对地位有多少种可能存在的组合，这个问题的好答案就有多少个。

可是，如果问的是人们根据什么标志才能判断一个特定民族在治理方面的好坏，那就是另一码事了；作为一个实际的问题，这是可以回答的。

即便如此，人们还没有给出过确切的答案，因为每个人都会以自己的方式来回答这个问题。臣民珍视公共的安宁；公民珍视个体的自由——前者更喜欢财产安全，而后者则更喜欢人身安全；臣民认为最好的政府最苛刻，而公民则认为最好的政府最温和；前者要惩罚犯罪，而后者则要避免犯罪；臣民认为让邻国惧怕是一件好事，而公民则宁愿被邻国忽视；只要货币流通，前者就满足，而后者则要求人们必须有面包吃。那么，纵使各方能在诸如此类的问题上达成一致，我们就能更进一步地探讨吗？道德的尺度没有精确的衡量标准；即使我们认同了这些标志，我们又该如何认同其价值呢？

对我自己来说，我总感到惊讶的是，人们竟识别不出一个如此简单的标志，或者竟如此不诚实地否认这个标志。什么是一切政治团体的目标呢？这个目标就是保护其成员，让他们繁荣起来。什么又是他们被保护和得到繁荣的标志呢？是人口的数量。那么，就别再舍近求远，去找别的未经论证的证据了。由于所有其他条件都是平等的，所以要是没有像移民这样的外援，使公民人数增加最多的政府，必然是最好的政府。而使公民减少、民族衰亡的政府就是最差的政府。统计学家们，这可是你们的工作了：请你们算一算、测一测、比一比吧。[25]

第十章　论政府的滥用职权及其衰退的趋势

就像特殊意志不断反对公意一样，政府也不断极力反对主权。这种努力越加大，体制向坏处转变得就越多。由于在这种情况下，没有明显的团体意志能够与君主意志相抗衡并达到一种平衡状态，所以君主意志迟早将不可避免地压制主权，破坏社会公约。这是政府固有的、无法回避的缺陷，这一缺陷从政体诞生之日起就无情地使其趋于毁灭，就像老年与死亡必然摧毁一个人的身体一样。

政府的衰退通常有两种方式——其本身的萎缩和国家的解体。

当政府成员人数从较多变为较少，即民主制转向贵族制，或贵族制转向王室政府时，政府就萎缩。这是政府发展的自然趋势。[26]如果成员人数从较少变为较多，政府可以说是松散了；但是，这样一种逆向发展是不可能的。

事实上，政府从来不会改变其形式，除非它消耗了太多能量以至于无法保持原有的状态。假如政府要一边扩大，一边使自身变得松散，它就必然会失去所有力量，更有可能直接消亡。因此，当政府开始松散时，一定要收拢并紧缩结构，因为不这样的话，依赖于政府的国家将陷于毁灭的境地。

国家的解体可能以两种方式发生。

第一，当君主不再依法治国而是侵占主权时，国家便解体。接着一个显著的变化就发生了，由于不是政府在收缩，而是国家在收缩——我的意思是，国家作为一个整体解体，并在其内部形成一个仅由原政府成员组成的国家，对其余人民来说，这个新国家只能是主人，是暴君。其结果是，新政府一旦侵占主权，社会公约便遭到破坏。于是依照权利恢复其自然自由的所有普通公民，便被强迫——并不是由道德驱使地——顺从新政府。

当作为个体的政府成员分别侵占了只能由集体来行使的权力时，同样的情形也会发生，因为这同样违反了法律，而且还会产生更大的混乱。到那时候，可以说每位行政官都成了君主，而国家和政府一样处于四分五裂的状态，不是灭亡就是改变形式。

当国家解体时，政府滥用权力，不论是以什么样的形式，这种情况都可以称为无政府状态。更准确地说，民主政治退化为暴民政治，贵族政治退化为寡头政治，而且我还得补充说，王室政治退化为暴君政治，但最后这个词含糊不清，需要加以解释。

在通常理解的意思中，暴君就是凭借暴力而非正义和法律来治理国家的国王。但更严谨地说，暴君应该是指一个没有任何王室权利却将王室权力据为己有的人。这就是希腊人对“暴君”一词的理解。不管是一位好君主还是坏君主，只要他权力的来源是不合法的，希腊人就会说他是暴君。[27]因而，暴君和篡权者的意思是相同的。为了进行区别，我称王室权力篡夺者为“暴君”，称主权权力篡夺者为“专制君主”。暴君是一个违法干政却依法治国的人；而专制君主则是一个让自己凌驾于法律之上的人。所以，暴君不必是专制君主，而专制君主则永远是暴君。

第十一章　论政体的灭亡

制度健全的政府不可避免的趋势自然就是如此。既然斯巴达和古罗马都灭亡了，还有什么国家能期望永世长存呢？如果我们希望建立起一种持久的体制，那就别幻想让它永恒不朽。只有当我们既不去进行徒劳的尝试，也不因自己能够为人类之事业付出超人的耐力而沾沾自喜时，我们才会成功。

政体跟人的身体一样，一出生就开始走向死亡，其内部有着导致自身毁灭的种种原因。但是，这两种体质都有可能拥有一个特定强健程度的构成，而这种构成最为适合维持其或长或短的生命。一个人的身体组织是自然的产物，而国家的组织则是人为的产物；人对延长自身的寿命无能为力，但尽量给予国家可能拥有的最好组织来延长其生命，却是我们可以做到的事。最好的体制虽然也会走到尽头，但总归是比其他形式的体制终结得更晚，除非一些预料不到的危险在那之前降临。

政治生命的原则在于主权的权威。立法权是国家的心脏，而行政权是控制所有活动器官的头脑。头脑瘫痪了，个体会陷入痴呆状态，但仍然有可能活下去，可心脏一旦不起作用，人就会死亡。

国家能维持生存并不是借助法律，而是借助立法权。昨天的法律并不约束今天的行动，然而我们可以把沉默当作默许，将主权者有权废除但没有废除的法律视为可以继续生效的。主权者宣布过的一切意志——至少在主权者发布一道废除令之前，它们永远会是主权者的意志。

那么，为什么古代法律会博得那么多人的青睐呢？准确地说，就是因为它们的古老。我们应当相信，正是这种法律的卓越才使它们可以持续那么长时间；如果主权者不是一直都认为它们是有益的，它们肯定已经被废除过成百上千次了。这就是每个体制健全之国家的法律不但不会被削弱、反而不断获得新生力量的原因之所在；人们对古老之物有一种偏爱，因此它们会越来越受到尊敬；另一方面，若是法律随着时代的变化愈加软弱，那便说明这个国家已经不再有立法权，而且必将走向灭亡。

第十二章　论主权者权威如何维护

主权者只能借助法律而行动，因为他除了立法权以外没有任何其他权力。而既然法律就是公意的正当表达，那么主权者行动时还必须将公民聚集到一起。把公民召集起来，可以说——简直就是幻想！在今天，这确实是一个幻想；可在两千年前其实不然。难道是人性发生了如此大的变化吗？

道德领域可能存在的界线并不像我们想象中一样狭隘；正是我们的弱点、恶习及其偏见才限制了它们的拓展。卑鄙的头脑不会去相信伟人；低贱的奴隶则嘲笑“自由”这个词。

根据我们过去的所作所为，让我们来考虑一下现在有什么是可以做的。古希腊共和国我就不谈了；不过在我看来，古罗马共和国是一个伟大的国家，罗马城也是一个伟大的城市。最后一次人口普查给出的数据是，古罗马有四十万武装人员，而整个帝国不算臣民、外国人、妇女、儿童和奴隶，总共有四百多万公民。

人们总是认为，把首都及其周边大量的人经常集中起来必然是一件难事。然而，古罗马人基本每周都有集会，甚至一周还可以集中好几次。他们不但行使主权，而且还行使一部分政权，比如处理某些事务、审理某些案件等。在集会中，全体人民都扮演行政官的角色，而且他们使用这一身份的时间和使用公民身份的时间是一样长的。

回顾各国最早的历史，我们注意到，大多数古代政府，甚至像马其顿和法兰克那样的君主政府，都有过类似的民众集会。不管怎样，一个不可争议的事实已经回答了我们的问题；在我看来，从实际情况推论可能存在的情况，是很符合逻辑的。

第十三章　论主权者权威如何维护（续）

集会的人们一旦认可一套法律，就等于是确定了国家的体制，但这是不够的；他们创建了一个永久性的政府，或者为行政官的选举制定了一劳永逸的方法，但还是不够。除预料不到的事情可能需要的特别集会之外，还必须有固定的、周期性的、任何事都不可取消或中止的集会，使人们在指定日期依法正当地被召集在一起，而无需任何其他正式的召集手续。

但是，除这些按期举行的合法集会外，任何——只要不是由职责在身的行政官按规定形式召集的——公民集会，都应该被视作不合法的，而且其所做的一切决定都应该是无效的，因为召集集会的命令本身必须合法下达。

至于合法的集会应该以怎样的频率举行，这取决于无法预先规定准确规则的许多情况。我们只能说，通常政府拥有的权力越大，主权者就越应该经常举行集会。

有人会告诉我，这种集会可能对单个城市来说是有好处的，可如果国家有若干个城市，那又得怎么办呢？主权者的权力要进行分割吗？或者主权者应该集中在某一个城市，并使所有其他城市成为其附属吗？我的回答是，这样那样的事都不该做。首先，主权者权力只是一个单一的单位，分割就意味着将它摧毁。其次，一个城市同一个国家一样，不能合法地屈从于另一个城市，因为政体的本质在于自由与服从的结合，这样，“臣民”与“主权者”才是同义且相关的两个词，而它们的意思也就共同构成了“公民”。

我应当更进一步回答，要把一个国家中的若干个城市联合起来，这始终不是件好事。不论谁希望形成这样的联盟，都不能自以为能避免种种天然的负面影响。向那些只想要小国的人抱怨大国带来的祸害，是没有用的。可是，怎样给予小国足够的力量以抵抗大国，就像希腊城邦抵抗过波斯王，以及前不久荷兰和瑞士抵抗过奥地利王朝一样？

无论如何，假如国家无法被限定在合理的边境内，那么就只剩一种办法，即不设立固定的首都，而将政府所在地不断从一个地方迁移到另一个地方，在各个城市轮流举行全国会议。

让人口均匀地分布在国土上，赋予每个人相同的权利，并且使每个地区同样富足、生机勃勃——只有这样，才会产生一个在力量和治理方面都尽善尽美的国家。请记住：城墙造得越雄伟，乡村的房屋就越破败。每当我在首都看到一幢在建的大楼，我心里都会想，我能看到整个农村遍地布满简陋的茅舍。

第十四章　论主权者权威如何维护（再续）

当人民作为主权者团体合法集会之时，政府的所有管辖权就不再起作用，其行政权也就中断。于是最卑贱的公民跟最高贵的行政官具有同样神圣不可侵犯的人格，因为既然被代表人全部在场，就再也不需要什么代表人了。古罗马各种集会上的骚乱，大多数都是因为人们不知道、不重视这条法则才发生的。在集会中，执政官只不过是人民的首领，保民官仅仅是人民的议长[28]，而元老院就什么都不是了。

在这种权力中断的间歇，君主将认识到——或者应该认识到——一个比他地位更高的存在，而这总是会使他警觉起来；人民的集会是政体的盾牌和政府的制动器，并且一直是首领的梦魇；所以，身居高位的人不余遗力地提出异议、问题、许诺，希望使公民转而反抗集会。如果公民贪图钱财、胆怯懦弱、热爱休息胜过热爱自由，他们就很容易在政府的这种长期攻势下服软。由于反对派势力不断增加，最终主权者的权威一落千丈而不复存在，于是大多数共和国纷纷崩溃，提前灭亡。

但是，在主权权威与专断政府之间，有时会插入一种我们现在必须论及的中间力量。

第十五章　论议员或代表

当公共服务不再是公民关注的主要对象，并且他们逐渐更乐于以资金而非人力来提供服务时，国家就已接近毁灭。军队需要参战吗？他们可以给雇佣兵报酬，而自己呆在家里。人们需要参加集会吗？他们可以给议员报酬，而自己呆在家里。由于懒惰和金钱，这个国家最终将被士兵奴役、被官员出卖。

正是由于商业和手工业的兴旺，正是由于唯利是图、柔弱娇气、贪图安逸，原本由人提供的服务才转变为金钱交易。人们放弃一部分利益以增加舒适的休闲时间。就这样利用金钱吧！你很快就会为金钱所束缚。“钱财”这个词是奴隶的话语，土生土长的共和国公民都不会知道它。在一个真正的自由国家，公民们用自己的双手做每样事情，而用钱是办不了任何事的；他们非但不会花钱免除职责，反而会为了亲自履行义务而付出金钱。我完全不同意目前大众普遍接受的观念，反之，我认为，税收比义务服务更违背自由。

国家创建得越好，公务便越优先于公民心目中的私事。而且私事的数量会大大减少，因为整个公众幸福就代表大部分的个人幸福，于是，个体便没有太多需要追求的幸福了。在一个管理完善的国家，每个人都会赶去参加各种集会；而在一个管理不善的国家，没人愿意参加集会，而且连这样的念头都不会有，因为他们对大会上发生的事一点也不感兴趣。毕竟，正如他们所料，公意在那里并不占优势。归根结底，人们的注意力已经全都放在了家庭事务上，所以无暇参与集会。好法律使人制定出更好的法律；而坏法律则使人制定出更坏的法律。要是有人一谈到国事，就说：“这关我什么事？”到那时一个国家就算完了。

爱国心的冷却、私人利益的活动、国家的庞大、征服他人、滥用政权——所有这些都导致我们不得不在国家的各种集会中任命人民议员或人民代表作为权宜之计。他们被某些国家的人们公然称为第三阶层——把两个阶级的私有利益摆在前两位，而公共利益只占第三位。

主权不能被代表，就像主权不能被转让一样；主权的本质是公意，而意志是不能由他人代表的——它要么是自己，要么就是另外一种东西，不存在中间的可能性。因而，人民议员不是也不可能是人民代表；他们只不过是办事员而已；他们无法最终决定任何事。人民未亲自认可的一切法律都是无效的，根本就不算什么法律。英国人认为自己是自由的；他们是大错特错了；他们只在选举议会议员的时候是自由的；议员一选出来，人民就遭受奴役，变得什么也不是了。在那短暂的自由时刻，英国人是如此充分地使用了自己的自由，所以他们之后失去自由也就不那么可惜了。

代表是一个近代的观念。它从封建政权——人类就是被这种邪恶荒唐的体制玷污了名声、剥夺了尊严的——中诞生，一直发展到今天。在共和国中，甚至在古代的君主制中，人民从来就没有什么代表，也没听说过代表这个词。值得注意的是，在古罗马，保民官的职责是如此神圣，以至于人们从未想过他们会不会篡夺人民的权力；同时，尽管有那么多的公民，但任何一次公民投票都没有出现过有人试图转让自己权力的情况。要知道，在格拉古时代，许多公民甚至得站在屋顶上投票，造成十分尴尬的局面。

在权利和自由就是一切的地方，没有人会怕麻烦。这些明智的人们会对每样东西给予公正的衡量；保民官不敢做的事，就让执法吏去做，而人们无需担心这些执法吏会企图越俎代庖。

即便如此，要解释保民官究竟如何代表人民，想一想政府是如何代表主权者就足够了。既然法律除了是公意的宣言之外什么都不是，那么显然在立法权上就不可能有人民的代表；不过，行政权，可能并且应该有这样的代表，因为行政权仅仅是行使法律的工具。由此得知，我们只要仔细观察，就会发现几乎没有什么国家拥有法律。无论如何，有一点是确凿无疑的，即没有任何行政权的保民官，决不可能以自己的职权来代表罗马人民，除非他篡夺了元老院的权力。

在希腊人当中，人民要做的一切都由他们自己来做；市场中经常举办集会。希腊人生活在温和的气候中；他们不具备贪婪的个性。奴隶负责干活，而希腊人整天要考虑的是他们的自由。如今，没了这些有利条件，同样的权利又怎么能维持呢？严酷的气候使得你们产生更多的需求；[29]公共场所一年中有六个月都无法举办集会；你们那发不出声音的舌头在露天说话都难以让人听清；比起你们的自由，你们更在乎自己的利益；你们觉得当奴隶也不比当穷人更可怕。

什么？自由只有依靠奴隶制才能维持吗？或许吧。自由与奴隶制两个极端碰到了一起。任何诞生于自然之外的事物都有其不利之处，而文明社会是所有这些事物中最为不利的。确实有一些如此不幸的情形，以致于人们只能牺牲别人的自由来维护自己的自由；而且只有当奴隶完全是奴隶时，公民才能完全自由。斯巴达的情况就是如此。至于你们这些现代人，你们没有奴隶，可你们自身就是奴隶；你们用自己的自由为奴隶的自由买单。你们认为这是一桩善事，并自吹自擂，但在我看来这只是徒劳；我从中看到的更多是懦弱，而不是仁慈。

我所说的这些并非想暗示奴隶的存在是必要的，或奴隶制的存在是合法的，因为我所证明过的与之恰恰相反。我只是想说明，自认为自由的现代人为何还要有代表、以及古代人为何不曾有代表的种种理由。无论如何，一个民族一旦接受了代表，它就不再自由，也不再存在了。

纵观一切之后，我认为主权者已经无法继续在我们之间行使自己的权利，除非我们是在一个非常小的共和国。可是，如果非常小，它会不会被别国征服呢？我的答案是，不会的。大民族的防御力量怎样才能与小国的自由政权及其良好的秩序结合在一起，我将在后面的文章中[30]对此加以说明。

第十六章　论政府的建制并不是一种契约

确立了立法权之后，就应该以同样的方式确立行政权，因为只由特殊行为操作的行政权与立法权迥然不同，且自然分离。设想，如果主权者拥有了行政权，那么法律与事实将被混淆，以致于人们再也不知道什么是法律、什么不是法律；由此，这种误入歧途的政体很快就会成为暴力的牺牲品，尽管政体设立的初衷就是要避免暴力。

所有公民按照社会契约一律平等，于是集体中的个体便集体的行动有决定权。原本，一个人是无权要求另一个人必须替自己做事的，但在这种情况下这一点却能成立。主权者在创建政府时赋予君主的，正是这种对政体生命和活动不可或缺的权利。

一些理论家主张，创建政府这种行为是人民与其自身指派的行政官之间的一项契约，即一项双方之间规定一方施令而另一方服从的契约。我确信，应当承认的是，这是一种奇特的契约方式。但是，让我们看一看这种理论是否站得住脚吧。

第一，最高权威不可转让，同样也是不可更改的；限制最高权威就等于破坏最高权威。让主权者设立一个比自身更高的存在，这是荒唐可笑、自相矛盾的，就好比一边使自己服从一个主人的命令，一边又要求回归到绝对的自由状态。

第二，我们很清楚，人们与这样那样的人签订契约总是一种特别行为。由此可见，这种契约既不可能是法律，也不可能是一种主权行为，所以它就是不合法的。

进一步讲，契约签订的各方只服从于自然法则，于是就不存在什么他们相互约束的保证——这与公民国家完全是对立的。既然大权在握的人最终总是做决定的那一方，这就像是在说，“契约”的意思是一个人告诉另一个人：“我把所有的财产给你，你可以随意决定要还给我多少。”

国家只有一种契约：联合体本身的契约，且它把所有其他契约排除在外。要想出一个不违背原始契约的公共契约，是绝无可能的。

第十七章　论政府的建制

那么，我们应该以什么概念来看待建立政府这一行为呢？我得先解释一下，这种行为是复杂的，或者说是由其他两种行为构成的，即法律的制定与法律的执行。

第一种行为使主权者规定，一个政府主体要以这样那样的形式建立起来；显然，这种行为就是一项法律。

第二种行为使人民任命行政官来管理已经建立好的政府。由于人民的任命是一种特殊行为，它就不是第二项法律，而只是第一项法律的后果，是政府的一种职能。

令人费解的是，在政府存在之前怎么就有了政府的行为，还有，仅仅是主权者或臣民的公民在某些情况下怎么会成为君主或行政官。

于是，正是在此处，我们得以再一次发现政体中的一个令人惊讶的特性，按照这一特性，政体调和了似乎相互矛盾的行动。由于这种调和是通过主权到民主制的突然转变来完成的，所以政体没有发生显而易见的变化。仅仅是出于一种整体与整体的新型关系，公民就变成了行政官，而且实现了从普遍行为到特殊行为、从法令到执行的过渡。

这种关系的变化并非是纸上谈兵的投机性理论；相反，我们每天都可以在英国议会找到这样的实例。在某些场合中，议会下院往往担任代表上、下议院的委员会，以便更好地商讨事务，这样，下院就一瞬间从主权之所在转变成了一个单纯的委员会，尽管它实际上依旧是原来的那个下院。于是，就出现了这样的情形：身为委员会的下院自己对自己作报告，声明自己刚刚成为了上下两院的委员会，并且以一个新名义再次讨论它之前已经以旧名义所决定的事项。

正是由于这种民主政府特有的优势，它的建立只需要公意的一个简单行为。在此之后，如果这个临时政府的形式刚好是人们所需要的，那么它就会被沿用下去；如果不是，那么就以主权者的名义重新确立一个遵循法律的政府。这样一来，一切就都符合规定了。这也是唯一一种方式，能既不违背之前所说的原则，又以合法的方式创建政府。

第十八章　论预防篡夺政府权力的手段

综上所述，就可以得出符合第十六章内容的结论，即创建政府的行为不是一种契约，而是一项法律；行政权的持有者并不是人民的主人，而是人民的办事员；人民可以随心所欲地任命和开除他们；而对办事员来说，这不是要他们签订契约，是要他们服从；在履行国家赋予他们的职务时，他们只是在行应尽的义务，并没有谈条件的权利。

因而，当人民创建一个世袭政府时，无论它是家族世袭的君主制，还是特定公民阶层世袭的贵族制，那都不是真正的政府形式，而只是人民在出于自己的意愿另作安排之前给予管理机构的一个临时形式。

确实，如果真的要改变政府形式，那总是很危险的，人们决不应该去碰一个已经建立好的政府，除非它变得与公共利益水火不容；不过，如此的慎重只是政治的箴言，而不是法律的规则；同样，就像国家没有必要把军事权交给将军一样，它也没必要把公民权交给行政官。

还有一点是千真万确的。在此类情况下，为了正确区分合法的行为与煽动性的骚乱、区别全体人民的意志与派系的要求，人们再怎么小心谨慎地仔细观察也不为过。其中，人们尤其必须避免屈从于社会上有害的主张，除非是在法律的容许范围内。同时，正是在这一义务的履行中，君主才得了大好的机会，掌握了与人民相抗衡的力量，而且人民还不能说他是篡夺了权力。因为对君主来说，当他看起来似乎只是在行使其权利时，其实就能轻而易举地扩大那些权利，并以公众安宁为托辞阻止为重建良好政府而策划的种种集会。通过这样一种方式，君主使人民难以打破一种沉默，或不得不承认一种特殊事态，这正是他的目的，因为接下来他便可以假定那些因害怕而一言不发的人都是他的支持者，并惩罚那些胆敢发言的人。古罗马的十人会议就是如此。最初他们当选时，规定的任期是一年。第二年，他们连任了。到了第三年，他们终于不再允许公民集会，以期用这种方式永久地保留其权利。世界上所有的政府，一旦有了公共力量作武装，迟早会通过这种简单的手段篡夺主权权威。

我已说到的那些周期性集会——尤其是那些不需要通过正式手续召集的集会——都是避免或延缓这种恶行的正确方法，因为君主若是阻止集会，就等于宣布自己是法律的违犯者和国家的敌人。

这些只以维护社会公约为目的的集会，应该以两个决不可取消且必须单独表决的提议为开场。

第一个提议：“主权者期望保持现有的政府形式吗？”

第二个提议：“人民期望那些目前负责管理机构的人继续当政吗？”

我相信我已经论证了一些东西，所以我在这里就以它们作为假设的前提：国家不存在任何不可废除的基本法，甚至也不存在不可废除的社会公约，因为如果所有公民聚集起来，一致决定终止这条公约，我们就必须认为它是被非常合法地终止的。格老秀斯确实也认为，每个公民都可以放弃其公民资格、从一个国家离开，并即刻恢复其自然的自由及本来拥有的财物。[31]这样看来，如果所有联合起来的公民甚至都不能做他们中的每个人单独能做的事，那肯定是荒谬可笑的。

第四卷

第一章　论公意是不可摧毁的

只要聚集在一起的几个人认为他们自己是一个整体，他们的意志就合而为一，为他们的共同生存和普遍幸福做考虑。这时，国家所有充满活力的力量都变得朝气蓬勃、单纯朴素；其原则也都变得清清楚楚；它的内部不存在不可兼容或相互冲突的利益；而且对所有具备常识的人来说，共同利益是如此显而易见。和平、团结和平等是政治之算计的敌人。正直朴素的人正因为他们的质朴而不会轻易受骗；花言巧语会使傻瓜上当，却打动不了他们，因为他们甚至比傻瓜还要不敏锐。当我们看到一群世上最幸福的人，看到一群农民在橡树下规划国家事务、作出明智决定时，难道不会情不自禁地瞧不起那些处心积虑使自身变得显赫、然而时常失算的精明国家吗？

治理有道的国家只需要少量的法律条文。如果某一天它需要颁布新法律，那么这种需要肯定已经被每个人意识到了。第一个提出颁布新法的人，只不过是说出每个人已经感觉到的东西；把人人都已经决意要做的事情变成法律，这既不是阴谋也不是雄辩问题，只要这个人能确定别人的想法都同他一样就可以了。

使理论家们误入岐途的是，由于他们只看到一开始就创建得很坏的国家，所以便认定这样的政体不可能长久。他们嘲笑大众都是愚钝之人，因为仅仅一个聪明的流氓或狡猾的雄辩家就能唆使巴黎人或伦敦人干出蠢事。但他们没有意识到，自己远远低估了人民的力量。克伦威尔差点被伯尔尼人关进监狱，波弗特公爵曾被日内瓦人监禁起来。

但是，当社会的纽带开始松懈，而国家变得衰弱时，当特殊利益初现苗头、部分社会开始对总体社会施加影响时，共同利益就从内部变得腐败，并与其原本目标背道而驰；这时，投票不再是一致通过；公意不再是大家的意志；矛盾与争端出现；甚至最好的意见也会遭受许多阻挠、难以实行。

最后，处在覆灭边缘的国家只能以空洞虚幻的方式维护自身，人们心中的社会契约不复存在，而最自私的利益则洋洋得意地为自己套上公共利益的神圣名称。到那时，公意便沉默了：在隐秘动机的促使下，每个人作为公民再也不发表言论了，仿佛这个国家从未存在过；更有甚者，表面奉行法律，实则推出以私利为唯一目的的不公正政令。

那么，照这样发展下去，公意将消亡或腐化吗？不，公意总是不变的、坚定的、纯粹的，只不过有些时候它会屈服于压倒它的其他意志。每个要将私利从公共利益中分离出来的人都清楚地明白，他无法将两种利益彻底分开，但是，与他试图独占的那份个人利益相比，他需要承担的公共利益的损失就不算什么了。如果不涉及个人私利，那么他还是会像任何其他人一样迫切追求公共利益的。甚至在为了金钱而出卖其选票的时候，他也不是消灭了自身内在的公意，而是一时回避了它。他所犯的错误，在于改变了提问方式，而且还答非所问。所以，他的投票不是在表示：“这样做对国家是有益的。”而是在说：“若采纳这样那样的提议，某个特定的人或党派会从中受益。”由于这种原因，公众集会规则的制定目标便不仅是要支持公意，而更是要确保公意总是能被质疑，并总是能给出答复。

在此，我对任何人无法从公民身上剥夺掉的、每个主权行动中最简单的投票权有很多想谈的。另外还有关于发言权、建议权、分议权和讨论权的问题——政府向来小心确保只有本国成员拥有这些权利。然而，这些重要的主题需要单独论述，我无法将其一一收录于本书中。

第二章　论投票权

显然，根据上一章所说，管理公共事务的方式足以表明一个政体的道德品质和健康状况。在公众集会中，人们越是能协调一致，换句话说，公众意见越接近统一，公意就越占统治地位；反之，长期的争论、分歧和骚乱象征特殊利益的增加和国家的衰弱。

当国家体制包含有两种或若干种等级时，这一结论便不那么明显。比如，古罗马有贵族也有平民，而这些人的争论甚至在共和国的鼎盛时期也常常扰乱公民大会。可是，这并不能算是真正的例外情况，因为在古罗马，由于政体与生倶来的缺陷，国家相当于是分裂成了两个。上述结论不适用于整体国家，但对这两个部分来说却是准确的。事实上，即使在最动荡的年代，只要元老院不对他们加以干涉，公民们总是能将投票流程很平静地走完，并遵守少数服从多数原则。公民的利益只有一种；公民意志也只有一个。

但是，在循环的另一极端，即沦落到奴隶状态的公民再也没有自由或意志的时候，全体一致便会再次出现。这时，人们出于恐惧或讨好，对所有投票都只会表示赞成；公民已经不是在商讨问题，而是在表达崇拜或者暗自诅咒。在罗马皇帝的统治下，元老院就用这种可耻的方式对人民施加自己的意志的，而且有时候它会以一种荒诞的谨慎来做这件事。塔西佗讲过：在奥索的统治时期，元老们对维特里乌斯非常憎恨，但在咒骂他的时候却又小心留意，将自己的话语混入众人的吵闹中。这样，万一维特里乌斯有朝一日成为主人，他也无法辨别出他们每个人都说过些什么。

基于以上这些各种各样的考量，人们应该制定计票和比较不同意见的规则。这不但取决于公意被认知的难易程度，还取决于国家的盛衰程度。

世界上只有一种法律因其天性需要人们的一致赞成。那就是社会公约：因为公民联合是世界上最自愿的行为；每个人都是生来自由的，并且都是自己的主人，若未经其同意，任何人都不得以任何借口使其屈从。断言奴隶的儿子天生是奴隶，这等于断言他天生就不是人。

然而，即使在社会公约制定时出现了反对意见，契约也并不会作废；它只不过是把反对派排除在外了；由此，反对派在公民当中成了外人。而在国家创建之后，居留便代表同意，人们居住在哪块领土上就要服从哪个主权。[32]

除了这种原始契约之外，投票中的多数派始终可以约束其余的人；这是契约本身产生的结果。然而，人们可能要问，一个人怎样才能获得自由，而不用被迫遵从他人的意志呢？投票中的少数派怎样才能做到既自由又服从于他们所不赞成的法律呢？

我的回答是，这个问题提得很糟糕。所有法律都已经被公民所同意。即使某些法律有违部分人的意志，即使人们违反任何一条法律都会受到惩罚，但这一前提始终是成立的。国家所有公民的长期意志就是公意；正是通过公意他们才成为公民，才变得自由。[33]当一条法律在公民大会上提出时，这并非是在问每个人批不批准，而是要看这条法律与代表他们意志的公意是否一致；每个人都会通过投票就这一问题提出意见，于是票数的统计就说明了公意。因此，当与我本人相反的意见占上风时，这仅仅表明，我犯了错误；我所认为的公意其实并不是公意。而且，如果我的个人意见竟然压倒了公意，那么这个结果其实是不符合我的意愿的，所以我也就不是一个自由人了。

诚然，这一结论的前提条件是，公意的所有特性能够在多数派中找到；若是公意的特性不存在于任何一方，那么不管人们采取什么主张，都是毫无自由可言的。

我在前些章节里就已经解释了特殊意志是如何在公众商讨中逐渐取代公意的，并且十分清楚地说明了有哪些可行的手段能够避免这种情况。下面，我将重新回到这一主题。至于可以用来宣布公意的投票比例数，我也已经制定了种种原则来对它进行测算。一票之差会破坏双方相等；一票反对也会破坏全体一致；可是，在全体一致与双方相等之间，还有许多数字不等的比例，而根据政体的状况和需求，我们可以找到任何一种符合条件的适当比例。

确定这些比例时，可以遵照两条普遍的准则：第一，要决定的事情越重要越严肃，人们意见应该越接近全体一致；第二，问题要求决断得越快，对赞同票的比例要求就可以越低；在必须立刻作出决定时，只要一方比另一方多一票就可以了。第一条准则似乎更适宜于法律；第二条则更适宜于管理事务的派遣。无论如何，必须将这两条准则结合，我们才能确定多数派的适当比例。

第三章　论选举制

如我所述，君主和行政官的选举是一种纷繁复杂的活动，可以通过自愿或抽签两种方法进行筹备。这两种方法都曾在不同的共和国使用过，而在威尼斯共和国的执政者选举中，我们还可以看到两种方法被十分复杂地混和使用。孟德斯鸠说：“抽签选举是民主制的天性。”这我同意。可为何会是如此呢？他继续说：“抽签是一种选举法，这种办法不伤害任何人，还能让每个公民有一种服务国家的合理愿望。”不过，这些都不是充分的理由。

假如我们记得，行政官的选举是政府而不是主权的一项职能的话，我们就会明白，为何抽签法对民主制而言是自然的。这是因为，在民主制中，行政机构的活动越少，它就越能达到越好的状态。

在每个真正的民主制中，行政官并不是一种特权，而是一副沉重的担子，所以不管它落在谁的身上，都有失公平。唯独法律可以将这种担子强加给抽到签的人，因为在这种情况下，既然各种条件对大家都是平等的，选择又不取决于任何人的意志，那么法律的普遍性就不会被哪个特殊作用所影响。

在贵族制中，君主选择君主，而政府靠自己的运作使自己永存不朽。所以，按个体意志进行选举，在这里是非常合适的。

威尼斯共和国执政者选举的例子非但不是对这种差异的否定，反而还对其有所加强：如此的混合形式正适宜于混合政府。认为威尼斯政府是真正的贵族制，那本来就是一种误解。与其说那里的人民在政府中不占一席之地，不如说真正能算威尼斯人民的其实是威尼斯贵族。贫穷的巴纳比人数量众多，他们是绝对当不了行政官的，即使是他们之中的显贵，也只不过是拥有一个阁下的空头衔、被允许出席大会议而已。而由于那个大会议的参与者跟我们的日内瓦众议会一样多，所以其中最杰出的议员也并不比我们普通公民有更多的特权。因此，若是不看两个共和国之间的悬殊差异，那么我们日内瓦的资产阶级分子就对应威尼斯的贵族；我们的本地人和居民对应威尼斯的公民和平民，而我们的农民对应威尼斯陆上的臣民。概而言之，除了威尼斯的面积大小之外，无论我们从什么观点来看这个共和国，它的政府都跟我们的一样，决不会是贵族制。区别仅仅在于，我们没有终身在职的首领，于是我们也不需要抽签。

在真正的民主制中，抽签几乎没什么不利之处，因为当所有人都既在天性和才能上平等，又在原则和财富上平等时，选中谁其实都是一样的。不过，正如我曾说过的，真正的民主制是不存在的。

当同时采用选举法和抽签法时，选举应该用在特殊人才的选择上，例如军事指挥。而对于需要常识、公正、正直品性的政治职位，抽签就足够了，因为在一个体制健全的国家，这样的品性在所有的公民的身上都能找到。

在君主制的统治下，抽签和选举都不会被采用。既然君主既是唯一的国王又是仅有的长官，那么其属下的任命都只能取决于他。当圣彼埃尔的神父建议增加法国国王的内阁阁臣，并通过投票选举成员时，他没有意识到他那时正在建议改变政权的形式。

我还想谈一谈投票和在公民大会的计票方法，但或许古罗马的政体历史能更好地说明我想提出的所有原则。深入地思考一下一个拥有二十万人的大会是如何处理公众事务和个人事务的，这对一个有头脑的读者来说想必并不在话下。

第四章　论古罗马公民大会

我们没有可信赖的古罗马早期历史记载，甚至大多数我们听说过的故事都可能只是传说。[34]事实上，一般各民族编年史中最有教育意义的部分就是他们的政体创建史，而这也是我们最缺少的部分。过去的经验每天都在告诉我们帝国大变革的种种原因，可是，由于现在不再有新的民族崛起，所以我们也就只能靠推测来解释过去的民族是怎么创建起来的。

我们已经发现了许多惯例，这起码可以表明：它们必然有一个源头。所以，如果有传说能追溯这个源头，或者得到最权威的支持和最理性的认可，那么我们就应该认为这样的传说是最真实可信的。在探究世上最自由最强大的民族如何行使他们的最高权力时，我试图遵循的原则就是如此。

古罗马创建之后，新生的共和国，即建国者队伍由三种人组成：奥尔本人、萨宾人和异乡人。他们以部族作为区分。每一个部族分为十个库里亚，每一个库里亚又细分为若干德库里亚，它们的首领分别叫库里昂和德库里昂。

此外，每个部族选出一百个特权市民或骑士，&nbsp；他们组成的团体称为百人团。这表明，最初是军事上的需要产生了这些对城市来说没什么意义的分类。然而，就好像有一种伟大的本能引领着古罗马一般，这个小城用完全适合打造世界之都的体制开始了自己的发展。

可这种原始分类很快就产生了不利的后果。奥尔本人和萨宾人的部族保持原来的状态，而异乡人的部族则因人口增长不断扩大，不久，它容纳的成员就比其他两个部族合在一起还要多了。塞尔维乌斯为了纠正这个致命错误，决定改变分类的依据。他废除了旧的分类法，重新以每个部族占据的城市区域进行划分。他将原来的三个部族分为四个，使它们各自占领罗马的一个山岗，并以此为名。于是，他既纠正了现存的不平等，又预防了将来的不平等；为确保这种分类是按人而不是按区进行，他禁止居民在区域间搬迁，以避免不同部族的融合。

他还把自古以来就有的三个骑兵百人团增加了一倍，并额外编制了十二个团，不过它们都保留原有的名称；这是一种精明简单的手段，他用这种手段成功地将骑士主体与公民主体区分开来，而且不使后者抱怨。

在四个城市部族的基础上，塞尔维乌斯又按区域划分增加了十五个由乡村居民构成的乡村部族。此后，随着新部族陆续建立完毕，古罗马人最终被分为了三十五个部族，这一数目直到共和国终结都没有改变过。

城市部族与乡村部族之间的区别产生了一个值得注意的现象，它之所以特别，一方面是因为没有类似的先例，一方面也是因为古罗马的道德存续和帝国发展都要归功于它。肯定有人会想，一旦划分完成，城市部族必然很快将权力和荣誉垄断，并且迅速贬低乡村部族的地位。然而，实际发生的事情却恰恰相反。早期古罗马人对乡村生活的喜好众所周知。这种喜好源自于他们智慧的创立者，他不但将自由精神结合到乡村劳动和兵役之中，还在某种意义上将手工业、贸易、阴谋算计、财富和奴隶制全部转移到了城市。

这样一来，既然所有杰出的罗马人都居住在乡村耕田种地，那么把乡村看作共和国中流砥柱的观点就变得非常普遍了。由于这种生活方式被大多数贵族所采用，大家便对它十分青睐；在众人眼里，乡下人朴素的劳动生活比古罗马资产阶级分子宽松空闲的城市生活更优越。而且，一个在城里不过是可怜的无产者的人，一旦下乡种地，就立刻成了受人尊重的公民。瓦戎说过，我们开明的祖先将乡村作为那些强健者和勇敢者的休养生息之地，使后者在战争期间保卫他们，在和平时期滋养他们。这话是很有道理的。普林尼也声明，乡村部族之所以受到尊敬，是因为那些居住其中的人；而当人们故意要羞辱一个胆怯者时，他就会被不留情面地送到城市部族里去。萨宾人阿皮乌斯·克劳底乌斯在罗马是一位显赫人物，他被授予各种荣誉，并作为乡村部族的一员为后人所铭记。这个乡村部族后来沿用了他家族的名字。最后，所有被释放的奴隶都加入了城市部族，而且他们永远也进不了乡村部族。毕竟，共和国上下没有任何一个先例是让被释放的奴隶来当行政官的，即便他们已经成了公民。

这种原则本来是很好的，但它被推行得太过火，所以最终发生了变化，实际上成了政体中被滥用的手段。

首先，由于监察官长期掌握将公民从一个部族转换到另一个部族的仲裁权，他们渐渐竟容许大多数人随意加入自己挑选的部族。这一让步肯定没有什么好处，它使审查制度失去了一种最大的能力。况且，既然大权在握的高贵者们都加入了乡村部族，而被释放的奴隶和普通人留在了城市部族中，那么部族就不再以地方或领地为基础了。大家混杂在一起，人们不查登记表就无法确定任何人的身份。这就是为什么部族这个词逐渐有了个人的而非地域的含义，更准确地说，逐渐变得徒有虚名。

还发生过这样的事：更接近市中心的城市部族由于距离优势，在公民大会中往往一家独大，而他们在接受了别有居心之人的贿赂之后，竟任其操纵投票，以卑鄙的方式出卖国家。

再来说说库里亚。由于创立者己在每个部族中成立了十个库里亚，所以当时城墙以内的全体古罗马人由三十个库里亚组成。每个库里亚都有自己的神殿、神祇、官员、祭司以及自己的各种节日，这些节日称为大路节，类似后来乡村部族举办的乡村节。

当塞尔维乌斯引入他的新分类法时，三十个库里亚无法平分为四个部族，于是他就没有进行划分；结果是，库里亚独立于部族，成了罗马的另一种分类方式。不过，在乡村部族或属于部族的人当中不存在有关库里亚的问题，因为部族已经成为纯粹的公民组织，且在引入了新的征兵体制后，罗穆卢斯的军事划分便没有什么意义了。这样一来，虽然每个公民都必然是某一部族的成员，但他们却往往不是库里亚的成员。

塞尔维乌斯还做了与前两种毫无关系的第三种分类，这种分类从其结果看是三者中最重要的。他既不以人也不以其住处，而是以财富将整个罗马的公民分成六类。其结果是，第一类挤满了富人；最后一类净是穷人；而中间一类为拥有中等财富的人。这六大类细分为一百九十三个团体，称为百人团。这些团体又有另外的分类方式：第一类占半数以上，而最后一类却只包括一个百人团。于是我们发现，人数最少的那一类拥有最多的百人团，而最后一类只作一个百人团的细分类来算，尽管它容纳罗马半数以上的居民。

为了不让人们察觉这种分类的后果，塞尔维乌斯以军事的形式掩饰它；他在第二类和第四类各放入了两个军队百人团。而且除了最后一类，他在其他每个类别中都做了老少之间的划分，换句话说，就是划分需服兵役的人与年纪太大不必服役的人；比起财富的区分，这种划分更有必要进行经常性的人口统计。最后，他还规定集会应在玛尔斯教场上举行；所有那些兵役适龄者都应扛着武器参加集会。

他在最后一类的老少之间不做同样区分的理由只是，参军为国效力是一种荣誉，而属于这一类的人没有资格获得这种荣誉；一个人只有先拥有家园，才有保卫它的权力。虽然今天各个国家的军队里都有无数乞丐，但在士兵被视为自由保卫者的那个年代，大概每一个乞丐都会被古罗马人轻蔑地逐出军团。

然而，在最后一类中，还有对无产者和被称作“按人头计数”的人的区分。前者并非是完全没有地位，他们至少算是国家公民，甚至在国家万分急需时也可以当兵。但是，那些一无所有、只充当计算人数之用的人，就相当于是不存在的。直到马留乌斯的时代，他才第一个打破陈规，招收他们入伍。

在此，我们不讨论这第三种分类实际上是好是坏，可以确定的一点是，它之所以可行，正是因为早期古罗马人简朴的习惯、对农业的喜好，以及相应的对商业和敛财的蔑视。然而，与他们相反，现代民族往往贪得无厌、内心不安、耍弄阴谋，且永远处在局势的变化和盛衰的循环中。有哪个这样的民族能够让这一体制持续二十年而不将整个国家颠覆呢？我们还应该记住一点，古罗马的人民和审查机构拥有足以纠正这种体制之弊端的道德力量，而且在当时，富人若是过度炫富自己的财产，就会被转到穷人的阶级中去。

了解了这些情况，我们便不难理解，为何人们总是只提到五种古罗马人的分类，而实际上却有六类。第六个类别极少受到关注，因为它既不为军队输送士兵，也不为玛尔斯教场[35]提供选民，于是在共和国中便几乎起不到任何实际作用。

古罗马人的不同分类就是如此。接下来，让我们来关心一下这些类别在各种集会中所产生的影响。那些合法召集的集会被称作公民大会，它们通常在古罗马的公共会场或玛尔斯教场上举行，根据所采用的形式，它们可以分为库里亚大会、百人团大会和部族大会三个种类。库里亚大会和百人团大会分别由罗穆卢斯和塞尔维乌斯创立，而部族大会则由保民官发明。除了公民大会，没有任何其他地方能批准法律、选举行政官。由于每个公民至少是库里亚、百人团和部族三者之一的成员，所以他们所有人都拥有投票权，且在法律和事实上都是真正的主权者。

为了合法召集公民大会，并使其行动有法律约束力，必须满足三个条件：第一，召集集会的主体或行政官必须被授予必要的权威；第二，集会必须在法律规定的某一天举行；第三，必须有一个好的占卜的结果。

第一个条件的理由无需解释。第二个条件与政策相关，集会不可以在假日或集市日进行，因为那几天人人都去了罗马城里办事，没时间在广场上参加集会。第三个条件使元老院得以遏制一个自负且躁动的民族，并缓和保民官的激情，让他们不要再继续煽动人民——尽管保民官也有种种逃避审查的方式。

公民大会的作用并不仅仅是裁决法律和选举官员。由于政府最重要的那些职能都掌握在古罗马人民的手里，我们可以说，欧洲的命运就在那些集会上决定的。公共事务具有多样性，因此根据集会讨论的内容，公民大会采用过若干方式。

为了判断这些不同的方式，有必要将它们做一番比较。在建立库里亚的过程中，罗穆卢斯的打算是让元老院和公民处于平衡状态、互相防备，好让他本人同时对双方施加控制。在这样的精心筹划下，他赋予人民数量上的权威，用以平衡他留给贵族的权力与财富的权威。不过，按照君主制的精神，他仍然给了贵族极大的利益，因为他们可以用钱收买人心，从而使人民这一方不再具有人数上的优势。这种妙不可言的庇护人制度和受庇护人制度是政治和人道的杰作，没有这一制度，与共和国精神如此对立的贵族制就无法存续。给予世界以这一崇高范例的荣誉应当独属于古罗马人；在这种制度中，权力从未被滥用，但至今还没有任何国家对其进行仿效。

库里亚的这种方式一直延续到塞尔维乌斯的统治时期，且由于人们通常认为塔尔昆的统治是建于非法基础之上的，所以古罗马王政时代的法令就被统称为库里亚法。

在共和国中，库里亚仍然被限制在那四个城市部族之内，并且仍然只包括罗马城内的居民，不管是对领导着贵族的元老院，还是对本身不是平民、但领导着较富有公民的保民官，它都提供不了什么便利。由此，库里亚陷入了不被信任的尴尬境地，它陷得如此之深，以致于需要由一整个公民大会去做的事情，他们只能交给三十个扈从去做。

百人团的分类对贵族制极为有利，因而人们最初不易看出，为何元老院始终不能在以百人团为名的公民大会中占优势，而审议会、监察官和其他行政官却借此名义当选。事实上，在构成全体罗马人六个类别的一百九十三个百人团中，第一分类有九十八个百人团。既然投票是以百人团来计数的，那么第一类的票数就比所有其他类别加起来还要多。当所有第一类的百人团抱成一团时，剩余的投票甚至都不用计算了。此时，由少数人决定的东西被看作是多数人的决议，并顺利通过了；于是我们可以说，在百人团大会中，事事都由金钱多少来决定，而不由选票多少来决定。

可是，这种过度的权力在两个方面得到了调节。第一，保民官和大多数平民通常都被归为富人那一阶级，因此他们抑制了贵族在第一类中的影响。

第二，百人团并不总是被召集起来按顺序或按等级投票，否则的话，投票就会永远从第一类开始；百人团是通过抽签选出来的。[36]先让这个百人团进行选举，之后再在不同的日子召集其他百人团重新按等级顺序重复该项选举，通常结果都是一样的。于是，范例的权威便根据民主制的原则，不再属于等级，而属于偶然性。

这种惯例还有另一个好处；它意味着来自乡村的居民在数次选举之间，有时间亲自了解暂时被提名的候选人的优点，因而他们就不会在无知中投票。但是，借着加快投票程序的名头，这一惯例最终被废除了。两次选举还是被放在同一天进行。

严格地说，部族大会才是古罗马人的议会，它只能由保民官召集。保民官在这里被选举出来以后，又在同样的这个地方批准通过公民投票的结果。元老院不但在部族大会中没有地位，其成员甚至还被大会排斥在外。于是，他们就不得不服从那些在他们没有发言权的情况下被制定出来的法律，在这一点上，他们还不如最卑贱的公民来得自由。这种不公正在构想上是非常不妥当的，因为光凭这一点，就可以证明一个主体没有将它所有公民的意见考虑在内，所以它颁布的法律理应是无法成立的。所有贵族在出席大会的时候都只是单纯的个体，并不会对按人计数的投票产生巨大影响，因为在这里，最卑贱的无产者与首席元老享有同样的地位。

由此可知，除了由众多公民投票采用的不同方法产生的秩序之外，这几种方法本身也具有相当的重要性；每一种方法都会产生各种影响，这些影响与引导人们选择这种方法的观念息息相关。

我不想再深究细节，依照前文给出的解释，我们已经可以得出结论，即部族大会最有利于人民的政府；百人团大会最有利于贵族制。而在库里亚大会中，古罗马人民仅在人数上构成了大多数，这就有利于暴政的施行以及不光彩的恶行的滋生。正是出于这个原因，甚至连那些想要煽风点火的势力都尽量不参加库里亚大会，免得他们的野心暴露得过于彻底。毫无疑问，古罗马人的尊严只有在百人团大会上才能显示得淋漓尽致；只有这样一种集会才是包括了所有人的。与其相反，库里亚大会把乡村部族排除在外，而部族大会又将元老院和贵族拒之门外。

古罗马人所使用的投票制就像他们的举止和道德一样简单，虽然比起斯巴达人来说还是要稍微复杂一点儿。每个人以口头表决的方式投票，然后由一个书记员将票数记下来；在每个部族中，多数派的决定等于本部族的投票结果，而多数部族的决定就等于全体人民的投票结果；库里亚和百人团也是如此。这种投票方式不失为一种好办法，但只有在参加投票的公民普遍诚实正直、耻于当众支持一种非正义的动机或一个无才无德的候选人的情况下，这种方式才行得通。所以，当人们变得腐败，且选票可以被任意买卖时，就应该采用秘密计票的方式，让贿选者无法确保他们的钱能买来选票，也让那些流氓无赖们由于无处抛售选票而不必沦为卖国贼。

我清楚，西塞罗是谴责这种方式的改变的，他还表示，这种改变得为共和国的衰败承担部分责任。虽然西塞罗在这方面的权威毋庸置疑，我却不能同意他的看法。相反，我认为正是因为此类改变做得还不够，才加速了国家的衰败。就像健康者的食物不合适给病人吃一样，人们也不该试图用适用于善良人民的法律来管理腐化的人民。没有什么会比威尼斯共和国的经久不衰更能证实这一原理了，这一政体之所以至今仍有痕迹存留，就是因为威尼斯的法律仅适用于坏人。

现在，罗马公民每个人都被分到了一张选票，他们可以在别人不知其意见的情况下把它投出去。同时，罗马人还为收牌、计票、监表等作出新的安排，但这并不表示那些被委以职责的官员们就可以不受到监督，相反，他们的忠诚会一直接受人们的质疑。最后，设计好的法令通告被大量散发，以防有人密谋和买卖选票，结果，法令的数目之多反而使其显得毫无效率。

在共和国的最后几年，古罗马人常常被迫求助于特别的权宜之计以弥补法令的不足。有时，他们假借神意，故意制造一些奇迹，但那些手段只能使人民上当，并不能吓住人民的统治者。有时，大会被仓促召集，为的是让候选人来不及进行贿赂；有时，若人们被邪恶的一方引诱、即将作出错误的决策，一些变故就会突然发生，阻碍议案的通过。但是，野心勃勃的人最终还是使这一切努力落了空；在所有的事实中最令人难以置信的是：多亏那些古老的秩序规定，即使是在权力被如此滥用的年代，广大人民仍也能继续选举行政官、制定法律、判决案件、经营私事、管理公务，而且这些事做起来并不艰难，因为人民所掌握的资源和元老院几乎是一样多的。

第五章　论保民官制

当国体的不同部分之间无法达成一个精确的平衡，或者当无法控制的因素持续改变它们之间的关系时，一个特别的行政机构便被建立起来。它虽然独立于别的行政机构，却能使各种因素趋于平衡；在君主与人民、君主与主权者之间，它起到联系或从中协调的作用，而且，如有必要，这两种关系的协调也可以同步进行。

我称之为保民官制度的这个主体，是法律和立法权的监护人。它有时保护主权者以对抗政府，就像罗马的保民官所做的那样；有时支持政府以对抗人民，就像现今十人会议在威尼斯所做的一样；有时，它又在二者之间维持一种平衡，就像斯巴达的监察官所做的一样。

保民官制度并不是共和国体制的一部分，它既不该分享立法权，也不该分享行政权，可正是由于这种原因，保民官制度自身的权力才达到最大的极限，因为它虽然自身无所作为，却可以阻止他人作为。作为法律的保卫者，它比行使法律的君主和确立法的主权者更加神圣、更加令人崇拜。这一点十分清楚地体现在罗马的情形中，在罗马，傲慢的贵族总是鄙视所有人民，但却不得不在一位普通的人民官员面前点头哈腰，即使这个官员既无神职上的权威，又无法律上的权威。

保民官制度若是把控得高明，便是一个良好国体强有力的支柱，而一旦它拥有了超过其所必要的最底限度的权力，它就将颠覆一切。保民官制度本性上并不趋于软弱。只要它存在，它的力量就必定会比其应有的更强。

保民官制度原本的作用是充当行政权的协调员并保护法律，而当它侵占了这一权力并试图制定法律时，它就会退化为暴政。在斯巴达士气高涨的时候，监察官的巨大权力并不会带来什么危险，但只要国家出现了一点腐败的迹象，它就会大大加速这一进程。阿吉斯虽然被暴君们杀死，但他继承者最终完成了复仇；同样，监察官犯下的罪行和受到的惩罚也加速了共和国的崩溃。克利蒙特的时代结束后，斯巴达的辉煌便不复存在了。古罗马也是以同样的方式灭亡的，而且，虽然法律是为维护自由而制定的，但它却最终使保民官所拥有的过多权力落入了毁掉自由的君主之手。至于威尼斯的十人会议，那是一个血腥的法庭，这种法庭对贵族和人民同样有害；它决不是给予现已降格的法律以最高的保护，而只是为无人敢于揭露的隐秘恶行而服务。

像政府那样，保民官制度也会随其成员的增加而受到削弱。当古罗马人的保民官——原来是两个，后来增加到五个——试图再增加一倍时，元老院同意了，并自信可以利用一方控制另一方，这一招果然奏效。

阻止这样一个强大主体篡权的最好方法——尽管它是任何政府从未留意过的方法——就是不让保民官制度持久存在，并规定一个其应处于暂停期的时间间隔。这些时间间隔不宜太长，以免使人有机会滥用各种权利，为此，可以制定详细的法律，规定这一间隔可以在必要时被特别的职权所缩短。

这种方法对我来说没有什么缺点，因为既然保民官制度如我所述决不是国体的一部分，那么将它删去也必定不会有什么害处；我还认为这种方法是非常灵验的，因为一个刚上任的行政官不会用他前任所拥有的权力，而只会用法律所赋予他的权力来执政。

第六章　论独裁制

法律的不变性妨碍法律适应于环境，所以它不但可能在某种情况下使法律变得腐败，还会在紧要关头导致国家的覆灭。法律所规定的正式程序往往进展缓慢，但很多时候局势并不容许它耗费这么长时间。有许多事是立法者无法预见的，而光是明白这一点，就是一种非常必要的预见了。

由于这种原因，人们不应试图使政治制度变得如此僵化，以致于让自己丧失了中止政治制度运行的能力。即便是斯巴达，有时也会让其法律处于休眠的状态。

然而，唯有最大的危险才值得人们去冒变更公共秩序的危险；法律神圣的权力决不应该被中止，除非国家正处于生死关头。在这些极为罕见但很容易就能理解的情况下，一道特别的法令会将公共安全托付给一位最靠得住的人物。托付方式有两种，具体的选择取决于紧急情况的性质。

如果只靠政府增加活动就足以排除危险，那么这种活动应该集中在政府的一两个成员手中。在这种情况下，并不是法律的权威被削减了，而只是行政方式发生了变更。然而，如果情况已经危险到连法律机器本身都成为了安全障碍，那么就必须任命一个人为最高首领，并赋予其压制一切的法律权力，同时暂时中止主权者的权力。在这种情况下，公意就不容置疑，因为很显然，人们主要关注的是国家的生死存亡。因而，中止立法权并非废止立法权，压制立法权的行政官也不能直接掌握这一权力；他控制立法权，却不是它的代表。他可以做其他任何事情，唯独不能立法。

古罗马元老院使用的是第一种方法，它根据一项神圣的程序将共和国安全委托给两位执政官；而当他们之一拥立一个独裁者掌权时，方法一变更为方法二。这种方法是古罗马从阿尔巴那里学到的。[37]

在共和国初期，古罗马人常常采用独裁的手段，因为国家的根基尚未稳固，光靠宪法是不足以维护自身的。然而，古罗马人的道德品质使得他们不必像其他国家那样进行诸多防范，人们既不担忧独裁者会滥用职权，也不担忧他会企图超限延长执政时间。相反，如此多的权力对那些行使权力的人来说倒成了一个负担，因为他们急急忙忙想使自己摆脱这些权力，仿佛将行使法律的权力握在手里是什么极其麻烦又危险的职责似的。

所以，这里的危险情况并不是权力的滥用，而是对权力的贬低。人们往往因此而谴责罗马共和国在早期对这种最高行政官制度的使用过于轻率。因为当权力被浪费在选举、献祭以及纯粹的形式化的事情中时，他们便有理由担心权力会在真正需要它施展力量的时候显得软弱无力，并且他们也会逐渐认为，独裁只是一种空洞的形式，其唯一作用便是让种种毫无用处的仪式显得煞有其事。

到共和国晚期，比以往慎重许多的古罗马人在实行独裁的过程中又变得十分吝啬，这一切是没什么理由的，就像他们同样解释不了为什么之前对权力如此放任一样。不难看出，他们的谨慎并没有确实的根据。当时，为了不让行政官拥有太大的权力，人们的对策是让首都处于较弱的地位；独裁者在某种情况下可以保护公众自由，却不能侵犯它；古罗马的镣铐不是在它内部铸成的，而是在军队之中；塞尔维乌斯无力抵抗苏拉和庞培无力抵抗恺撒这两件事清楚地表明，内部的权威在面临外部的力量是多么不堪一击。

这种偏差导致古罗马人犯下极大的错误。例如，在喀提林事件中，人们没能扶持一位独裁者上位。鉴于那次事件只关系到城市本身，或者顶多还涉及意大利的几个省区，法律赋予独裁者的无限权力本该轻易粉碎那场阴谋，但事实上，若不是发生了一连串侥幸的意外事件，情况还会继续恶化。这种侥幸，恰恰是与古罗马人的谨慎最不相容的。

元老院不去任命独裁者，反而十分满意地将其所有权力交给执政官，这就导致西塞罗为进行有效的行动而不得不在关键时刻僭越了他的权限。并且，尽管在最初的喜悦之中，古罗马人赞成了他的举动，他也依然应当为其行为造成的后果负全责，包括公民因违反法律而受到的肉体伤害——这原本是一种不可能向独裁者提出的指责。然而，这位执政官的雄辩却为他扫清了一切障碍。他本人尽管是一个古罗马人，可是他爱自己的荣耀胜过爱自己的国家；他企图在国务中为自己获得一切荣誉，而不去寻求一种报国的合理合法手段。[38]因而，他被公正地誉为罗马的解放者，同时也作为古罗马法律的违犯者受到了应有的惩罚。不管他所描述的自己被流放的经历有多么辉煌，那也毫无疑问是在赎罪。

此外，无论这个重要的独裁者的任命是以什么方式被授予的，其任期都必须被限制为一个绝对不能延长的、较短的时间；在需要建立独裁制的紧急情况下，国家要么很快灭亡，要么很快脱离险境。一旦这种急需没有了，独裁不是变成暴政就是变得一文不值。在古罗马，这个期限是六个月，大多数独裁者会在期满之前辞职。假设这个期限可以被延长，那他们就可能在延长的基础上再作出调整，以进一步延长期限，就像原本任期一年的古罗马十大行政官那样。独裁者被给予的时间，只能刚好够他解决当前的问题，而不能让他有余地考虑更长远的计划。

第七章　论监察官制

正如公意是通过法律途径加以宣布的一样，公众的裁决是通过监察官来宣布的；公众的意见是一种法律，而监察官就是这种法律的执行者，而且，按照君主的模式，这种法律也只能应用在特殊情况中。

由此，监察官仲裁的决不是公众意见，它只是代言人；一旦脱离了这一点，其种种决策就空洞无效。

将民族的道德与其尊崇的对象分隔开来是徒劳无益的，因为两者都源自同样的原理，必然会相互混杂。对世上所有的民族来说，并不是天性，而是意见决定了他们对快乐的选择。若是改变人们的意见，他们的道德便将自动得到净化。人们总是喜爱好东西或他们认为好的东西，然而，正是由于这种判断，他们才会犯下错误；所以，应该对他们的判断加以调整。判断道德，就是判断荣誉的授予标准；判断荣誉的授予标准，就是把意见当作法律来看待。

一个民族的种种意见都来源于其自身的体制；尽管法律并不规定道德，但道德确实是因立法才产生的；当立法被弱化时，道德就堕落；而监察官的裁决势必完成不了法律尚未完成的任务。

由此可见，在维护道德方面，监察官制度可能有所作为，但是在恢复道德方面它却绝对无能为力。监察官制度应该建立在法律仍然充满活力的时候，因为活力一旦失去，一切就都无所指望；法律一旦不再具有力量，任何合法的东西也就不具有力量了。

监察官制度为了维护道德，不但要防止各种意见受到腐化、用明智的规划阻止它们偏离正道，有时还要在它们尚未成形时就对其加以固定。在法兰西王国，决斗中使用助手曾经是人们强烈支持的做法，但仅仅由于国王在法令中说了一句话——“至于那些胆怯到要找助手的人”——这种做法就被废止了。公共意见之所以能一下子被扭转过来，是因为有人对它进行了准确预判。可当同样的法令试图表明对抗决斗也是胆怯时——尽管这很有道理，但却与大众意见背道而驰——大众就会对此加以嘲笑，因为他们自己已经有了对这件事的判断。

我在其他地方说过，既然公众意见并不屈从于强制力，那么在已建立起的代表公众意见的监察官制中就不该留下强制的痕迹。这种现代人完全不熟悉的技巧，古罗马人曾经运用得很好，而斯巴达人更是深谙此道。在此，我们只能对他们致以最高的敬意。

过去，有一个品行不好的人在斯巴达内阁会议上提出了一个很好的想法，监督官对他不屑一顾，却听取了一个善良公民提出的同样的意见。二者既没受到表扬，也没受到责备，然而这对后者来说是怎样的荣誉、对前者来说是怎样的耻辱啊；来自萨摩斯岛的几个醉鬼曾经弄脏监察官的席位，次日，就有公共布告允许萨摩斯岛居民今后可以做各种坏事。这种惩罚比真正的惩罚更为严厉。在斯巴达声明了什么是体面的、什么是不体面的之后，希腊便直接接受了这一判断标准。

第八章　论公民宗教

原始时期，人们没有国王，却有神祇。他们唯一的政权就是神权。他们像卡力古拉那样推理，因此便能得出正确的结论。在一个人决定接受自己的同类作为主人，并说服自己做此决定是有益处的之前，他需要一段较长的时间来调整他的感觉和观念。

每个政治社会都有其信奉的神。由这一事实可见，神跟民族是一样多的。两个互相疏远、几乎总是敌对的民族，不可能长期认同同一个主人，两支交战的军队也不可能服从同一个指挥官。因而，民族的互不相容就产生了如此之多的神，而且这反过来又产生了宗教层面和民间层面的不宽容。之后我便要解释，这两种不宽容必然是相同的。

古希腊人的幻想——他们是在野蛮人崇拜的诸神中找到自己的神祇的——源于他们的一种习惯，即把自己看作那些民族的自然主权者。可到了我们这个时代，若是还不懂得如何分辨各民族的神——不管是无法区别闪米族神、农神和克罗诺，还是把腓尼基人的邪神、希腊人的宙斯和古罗马人的朱庇特混为一谈——就未免过于可笑了；仿佛是在说，这些拥有不同名称的幻想生命之间是有共通之处的！

可是，或许有人会问，为何那些国家在有自己的宗教礼拜和神祇且信奉异教的情况下没有发生宗教战争？我的回答是：这是由于这样一个真实的情况——每个拥有自己的信仰和自己的政权的国家，并不区分自己的神祇和法律。政治战争就是神学战争。每个神的职权是由不同民族的边界所决定的。一个民族的神无权超越其他民族的神。异教徒的神决不是嫉妒的，它们在彼此之间划分世界；甚至连摩西人和希伯莱人在论及以色列的神时也会采用这个观念。诚然，他们完全不在乎迦南人的神，迦南人是一个受排斥的民族，注定要毁灭，而他们将要占领迦南人的国家。但是，想一想他们是怎样谈论自己无法侵略的邻国民族的神的吧。耶弗他对阿摩尼特斯人说：“属于你们的神基抹的东西难道不是你合法应得的东西吗？正如我们有权占领一块土地，只要我们善于征伐的神已经攻下了它。”[39]

但是，犹太人以前屈从于巴比伦君主，后来屈从于叙利亚君主，当他们试图坚定不移地承认自己的神祇，而不承认其他神祇时，这番拒绝就被视为一种向征服者发起的叛乱。我们在犹太人历史上所读到的那些迫害，正是因这个理由而发生的，而且在基督教诞生之前，我们没有找到其他这样的例子。[40]

既然每种宗教都如此唯一地依附于对它作出规定的国家法律，且既然除了征服就没有使人皈依宗教的手段，那么，唯有征服者才是传教士；既然改变信仰是被征服国家的法定义务之一，那么就有必要在布道使人皈依之前就进行征服。比起人类为了神而战，情况倒更像是荷马书中所说的那样，是诸神为了人类而战；每个民族都会向神祈求胜利，并偿还神以新的祭坛。古罗马人在拿下一座城池之前，都会拜请那儿的神放弃城池；他们之所以允许塔伦土姆人维护他们愤怒的神，是因为他们相信，别的神已经屈从于他们的神，并被迫向他们表示敬意。他们允许被征服者保有自己的神，就好比是允许被征服者保有自己的法律。通常，这种宽容的唯一条件，就是被征服者必须向主神殿的朱庇特献上一顶王冠。

最后，随着帝国的扩张，古罗马人也传播了他们的信仰和神，而且他们还常常给予所有人同等的公民权利，从而将被征服者的宗教和神都纳入了自己的体系。这个庞大帝国的各民族逐渐发现自己拥有许多的神祇和信仰，而且各地的情况都差不多；这就是异教在当时世界成为了唯一宗教形式的原因。

正是在这些情况下，耶稣出现了，并在全球建立起一个精神王国；这个将神学体系与政治分离的王国，不但意味着国家已不是一个统一体，还造成了宗教内部的分裂，将信仰基督教的各民族置于无休无止的动荡之中。可是，既然另一世界王国的新观念从未被灌输到异教徒的头脑中，他们就始终把基督教徒视为真正的叛乱者，并且认为这些叛乱者披着虚情假意屈服的外衣，在力量薄弱时服从权威，但一有机会就会侵占这种权威、独立称霸。宗教迫害的原因便是如此。

异教徒所担忧的事真的发生了；那时一切都变了样；谦卑的基督教徒改变了他们的调子，并且在一个具有实体的首领的统治下，所谓另一世界的王国很快变成了这世上最暴力的专制。

然而，既然各位君主和各种公民法律依旧存在，这个双重权力的结果就只能是一场没完没了的司法冲突，这场冲突基督教国家不可能拥有任何一种好的政府制度，因为在这些国家，人们从来就不知道他们是该服从公民的统治者，还是该听从神父。

许多民族，甚至包括欧洲或其周边国家的民族，都曾试图维护或重新建立古代的制度，可它们都没有成功：基督精神已大获全胜。宗教崇拜一直保持着，或重新恢复了其独立于主权的地位，并且与国家没有必要的联系。穆罕默德的观念是很合理的，他努力维护其政体的统一，而且只要在他的继任者哈里发的掌权期间，这一政体形式能够维持下去，从今以后它就是牢不可破的了，从某种程度上来说，它也会是一个很好的政体。然而，阿拉伯人后来变得富裕、有教养了，同时也更文雅、娇贵和软弱了，以至于被野蛮人征服；然后两权分割重新开始。即使与基督教徒相比，穆斯林之间的分裂更不明显，但它确实是存在的，阿里教派的这一现象尤为严重，而在像波斯那样的国家中，人们一直都会有分裂的感觉。

在我们当中，英国国王和沙皇已经自封为教会领袖了。然而这个称号并非使他们真正成为了教会的主人，倒更像是成了教会的大臣，而他们掌握的力量也只够保存教会，并不能让其作出改变；他们并不是立法者，而只是君主。无论牧师在哪里设立一个团体，[41]他在自己的机构中就是主人和立法者。因而，英国和俄国就有两种权力、两个主权者，和别的国家并没有区别。

在所有基督教作家中，哲学家霍布斯是唯一清楚地看出了其邪恶之处，并找到了根治方法的人，他敢于建议将鹰的两个头重新合并，彻底恢复政治统一，因为如果不统一，国家和政府就都无法健全。不过，他应该也已看出基督教的主导精神与其体制互不相容——君主利益总是高于国家利益。霍布斯体系招人憎恨的原因不在于它的可怕、虚假的部分，而恰恰在于其合理、真实的部分。[42]

我相信，如果用这个观点来分析历史事实，我们就不难反驳贝尔和华伯登相互对立的观念了，他们一个认为宗教对政体无益，一个认为基督教是政体的坚强后盾。通过阐述国家没有宗教作为基础就无法创建的道理，我们可以驳斥第一个观点；通过证明基督教法则对健全的国体其实不是有利而是有害，我们也可以驳斥第二个观点。为了使大家理解得更透彻，我想我只需把与主题有关的、特别含混不清的宗教观念说得更明确一点即可。

从与社会的联系——不管是普通的还是特别的——来看，宗教可以分为两种：人类宗教和公民宗教。人类宗教没有神殿、祭坛或仪式，只受限于对至高无上神的内在忠诚和道德的外在义务，它是纯洁朴素的福音宗教、是真正的有神论，可以被称为神圣的自然法则。公民宗教是在一国之内建立起来的宗教；它让那个国家拥有自己的神祇，也就是特别的守护神；它有自己的教条、礼节和由法律规定的崇拜形式；对一个提倡这种宗教的国家来说，外在的一切都是异教的、不相容的、野蛮的；它只把人的权利与义务限定在祭坛一样狭窄的范围内。所有早期民族的宗教就是如此；我们可以给它取名为公民的或积极的神圣法则。

还有第三种更古怪的宗教，它们给予人们两套立法规则、两位统治者、两个祖国，让人们承担两种相互矛盾的义务，并且阻止人们同时具有教民与公民的身份。拉马斯人的宗教如此，日本人的宗教如此，天主基督教也如此。人们可以称其为牧师的宗教。它产生一种混合的、反社会的法律体系，这种体系没有名称。

从政治上看，这三种宗教每一种都有其缺陷。第三种宗教坏得如此明显，以至于一切对其坏处的证明都是在浪费时间。破坏社会统一的一切事物都是毫无价值的；使人自相矛盾的一切制度也是毫无价值的。

第二种宗教的优点在于它把拜神与守法相结合，而且，通过使公民崇拜祖国，它也教会了他们一点：为国家作贡献就是为守护神作贡献。这是一种君主即为唯一教主、行政官即为唯一牧师的神权政体。在这里，为自己国家而死的人就是殉道者；违法就是不虔诚；让罪人承受大众的诅咒就等于让神的怒火来裁决他：sacer esto（让神诅咒他去吧！）。

不过，这种宗教也是恶劣的；既然它依赖谬误和谎言，它就会欺骗人们，使人们轻信、迷信；它在空洞的礼仪中将对神的真正崇拜掩盖起来。当它变得孤傲、残暴，并且使一个民族变得嗜血、偏狭时，它就更加恶劣了，不但让人们成天只顾谋杀和屠杀，还让他们相信杀害那些不接受其神明的人是一桩神圣的义举。这样一来，这个民族就陷入与其他所有民族对峙或交战的自然状态，它的自身安全于是毫无保障。

剩下的就只有人类宗教，也就是基督教。这里讲的不是如今的基督教，而是那种完全不同的的福音基督教。在这种神圣的、崇高的、真正的宗教的影响下，人们作为同一个神的孩子，把其他人视为兄弟姐妹，并且他们联结而成的那个社会自始至终都不会解体。

可是，这种宗教既没有与政体的特定联系，也不能让法律在原有的基础上增加任何权力，所以它就缺乏一种维系特别社会所必需的纽带。更有甚者：这种宗教非但不会使公民的内心依附于国家，反而会使他们与尘世的一切东西分离。我不知道还有什么会比这更加违反社会精神了。

有人说，一个真正基督教徒的民族总是可以建立人们所能想到的最完美无缺的社会。我只看出这个假设有一个大缺陷，即一个真正基督教徒的社会肯定不是一个人类社会。

我甚至还要说，这个想象的社会若有尽善尽美的一切，就决不会是最强大、最持久的。它的完美使它缺乏连结的纽带；其致命的缺陷就在于其极致的完美。

人人都要履行义务；人人都要服从法律；统治者要公正温和；行政官要诚实廉洁；士兵要藐视死亡；既不能虚荣也不能奢侈；这一切十分美好。不过，让我们再往下瞧一瞧吧！

基督教是一种地地道道精神上的宗教，它只涉及天堂的东西；基督教徒的祖国并不属于这个世界。基督教徒履行其义务，这一点并不假，可他是抱着一种完全不在乎行为成功与否的态度在履行义务。假如他对自己没什么好责备的话，那这世上的一切是否顺利对他来说便无关紧要了。如果国家繁荣昌盛，他就几乎不敢享受公众的快乐，而是害怕他会因国家的荣耀而骄傲起来；如果国家灭亡，他就会祝福上帝对其子民施加的重压。

为了使社会得以太平、和谐得以保持，每个公民毫无例外都必须成为好的基督徒。假如不幸出现了一个野心勃勃的家伙、一个伪君子、一个谋反者，或者比如在他们当中出现了一个克伦威尔的话，那人一定会轻易地将他虔诚的同胞玩弄于股掌之中。因为基督的仁慈不容许我们动不动就把邻居往坏处想。当那人狡猾到掌握了利用别人的技巧，并成功窃取了一部分公共权威时，他就会得到无上荣誉；神的意志就要求人们对他尊敬；不久，他的权利越来越大，神的意志就要求人们服从他。就算他想滥用人们委托给他的权力，他也可以说是神在惩罚其子民。基督教徒会对驱逐篡夺者顾虑重重，因为那意味着妨碍大家的和睦相处，还要动用暴力，导致流血事件，而所有这些极不符合基督教的温和精神。一个人活在苦难的世间，是享受自由还是当个奴隶都无所谓，重要的只有上天堂这一件事，而听天由命正是升入天堂的方法之一。

假如爆发了一场对外战争，公民们会欣然上战场；他们当中没有人会想逃之夭夭；大家都会尽义务——不过他们不以胜利的激情来尽义务；比起如何打胜仗，他们更知道如何去献身。他们不在乎自己是胜利者还是失败者。上帝难道不比他们更清楚什么是必要的吗？可想而知，一个得意的、蛮横的、意气风发的敌人会从他们的斯多葛哲学中汲取到什么好处。找一个慷慨激昂、内心充满对荣誉和国家的热爱的民族，让基督徒去与他们对战吧；设想一下基督教共和国遇上斯巴达或古罗马，那些虔诚的基督教徒在发挥出他们的聪明才智之前就会被挫败、镇压和消灭；如果没有，那只是因为敌人对他们心怀鄙夷。

我自己认为，费比乌斯手下的士兵们遵循的是非常好的誓言；他们并不发誓要去征服他人，或是为国献身，而只是发誓要以凯旋的姿态归来，他们说到做到。而基督教徒从来不敢这样做；他们会以为这是在试探上帝。

不过，我在谈到基督教共和国时，就已经犯了一个错，因为这两个术语是相互矛盾的。基督教只宣扬奴性和顺从。它的精神对暴政太有利了，以致于专制政治想不得到好处都不行。真正的基督教徒就是要当奴隶的；他们对此很清楚，却毫不在乎；因为尘世的短暂生活在他们眼里太没有价值了。

有人说基督教军队很出色。我否认这种说法。给我展示一下这样的军队吧。据我所知，世上根本就没有这样的例子。人们可能会提到十字军东征。我不会否认十字军东征的英勇无畏，可我必须说，他们决不是基督教徒。他们是牧师的士兵，是教派的公民；他们为了教派的精神家园而战，而教派却以某种奇特的方式使这个精神家园落在了现实世界。严格地说，这个讨论又属于异教的主题了；因为既然福音书从不创立任何国教，那么在基督教徒当中便不可能有神圣的战争。

在异教徒君主的统治下，基督教徒士兵个个骁勇善战。所有基督徒作家都告诉我们这一点。我相信他们说的；但那些士兵正是为了抗击异教徒的荣誉才战斗。一旦君主们都成为基督教徒，这种对抗就会终止；一旦十字架将鹰驱赶出去，所有古罗马人的英勇无畏精神就会消失。

现在把政治考虑搁置一边，让我们回到关于权利的问题上来，再确定一下解决这个重要问题的种种原则。如我所说，社会公约给予主权者统治臣民的权利不能超过公共实用的界限。[43]臣民没有义务向主权者说明他们的信仰，除非那些信仰对共同体来说意义重大。有一点对国家非常关键，那就是每个公民都应该有一种使其热爱自己职责的宗教，但那种宗教的教条既不是为国家谋利，也不是为国家成员谋利，除非只要那些教条涉及道德和义务，这些道德和义务就必然为每个以那种宗教为业者所履行。此外，每个人都可以依据自己的喜好持有意见，不必经主权者的审查，因为在另一个世界里，主权者显然没有任何力量；只要臣民在今生的生活中当好公民，他们后世的命运不管怎样都跟主权者无关。

因而，就有了一种纯粹为公民信仰的宣言，而主权者的职能就是确定条条框框。它们并非严格得像宗教的教条，而更像像社会良知的表达，没有这种良知，想成为一个好的公民或一个忠诚的臣民都是不可能的。[44]主权者不能强迫人人都得相信这些条条框框，但可以将任何不相信它们的人驱逐出境；驱逐的理由不是对神不敬，而是由于他是一个反社会的人，不能真诚热爱法律和正义，也不会在必要时为职责牺牲生命。如果有人已经公开接受了教条，他的行为却显示他并不相信它们，那么就把他处死吧，因为他犯下滔天大罪，即在法律面前撒谎的罪。

公民宗教的教条必须既简单又少量，表达精确，无需解释或评注。全能的、理智的、仁慈的、先知先觉神性的存在，来生，正义的快乐，惩罚罪人，社会契约和法律的圣洁——这些都是积极的教条。至于消极的教条，我把它们限于一条：不宽容。它属于我们已经拒绝的宗教之列。

依我看，那些区分政治的不宽容和神学的不宽容的人都错了。不宽容的这两种形式是不可分割的。我们无法与将堕入地狱的人和睦相处，爱他们就等于憎恨将要惩罚他们的神；我们若不挽救他们，就得折磨他们，这是一项责无旁贷的义务。无论神学的不宽容在哪里被应用，它必然造成某种政治的结果，[45]这时，主权者就不再是主权者了，即使是在世俗层面上；在这个阶段，牧师成为真实的主人，而君主只不过成了牧师的办事员。

由于现在没有也不再可能有一个唯一的国教，凡是对其他宗教宽容的宗教，我们就必须宽容，只要它们的教条不含任何与公民的义务相对立的东西。然而，任何敢说“在教堂之外没有拯救”的人都应该从他的国家被驱逐出去，除非那个国家就是教会，并且君主就是主教。这样一种教条只有在神权政体中是好的；而在任何其他政体中却是有害的。据说，亨利四世接受天主教的那个理由，本该使所有诚实的人——特别是所有懂得思考的君主——都放弃天主教。

第九章　结论

在陈述了政治权利的真正原则，并且尝试在这些原则的基础上创建国家之后，我应该思考国家的对外关系，包括国际法、商业、战争权与征服权、公共法、联盟、谈判、条约等等，以此来结束我的研究。但是，所有这些都代表一个新主题，这个主题对才疏识浅的我来说显得太大了；我应该始终关注我力所能及的种种问题。

[1]见普鲁塔克的一篇题为《动物应用理性》的短论文。

[2]古罗马人比世上任何民族都更了解也更尊重战争权。在这方面，他们非常顾忌，以至于在一个公民未正式表示反抗敌人，并特别指名反抗某个敌人之前，不许作为志愿军服役。当小卡图最先参加波比里乌斯领导的军队改编时，老卡图就写信给波比里乌斯说，如果他仍然要他的儿子继续在他手下服役的话，就应让他重新进行一次战争宣誓。其理由是他儿子的第一次宣誓已经无效，儿子不能再扛枪杀敌。卡图还写信给儿子，警告他没有再宣誓就别参战。＜br/＞我知道，有人可能引用克鲁修姆之围和古罗马历史上的其他例子来反驳我，但我引用的是法律和惯例。没有哪个民族会比古罗马人更遵纪守法，也没有哪个民族会比古罗马人有如此完善的法律。

[3]当城镇与城市被认为是同一的东西，公民被认为跟市民一样时，这个名词的真正含义在近代几乎完全消失了。人们忘了，城镇是由房屋构成的，而只有市民才能构成城市。迦太基人曾为这一错误付出惨重的代价。我从未见过（公民）这个称号赋予任何君主统治下的臣民，即使对古代马其顿人或当今英国人也不行，尽管他们比其他民族都更接近自由。唯独法语以相似的意思来处理“公民”这个词，因为他们不知道这个词是什么意思，他们的不同词典已证明了这一点。如果真知道这词的含义，他们就要犯大逆不道的篡位罪了。事实上，他们用这个词表示社会地位，而不表示合法权利。当博丹要表达公民与市民时，他完全错误地张冠李戴。达朗贝先生没犯这个错误，并且在他的《日内瓦》一文里，正确区别我们城镇所发现的四个等级的人（或五个等级的人，如果算上异邦人的话），而其中两个等级的人组成共和国。就我所知，没有别的法国作家了解“公民”这个词的真正含义。

[4]在一个不良政府的统治下，这种平等只是一种表面现象，一种幻想。它只能使穷人继续处于悲惨的境地，使富人继续处在富有的地位。事实上，法律总是有益于拥有财产的人，而对一无所有的人却是有害的。由此可见，只有当大家都拥有一些东西而又无人拥有过多的东西时，这种社会状态才会对人有益。

[5]由于意志要成为公意，所以意志没必要总是全体一致，但必须把全部票数都计算在内。任何形式上的例外都会破坏其普遍性。

[6]阿冉松侯爵说过：“每种利益都有其不同的原则。两种利益之间的协调是由与第三种利益相对立而形成的。”他可能会补充说，所有利益的协调是由与个人利益相对立而形成的。如果没有不同利益的话，我们就几乎意识不到一种永远都碰不到障碍的共同利益。一切都将轻松自如地运转，政治也就不再是一种艺术了。

[7]马基雅维利说：“事实上，划分有时有害于一个共和国，有时则是有益的。害处是由派系派别造成的，而益处则是由没有派系派别的党派带来的。因此，既然一个国家的缔造者不可能预防敌意，至少他必须尽可能预防派系纠纷。”（见《佛罗伦萨史》第七卷）

[8]请细心的读者不要因为矛盾而急于责备我。由于语言贫乏，所以我无法避免用语上的矛盾，不过等待吧。

[9]“共和的”这个词，我不仅理解贵族制或民主制，而且还大致理解在成为法律的公意指导下的任何政府。如果公意是合法的，政府就不能与主权者混为一谈，而只能是主权者的执政人，从而君主制也可以是共和制。这一点将在第三卷中加以说明。

[10]一个民族直到其国体开始衰退时才出名。我们不知道，在争相谈论希腊其他地方之前，莱格古士的国体给斯巴达人带来了多少世纪的幸福。

[11]把加尔文只当作是一位神学家的那些人，并没有意识到其天才的程度。他在我们充满智慧的法令汇编中起到很大的作用，这给他带来的莫大荣誉不亚于他的《基督教要义》。无论怎样的革命可能在我们的宗教信仰中发生，当对祖国和自由的热爱在我们心中没有泯灭时，那些宗教家们将永远以崇敬的心情缅怀这位伟人。

[12]马基雅维利在文中写道：“事实上，在任何国家从没有过任何不求助于上帝的特殊立法者；否则，法律便不为人所接受；一个智者知道许多有用的真理，而这些真理无法以像说服他人那样的一种方式加以示范。”（《论李维》第五卷第十一章）（原文为意大利语——译者注）

[13]（在1782年版中被修订为“大多数民族……”。——译者注）

[14]如果两个相邻的民族彼此依存，这种状况对一方是艰难而对另一方却是危险的。在这种情况下，任何聪明的民族都将尽快地让另一个民族从这种依附状态下摆脱出来。处于墨西哥帝国包围中的斯拉斯加拉共和国，不但不向墨西哥人购买食盐度日，甚至也不接受他们馈赠的食盐。聪明的斯拉斯加拉人看出隐藏在对方宽宏大量背后的阴谋诡计。他们维护了自己的自由，而这个封锁在大帝国领土内的小国最终成为帝国毁亡的原因。

[15]你希望国家具有凝聚力吗？那么就尽可能地消除贫富悬殊现象吧；不许有富豪，也不许有赤贫。这两个自然分化的阶级对公共幸福来说是同样致命的；一个阶级会产生暴政的支持者，而另一个阶级则会产生暴君。这两个阶级始终在做公共自由的交易：一个购买自由，另一个则出卖自由。

[16]阿冉松侯爵说过：“任何外贸部门对整个王国来说，都只不过带来一种虚幻的利益；它可以使一些人甚至一些城市发财致富，但是整个国家却一无所获，而且全体人民的生活也没有因此变得更好。”

[17]因此，在威尼斯人们仍称大议会为最尊敬的君主，即使当大公不出席的时候。

[18]波兹南侯爵，即波兰国王的父亲，洛林公爵。

[19]“我愿自由而有危险，但不愿安宁而受奴役。”

[20]很显然，对古人来说“贵族”这个词并不是指最好，而是指最强。

[21]最为重要的是，必须用法律来规定行政官的选举方式；因为如果这是委托给君主的意志，那就不可避免地会沦为世袭贵族制，就像威尼斯共和国和伯尔尼共和国曾发生过的那样。威尼斯长期以来就是一个衰败的国家，而伯尔尼则仅由于其元老院极其英明才得以生存——这一规则无一例外是很荣耀的，可也是很危险的。

[22]马基雅维利是个绅士，也是个良好公民；可因为他依附于梅狄奇家族，所以不得不在国人的压迫下把对自由的热爱伪装起来。他恰好选择了一位可恶的主人公，这就显示了他的秘密意图；而他的《君王论》一书的准则与他的《李维论》和《佛罗伦萨史》两书的准则之间相互对立，这种对立证明，这位深刻的政治思想家至今都只有一些肤浅的或曲解的读者。罗马教皇曾严禁这本书。我确信这一点，因为这本书描写得最直白的就是罗马宫廷。

[23]“因为辨别好坏最有效也是最简洁的方法，就是假如做国王的不是自己而是另一个人的话，想一想自己要什么，不要什么。”（见塔西佗《历史》，第一卷）

[24]这跟我在第二卷第九章论大国的劣势时所说的并不矛盾，因为前面我论述的是政府对其成员的权威，而这里的问题则是它对付臣民的势力。它分散各地的官员，作为它从远距离给公民施压的许多支点，可它却没有可以给官员施压的支点。因此，在一种情况下，杠杆过长便成了政府的软肋；而在另一种情况下，则又成了政府的力量。

[25]人们必须根据这同一条原则来判断，就人类繁荣而言，哪些是值得我们赞许的世纪。对于所目睹的工艺品和文学的繁荣，我们赞美得太多了，但却从未深究这些文化隐藏的目的，也未考虑它们致命的后果：“愚人称之为人道的，其实那已是奴役的开始。”难道在书中的那些箴言背后，我们就看不出促使作者们说的那些原始的私利吗？不，无论他们说些什么，一个国家尽管灿烂辉煌，可只要其人口减少，就绝不会真的是一切都好。一个诗人年薪十万里弗，这不足以说明他所处的就是历史长河中最好的时代。应该少考虑表面的平静和统治者的安宁，而更多地关注整个民族的幸福，特别是那些人口最多国家的幸福。冰雹可能毁坏一些国家的行政区，却很少造成饥荒。骚动和内战可能引起统治者的强烈恐慌，它们却并非民族真正的不幸；当谁是下一个暴君尚未定论时，公民至少有数月可以休养生息。他们的灾难和幸福都起于他们的持久状态。当大家仍处在枷锁的束缚时，一切都将衰败；只有在这时统治者才能任意摧残公民，当他们把国土沦为废墟时，他们会说和平到来了。当举国的争论搅动着法兰西王国时，当巴黎副主教怀揣匕首出席会议时，这并不妨碍法国公民在一种真正自由的安逸中享受幸福，生儿育女。古希腊是在最残酷的战争中达到繁盛的巅峰；虽然血流成河，可是整个国土上还是住满了人。马基雅维利说过：“看起来我们的共和国似乎就是在暗杀、流放与内战之中变得比以往任何时候都强大；公民的德行、道德与独立性起到的加强国家的作用，胜过一切争端引起的削弱作用。”一点点震荡倒会使人们的内在富有活力；真正能使种族繁荣昌盛的不是和平，而是自由。

[26]威尼斯共和国在其环礁湖中缓慢形成与发展，提供了这个过程一个值得注意的范例；一千二百多年之后，威尼斯人似乎仍处在1198年由西拉尔·康塞里奥开启的第二个阶段，这真令人惊讶。至于人们所责难的那些古代大公们，无论《威尼斯自由论》这本书怎么讲，都不是他们的主权者，这一点有据可循。＜br/＞肯定会有人引用罗马共和国的例子来反驳我，说罗马共和国遵循了一个完全相反的时间顺序，它从君主制过渡到贵族制，再从贵族制过渡到民主制。可我却决不同意这种看法。＜br/＞罗穆鲁斯最初创建的是一个混合政府，这个混合政府迅速退化为一个专制政体。由于特殊原因，这个国家过早夭折，就像人们有时看到婴儿在未成年以前就死去一样。驱逐塔尔干王朝之日才是共和国真正诞生之时。但是罗马共和国起初并非采取一种固定的形式，因为罗马人尚未废除贵族制，只是半途而废。因为在所有合法管理机构中最糟糕的世袭贵族制仍然与民主制相冲突，所以政府的形式总是变幻不定，直到设立保民官时才固定下来（正如马基雅维利证明过的一样）；只有到那时才有了真正的政府和真正的民主制；事实上，到那时公民不仅是主权者，还是行政官和法官；元老院不过是一个从属的执政议会，用以调和与集中政权，而执政官本身——尽管他们是贵族、首席行政官、战时的绝对指挥官——在罗马不过是公民的议长罢了。＜br/＞从那时起，我们看得出来，罗马政府遵循其自然倾向并强烈地趋于贵族制。贵族制似乎是自我毁灭，因此也就不再处于贵族的主体内，像是在威尼斯和热那亚一样，而是处在由贵族和平民所组成的元老院的主体内，甚至处在——当保民官开始篡夺主动权时——保民官的主体内，因为名字是改变不了什么的，所以当公民有了代表他们治理国家的首领时，无论这些人有什么称号，这仍然是一个贵族制。＜br/＞贵族制的滥用造成了内战与三人执政的局面。苏拉、尤利西斯·恺撒、奥古斯都实际上相当于君主；最后，在提贝留乌斯的专制下，国家终于解体。那么，罗马的历史不是与我的原则不相符，而是肯定了我的原则。

[27]“凡是在一个习惯于自由的城市里永远当权的人，就会被人称为或视为暴君。”（见科尔奈利乌斯·尼波斯的《密蒂阿德传》）确实，亚里士多德（见《尼各马可伦理学》第八卷第十章）区分过暴君与国王，暴君是为自己的利益而统治，国王则只是为臣民的利益而统治；然而，所有的希腊作家通常都在另一层意思上使用“暴君”这个词，尤其像色诺芬所写的《希罗》那样；此外，根据亚里士多德的这一准则还可以得出：自从有了这个世界，还从未有过一个国王。

[28]这个词在此的用法有几分英国议会所具有的意思。纵然一切管辖权都巳中止，这种职能之间的相似性还是会引起执政官与保民官之间的冲突的。

[29]要在寒冷的国家接受东方人的奢侈与温柔，就等于想给自己戴上枷锁，也就等于比东方人更不可避免地向这两者屈服。

[30]这就是我在本书剩余部分所要做的事，在论述对外关系中，我将要涉及到邦联制的主题。这是一个全新的主题，其原则还有待确定。

[31]这可以理解为：没有人可能为逃避职责而离开自己的国家，或者当国家需要他时为避免拯救自己的国家而离开。在这种情况下，逃跑一定是犯罪，该受惩罚；逃跑不一定是撤退，而一定是潜逃。

[32]这应该始终理解为仅指自由的国家，因为在别处家庭、财产、缺乏庇护、必需品以及暴力，这些都可能勉强使一个居民留在国内；到那时纯粹的居住不再表示他是同意契约还是违背契约。

[33]在热那亚，所有监狱的大门上和大帆船的锁链上，都可以看到“自由”这个词。把这个词当作座右铭来用真是美妙又恰当。其实，正是各国犯罪分子才妨碍公民得到自由。在一个所有这般人都在大帆船上的国家里，人们一定会享受到最完美的自由。

[34]“罗马”这个名字，据说出自罗穆鲁斯，其实是希腊语，意思是“力量”；“努玛”这个名字也是希腊语，意思是“法律”。罗马城最早的两位国王在其执政前就有了与他们所从事的事业极其有关的名字，这样的可能性有多大呢？

[35]我之所以说“玛尔斯教场”，是因为百人团大会在这里召开。至于集会的其他两种形式，人民在广场上或在别的地方开会，而“按人头计数”的人就具有跟一流公民同样的影响和权威。

[36]被这样抽中的百人团享有“优先权”，因为要求它第一个投票；这就是我们所用的“特权”这个词的由来。

[37]这一任命在夜间秘密进行，好像他们为把一个人凌驾于法律之上而感到羞耻。

[38]如果他提出任命一名独裁者，他原本对此并无把握，因为他既不敢毛遂自荐，也无法确定他的同僚会提他的名。

[39]‘Nonne ea quae possidet Chamos deus tuus, tibi jure debentur?’，这句话是拉丁文圣经的原文。贾立蔼神父将它译为：“你们难道不认为有权拥有属于你们的神基抹的东西吗？”我不知道希伯来原文写的是什么；可我注意到：在拉丁文中耶弗肯定地承认神基抹的权力，但是法语译文却增加了拉丁文本中所没有的“依你的说法”，从而削弱了原意。

[40]那场号称圣战的福西人的战争并不是一场宗教战争。其目的是要惩罚渎神者，而不是要使不信教者屈从，这显然没有争论的余地。

[41]应当注意到，把教士集中在一个团体中，这并不是很正式的集会（像法国的那样），倒更像是教会的圣餐。圣餐与开除教籍是教士们的社会契约；通过这个公约，他们始终既是人民的主人，又是国王的主人。所有一起沟通的牧师都是同胞公民，纵然他们身处地球的两极。这种发明成为政治的一大杰作。在异教的牧师当中未曾有过像这样的事，所以他们也就从未组织过教士团体。

[42]此外，请看格老秀斯1643年4月11日给他兄弟的一封信，从中可以看出，在《公民论》一书中这位学者赞许什么，反对什么。诚然，他看在作者优点的份上很宽容地原谅了作者的缺点；可并非人人都如此宽宏大度。

[43]阿冉松侯爵说过：“在共和国，每个人都可以完全自由地不做伤害别人的事。”这是一条不可更改的做人底线；人们无法更确切地表达这句话。尽管他的手稿并不为人所知，可是我一直无法否认有时引用他的手稿中时的愉快心情，以对这位卓越可钦的人物表示敬意，甚至作为首相，他还始终保持着一颗真正的公民之心，并且对本国政府持有一种公正、坚定的观点。

[44]恺撒在为卡提里那辩护时，曾试图确立一种灵魂死亡的教条。卡图和西塞罗在反驳这一教条时，根本就不想费功夫用哲学去论证；他们满意地指出：恺撒像一个坏公民那样在发言，并提出一种有害于国家的学说。罗马元老院要判决的正是这一点，而不是什么神学问题。

[45]例如，婚姻是一项公民契约，具有政治影响，没有了这项契约，社会本身想要生存下去是不可能的。现在让我们设想一下，在一个特定的国家，牧师居然获得婚姻许可权，而这种权利也是任何不宽容的宗教必然要争取的；他们就此在提高教会权威中取消君主的权威，那么君主所剩的只有牧师允许他拥有的臣民了，这不是很明显的吗？牧师可以根据人们是否接受这样那样的教义，承认或拒绝这样那样的婚姻，或者根据人们的虔诚程度，如果牧师精明地行事并坚定地执行，难道这不是明显地说，只有它才能适时处理继承、职位、公民等事务，甚至治理国家吗？因为全靠私生子组成的国家是不会长久生存下去的。可你们也许会说，我们可以号召现有的力量，发布命令，授予权利并占领教会财产。多么可怜的见解！如果牧师有一点点的常识——我不是说有一点点的勇气，它会任凭一切顺其自然；它可以安然地让别人去宣告，授权和接管，最终他还是主人。我以为，当你有把握获得整体时，放弃局部并不算作出很大的牺牲。

Book Ⅰ

MY purpose is to consider if, in political society, there can be any legitimate and sure principle of government, taking men as they are and laws as they might be. In this inquiry I shall try always to bring together what right permits with what interest prescribes so that justice and utility are in no way divided.

I start without seeking to prove the importance of my subject. I may be asked whether I am a prince or a legislator that I should be writing about politics. I answer no: and indeed that that is my reason for doing so. If I were a prince or a legislator I should not waste my time saying what ought to be done; I should do it or keep silent.

Born as I was the citizen of a free state and a member of its sovereign body, the very right to vote imposes on me the duty to instruct myself in public affairs, however little influence my voice may have in them. And whenever I reflect upon governments, I am happy to find that my studies always give me fresh reasons for admiring that of my own country.

CHAPTER 1

The subject of Book Ⅰ

MAN was born free, and he is everywhere in chains. Those who think themselves the masters of others are indeed greater slaves than they. How did this transformation come about? I do not know. How can it be made legitimate? That question I believe I can answer.

If I were to consider only force and the effects of force, I should say: 'So long as a people is constrained to obey, and obeys, it does well; but as soon as it can shake off the yoke, and shakes it off, it does better; for since it regains its freedom by the same right as that which removed it, a people is either justified in taking back its freedom, or there is no justifying those who took it away.' But the social order is a sacred right which serves as a basis for all other rights. And as it is not a natural right, it must be one founded on covenants. The problem is to determine what those covenants are. But before we pass on to that question, I must substantiate what I have so far said.

CHAPTER 2

The First Societies

THE oldest of all societies, and the only natural one, is that of the family; yet children remain tied to their father by nature only so long as they need him for their preservation. As soon as this need ends, the natural bond is dissolved. Once the children are freed from the obedience they owe their father, and the father is freed from his responsibilities towards them, both parties equally regain their independence. If they continue to remain united, it is no longer nature, but their own choice, which unites them; and the family as such is kept in being only by agreement.

This common liberty is a consequence of man's nature. Man's first law is to watch over his own preservation; his first care he owes to himself; and as soon as he reaches the age of reason, he becomes the only judge of the best means to preserve himself; he becomes his own master.

The family may therefore perhaps be seen as the first model of political societies: the head of the state bears the image of the father, the people the image of his children, and all, being born free and equal, surrender their freedom only when they see advantage in doing so. The only difference is that in the family, a father's love for his children repays him for the care he bestows on them, while in the state, where the ruler can have no such feeling for his people, the pleasure of commanding must take the place of love.

Grotius denies that all human government is established for the benefit of the governed, and he cites the example of slavery. His characteristic method of reasoning is always to offer fact as a proof of right.[【1】] It is possible to imagine a more logical method, but not one more favourable to tyrants.

According to Grotius, therefore, it is doubtful whether humanity belongs to a hundred men, or whether these hundred men belong to humanity, though he seems throughout his book to lean to the first of these views, which is also that of Hobbes. These authors show us the human race divided into herds of cattle, each with a master who preserves it only in order to devour its members.

Just as a shepherd possesses a nature superior to that of his flock, so do those shepherds of men, their rulers, have a nature superior to that of their people. Or so, we are told by Philo, the Emperor Caligula argued, concluding, reasonably enough on this same analogy, that kings were gods or alternatively that the people were animals.

The reasoning of Caligula coincides with that of Hobbes and Grotius. Indeed Aristotle, before any of them, said that men were not at all equal by nature, since some were born for slavery and others born to be masters.

Aristotle was right; but he mistook the effect for the cause. Anyone born in slavery is born for slavery—nothing is more certain. Slaves, in their bondage, lose everything, even the desire to be free. They love their servitude even as the companions of Ulysses loved their life as brutes.[【2】] But if there are slaves by nature, it is only because there has been slavery against nature. Force made the first slaves; and their cowardice perpetuates their slavery.

I have said nothing of the King Adam or of the Emperor Noah, father of the three great monarchs who shared out the universe between them, like the children of Saturn, with whom some authors have identified them. I hope my readers will be grateful for this moderation, for since I am directly descended from one of those princes, and perhaps in the eldest line, how do I know that if the deeds were checked, I might not find myself the legitimate king of the human race? However that may be, there is no gainsaying that Adam was the king of the world, as was Robinson Crusoe of his island, precisely because he was the sole inhabitant; and the great advantage of such an empire was that the monarch, secure upon his throne, had no occasion to fear rebellions, wars or conspirators.

CHAPTER 3

The Right of the Strongest

THE strongest man is never strong enough to be master all the time, unless he transforms force into right and obedience into duty. Hence 'the right of the strongest'—a 'right' that sounds like something intended ironically, but is actually laid down as a principle. But shall we never have this phrase explained? Force is a physical power; I do not see how its effects could produce morality. To yield to force is an act of necessity, not of will; it is at best an act of prudence. In what sense can it be a moral duty?

Let us grant, for a moment, that this so-called right exists. I suggest it can only produce a tissue of bewildering nonsense; for once might is made to be right, cause and effect are reversed, and every force which overcomes another force inherits the right which belonged to the vanquished. As soon as man can disobey with impunity, his disobedience becomes legitimate; and as the strongest is always right, the only problem is how to become the strongest. But what can be the validity of a right which perishes with the force on which it rests? If force compels obedience, there is no need to invoke a duty to obey, and if force ceases to compel obedience, there is no longer any obligation. Thus the word 'right' adds nothing to what is said by 'force'; it is meaningless.

'Obey those in power.' If this means 'yield to force' the precept is sound, but superfluous; it will never, I suggest, be violated. All power comes from God, I agree; but so does every disease, and no one forbids us to summon a physician. If I am held up by a robber at the edge of a wood, force compels me to hand over my purse. But if I could somehow contrive to keep the purse from him, would I still be obliged in conscience to surrender it? After all, the pistol in the robber's hand is undoubtedly a power.

Surely it must be admitted, then, that might does not make right, and that the duty of obedience is owed only to legitimate powers. Thus we are constantly led back to my original question.

CHAPTER 4

Slavery

SINCE no man has any natural authority over his fellows, and since force alone bestows no right, all legitimate authority among men must be based on covenants.

Grotius says: 'If an individual can alienate his freedom and become the slave of a master, why may not a whole people alienate its freedom and become the subject of a king?' In this remark there are several ambiguous words which call for explanation; but let us confine ourselves to one — to 'alienate'. To alienate is to give or sell. A man who becomes the slave of another does not give himself, he sells himself in return for at least a subsistence. But in return for what could a whole people be said to sell itself? A king, far from nourishing his subjects, draws his nourishment from them; and kings, according to Rabelais, need more than a little nourishment. Do subjects, then, give their persons to the king on condition that he will accept their property as well? If so, I fail to see what they have left to preserve.

It will be said that a despot gives his subjects the assurance of civil tranquillity. Very well, but what does it profit them, if those wars against other powers which result from a despot's ambition, if his insatiable greed, and the oppressive demands of his administration, cause more desolation than civil strife would cause? What do the people gain if their very condition of civil tranquillity is one of their hardships? There is peace in dungeons, but is that enough to make dungeons desirable? The Greeks lived in peace in the cave of Cyclops awaiting their turn to be devoured.

To speak of a man giving himself in return for nothing is to speak of what is absurd, unthinkable; such an action would be illegitimate, void, if only because no one who did it could be in his right mind. To say the same of a whole people is to conjure up a nation of lunatics; and right cannot rest on madness.

Even if each individual could alienate himself, he cannot alienate his children. For they are born men; they are born free; their liberty belongs to them; no one but they themselves has the right to dispose of it. Before they reach the years of discretion, their father may, in their name, make certain rules for their protection and their welfare, but he cannot give away their liberty irrevocably and unconditionally, for such a gift would be contrary to the ends of nature and an abuse of paternal right. Hence, an arbitrary government would be legitimate only if every new generation were able to accept or reject it, and in that case the government would cease to be arbitrary.

To renounce freedom is to renounce one's humanity, one's rights as a man and equally one's duties. There is no possible quid pro quo for one who renounces everything; indeed such renunciation is contrary to man's very nature; for if you take away all freedom of the will, you strip a man's actions of all moral significance. Finally, any covenant which stipulated absolute dominion for one party and absolute obedience for the other would be illogical and nugatory. Is it not evident that he who is entitled to demand everything owes nothing? And does not the single fact of there being no reciprocity, no mutual obligation, nullify the act? For what right can my slave have against me? If everything he has belongs to me, his right is my right, and it would be nonsense to speak of my having a right against myself.

Grotius and the rest claim to find in war another justification for the so-called right of slavery. They argue that the victor's having the right to kill the vanquished implies that the vanquished has the right to purchase his life at the expense of his liberty — a bargain thought to be the more legitimate because it is advantageous to both parties.

But it is clear that this so-called right to kill the vanquished cannot be derived from the state of war. For this reason alone, that men living in their primitive condition of independence have no intercourse regular enough to constitute either a state of peace or a state of war; and men are not naturally enemies. It is conflicts over things, not quarrels between men which constitute war, and the state of war cannot arise from mere personal relations, but only from property relations. Private wars between one man and another can exist neither in a state of nature, where there is no fixed property, nor in society, where everything is under the authority of law.

Private fights, duels, skirmishes, do not constitute any kind of state; and as for the private wars that were permitted by the ordinances of Louis Ⅸ, King of France, and suspended by the Peace of God, these were no more than an abuse of feudal government, an irrational system if there ever was one, and contrary both to natural justice and to all sound polity.

War, then, is not a relation between men, but between states; in war individuals are enemies wholly by chance, not as men, not even as citizens,[【3】] but only as soldiers; not as members of their country, but only as its defenders. In a word, a state can have as an enemy only another state, not men, because there can be no real relation between things possessing different intrinsic natures.

This principle conforms to the established rules of all times and to the constant practice of every political society. Declarations of war are warnings not so much to governments as to their subjects. The foreigner —whether he is a king, a private person or a whole people — who robs, kills or detains the subjects of another prince without first declaring war against that prince, is not an enemy but a brigand. Even in the midst of war, a just prince, seizing what he can of public property in the enemy's territory, nevertheless respects the persons and possessions of private individuals; he respects the principles on which his own rights are based. Since the aim of war is to subdue a hostile state, a combatant has the right to kill the defenders of that state while they are armed; but as soon as they lay down their arms and surrender, they cease to be either enemies or instruments of the enemy; they become simply men once more, and no one has any longer the right to take their lives. It is sometimes possible to destroy a state without killing a single one of its members, and war gives no right to inflict any more destruction than is necessary for victory. These principles were not invented by Grotius, nor are they founded on the authority of the poets; they are derived from the nature of things; they are based on reason.

The right of conquest has no other foundation than the law of the strongest. And if war gives the conqueror no right to massacre a conquered people, no such right can be invoked to justify their enslavement. Men have the right to kill their enemies only when they cannot enslave them, so the right of enslaving cannot be derived from the right to kill. It would therefore be an iniquitous barter to make the vanquished purchase with their liberty the lives over which the victor has no legitimate claim. An argument basing the right over life and death on the right to enslave, and the right to enslave on the right over life and death, is an argument trapped in a vicious circle.

Even if we assumed that this terrible right of massacre did exist, then slaves of war, or a conquered people, would be under no obligation to obey their master any further than they were forced to do so. By taking an equivalent of his victim's life, the victor shows him no favour; instead of destroying him unprofitably, he destroys him by exploiting him. Hence, far from the victor having acquired some further authority besides that of force over the vanquished, the state of war between them continues; their mutual relation is the effect of war, and the continuation of the rights of war implies that there has been no treaty of peace. An agreement has assuredly been made, but that agreement, far from ending the state of war, presupposes its continuation.

Thus, however we look at the question, the 'right' of slavery is seen to be void; void, not only because it cannot be justified, but also because it is nonsensical, because it has no meaning. The words 'slavery' and 'right' are contradictory, they cancel each other out. Whether as between one man and another, or between one man and a whole people, it would always be absurd to say: 'I hereby make a covenant with you which is wholly at your expense and wholly to my advantage; I will respect it so long as I please and you shall respect it so long as I wish.'

CHAPTER 5

That We Must Always Go Back To an Original Covenant

EVEN if I were to concede all that I have so far refuted, the champions of despotism would be no better off. There will always be a great differece between subduing a multitude and ruling a society. If one man successively enslaved many separate individuals, no matter how numerous, he and they would never bear the aspect of anything but a master and his slaves, not at all that of a people and their ruler; an aggregation, perhaps, but certainly not an association, for they would neither have a common good nor be a body politic. Even if such a man were to enslave half the world, he would remain a private individual, and his interest, always distinct from that of the others, would never be more than a personal interest. When he died, the empire he left would be scattered for lack of any bond of union, even as an oak crumbles and falls into a heap of ashes when fire has consumed it.

'A people,' says Grotius, 'may give itself to a king.' Therefore, according to Grotius a people is a people even before the gift to the king is made. The gift itself is a civil act; it presupposes public deliberation. Hence, before considering the act by which a people submits to a king, we ought to scrutinize the act by which people become a people, for that act, being necessarily antecedent to the other, is the real foundation of society.

In fact, if there were no earlier agreement, how, unless the election were unanimous, could there be any obligation on the minority to accept the decision of the majority? What right have the hundred who want to have a master to vote on behalf of the ten who do not? The law of majority-voting itself rests on an agreement, and implies that there has been on at least one occasion unanimity.

CHAPTER 6

The Social Pact

I ASSUME that men reach a point where the obstacles to their preservation in a state of nature prove greater than the strength that each man has to preserve himself in that state. Beyond this point, the primitive condition cannot endure, for then the human race will perish if it does not change its mode of existence.

Since men cannot create new forces, but merely combine and control those which already exist, the only way in which they can preserve themselves is by uniting their separate powers in a combination strong enough to overcome any resistance, uniting them so that their powers are directed by a single motive and act in concert.

Such a sum of forces can be produced only by the union of separate men, but as each man's own strength and liberty are the chief instruments of his preservation, how can he merge his with others' without putting himself in peril and neglecting the care he owes to himself? This difficulty, in terms of my present subject, may be expressed in these words:

'How to find a form of association which will defend the person and goods of each member with the collective force of all, and under which each individual, while uniting himself with the others, obeys no one but himself, and remains as free as before.' This is the fundamental problem to which the social contract holds the solution.

The articles of this contract are so precisely determined by the nature of the act, that the slightest modification must render them null and void; they are such that, though perhaps never formally stated, they are everywhere the same, everywhere tacitly admitted and recognized; and if ever the social pact is violated, every man regains his original rights and, recovering his natural freedom, loses that civil freedom for which he exchanged it.

These articles of association, rightly understood, are reducible to a single one, namely the total alienation by each associate of himself and all his rights to the whole community. Thus, in the first place, as every individual gives himself absolutely, the conditions are the same for all, and precisely because they are the same for all, it is in no one's interest to make the conditions onerous for others.

Secondly, since the alienation is unconditional, the union is as perfect as it can be, and no individual associate has any longer any rights to claim; for if rights were left to individuals, in the absence of any higher authority to judge between them and the public, each individual, being his own judge in some causes, would soon demand to be his own judge in all; and in this way the state of nature would be kept in being, and the association inevitably become either tyrannical or void.

Finally, since each man gives himself to all, he gives himself to no one; and since there is no associate over whom he does not gain the same rights as others gain over him, each man recovers the equivalent of everything he loses, and in the bargain he acquires more power to preserve what he has.

If, then, we eliminate from the social pact everything that is not essential to it, we find it comes down to this: 'Each one of us puts into the community his person and all his powers under the supreme direction of the general will; and as a body, we incorporate every member as an indivisible part of the whole.'

Immediately, in place of the individual person of each contracting party, this act of association creates an artificial and corporate body composed of as many members as there are voters in the assembly, and by this same act that body acquires its unity, its common ego, its life and its will. The public person thus formed by the union of all other persons was once called the city,[【4】] and is now known as the republic or the body politic. In its passive role it is called the state, when it plays an active role it is the sovereign; and when it is compared to others of its own kind, it is a power. Those who are associated in it take collectively the name of a people, and call themselves individually citizens, in that they share in the sovereign power, and subjects, in that they put themselves under the laws of the state. However, these words are often confused, each being mistaken for another; but the essential thing is to know how to recognize them when they are used in their precise sense.

CHAPTER 7

The Sovereign

THIS formula shows that the act of association consists of a reciprocal commitment between society and the individual, so that each person, in making a contract, as it were, with himself, finds himself doubly committed, first, as a member of the sovereign body in relation to individuals, and secondly as a member of the state in relation to the sovereign. Here there can be no invoking the principle of civil law which says that no man is bound by a contract with himself, for there is a great difference between having an obligation to oneself and having an obligation to something of which one is a member.

We must add that a public decision can impose an obligation on all the subjects towards the sovereign, by reason of the two aspects under which each can be seen, while, contrariwise, such decisions cannot impose an obligation on the sovereign towards itself; and hence it would be against the very nature of a political body for the sovereign to set over itself a law which it could not infringe. The sovereign, bearing only one single and identical aspect, is in the position of a private person making a contract with himself, which shows that there neither is, nor can be, any kind of fundamental law binding on the people as a body, not even the social contract itself. This does not mean that the whole body cannot incur obligations to other nations, so long as those obligations do not infringe the contract; for in relation to foreign powers, the body politic is a simple entity, an individual.

However, since the body politic, or sovereign, owes its being to the sanctity of the contract alone, it cannot commit itself, even in treaties with foreign powers, to anything that would derogate from the original act of association; it could not, for example, alienate a part of itself or submit to another sovereign. To violate the act which has given it existence would be to annihilate itself; and what is nothing can produce nothing.

As soon as the multitude is united thus in a single body, no one can injure any one of the members without attacking the whole, still less injure the whole without each member feeling it. Duty and self-interest thus equally oblige the two contracting parties to give each other mutual aid; and the same men should seek to bring together in this dual relationship, all the advantages that flow from it.

Now, as the sovereign is formed entirely of the individuals who compose it, it has not, nor could it have, any interest contrary to theirs; and so the sovereign has no need to give guarantees to the subjects, because it is impossible for a body to wish to hurt all of its members, and, as we shall see, it cannot hurt any particular member. The sovereign by the mere fact that it is, is always all that it ought to be.

But this is not true of the relation of subject to sovereign. Despite their common interest, subjects will not be bound by their commitment unless means are found to guarantee their fidelity.

For every individual as a man may have a private will contrary to, or different from, the general will that he has as a citizen. His private interest may speak with a very different voice from that of the public interest; his absolute and naturally independent existence may make him regard what he owes to the common cause as a gratuitous contribution, the loss of which would be less painful for others than the payment is onerous for him; and fancying that the artificial person which constitutes the state is a mere fictitious entity (since it is not a man), he might seek to enjoy the rights of a citizen without doing the duties of a subject. The growth of this kind of injustice would bring about the ruin of the body politic.

Hence, in order that the social pact shall not be an empty formula, it is tacitly implied in that commitment — which alone can give force to all others — that whoever refuses to obey the general will shall be constrained to do so by the whole body, which means nothing other than that he shall be forced to be free; for this is the necessary condition which, by giving each citizen to the nation, secures him against all personal dependence, it is the condition which shapes both the design and the working of the political machine, and which alone bestows justice on civil contracts — without it, such contracts would be absurd, tyrannical and liable to the grossest abuse.

CHAPTER 8

Civil Society

THE passing from the state of nature to the civil society produces a remarkable change in man; it puts justice as a rule of conduct in the place of instinct, and gives his actions the moral quality they previously lacked. It is only then, when the voice of duty has taken the place of physical impulse, and right that of desire, that man, who has hitherto thought only of himself, finds himself compelled to act on other principles, and to consult his reason rather than study his inclinations. And although in civil society man surrenders some of the advantages that belong to the state of nature, he gains in return far greater ones; his faculties are so exercised and developed, his mind is so enlarged, his sentiments so ennobled, and his whole spirit so elevated that, if the abuse of his new condition did not in many cases lower him to something worse than what he had left, he should constantly bless the happy hour that lifted him for ever from the state of nature and from a stupid, limited animal made a creature of intelligence and a man.

Suppose we draw up a balance sheet, so that the losses and gains may be readily compared. What man loses by the social contract is his natural liberty and the absolute right to anything that tempts him and that he can take; what he gains by the social contract is civil liberty and the legal right of property in what he possesses. If we are to avoid mistakes in weighing the one side against the other, we must clearly distinguish between natural liberty, which has no limit but the physical power of the individual concerned, and civil liberty, which is limited by the general will; and we must distinguish also between possession, which is based only on force or 'the right of the first occupant', and property, which must rest on a legal title.

We might also add that man acquires with civil society, moral freedom, which alone makes man the master of himself; for to be governed by appetite alone is slavery, while obedience to a law one prescribes to oneself is freedom. However, I have already said more than enough on this subject, and the philosophical meaning of the word 'freedom' is no part of my subject here.

CHAPTER 9

Of Property

EVERY member of the community gives himself to it at the moment it is brought into being just as he is — he himself, with all his resources, including all his goods. This is not to say that possession by this act changes its nature in changing hands and becomes property in the grasp of the sovereign; but rather, that as the resources of the nation are incomparably greater than those of an individual, public possession is in simple fact more secure and more irrevocable than private possession, without being any more legitimate — at any rate, in the eyes of foreigners; for the state, vis-à-vis its own members, becomes master of all their goods by virtue of the social contract, which serves, within the state, as the basis of all other rights; while vis-à-vis other nations, the state has only the 'right of the first occupant', which it derives from individuals.

The 'right of the first occupant', although more real than the 'right of the strongest', does not become a true right until the institution of property. Every man has a natural right to what he needs; but the positive act which makes a man the proprietor of any estate excludes him from everything else. His share having once been settled, he must confine himself to it, and he has no further right against the community. Thus we see how 'the right of the first occupant', weak as it is in the state of nature, compels in political society the respect of all men. What this right makes one aware of is less what belongs to others than what does not belong to oneself.

As a general rule, to justify the right of the first occupant to any piece of land whatever, the following conditions must obtain: first, that the land shall not already be inhabited by anyone else; secondly, that the claimant occupies no more than he needs for subsistence; thirdly, that he takes possession, not by an idle ceremony, but by actually working and cultivating the soil — the only sign of ownership which need be respected by other people in the absence of a legal title.

It can, indeed, be said that tying 'the right of the first occupant' to need and work is stretching it as far as it will go. Can one really avoid setting limits on the right? Is it enough to put one's feet on a piece of common land in order to claim it at once as one's own? Is it enough to have the power to keep other men off for one moment in order to deprive them of the right ever to return? How could a man or a people seize a vast territory and keep out the rest of the human race except by a criminal usurpation — since the action would rob the rest of mankind of the shelter and the food that nature has given them all in common? When Nunez Balbao stood on the shore and took possession of the southern seas and of South America in the name of the crown of Castille, was that enough to dispossess all the inhabitants and to exclude all the other princes of the world? If so, such idle ceremonies would have had no end; and the Catholic King might without leaving his royal chamber have taken possession of the whole universe, only excepting afterwards those parts of his empire already belonging to other princes.

We can see how the lands of private persons, when they are united and contiguous, become public territory; and how the right of sovereignty, extending from the subjects to the soil they occupy, covers both property and persons; it makes the owners all the more dependent, and turns their own strength into the guarantee of their fidelity. This advantage seems to have eluded the ancient monarchs, who, in calling themselves simply the King of the Persians or the Scythians or the Macedonians, appear to have regarded themselves rather as rulers of men than as masters of their countries. Monarchs of the present day call themselves more shrewdly the King of France, or of Spain, or of England and so on; in holding thus the land, they are very sure of holding the inhabitants.

What is unique about the alienation entailed by the social contract is that the community in accepting the goods of an individual is far from depriving him of them; on the contrary it simply assures him of their lawful possession; it changes usurpation into valid right and mere enjoyment into legal ownership. Since every owner is regarded as a trustee of the public property, his rights are respected by every other member of the state, and protected with its collective force against foreigners; men have, by a surrender which is advantageous to the public and still more to themselves, acquired, so to speak, all that they have given up — a paradox which is easily explained by the distinction between the rights which the soverign has and which the owner has over the same property, as will be seen later.

It may also happen that men begin to unite before they possess anything, and spreading over a territory large enough for them all, proceed to enjoy it in common, or, alternatively, divide it among themselves either equally or in shares determined by the sovereign. In whatever manner this acquisition is made, the right of any individual over his own estate is always subordinate to the right of the community over everything; for without this there would be neither strength in the social bond nor effective force in the exercise of sovereignty.

I shall end this chapter — and Book Ⅰ — with an observation which might serve as a basis for the whole social system: namely, that the social pact, far from destroying natural equality, substitutes, on the contrary, a moral and lawful equality for whatever physical inequality that nature may have imposed on mankind; so that however unequal in strength and intelligence, men become equal by covenant and by right.[【5】]

Note

【1】 'Learned researches on public law are often only the history of ancient abuses, and one is misled when one gives oneself the trouble of studying them too closely.' Traité manuscrit des intérêts de la France avec ses voisins by the Marquis d'Argenson.

【2】 See a short treatise of Plutarch entitled: That Animals use Reason.

【3】 The Romans, who understood and respected the rights of war better than any other nation, carried their scruples on this subject so far that a citizen was forbidden to volunteer without engaging himself expressly against the enemy and against an enemy specifically named. When the legion in which the younger Cato fought his first campaign under Popilius was re-formed, the elder Cato wrote to Popilius saying that if he wished his son to continue to serve under him, he should administer a fresh military oath, on the grounds that his son's first oath was annulled, and that he could no longer bear arms against the enemy. Cato also wrote to his son warning him not to go into battle without first taking the oath.

I realize that the siege of Clusium and other incidents from Roman history may be quoted against me, but I am citing laws and customs. No nation has broken its own laws less frequently than the Romans, and no nation has ever had such excellent laws.

【4】 The real meaning of this word has been almost entirely lost in the modern world, when a town and a city are thought to be identical, and a citizen the same as a burgess. People forget that houses may make a town, while only citizens can make a city. The Carthaginians once paid dearly for this mistake. I have never read of the title cives being given to the subject of any prince, not even to the Macedonians in ancient times or the English today, in spite of their being closer to liberty than any other people. The French alone treat the same 'Citizen' with familiarity, and that is because they do not know what it means, as their Dictionaries prove; if they did know, they would be guilty, in usurping it, of lèse-majesté; as it is, they use the word to designate social status and not legal right. When Bodin wanted to speak of citizens and burgesses, he made the gross error of mistaking the one for the other. Monsieur d'Alembert avoids this mistake; and in his article on 'Geneva' he correctly distinguishes between the four orders of men (five, if aliens are included) which are found in our town, and of which only two compose the republic. No other French author to my knowledge has understood the real meaning of the word 'citizen'.

【5】 Under a bad government, this equality is only an appearance and an illusion; it serves only to keep the poor in their wretchedness and sustain the rich in their usurpation. In truth, laws are always useful to those with possessions and harmful to those who have nothing; from which it follows that the social state is advantageous to men only when all possess something and none has too much.

Book Ⅱ

CHAPTER 1

That Sovereignty is Inalienable

THE first and most important consequence of the principles so far established is that the general will alone can direct the forces of the state in accordance with that end which the state has been established to achieve — the common good; for if conflict between private interests has made the setting up of civil societies necessary, harmony between those same interests has made it possible. It is what is common to those different interests which yields the social bond; if there were no point on which separate interests coincided, then society could not conceivably exist. And it is precisely on the basis of this common interest that society must be governed.

My argument, then, is that sovereignty, being nothing other than the exercise of the general will, can never be alienated; and that the sovereign, which is simply a collective being, cannot be represented by anyone but itself — power may be delegated, but the will cannot be.

For indeed while it is not impossible for a private will to coincide with the general will on some point or other, it is impossible for such a coincidence to be regular and enduring; for the private will inclines by its very nature towards partiality, and the general will towards equality. It is even more inconceivable that there could be a guarantee of harmony between the private and the general will, even if it were to continue always, for such lasting harmony would be the result of chance and not of design. The sovereign might say: 'What I want at present is precisely what this man wants, or at least what he says he wants'; but no sovereign could say: 'What this man is going to want tomorrow I too shall want', for it is absurd that anyone should wish to bind himself for the future, and it is a contradiction in terms to say that any human being should wish to consent to something that is the reverse of his own good. If a people promises simply and solely to obey, it dissolves itself by that very pledge; it ceases to be a people; for once there is a master, there is no longer a sovereign, and the body politic is therefore annihilated.

This is not to say that the commands of leaders may not pass for the general will if the sovereign, while free to oppose them, does not do so. In such a case the silence of the people permits the assumption that the people consents. This will be explained more fully in a later chapter.

CHAPTER 2

That Sovereignty is Indivisible

JUST as sovereignty is inalienable, it is for the same reason indivisible; for either the will is general[【1】] or it is not; either it is the will of the body of the people, or merely that of a part. In the first case, a declaration of will is an act of sovereignty and constitutes law; in the second case, it is only a declaration of a particular will or an act of administration, it is at best a mere decree.

Nevertheless, our political theorists, unable to divide the principle of sovereignty, divide it in its purpose; they divide it into power and will, divide it, that is, into executive and legislative, into the rights of levying taxation, administering justice and making war, into domestic jurisdiction and the power to deal with foreign governments. Sometimes our theorists confuse all the parts and sometimes they separate them. They make the sovereign a creature of fantasy, a patchwork of separate pieces, rather as if they were to construct a man of several bodies — one with eyes, one with legs, the other with feet and nothing else. It is said that Japanese mountebanks can cut up a child under the eyes of spectators, throw the different parts into the air, and then make the child come down, alive and all of a piece. This is more or less the trick that our political theorists perform —after dismembering the social body with a sleight of hand worthy of the fairground, they put the pieces together again anyhow.

The mistake comes from having no precise notion of what sovereign authority is, and from taking mere manifestations of authority for parts of the authority itself. For instance, the acts of declaring war and making peace have been regarded as acts of sovereignty, which they are not; for neither of these acts constitutes a law, but only an application of law, a particular act which determines how the law shall be interpreted — and all this will be obvious as soon as I have defined the idea which attaches to the word 'law'.

If we were to scrutinize in the same way the other supposed divisions of sovereignty, we should find that whenever we thought that sovereignty was divided, we had been mistaken, for the rights which are taken to be part of that sovereignty prove in fact to be subordinate to it, and presuppose the existence of a supreme will which they merely serve to put into effect.

This want of precision has obfuscated immeasurably the conclusions of our legal theorists when they have come to apply their own principles to determine the respective rights of kings and of peoples. Every reader of the third and fourth chapters of the first book of Grotius can see how that learned man and his translator, Barbeyrac, are trapped in their own sophisms, frightened of saying either too much or alternatively too little (according to their prejudices) and so offending the interests they wish to flatter. Grotius, a refugee in France, discontented with his own country and out to pay court to Louis XIII, to whom his book is dedicated, spares no pains to rob peoples of all their rights and to invest those rights, by every conceivable artifice, in kings. This would have been very much to the taste of Barbeyrac, who dedicated his translation of Grotius to the King of England, George Ⅰ. But unfortunately the expulsion of James Ⅱ — which Barbeyrac calls an 'abdication' — obliged him to speak with a marked reserve, to hesitate and equivocate, so as not to suggest that William Ⅲ was a usurper. If these two writers had adopted sound principles, all their difficulties would have vanished, and their arguments would have been logical; but then they would, alas for them, have told the truth and paid court only to the people. The truth brings no man a fortune; and it is not the people who hand out embassies, professorships and pensions.

CHAPTER 3

Whether the General Will Can Err

IT follows from what I have argued that the general will is always rightful and always tends to the public good; but it does not follows that the deliberations of the people are always equally right. We always want what is advantageous to us but we do not always discern it. The people is never corrupted, but it is often misled; and only then does it seem to will what is bad.

There is often a great difference between the will of all [what all individuals want] and the general will; the general will studies only the common interest while the will of all studies private interest, and is indeed no more than the sum of individual desires. But if we take away from these same wills, the pluses and minuses which cancel each other out, the balance which remains is the general will.[【2】]

From the deliberations of a people properly informed, and provided its members do not have any communication among themselves, the great number of small differences will always produce a general will and the decision will always be good. But if groups, sectional associations are formed at the expense of the larger association, the will of each of these groups will become general in relation to its own members and private in relation to the state; we might then say that there are no longer as many votes as there are men but only as many votes as there are groups. The differences become less numerous and yield a result less general. Finally, when one of these groups becomes so large that it can outweigh the rest, the result is no longer the sum of many small differences, but one great divisive difference; then there ceases to be a general will, and the opinion which prevails is no more than a private opinion.

Thus if the general will is to be clearly expressed, it is imperative that there should be no sectional associations in the state, and that every citizen should make up his own mind for himself[【3】] — such was the unique and sublime invention of the great Lycurgus. But if there are sectional associations, it is wise to multiply their number and to prevent inequality among them, as Solon, Numa and Servius did. These are the only precautions which can ensure that the general will is always enlightened and the people protected from error.

CHAPTER 4

The Limits of Sovereign Power

IF the state, or the nation, is nothing other than an artificial person the life of which consists in the union of its members and if the most important of its cares is its preservation, it needs to have a universal and compelling power to move and dispose of each part in whatever manner is beneficial to the whole. Just as nature gives each man an absolute power over all his own limbs, the social pact gives the body politic an absolute power over all its members; and it is this same power which, directed by the general will, bears, as I have said, the name of sovereignty.

However, we have to consider beside the public person those private persons who compose it, and whose life and liberty are naturally independent of it. Hence we have to distinguish clearly the respective rights of the citizen and of the sovereign,[【4】] and distinguish those duties which the citizens owe as subjects from the natural rights which they ought to enjoy as men.

We have agreed that each man alienates by the social pact only that part of his power, his goods and his liberty which is the concern of the community; but it must also be admitted that the sovereign alone is judge of what is of such concern.

Whatever services the citizen can render the state, he owes whenever the sovereign demands them; but the sovereign, on its side, may not impose on the subjects any burden which is not necessary to the community; the sovereign cannot, indeed, even will such a thing, since according to the law of reason no less than to the law of nature nothing is without a cause.

The commitments which bind us to the social body are obligatory only because they are mutual; and their nature is such that in fulfilling them a man cannot work for others without at the same time working for himself. How should it be that the general will is always rightful and that all men constantly wish the happiness of each but for the fact that there is no one who does not take that word 'each' to pertain to himself and in voting for all think of himself? This proves that the equality of rights and the notion of justice which it produces derive from the predilection which each man has for himself and hence from human nature as such. It also proves that the general will, to be truly what it is, must be general in its purpose as well as in its nature; that it should spring from all for it to apply to all; and that it loses its natural rectitude when it is directed towards any particular and circumscribed object — for in judging what is foreign to us, we have no sound principle of equity to guide us.

For, indeed, whenever we are dealing with a particular fact or right, on a matter which has not been settled by an earlier and general agreement, that question becomes contentious. It is a conflict in which private interests are ranged on one side and the public interest on the other; and I can see neither the law which is to be followed nor the judge who is to arbitrate. It would be absurd in such a dispute to rely on an express decision of the general will; for a decision could only be a conclusion in favour of one of the contending parties, and it would be regarded by the other party as an alien, partial will, a will liable in such circumstances to be unjust and so to fall into error. So we see that even as a private will cannot represent the general will, so too the general will changes its nature if it seeks to deal with an individual case; it cannot as a general will give a ruling concerning any one man or any one fact. When the people of Athens, for example, appointed or dismissed its leaders, awarding honours to one, inflicting penalties on another, and by a multitude of particular decrees indiscriminately exercised all the functions of an administration, then the people of Athens no longer had what is correctly understood as a general will and ceased to act as sovereign and acted instead as magistrate. All this may seem at variance with commonly accepted notions; but I must be given time to expound my own.

It should nevertheless be clear from what I have so far said that the general will derives its generality less from the number of voices than from the common interest which unites them — for the general will is an institution in which each necessarily submits himself to the same conditions which he imposes on others; this admirable harmony of interest and justice gives to social deliberations a quality of equity which disappears at once from the discussion of any individual dispute precisely because in these latter cases there is no common interest to unite and identify the decision of the judge with that of the contending parties.

Whichever way we look at it, we always return to the same conclusion: namely that the social pact establishes equality among the citizens in that they all pledge themselves under the same conditions and must all enjoy the same rights. Hence by the nature of the compact, every act of sovereignty, that is, every authentic act of the general will, binds or favours all the citizens equally, so that the sovereign recognizes only the whole body of the nation and makes no distinction between any of the members who compose it. What then is correctly to be called an act of sovereignty? It is not a covenant between a superior and an inferior, but a covenant of the body with each of its members. It is a legitimate covenant, because its basis is the social contract; an equitable one, because it is common to all; a useful one, because it can have no end but the common good; and it is a durable covenant because it is guaranteed by the armed forces and the supreme power. So long as the subjects submit to such covenants alone, they obey nobody but their own will; and to ask how far the respective rights of the sovereign and the citizen extend is to ask how far these two can pledge themselves together, each to all and all to each.

From this it is clear that the sovereign power, wholly absolute, wholly sacred, wholly inviolable as it is, does not go beyond and cannot go beyond the limits of the general covenants; and thus that every man can do what he pleases with such goods and such freedom as is left to him by these covenants; and from this it follows that the sovereign has never any right to impose greater burdens on one subject than on another, for whenever that happens the matter becomes private and is outside the sovereign's competence.

Granted these distinctions, it becomes manifestly false to assert that individuals make any real renunciation by the social contract; indeed, as a result of the contract they find themselves in a situation preferable in real terms to that which prevailed before; instead of an alienation, they have profitably exchanged an uncertain and precarious life for a better and more secure one; they have exchanged natural independence for freedom, the power to injure others for the enjoyment of their own security; they have exchanged their own strength which others might overcome for a right which the social union makes invincible. Their very lives, which they have pledged to the state, are always protected by it; and even when they risk their lives to defend the state, what more are they doing but giving back what they have received from the state? What are they doing that they would not do more often, and at greater peril, in the state of nature, where every man is inevitably at war and at the risk of his life, defends whatever serves him to maintain life? Assuredly, all must now fight in case of need for their country, but at least no one has any longer to fight for himself. And is there not something to be gained by running, for the sake of the guarantee of safety, a few of those risks we should each have to face alone if we were deprived of that assurance?

CHAPTER 5

The Right of Life and Death

IT will be asked how individuals, who have no right whatever to take their own lives, can transfer to the sovereign a right they do not possess. This question looks difficult to answer only because it is badly formulated. Every man has the right to risk his own life in order to preserve it. Has it ever been said that a man who leaps out of a window to escape from a fire is guilty of suicide? Would the same crime be imputed to a man who perishes in a storm on the grounds that he knew of the danger when he embarked?

The purpose of the social treaty is the preservation of the contracting parties. Whoever wills the end wills also the means, and certain risks, even certain casualties are inseparable from these means. Whoever wishes to preserve his own life at the expense of others must give his life for them when it is necessary. Now, as citizen, no man is judge any longer of the danger to which the law requires him to expose himself, and when the prince says to him: 'It is expedient for the state that you should die', then he should die, because it is only on such terms that he has lived in security as long as he has and also because his life is no longer the bounty of nature but a gift he has received conditionally from the state.

The death-penalty inflicted on criminals may be seen in much the same way: it is in order to avoid becoming the victim of a murderer that one consents to die if one becomes a murderer oneself. Far from taking one's life under the social treaty, one thinks only of assuring it, and we shall hardly suppose that any of the contracting parties contemplates being hanged.

Moreover, since every wrongdoer attacks the society's law, he becomes by his deed a rebel and a traitor to the nation; by violating its law, he ceases to be a member of it; indeed, he makes war against it. And in this case, the preservation of the state is incompatible with his preservation; one or the other must perish; and when the guilty man is put to death, it is less as a citizen than as an enemy. Trial and judgement are the proof and declaration that he has broken the social treaty, and is in consequence no longer a member of the state. And since he has accepted such membership, if only by his residence, he must either be banished into exile as a violator of the social pact or be put to death as a public enemy: such an enemy is not a fictitious person, but a man, and therefore the right of war makes it legitimate to kill him.

But, it will be said, the condemnation of a criminal is an individual act. Agreed; and it follows that such duties do not pertain to the sovereign; condemnation of criminals is a right the sovereign can confer but not exercise himself. All my ideas hold together, but I cannot elaborate them all at once.

In any case, frequent punishments are a sign of weakness or slackness in the government. There is no man so bad that he cannot be made good for something. No man should be put to death, even as an example, if he can be left to live without danger to society.

As for the right of pardon, or of exempting a guilty man from the penalty prescribed by law and imposed by a judge, this belongs only to that entity which is superior to both the judge and the law, namely the sovereign; but even this right is not entirely clear and it will be exercised very seldom. In a well-governed state few are punished, not because there are many pardons but because there are few criminals. In a decaying state the very multiplicity of crimes assures impunity. Under the Roman Republic neither the Senate nor the consuls ever attempted to pardon criminals; nor did the people do so, though they sometimes revoked their own sentences. Frequent pardons signalize that crimes will soon need no pardon; and anyone can see what that must lead to. However, I can feel my heart whispering and restraining my pen; let us leave the discussion of these questions to the just man who has never erred and has therefore had no need of pardons.

CHAPTER 6

On Law

WE have given life and existence to the body politic by the social pact; now it is a matter of giving it movement and will by legislation. For the original act by which the body politic is formed and united does not determine what it shall do to preserve itself.

What is good and in conformity with order is such by the very nature of things and independently of human agreements. All justice comes from God, who alone is its source; and if only we knew how to receive it from that exalted fountain, we should need neither governments nor laws. There is undoubtedly a universal justice which springs from reason alone, but if that justice is to be acknowledged as such it must be reciprocal. Humanly speaking, the laws of natural justice, lacking any natural sanction, are unavailing among men. In fact, such laws merely benefit the wicked and injure the just, since the just respect them while others do not do so in return. So there must be covenants and positive laws to unite rights with duties and to direct justice to its object. In the state of nature, where everything is common, I owe nothing to those to whom I have promised nothing, and I recognize as belonging to others only those things that are of no use to me. But this is no longer the case in civil society, where all rights are determined by law.

Yet what, in the last analysis, is law? If we simply try to define it in terms of metaphysical ideas, we shall go on talking without reaching any understanding; and when we have said what natural law is, we shall still not know what the law of the state is.

I have already said that the general will cannot relate to any particular object. For such a particular object is either within the state or outside the state. If it is outside, then a will which is alien to it is not general with regard to it: if the object is within the state, it forms a part of the state. Thus there comes into being a relationship between the whole and the part which involves two separate entities, the part being one, and the whole, less that particular part, being the other. But a whole less a particular part is no longer a whole; and so as long as this relationship exists there is no whole but only two unequal parts, from which it follows that the will of the one is no longer general with respect to the other.

But when the people as a whole makes rules for the people as a whole, it is dealing only with itself; and if any relationship emerges, it is between the entire body seen from one perspective and the same entire body seen from another, without any division whatever. Here the matter concerning which a rule is made is as general as the will which makes it. And this is the kind of act which I call a law.

When I say that the province of the law is always general, I mean that the law considers all subjects collectively and all actions in the abstract; it does not consider any individual man or any specific action. Thus the law may well lay down that there shall be privileges, but it may not nominate the persons who shall have those privileges; the law may establish several classes of citizen, and even specify the qualifications which shall give access to those several classes, but it may not say that this man or that shall be admitted; the law may set up a royal government and an hereditary succession, but it may not elect a king or choose a royal family — in a word, no function which deals with the individual falls within the province of the legislative power.

On this analysis, it is immediately clear that we can no longer ask who is to make laws, because laws are acts of the general will; no longer ask if the prince is above the law, because he is a part of the state; no longer ask if the law can be unjust, because no one is unjust to himself; and no longer ask how we can be both free and subject to laws, for the laws are but registers of what we ourselves desire.

It is also clear that since the law unites universality of will with universality of the field of legislation, anything that any man, no matter who, commands on his own authority is not a law; even what the sovereign itself commands with respect to a particular object is not a law but a decree, not an act of sovereignty but an act of government.

Any state which is ruled by law I call a 'republic', whatever the form of its constitution; for then, and then alone, does the public interest govern and then alone is the 'public thing' — the res publica — a reality. All legitimate government is 'republican'.[【5】] I shall explain later what government is.

Laws are really nothing other than the conditions on which civil society exists. A people, since it is subject to laws, ought to be the author of them. The right of laying down the rules of society belongs only to those who form the society; but how can they exercise it? Is it to be by common agreement, by a sudden inspiration? Has the body politic an organ to declare its will? Who is to give it the foresight necessary to formulate enactments and proclaim them in advance, and how is it to announce them in the hour of need? How can a blind multitude, which often does not know what it wants, because it seldom knows what is good for it, undertake by itself an enterprise as vast and difficult as a system of legislation? By themselves the people always will what is good, but by themselves they do not always discern it. The general will is always rightful, but the judgement which guides it is not always enlightened. It must be brought to see things as they are, and sometimes as they should be seen; it must be shown the good path which it is seeking, and secured against seduction by the desires of individuals; it must be given a sense of situation and season, so as to weigh immediate and tangible advantages against distant and hidden evils. Individuals see the good and reject it; the public desires the good but does not see it. Both equally need guidance. Individuals must be obliged to subordinate their will to their reason; the public must be taught to recognize what it desires. Such public enlightenment would produce a union of understanding and will in the social body, bring the parts into perfect harmony and lift the whole to its fullest strength. Hence the necessity of a lawgiver.

CHAPTER 7

The Lawgiver

To discover the rules of society that are best suited to nations, there would need to exist a superior intelligence, who could understand the passions of men without feeling any of them, who had no affinity with our nature but knew it to the full, whose happiness was independent of ours, but who would nevertheless make our happiness his concern, who would be content to wait in the fullness of time for a distant glory, and to labour in one age to enjoy the fruits in another.[【6】] Gods would be needed to give men laws.

The same reasoning which Caligula used empirically, Plato used philosophically in his dialogue The Statesman to reach a definition of civil or kingly man. But if it is true that great princes seldom appear, how much more rare must a great lawgiver be? A prince has only to follow a model which the lawgiver provides. The lawgiver is the engineer who invents the machine; the prince is merely the mechanic who sets it up and operates it. Montesquieu says that at the birth of political societies, it is the leaders of the republic who shape the institutions but that afterwards it is the institutions which shape the leaders of the republic.

Whoever ventures on the enterprise of setting up a people must be ready, shall we say, to change human nature, to transform each individual, who by himself is entirely complete and solitary, into a part of a much greater whole, from which that same individual will then receive, in a sense, his life and his being. The founder of nations must weaken the structure of man in order to fortify it, to replace the physical and independent existence we have all received from nature with a moral and communal existence. In a word each man must be stripped of his own powers, and given powers which are external to him, and which he cannot use without the help of others. The nearer men's natural powers are to extinction or annihilation, and the stronger and more lasting their acquired powers, the stronger and more perfect is the social institution. So much so, that if each citizen can do nothing whatever except through cooperation with others, and if the acquired power of the whole is equal to, or greater than, the sum of the natural powers of each of the individuals, then we can say that law-making has reached the highest point of perfection.

The lawgiver is, in every respect, an extraordinary man in the state. Extraordinary not only because of his genius, but equally because of his office, which is neither that of the government nor that of the sovereign. This office which gives the republic its constitution has no place in that constitution. It is a special and superior function which has nothing to do with empire over men; for just as he who has command over men must not have command over laws, neither must he who has command over laws have command over men; otherwise, the laws, being offspring of the legislator's passions, would often merely perpetuate his injustices, and partial judgements would inevitably vitiate the sanctity of his works.

When Lycurgus gave laws to his country, he began by abdicating his monarchical functions. It was the habit of most Greek cities to confer on foreigners the task of framing their laws. The modern republics of Italy have often copied this custom; the republic of Geneva did so, and found that it worked well.[【7】] Rome in its happiest age saw all the crimes of the Tyranny revived within its borders, and came near to perishing simply because it had put both the legislative authority and the sovereign power in the same hands.

And yet even the decemvirs themselves never arrogated the right to make any law on their own authority alone. 'Nothing we propose to you,' they said to the people, 'can become law without your consent. Romans, be yourselves the authors of the laws which are to ensure your happiness.'

Thus the man who frames the laws has not nor ought to have any legislative right, and the people itself cannot, even should it wish, strip itself of this untransferable right; for, according to the fundamental compact, it is only the general will which binds individuals and there can be no assurance that an individual will is in conformity with the general will until it has submitted to the free suffrage of the people — I have said this already, but it is worth repeating.

And so we find in the work of the lawgiver two things which look contradictory — a task which is beyond human powers and a non-existent authority for its execution.

There is another difficulty which deserves mention. Those sages who insist on speaking in their own language to the vulgar instead of in the vulgar language will not be understood. For there are thousands of ideas which cannot be translated into the popular idiom. Perspectives which are general and goals remote are alike beyond the range of the common herd; it is difficult for the individual, who has no taste for any scheme of government but that which serves his private interest, to appreciate the advantages to be derived from the lasting austerities which good laws impose. For a newly formed people to understand wise principles of politics and to follow the basic rules of statecraft, the effect would have to become the cause; the social spirit which must be the product of social institutions would have to preside over the setting up of those institutions; men would have to have already become before the advent of law that which they become as a result of law. And as the lawgiver can for these reasons employ neither force nor argument, he must have recourse to an authority of another order, one which can compel without violence and persuade without convincing.

It is this which has obliged the founders of nations throughout history to appeal to divine intervention and to attribute their own wisdom to the Gods; for then the people, feeling subject to the laws of the state as they are to those of nature, and detecting the same hand in the creation of both man and the nation, obey freely and bear with docility the yoke of the public welfare.

This sublime reasoning, which soars above the heads of the common people, is used by the lawgiver when he puts his own decisions into the mouth of the immortals, thus compelling by divine authority persons who cannot be moved by human prudence.[【8】] But it is not for every man to make the Gods speak, or to gain credence if he pretends to be an interpreter of the divine word. The lawgiver's great soul is the true miracle which must vindicate his mission. Any man can carve tablets of stone, or bribe an oracle, claim a secret intercourse with some divinity, train a bird to whisper in his ear, or discover some other vulgar means of imposing himself on the people. A man who can do such things may conceivably bring together a company of fools, but he will never establish an empire, and his bizarre creation will perish with him. Worthless tricks may set up transitory bonds, but only wisdom makes lasting ones. The Law of the Hebrews, which still lives, and that of the child of Ishmael which has ruled half the world for ten centuries, still proclaim today the greatness of the men who first enunciated them; and even though proud philosophy and the blind spirit of faction may regard them as nothing but lucky impostors, the true statesman sees, and admires in their institutions, the hand of that great and powerful genius which lies behind all lasting things.

Even so, we must not conclude from this, with Warburton, that religion and politics have the same purpose among men; it is simply that at the birth of nations, the one serves as the instrument of the other.

CHAPTER 8

The People

JUST as an architect who puts up a large building first surveys and tests the ground to see if it can bear the weight, so the wise lawgiver begins not by laying down laws good in themselves, but by finding out whether the people for whom the laws are intended is able to support them. Such reasoning led Plato to refuse to provide laws for the Arcadians or the Cyreneans, because he well knew that those peoples, being rich, would not tolerate equality. Crete, too, provides an example of good laws and bad men, for the people Milos tried to discipline were dominated by their vices.

The world has seen a thousand splendid nations that could not have accepted good laws, and even those that might have accepted them could have done so only for short periods of their long history. Nations,[【9】] like men, are teachable only in their youth; with age they become incorrigible. Once customs are established and prejudices rooted, reform is a dangerous and fruitless enterprise; a people cannot bear to see its evils touched, even if only to be eradicated; it is like a stupid, pusillanimous invalid who trembles at the sight of a physician.

I am not denying that just as certain afflictions unhinge men's minds and banish their memory of the past, so there are certain violent epochs or revolutions in states which have the same effect on peoples that personal crises may have on individuals; only instead of forgetting the past, they look back on it in horror, and then the state, after being consumed by civil war, is born again, so to speak, from its own ashes, and leaps from the arms of death to regain the vigour of youth. Such was the experience of Sparta at the time of Lycurgus, of Rome after the Tarquins, and, in the modern world, of Holland and Switzerland after the expulsion of the tyrants.

But such events are unusual; they are exceptional cases to be explained by the special constitution of the states concerned. It could not even happen twice to the same people; because although a people can make itself free while it is still uncivilized, it cannot do so when its civil energies are worn out. Disturbances may then destroy a civil society without a revolution being able to restore it, so that as soon as the chains are broken, the state falls apart and exists no longer; then what is needed is a master, not a liberator. Free peoples, remember this maxim: liberty can be gained, but never regained.

For nations, as for men, there is a time of maturity which they must reach before they are made subject to law; but the maturity of a people is not always easily recognized; and something done too soon will prove abortive. Peoples differ; one is amenable to discipline from the beginning; another is not, even after ten centuries. The Russians will never be effectively governed because the attempt to govern them was made too early. Peter the Great had the talent of a copyist; he had no true genius, which is creative and makes everything from nothing. Some of the things he did were sound; most were misguided. He saw that his people was uncivilized, but he did not see that it was unready for government; he sought to civilize his subjects when he ought rather to have drilled them. He tried to turn them into Germans or Englishmen instead of making them Russians. He urged his subjects to be what they were not and so prevented them from becoming what they might have been. This is just how a French tutor trains his pupil to shine for a brief moment in his childhood and then grow up into a nonentity. The Russian Empire would like to subjugate Europe and will find itself subjugated. The Tartars, its subjects or neighbours, will become its masters — and ours. Such a revolution seems to me inevitable. All the kings of Europe are labouring in concert to hasten its coming.

CHAPTER 9

The People: Continued

JUST as nature has set bounds to the stature of a well-formed man, outside which he is either a giant or a dwarf, so, in what concerns the best constitution for a state, there are limits to the size it can have if it is to be neither too large to be well governed nor too small to maintain itself. In the body politic there is a maximum of strength which must not be exceeded, and which is often fallen short of as a result of expansion. The more the social bond is stretched, the slacker it becomes; and in general a small state is relatively stronger for its size than a large one.

A thousand considerations bear witness to the truth of this. First, administration becomes more difficult over great distances, just as a weight becomes heavier at the end of a long lever. Government becomes more burdensome as its area is enlarged, for each town has its own administration, which the people pays for, and each region has its administration, which the people also pays for, then each province has one, and so on up to the greater governments, the satrapies, the viceroyalties, each costing more the higher they rise and always paid for by the unfortunate populace; and then on top of all comes the supreme administration, bearing down on everyone. Such a great number of charges added to charges continually exhausts the subjects; and far from being better governed by this hierarchy of orders, they are much worse off than they would be if they had only one administration over them. As it is, there is hardly any public revenue available for emergencies, and when the state is faced with such a need, it trembles on the verge of ruin.

Nor is this all. Not only is the government less vigorous and swift in enforcing respect for the law, in preventing nuisances, correcting abuses and thwarting any seditious movements that may arise in distant quarters, but at the same time the people has less affection for governors whom it never sees, for a homeland that seems as vast as the world, and for fellow-citizens who are mostly strangers. The same laws will not suit so many various provinces, which, with their different customs and contrasting climates, cannot tolerate the same form of government. Having different laws only creates misunderstanding and confusion among peoples who live under the same governors and are in continuous communication with one another; they intermingle and intermarry, but if different sets of rules prevail, they will not even know if what they call their patrimony is really their own. Talents are hidden, virtues are ignored and vices remain unpunished when such a multitude of men, who do not know one another, is brought together in the same place by one single seat of supreme administration. The governors have too much to do to see everything for themselves; their clerks rule the state. And the measures needed to maintain a general authority, which so many scattered officials try to evade or exploit, absorb all political attention, so none is left to study the people's happiness, and hardly any left for its defence in case of need. This body which is too big for its constitution collapses and perishes, crushed by its own weight.

On the other hand, a state if it is to have strength must give itself some solid foundation, so that it can resist the shocks that it is bound to experience and sustain the exertions that it must make to preserve itself; for all peoples generate a kind of centrifugal force, by which they brush continuously against one another, and they all attempt to expand at the expense of their neighbours, like the vortices of Descartes. Thus the weak are always in danger of being swallowed up, and indeed no people can well preserve itself except by achieving a kind of equilibrium with all the others which makes the pressure everywhere the same for all.

This shows us that there are reasons for expansion and reasons for contraction; and indeed it is not the least part of political wisdom to judge, as between the one and the other, the precise balance which is most conducive to the preservation of the state. In general one might say that any reasons for expansion, which are exterior and relative, ought to be less compelling than the reasons for contraction, which are internal and absolute. A strong and healthy constitution is the first thing to look for because the strength which comes from good government is more reliable than the resources which large territories yield.

One may add that there have been states whose political structure was such that the necessity of conquest was part of their very constitution, states which, in order to maintain themselves at all, were obliged to enlarge themselves unceasingly. Possibly they have congratulated themselves on this, as a fortunate necessity; but reflection on the same necessity must also have shown them that at the end of their greatness lay the inevitable moment of their fall.

CHAPTER 10

The People: Continued

THERE are two ways of measuring a body politic, by the extent of its territory and by the number of its people; and there must be a certain balance between these two dimensions if the state is to achieve its best size. Men make the state and the soil nourishes men; thus the right balance requires that there be land enough to feed the inhabitants and as many inhabitants as the land can feed. It is in this proportion that the maximum strength of a given number of persons is brought forth; for if there is too much territory, care of it is burdensome, cultivation inadequate and produce excessive; and this soon becomes the cause of defensive wars; while if, on the other hand, there is too little land, the state must live on what it can import at the discretion of its neighbours, and this soon becomes the cause of offensive wars. Any people which has to choose between commerce and war is essentially weak; it depends on its neighbours; it depends on contingencies; it will never have more than a short, uncertain existence; either it conquers and ends its predicament, or it is conquered and exists no more. It can safeguard itself in freedom only by means of littleness or bigness.

One cannot specify the exact mathematical proportion there should be between the area of the land and the number of inhabitants, because of the different characteristics of different places, differences in degrees of fertility, in the nature of the produce, in the effects of climate; and also because of the differences there are between the temperaments of men who inhabit the different territories, some consuming little in a fertile country and others living well off a frugal soil. Again we should have to consider the greater or lesser fecundity of the women, the distinctive features of the land, whether more or less favourable to population; the number of immigrants that the lawgiver might hope to attract by his institutions. From this it follows that he must make his decisions in the light not of what he sees, but of what he foresees, calculating not so much the number of the existing population as the number which the population must naturally reach. Finally, there are a thousand occasions when some particular accident of situation demands or allows the assimilation of more land than appears necessary. In a mountainous country, where the type of cultivation — woodland and pastures — requires less work, where the women are shown by experience to be more fecund than in the plains, and where the steep slopes of hills leave only a marginal degree of that flat land which alone can be relied on for vegetation, men will spread out more widely. The contrary is the case on the edge of the sea, where men will draw together in a small area, even among rocks and sands that are almost barren; for fishing can make up for much of the deficiency of agricultural produce; and being close together enables such men the better to resist pirates; and they can easily rid themselves by overseas settlement of any surplus population.

There is yet another condition for the institution of a people, one condition which no other can replace and without which all the rest are unavailing: a peace and plenty must be enjoyed; for the period of the formation of a state, like that of the lining up of a regiment, is the time when it is least capable of resistance and most open to destruction. A state can defend itself more effectively amid total chaos than during the time of fermentation, when everyone is thinking about his own position and not about the common danger. If there is a war, famine or sedition during this critical period, the state will inevitably be overthrown.

It is true that many governments have been set up during such disturbances, but then it is the governments themselves which destroy the state. Usurpers always choose troubled times to enact, in the atmosphere of general panic, laws which the public would never adopt when passions were cool. One of the surest ways of distinguishing the work of a lawgiver from that of a tyrant is to note the moment he chooses to give a people its constitution.

Which people, then, is fit to receive laws? I answer: a people which, finding itself already bound together by some union of origin, interest or convention, has not yet borne the yoke of law; a people without deep-rooted customs or superstitions; one which does not fear sudden invasion, and which, without intervening in the quarrels of its neighbours, can stand up to any of them, or secure the help of one to resist another; a people in which every member may be known to all; where there is no need to burden any man with more than he can bear; a people which can do without other peoples and which other peoples can do without;[【10】] one which is neither rich nor poor, but has enough to keep itself; and lastly one which combines the cohesion of an ancient people with the malleability of a new one. What makes the task of the lawgiver so difficult is less what has to be established than what has to be destroyed; and what makes success so rare is the impossibility of finding the simplicity of nature together with the needs that society creates. It is difficult to combine all these conditions; and that is why so few well-constituted states exist.

There is still one country in Europe which is fit to receive laws, and that is the island of Corsica. The valour and fidelity with which this brave people has recovered and defended its freedom entitle it to be taught by some wise man how to preserve that freedom. I have a presentiment that this little island will one day astonish Europe.

CHAPTER 11

Various Systems of Law

IF we enquire wherein lies precisely the greatest good of all, which ought to be the goal of every system of law, we shall find that it comes down to two main objects, freedom and equality: freedom because any individual dependence means that much strength withdrawn from the body of the state, and equality because freedom cannot survive without it.

I have already explained what civil freedom is; as for equality, this word must not be taken to imply that degrees of power and wealth should be absolutely the same for all, but rather that power shall stop short of violence and never be exercised except by virtue of authority and law, and, where wealth is concerned, that no citizen shall be rich enough to buy another and none so poor as to be forced to sell himself; this in turn implies that the more exalted persons need moderation in goods and influence and the humbler persons moderation in avarice and covetousness.[【11】]

Such equality, we shall be told, is a chimera of theory and could not exist in reality. But if abuse is inevitable, ought we not then at least to control it? Precisely because the force of circumstance tends always to destroy equality, the force of legislation ought always to tend to preserve it.

However, these general objectives of all institutions must be modified in each country to meet local conditions and suit the character of the people concerned. It is in the light of such factors that one must assign to each people the particular form of constitution which is best, not perhaps in itself, but for that state for which it is destined. For example, is your soil meagre and barren or the territory too narrow for its inhabitants? Then look to industry and crafts, so that manufactured goods may be exchanged for the natural resources that are lacking. Suppose, on the other hand, you have rich plains and fertile slopes, good land too little inhabited. Then concentrate on agriculture, to increase the population, and eschew artisanry, which invariably depopulates the countryside and brings the few inhabitants there are together in certain urban centres.[【12】] Have you a long and convenient coastline? Then fill the sea with ships, develop trade and navigation, and you will have a brilliant if short existence. Does the sea, along your shores, wash against almost inaccessible rocks? Then remain ichthyphagous barbarians; you will live more peacefully, better perhaps, and certainly more happily. In short, apart from those principles which are common to all, each people has its special reasons for adopting these principles in its own way and for having laws that are fitted to itself alone. Thus it was, in the past, that the Hebrews, and more recently the Arabs, took religion as their chief object, while the Athenians had literature, Carthage and Tyre trade, Rhodes seafaring, Sparta war, and Rome civic virtue. The author of L'Esprit des lois has shown with scores of examples how the art of the lawgiver directs the constitution towards each of its ends.

What makes the constitution of a state really strong and durable is such a close observance of conventions that natural relations and laws come to be in harmony on all points, so that the law, shall we say, seems only to ensure, accompany and correct what is natural. But if the lawgiver mistakes his object and builds on principles that differ from what is demanded by the circumstances; if his principle tends towards servitude while circumstances tend towards liberty, the one towards wealth and the other towards increased population, the one towards peace and the other towards conquest, then the laws will be weakened imperceptibly, the constitution will deteriorate, and the state will continue to be disturbed until it is finally destroyed or transformed, and invincible Nature regains her empire.

CHAPTER 12

Classification of Laws

FOR everything to be well ordered and the best possible form given to the republic, there are various relations to be considered. First, there is the action of the whole body politic on itself, that is to say, the relation of all with all, or of the sovereign with the state, and this relation, as we shall see, is made up of relations between intermediary bodies.

The laws which regulate this relation bear the name of Political Laws, and are also called Fundamental Laws — not unreasonably, if the laws are wise ones. For if in each state there is only one good way of regulating it, the people which has found that way ought to keep to it. But if the established order is bad, why should the laws which prevent its being good be regarded as fundamental? Besides, a people is in any case entirely at liberty to alter its laws, even its best laws; and if it chooses to do itself an injury, who has the right to prevent it from doing so?

The second relation is that of the members of the body politic among themselves, or of each with the entire body: their relations among themselves should be as limited, and relations with the entire body as extensive, as possible, in order that each citizen shall be at the same time perfectly independent of all his fellow citizens and excessively dependent on the republic — this result is always achieved by the same means, since it is the power of the state alone which makes the freedom of its members. It is from this second relationship that Civil Laws are born.

We may consider a third kind of relation between the person and the law, namely that of disobedience and its penalty. It is this which gives rises to the establishment of Criminal Laws, though at bottom these are less a specific kind of law than the sanction behind all laws.

To these three sorts of law must be added a fourth, the most important of all, which is inscribed neither on marble nor brass, but in the hearts of the citizens, a law which forms the true constitution of the state, a law which gathers new strength every day and which, when other laws age or wither away, reanimates or replaces them; a law which sustains a nation in the spirit of its institution and imperceptibly substitutes the force of habit for the force of authority. I refer to morals, customs and, above all, belief: this feature, unknown to our political theorists, is the one on which the success of all the other laws depends; it is the feature on which the great law-giver bestows his secret care, for though he seems to confine himself to detailed legal enactments, which are really only the arching of the vault, he knows that morals, which develop more slowly, ultimately become its immovable keystone.

Among these various classes of law, it is only Political Laws, which constitute the form of government, that are relevant to my subject.

Note

【1】 For the will to be general, it does not always have to be unanimous; but all the votes must be counted. Any formal exclusion destroys its universality.

【2】 'Every interest,' says the Marquis d'Argenson, 'has its different principles. Harmony between two interests is created by opposition to that of a third.' He might have added that the harmony of all interests is created by opposition to those of each. If there were no different interests, we should hardly be conscious of a common interest, as there would be no resistance to it; everything would run easily of its own accord, and politics would cease to be an art.

【3】 'Divisions,' says Machiavelli, 'sometimes injure and sometimes aid a republic. The injury is done by cabals and factions; the service is rendered by a party which maintains itself without cabals and factions. Since, therefore, it is impossible for the founder of a republic to provide against enmities, he must make the best provision he can against factions.' History of Florence, Book Ⅶ.

【4】 Please, attentive reader, do not hasten to accuse me of contradiction. I cannot avoid a contradiction of words, because of the poverty of language; but wait.

【5】 By this word I understand not only an aristocracy or democracy, but generally any government directed by the general will, which is law. If it is to be legitimate, the government must not be united with the sovereign, but must serve it as its ministry. So even a monarchy can be a republic. This will be clarified in Book Ⅲ.

【6】 A people does not become famous until its constitution begins to decline. We do not know for how many centuries the constitution of Lycurgus gave happiness to the Spartans before there was talk about them in the rest of Greece.

【7】 Those who think of Calvin merely as a theologian do not realize the extent of his genius. The codification of our wise edicts, in which he had a large share, does him as much credit as his Institutes. Whatever revolutions may take place in our church, the memory of that great man will not cease to be honoured among the adepts of that religion while the love of country and of liberty still lives among us.

【8】 'The truth is,' writes Machiavelli, 'that there has never been in any country an extraordinary legislator who has not invoked the deity; for otherwise his laws would not have been accepted. A wise man knows many useful truths which cannot be demonstrated in such a way as to convince other people.' (Discourses on Livy, Book Ⅴ, Chapter xi.) [In Italian in original. Trans.]

【9】 (Altered in Edition of 1782 to 'Most nations...' Trans.)

【10】 If two neighbouring peoples cannot do without one another the situation is hard for the one and dangerous for the other. Any wise nation, in such a case, will hasten to deliver the other from its dependence. The republic of Thlascala, an enclave within the Mexican Empire, preferred to do without salt rather than buy it from the Mexicans, rather even than take it from them when it was offered as a gift. The wise Thlascalians saw the trap concealed in the Mexican generosity. They kept their freedom; and their little state, locked within the territory of a great Empire, was in the end the instrument of that Empire's ruin.

【11】 Do you want coherence in the state? Then bring the two extremes as close together as possible; have neither very rich men nor beggars, for these two estates, naturally inseparable, are equally fatal to the common good; from the one class come friends of tyranny, from the other, tyrants. It is always these two classes which make commerce of the public freedom: the one buys, the other sells.

【12】 Any branch of foreign trade, says the Marquis d'Argenson, brings only an illusory advantage to the kingdom in general; it may enrich a few individuals, even a few big towns, but the nation as a whole gains nothing and the people is none the better for it.

Book Ⅲ

BEFORE speaking of the various forms of government, let us try to fix the precise meaning of this word, which has not hitherto been very well explained.

CHAPTER 1

Of Government in General

I MUST warn the reader that this chapter should be read with care, for I have not the skill to make myself clear to those who do not wish to concentrate their attention.

Every free action has two causes which concur to produce it, one moral — the will which determines the act, the other physical — the strength which executes it. When I walk towards an object, it is necessary first that I should resolve to go that way and secondly that my feet should carry me. When a paralytic resolves to run and when a fit man resolves not to move, both stay where they are. The body politic has the same two motive powers — and we can make the same distinction between will and strength, the former is legislative power and the latter executive power. Nothing can be, or should be, done in the body politic without the concurrence of both.

We have seen that the legislative power belongs, and can only belong, to the people. On the other hand, it is easy to see from principles established above [Book Ⅱ, Chapters 4 and 6] that executive power cannot belong to the generality of the people as legislative or sovereign, since executive power is exercised only in particular acts which are outside the province of law and therefore outside the province of the sovereign which can act only to make laws.

The public force thus needs its own agent to call it together and put it into action in accordance with the instructions of the general will, to serve also as a means of communication between the state and the sovereign, and in a sense to do for the public person what is done for the individual by the union of soul and body. This is the reason why the state needs a government, something often unhappily confused with the sovereign, but of which it is really only the minister.

What, then, is the government? An intermediary body established between the subjects and the sovereign for their mutual communication, a body charged with the execution of the laws and the maintenance of freedom, both civil and political.

The members of this body are called magistrates or kings, that is to say governors, and the whole body bears the name of prince.[【1】] Thus, those theorists who deny that the act by which a people submits itself to leaders is a contract are wholly correct. For that act is nothing other than a commission, a form of employment in which the governors, as simple officers of the sovereign, exercise in its name the power it has placed in their hands, a power which the sovereign can limit, modify and resume at pleasure, since the alienation of such a right would be incompatible with the nature of the social body and contrary to the purpose of the social union.

I therefore call 'government' or 'supreme administration' the legitimate exercise of the executive power, and I call 'prince' or 'magistrate' the man or the body charged with that administration.

It is in the government that we may discern those intermediary forces whose relations constitute those of all with all, or of the sovereign with the state. This last relation can be depicted as one between the first and last terms of a geometric progression, of which the geometric mean is the government. The government receives from the sovereign the orders which it gives to the people; and if the state is to be well balanced, it is necessary, all things being weighed, that the product of the power of the government multiplied by itself should equal the product or the power of the citizens who are sovereign in one sense and subjects in another.

Furthermore, no one of these three terms can be changed without destroying the ratio. If the sovereign seeks to govern, or if the magistrate seeks to legislate, or if the subjects refuse to obey, then order gives way to chaos, power and will cease to act in concert, and the state, disintegrating, will lapse either into despotism or into anarchy. Lastly, as there is only one geometrical mean between two extremes, there is only one good government possible for any state; but as a thousand events may change the relations within a nation, different governments may not only be good for different peoples, but good for the same people at different times.

To try to give some idea of the various relations which may exist between the two extremes, I shall take as an example the number of the people, as this is a relation easily expressed as a ratio.

Suppose the state is made up of ten thousand citizens. The sovereign can only be considered collectively and as a body, but every member as a subject has to be considered as an individual. Thus the sovereign is to the subject as ten thousand is to one, that is to say, each single member of the state has as his own share only a ten-thousandth part of the sovereign authority, although he submits himself entirely to it. Now if the people is increased to a hundred thousand men, the position of each subject is unaltered, for each bears equally with the rest the whole empire of the laws, while as sovereign his share of the suffrage is reduced to one hundred-thousandth, so that he has ten times less influence in the formulation of the laws. Hence, while the subject remains always one single individual, the ratio of sovereign to subject increases according to the number of citizens. Whence it follows that the more the state is enlarged, the more freedom is diminished.

When I say that the ratio increases, I mean that it is farther removed from unity. So the greater ratio in the mathematical sense, the smaller the relationship in the popular sense; for in the former, the ratio, considered according to this, is measured by the quotient, whereas in the latter, the relationship, considered according to identity, is judged by similarity.

The smaller the relationship between the particular wills and the general will, that is, between the people's morals and the law, the more repressive force will have to be employed. Hence, for the government to be good, its strength must be increased to the extent that the people is more numerous.

In proportion as the enlargement of the state means offering the holders of public authority more temptations and more opportunities to abuse their power, it follows that the more power the government needs to control the people, the more power the sovereign needs, in its turn, to control the government. I am speaking here not of an absolute power, but of the relative power of the different elements in the state.

It follows from this dual relationship that the geometric progression between sovereign, prince and people is by no means an arbitrary idea, but a necessary consequence of the nature of the body politic. It follows further that one of the terms, namely the people as subject, is represented by unity, every time the square of the ratio is increased or diminished, the simple ratio increases or diminishes in the same way, and the middle term, the government, is in consequence changed. This shows that there is no one unique and absolute constitution of government, but that there may be as many different kinds of government as there are states of different sizes.

If anyone, wishing to ridicule this system, suggested that in order to find this geometrical mean and construct the body of the government one need only on my view take the square root of the number of the people, I should reply that I am here using numbers only as an example; and the ratios of which I speak are not measured merely by the number of men but more generally by the amount of activity, which results from the concurrence of innumerable causes; I should add that although I have borrowed momentarily for the sake of expressing myself in fewer words, the language of mathematics, I am still well aware that mathematical precision has no place in moral calculations.

The government is in small what the body politic (which includes it) is in large. It is a fictitious person endowed with certain faculties, active like the sovereign, passive like the state; and it can be broken down into similar relations; in consequence these relations yield a new ratio; and within each we can continue the process of analysis according to the order of the magistracies until we reach a single indivisible middle term, that is, a single chief or supreme magistrate, who may be shown at the centre of this geometrical progression, as the unifying term between the series of fractions and the series of whole numbers.

Without burdening ourselves with such a multiplication of terms, let us simply consider the government as a new body within the state, distinct from both people and sovereign and intermediary between the two.

There is this essential difference between the two bodies — the state exists in itself while the government exists only through the sovereign. Thus the dominant will of the prince is, or ought to be, only the general will or the law, and his force nothing other than the public force concentrated in his hands; as soon as he resolves to perform on his own authority some absolute and independent act, the union of all begins to slacken. And if in the end it comes about that the prince has a particular will more active than that of the sovereign, and if, to enforce obedience to this particular will, he uses the public force which is in his hands, with the result that there are, so to speak, two sovereigns, one de jure and the other de facto, then the social bond vanishes at once and the body politic is dissolved.

Even so, for the body of the government to have an existence, a real life distinct from the body of the state, and for all its members to be able to act in concert and serve the purpose for which the government has been set up, it must have a particular ego, a consciousness common to its members, a force, a will of its own tending to its preservation. Such a particular existence implies assemblies, councils, a power to deliberate and determine rights, titles, and privileges which belongs exclusively to the prince, and which should make the position of the magistrate the more honourable in proportion to the extent to which it is the more arduous. The difficulty is to find a method of ordering this subordinate whole within the greater whole, so that it does not weaken the general constitution while strengthening its own, and so that its private force, designed for its own preservation, shall always be distinct from the public force, designed for the preservation of the state; in short, so that it will always be ready to sacrifice the government to the people and not the people to the government.

Moreover, even though the artificial body of the government is the work of another equally artificial body, and even though it has only a kind of borrowed and subordinate life, this does not prevent its being able to act with greater or less vigour and speed, and enjoying, so to speak, a health that may be more robust or less. Lastly, without departing directly from the purposes for which it has been set up, it may deviate from them in varying degrees according to the manner in which it has been constituted.

It is all these differences which give rise to the various relations that ought to exist between the government and the body of the state, in accordance with the fortuitous and particular relations by which this same state is changed. For often the government which is in itself the best becomes the most evil unless its relations with the state are modified to meet the defects of the body politic to which it belongs.

CHAPTER 2

The Constitutive Principle of the Different Forms of Government

To explain the general reason for these differences, it is necessary to distinguish here between the prince and the government, as I have already distinguished between the state and the sovereign.

The body of the magistrates may be composed of a greater or lesser number of members. We have already observed that the ratio of sovereign to subjects is greater to the extent that the people are more numerous, and by an obvious analogy we can say the same of the government in relation to the magistrates.

As the total power of the government is at all times that of the state, it never varies; and from this it follows that the more force the government exerts over its own members, the less there remains for it to use over the whole people.

Hence the more numerous the magistrates, the weaker the government. As this principle is fundamental, let us try to make it clearer.

We may distinguish in the person of the magistrate three essentially different wills. First, there is the will which belongs to him as an individual, and tends only to his personal advantage. Secondly, there is the collective will of the magistrates; this is concerned only with the advantage of the prince, and might be called the corporate will, since it is general vis-à-vis the government and particular vis-à-vis the state of which the government is a part. Thirdly, there is the will of the people or the sovereign will, which is general both with regard to the state considered as a whole and with regard to the government considered as part of the whole.

In a perfect system of legislation, the individual or particular will would be nonexistent, the government's own corporate will very subordinate, and the general or sovereign will therefore always dominant and always the sole regulator of all the others.

In the order of nature, on the contrary, these different wills become the more active the more they are self-centred. Hence, the general will is always the weakest, the corporate will takes second place, and the particular will comes first of all; so much so, that within the government, each member is primarily a private self, secondly a magistrate, and thirdly a citizen. This sequence is exactly the reverse of what the social order demands.

That being so, let us suppose that the government is in the hands of a single individual. Then the particular will and the corporate will will be perfectly united, and the corporate will accordingly raised to its highest possible degree of intensity. Now, since the exercise of power depends on the degree of will, and since the absolute power of the government is invariable, it follows that the most active government is that of one man.

If, on the other hand, we combine the government and the legislative authority, make the prince the sovereign, and each citizen a magistrate — then the corporate will, being merged in the general will, will be no more active than the general will, and so leave the particular will to command the totality of power. Thus the government, having always the same absolute strength, will be left with a minimum of relative strength and activity.

These relations are indisputable, and other considerations add further confirmation. It is clear, for example, that each magistrate is more active within the body of the government than is each citizen within the body of the state, and hence that the particular will has more influence over the acts of the government than it has over those of the sovereign, for every magistrate is nearly always entrusted with some distinct function of government, while no citizen, taken singly, has any distinct function of sovereignty. Besides, the more the state expands, the more its real strength is increased, though not in proportion to its expansion; but if the state remains the same size, the magistrates can be multiplied without the government gaining thereby any real strength, since its strength is that of the state, which is always the same. In this way the relative strength or activity of the government diminishes without there being any possibility of its absolute or real power increasing.

Again, there is no doubt that the dispatch of public business becomes slower in proportion as there are more persons responsible for it; attaching too much importance to prudence, large bodies attach too little to luck; they miss opportunities, and they deliberate so long that they lose the profits of deliberation.

I have just shown that the government slackens to the extent that the magistrates are multiplied, and I showed earlier that the more numerous the people, the more the repressive force must increase. From this it follows that the ratio of magistrates to government should be the inverse of the ratio of subjects to sovereign; that is to say, the more the state is enlarged, the more the government must reduce its ranks, so that the number of magistrates diminishes in proportion to the increase of the people.

I should add that I am speaking here of the relative strength of the government and not the quality of its behaviour; for, on the contrary, the more numerous the magistrates, the closer their corporate will approaches the general will, while under a single magistrate that same corporate will is, as I have said, only a particular will. Thus there is lost on the one side what could be gained on the other; and the art of the lawgiver is to know how to settle the point at which the strength and the will of the government, which always stand in inverse ratio, can be combined in the proportion most beneficial to the state.

CHAPTER 3

Classification of Governments

IN the preceding chapter we saw why the different types or forms of government are distinguished according to the number of members who compose them; it remains to be seen in the present chapter how this classification is made.

First, the sovereign may put the government in the hands of the whole people, or of the greater part of the people, so that there are more citizen-magistrates than there are ordinary private citizens. This form of government is known as democracy.

Alternatively, the sovereign may confine the government to the hands of a few, so that there are more ordinary citizens than there are magistrates: this form of government is called aristocracy.

Yet again, the sovereign may concentrate the entire government in the hands of one single magistrate, from whom all the others will derive their power. This third form of government is the most common, and is called monarchy or royal government.

It should be noticed that all these forms, or at any rate the first two, can be had in greater or lesser degrees; they have a fairly marked elasticity. Democracy may include all the people or it may be limited so as to include only half. Aristocracy in its turn may extend to half the people or be limited to the smallest possible number. Even royal government can to some extent be shared. Sparta had always two kings according to its constitution, and the Roman Empire is known to have had as many as eight Emperors at once without it being true to say that the Empire was divided. Thus there is always a point at which each form of government overlaps the next form; and it is clear that although government has only three names, it is actually open to as many variations of form as the state has citizens.

Moreover, since a government is able in certain respects to divide itself into separate parts, one administered in one way and the other in another way, the three forms of government may be combined to yield a multitude of mixed forms, each of which it can multiply by the three simple forms.

Throughout the ages men have debated the question 'What is the best form of government?', and yet they have failed to see that each of the possible forms is the best in some cases and the worst in others.

If in each particular state the number of supreme magistrates should be in inverse ratio to the number of citizens, it follows that, in general, democratic government suits small states, aristocratic government suits states of intermediate size and monarchy suits large states. This rule follows directly from our axiom; but how are we to calculate the multitude of particular circumstances which may offer exceptions to the rule?

CHAPTER 4

Democracy

HE who makes the law knows better than anyone how it should be executed and interpreted. So it might seem that there could be no better constitution than one which united the executive power with the legislative; in fact, this very union makes that form of government deficient in certain respects, for things which ought to be kept apart are not, and the prince and the sovereign being the same person constitute, so to speak, a government without government.

It is not good that he who makes the law should execute it or that the body of the people should turn its attention away from general perspectives and give it to particular objects. Nothing is more dangerous in public affairs than the influence of private interests, and the abuse of the law by the government is a lesser evil than that corruption of the legislator which inevitably results from the pursuit of private interests. When this happens, the state is corrupted in its very substance and no reform is possible. A people which never misused the powers of government would never misuse independence, and a people which always governed itself well would not need to be governed.

In the strict sense of the term, there has never been a true democracy, and there never will be. It is contrary to the natural order that the greater number should govern and the smaller number be governed. One can hardly imagine that all the people would sit permanently in an assembly to deal with public affairs; and one can easily see that they could not appoint commissions for that purpose without the form of administration changing.

I believe indeed that one can lay down as an axiom that when the functions of government are divided between several commissions, those with the fewest members acquire sooner or later the greatest authority, if only because the facility of dispatching business leads naturally in that direction.

Besides, how many things that are difficult to have at the same time does the democratic form of government not presuppose? First, a very small state, where the people may be readily assembled and where each citizen may easily know all the others. Secondly, a great simplicity of manners and morals, to prevent excessive business and thorny discussions. Thirdly, a large measure of equality in social rank and fortune, without which equality in rights and authority will not last long. Finally, little or no luxury; for luxury is either the effect of riches or it makes riches necessary; it corrupts both the rich and the poor; it surrenders the country to indolence and vanity; it deprives the state of all its citizens by making some the slaves of others and all the slaves of opinion.

This is why a celebrated author has made virtue the cardinal principle of a republic; for all the conditions that I have named cannot prevail without virtue. But this same great genius, having failed to make the necessary distinctions, was often wrong and sometimes obscure, and failed to see that since the sovereign authority is everywhere the same, the same principles should have a place in every well-constituted state, though to a greater or lesser extent, assuredly, according to the form of the government.

We may add that there is no government so liable to civil war and internecine strife as is democracy or popular government, for there is none which has so powerful and constant a tendency to change to another form or which demands so much vigilance and courage to maintain it unchanged. It is under this constitution, more than others, that the citizen must be armed with strength and fidelity, and repeat from the bottom of his heart every day of his life the words a virtuous Palatine[【2】] once spoke in the Diet of Poland: 'Malo periculosam libertatem quam quietum servitium.'[【3】]

If there were a nation of Gods, it would govern itself democratically. A government so perfect is not suited to men.

CHAPTER 5

Aristocracy

WE have here two distinct artificial persons, namely the government and the sovereign, and therefore two general wills, one belonging to all the citizens, and the other to members of the administration only. Thus, although the government may regulate its interior discipline as it pleases, it can never speak to the people except in the name of the sovereign, that is, in the name of the people itself — something that must never be forgotten.

The first societies were governed aristocratically. The heads of families deliberated on public business among themselves; the young people yielded willingly to the authority of experience. Hence the names of priests, elders, the senate, gerontes. The savages of North America still retain today this method of government, and they are very well governed.

But to the extent that artificial inequality came to prevail over natural inequality, riches and power[【4】] came to be preferred to age, and aristocracy became elective. Lastly, the bequeathing of power together with property by fathers to their children made families patrician and so made government hereditary; and then there appeared senators aged twenty.

There are thus three types of aristocracy, natural, elective and hereditary. The first is suited only to primitive peoples; the third is the worst of all governments; the second is the best, and this is aristocracy in the true sense of the word.

Aristocracy has not only the advantage of distinguishing between the sovereign and the government, it has also the advantage of selecting its magistrates. Under popular government all the citizens are born magistrates, while this other system limits itself to a small number of magistrates, every one of whom is elected,[【5】] a method which makes honesty, sagacity, experience and all the other grounds of popular preference and esteem further guarantees of wise government.

Besides, assemblies can be more easily arranged, business can be better discussed and be dispatched with more order and diligence; the credit of the state is better upheld in the eyes of foreigners by venerable senators than it is by an unknown and despised multitude.

In a word, it is the best and most natural arrangement for the wisest to govern the multitude, if we are sure that they will govern it for its advantage and not for their own. One ought never to multiply devices uselessly, or employ twenty thousand men to do what a hundred picked men could do much better. But it must be noted that the corporate interest begins at this point to direct the forces of the state less strictly in accordance with the general will, and that a further inevitable tendency is for a part of the executive power to escape the control of law.

As for the circumstances which suit this form of government, it is not necessary to have the state so small or the people so simple and upright that the execution of the law follows directly from the public will, as is the case in a good democracy. Nor must the nation be so large that the magistrates, being widely scattered, have to take upon themselves some of the powers of the sovereign, each in his own region; and so begin by making themselves independent and end by becoming masters.

But if aristocracy calls for rather fewer virtues than does popular government, it still calls for virtues of its own, such as moderation among the rich and contentment among the poor; for it seems that strict equality would be out of place; it was not observed even in Sparta.

Moreover, if this form of government involves a certain inequality of wealth, it is good that the administration of public affairs be entrusted to those who can best give all their time to it, and not, as Aristotle asserted, so that the rich should always be chosen. On the contrary, it is necessary that an opposite choice should occasionally teach people that merit is a more important qualification than riches for preferment.

CHAPTER 6

Monarchy

So far we have considered the prince as a collective and artificial person, unified by the force of the law and acting as trustee of executive power in the state. We have now to consider that power being held in the hands of a natural person, a real man, one having the sole right to exercise it according to the law. Such a man is known as a monarch or king.

Contrary to the other administrations, where a collective being represents an individual, in this one an individual represents a collective being; so that the moral unity which constitutes the prince is at the same time a physical unity, bringing together naturally those faculties which the law brings together with such difficulty in the other forms of administration.

Thus the will of the people and the will of the prince, the public force of the state and the individual power of the government, all respond to the same mover; all the levers of the machine are in the same hands; all act towards the same end; there are no conflicting movements to counteract one another, and we cannot imagine any constitution where more action would be produced by less effort. Archimedes sitting quietly on the shore and effortlessly launching a large ship is the model of a skilful monarch governing his vast kingdom from his chamber and making everything move while he himself seems motionless.

But if there is no government more vigorous than monarchy, there is also none where the particular will has more command, and more easily dominates the other wills. Everything moves towards the same end, it is true, but that end is not the public happiness; and the very strength of the administration operates continuously to the disadvantage of the state.

Kings want to be absolute, and from afar men cry out to them that the best way of becoming absolute is to make themselves loved by their people. This is a fine precept; and even in some respects a very true one. Unfortunately, it will always be laughed at in courts. The power which rests on the love of the people is undoubtedly the greatest, but is precarious and provisional; and princes will never be satisfied with it. The best kings want to be able to be bad if they feel like it without ceasing to be masters; a political sermonizer may well tell kings that since the people's force is the king's force, a king's best interest is to have the people flourishing, numerous and formidable; but kings know very well that this is not true. Their personal interest is primarily that the people should be weak, wretched and never able to resist them. I admit that if the subjects were always perfectly submissive, then it would be to the interest of the prince for the people to be strong, so that the people's strength, being also the prince's strength, would make him feared by his neighbours; but since this is only a secondary and subordinate advantage, and since strength is incompatible with submissiveness, it is natural that princes always prefer the doctrine that is more immediately useful to them. This is what Samuel put forcefully to the Hebrews, and what Machiavelli has proved very clearly — under the pretence of instructing kings, he has taught important lessons to the people. Machiavelli's Prince is a handbook for republicans.[【6】]

We have seen from the discussion of general proportions that monarchy is suited only to large states, and we find this again when we examine monarchy in itself. The more numerous the public administrators, the more the ratio between prince and subjects diminishes and approaches parity, coming to a point where the ratio is one to one, or equality itself, in democracy. This same ratio is greater to the extent that the government contracts, and reaches its maximum when the government is in the hands of a single man. Then there is too great a distance between the prince and the people and the state lacks bonds of union. For such bonds to be formed there must be intermediary ranks, with princelings, grandees, and a nobility to fill them. But all this is unsuited to a small state, which would be ruined by so many social orders.

But if it is difficult for a large state to be well governed, it is still more difficult for it to be well governed by a single man; and everyone knows what happens when a king rules through deputies.

An essential and inevitable defect, which will always make monarchical government inferior to republican government, is that whereas in republics the popular choice almost always elevates to the highest places only enlightened and capable men, who fill their office with honour, those who rise under monarchies are nearly always muddled little minds, petty knaves and intriguers with small talents which enable them to rise to high places in courts, but which betray their ineptitude to the public as soon as they are appointed. The people is much less often mistaken in such choices than is a prince, and a man of real merit is almost as rare in a royal ministry as a fool at the head of a republican government. Thus, when by some happy chance a born ruler takes the helm of affairs in a monarchy that is almost wrecked by swarms of egregious administrators, then everyone is amazed at the resources he discovers, and his reign marks an epoch in the history of the country.

For a monarchy to be well governed, its size and extent ought to be proportionate to the talents of those who govern. It is easier to conquer than to administer. With enough leverage, a finger could overturn the world; but to support the world, one must have the shoulders of Hercules. However small the state may be, princes are almost always inadequate. When, on the other hand, it happens that the state is too small for its ruler, a very rare thing, then it is even worse governed, because such a ruler, in following his own broad vision, forgets the people's interest; and he makes them no less miserable by the misuse of his superabundant abilities than a mediocre ruler would make them through the defects of an insufficient talent. It is as if kingdoms ought, so to speak, to expand or contract with each successive reign, according to the capacity of the prince. In a republic, on the other hand, where the talents of the senate are of a more settled measure, the state can have fixed boundaries without the administration working any less well.

The most perceptible disadvantage of government by one man is the lack of that continuity of succession which provides an uninterrupted bond of union in the other two systems. When a king dies, another is needed; elections leave a dangerous interval; they are stormy; and unless the citizens have more disinterestedness and integrity than is usual under such governments, there will be bribery and corruption. It is difficult for one to whom the state has been sold not to sell it in his turn, and recover from the weak the gold which the strong have extorted from him. Sooner or later, under such an administration everything becomes venal; and the peace which is then enjoyed under kings is worse than the disturbances of interregnums.

What has been done to prevent this evil? Thrones have been made hereditary in certain families, and an order of succession thus set up to prevent any dispute on the death of the king — that is to say, by substituting for the disadvantages of elections, the disadvantages of regencies, apparent peace has been preferred to wise administration, and the risk of having children or monsters or imbeciles for rulers preferred to having to dispute the choice of a good king. People do not realize that in exposing themselves to the hazards of these alternatives, they are gambling against all the odds. It was a very shrewd remark that the young Dionysus made to his father, when his father, reproaching him for a dishonourable action, said: 'Did I set you such an example?' 'Ah,' replied the son, 'your father was not a king.'

When someone is brought up to command others, everything conspires to rob him of justice and reason. Great pains are taken, we are told, to teach young princes the art of ruling; but it does not appear that this education does them any good. It would be better to begin by teaching them the art of obeying. The greatest kings known to history were not among those brought up to rule, for ruling is a science that is least well mastered by too much practice; it is one a man learns better in obeying than in commanding. Nam utilissimus idem ac brevissimus bonarum malarumque rerum delectus, cogitare quid aut nolueris sub alio Principe aut volueris.[【7】]

One consequence of this lack of coherence is the instability of royal government, which, being sometimes directed according to one plan and sometimes according to another, depending on the personality of the king who rules, or of those who rule for him, cannot long have a fixed objective or a consistent policy; this unsettledness makes the state drift from principle to principle, and from project to project, a defect not found in those forms of government where the prince is always the same. Thus we see that, in general, if there is more cunning in a royal court, there is more wisdom in a republican senate, and that republics have a more stable and effective guidance — something which cannot obtain where every revolution in the administration means a revolution in the state — for it is the universal rule of all ministers and nearly all kings to reverse the policy of their predecessors.

This same lack of cohesion gives the lie to a fallacy which is very common among royalist political thinkers, that is, not only of comparing civil government to household government and the prince to the father of a family — a fallacy I have already refuted — but also of generously attributing to a royal ruler all the virtues he has need of, and always assuming that the prince is everything he should be. With the help of these assumptions, royal government becomes manifestly preferable to all other kinds, because it is incontestably the strongest, and needs only a corporate will more in harmony with the general will to be also the best form of government.

But if, according to Plato, a born king is a very rare being — how often do Nature and Fortune combine to enthrone such a man? And if a royal education necessarily corrupts those who receive it, what must be expected of a succession of men brought up to rule?

It is deliberate self-deception to confuse royal government with the government of a good king. To understand what this form of government is inherently, one must consider it as it is under mediocre or evil princes, for either princes will be such when they accede to the throne or such is what occupying the throne will make them.

Although these difficulties do not escape our authors, they have never been in the least embarrassed by them. The remedy, they say, is to obey without a murmur. God in his wrath inflicts bad kings on us, so they must be endured as a divine punishment. This argument is undoubtedly edifying; but I fancy it is more suited to the pulpit than to a book of political theory. What would be said about a physician who promised miracles, and whose whole art was to teach the sick to practise patience?

We all know that we have to put up with a bad government when it is bad; the problem is to find a good government.

CHAPTER 7

Mixed Forms of Government

STRICTLY speaking, no government of a simple form exists. A single head of state has to have subordinate magistrates; a people's government must have a head. Thus in the division of executive power there is always a gradation from the larger number to the smaller — with this difference, that sometimes the many submit to the few, and sometimes the few submit to the many.

Sometimes there is an equal division, either when the constitutive parts are mutually dependent, as in the government of England, or when the authority of each part is independent but imperfect, as in the case of Poland. This latter form is bad, because there is no unity in the government, and the state lacks bonds of union. Which is better: a simple form of government or a mixed one? This is a question much debated by political theorists, and one to which I myself must give the answer I gave earlier about all forms of government.

In itself, the simple form of government is the best, precisely because it is simple. But when the executive power is not sufficiently subordinate to the legislative — that is to say, when the ratio of prince to sovereign is greater than that of people to prince — this lack of proportion has to be remedied by dividing the government, for then all the diverse elements of the government will have no less authority over the subjects, but their separation will make them less powerful against the sovereign.

The same disadvantage can also be prevented by establishing intermediate magistrates who, separated from the government altogether, serve only to balance the two powers, and uphold their respective rights. Then the government is not mixed, it is tempered.

The opposite disadvantage can be remedied by similar means; and when the government is too slack, commissions can be set up to give it concentration. In the first case, the government is divided in order to weaken it; in the second, in order to strengthen it. This is the practice of all democracies. The maximum of strength and of weakness are equally found in the simple forms of government, whereas the mixed forms provide a moderate degree of strength.

CHAPTER 8

That All Forms of Government Do Not Suit All Countries

FREEDOM is not a fruit of every climate, and it is not therefore within the capacity of every people. The more one reflects on this doctrine of Montesquieu, the more one is conscious of its truth. And the more often it is challenged, the more opportunities are given to establish it with new evidence.

In every government in the world, the public person consumes but does not produce anything. Whence does it obtain the substance it consumes? From the labour of its members. It is the surplus of private production which furnishes public subsistence. From this it follows that the civil state can subsist only if men's work yields more than they themselves need.

But this surplus is not the same in every country of the world. In some it is substantial, in others middling, in some nil, in others a deficit. The proportion depends on the fertility of the climate, on the kind of labour which the soil requires, on the nature of its products, on the strength of the inhabitants, and on the degree of consumption that is necessary for them, and on various other factors which go to make up the whole proportion.

In addition, all governments do not have the same nature; some are more voracious than others; and their differences are based on this next principle — that the further public contributions are from their source, the more burdensome they are. This burden should not be measured by the quantity of the contributions exacted, but by the distance they have to go to return to the hands from which they come; when this circulation is rapid and well established, it does not matter whether much or little is paid; the people will always be rich and finances will flourish. Correspondingly, however little the people gives, when that little does not return to it, it soon exhausts itself in continuous payments; the state is never rich and the people is always penurious.

This demonstrates that the greater the distance between the people and the government, the more onerous the taxes become; so that in a democracy the people is least burdened, in an aristocracy more burdened, and in a monarchy it bears the greatest weight of all. Monarchy is thus suited only to opulent nations, aristocracy to those of moderate wealth and size, and democracy to small and poor countries.

Indeed, the more one reflects, the more one recognizes that in this matter there are differences between free states and monarchies: in the former everything is used for the common advantage, while in the latter, private power and public power are competitive, and the one is increased only by weakening the other. As for despotism, instead of governing the subjects in order to make them happy, it makes them miserable in order to govern them.

Thus in every climate there are natural factors on the basis of which one can determine the form of government to which that climate leads; and we can even say what sort of inhabitants each must have.

Mean and sterile places, where the product does not repay the labour, must remain uncultivated and deserted, or peopled only by savages. Places which yield only the bare necessities of men's lives must be inhabited by barbarous peoples, since no political society is possible. Places where the surplus of product over labour is moderate are suited to free peoples. Places where an abundant and fertile soil gives a lavish return for little labour will want monarchical government, so that the luxury of the prince may consume the surplus of the product of the subjects — for it is better that this surplus should be absorbed by the government than dissipated by private persons. There are exceptions, I know, but these exceptions themselves confirm the rule, in that sooner or later they produce revolutions which put things back into the order of nature.

We must always distinguish general laws from particular causes which can modify their effect. If all the South were covered with republics and all the North with despotic states, it would still be true that, in terms of climate, despotism suits hot countries, barbarism cold countries, and that a good polity suits temperate regions. I realize that this general rule may be admitted and its application disputed; it could be argued that there are very fertile cold countries and very barren southern ones. But this is a difficulty only for those who fail to see the thing in all its ramifications. One must, as I have already said, consider the factors of production, strength, consumption and so on.

Suppose there are two equal territories, one yielding five units, the other ten. If the inhabitants of the former consume four and those of the latter nine, the surplus of the one will be one-fifth and of the other one-tenth. The ratio of these two surpluses will then be the inverse of that of their products, so that the territory yielding five units will show a surplus double that of the territory yielding ten.

But there is no question of a double product, and I do not believe anyone could venture to equate the fertility of a cold country with that of a hot country. But let us assume such equality; let us, for example, compare England and Sicily, Poland and Egypt. Farther south there will be Africa and India; farther north, there will be nothing. What differences in agricultural technique will be needed to achieve this equality of product? In Sicily, it is enough simply to scratch the soil, while in England, how much effort is needed to work it! Now where more hands are required to obtain the same product, the surplus is necessarily less.

Note a further point, that the same number of men consume much less in hot countries. The climate requires a man to be abstemious to keep fit — and Europeans who try to live in hot countries as they live at home die of dysentry and stomach disorders. 'We,' says Chardin, 'are carnivorous beasts, wolves, compared to the Asians. Some attribute the abstemiousness of the Persians to the fact that their country is less cultivated; but I, on the contrary, believe that their country is less rich in foodstuffs because the inhabitants need less. If their frugality [he continues] were the effect of the poverty of the soil, it would be the poor alone who ate little; in fact everybody does; and instead of finding people eating less or more in each province according to the fertility of the land, one finds the same frugality throughout the kingdom. They are very proud of their way of life, and say that one has only to look at their complexions to see how superior their way is to that of other nations. And indeed, the complexion of the Persians is clear, their skin is fair, delicate and smooth, while that of the Armenians, their subjects who live in the European manner, is rough and blotchy, and their bodies are fat and heavy.'

The closer men are to the equator, the more frugally they live. They eat hardly any meat; rice, maize, couscous, millet and cassava are their daily food. In India there are millions of men whose food costs less than a penny a day. In Europe itself we notice a marked difference of appetite between the peoples of the north and those of the south. A Spaniard could live eight days on the dinner of a German. In countries where men are more gluttonous, luxury is turned towards the things men consume. In England, it shows itself in tables loaded with meats; in Italy one is regaled on sugar and flowers.

Luxury in clothing reveals similar differences. In countries where the changes of season are swift and violent, people have better and simpler clothes; in countries where they dress only for appearance, people care more for show than utility, and clothes themselves are a luxury. In Naples you will see men strolling daily along the Posillipo in gold-embroidered jackets and no hose. It is the same thing with buildings; people attach importance to magnificence when they have nothing to fear from the climate. In Paris or London people want to be housed warmly and comfortably. In Madrid, they have superb reception rooms, but no windows that close and their bedrooms are like rat holes.

Foodstuffs are more substantial and richer in hot countries — this is a third difference and it does not fail to influence the second. Why does one eat so many vegetables in Italy? Because they are good, nourishing and of excellent flavour. In France, where they get nothing but water, they are not at all nourishing, and count for nothing at the table; but even so they take up no less ground and cost just as much to cultivate. Experiment has shown that the wheats of Barbary, otherwise inferior to those of France, yield much more flour; and that the French wheats, in turn, yield more than those of the North. From this one can deduce that a similar gradation may be observed along a line from the equator to the pole. Now is it not a tangible disadvantage to have a smaller amount of nourishment in an equal quantity of produce?

To all these various considerations, I may add another which flows from, and which reinforces them, that is, that hot countries need fewer inhabitants than cold countries, and can feed more — which provides a double surplus to the advantage of despotism. The wider the area that is occupied by the same number of people, the more difficult revolts become; for the inhabitants cannot get together quickly and secretly, while it is always easy for the government to discover plots and to cut communications. On the other hand, the more a numerous people is packed together, the less easily can the government infringe on the sovereign; popular leaders deliberate as securely in their private rooms as the prince in his council, and the crowd gathers as swiftly in the public squares as the troops in their barracks. It is thus to the advantage of tyrannical government to act over great distances. With the aid of strongpoints to serve as fulcra, its strength increases with distance, on the principle of leverage.[【8】]

The strength of the people, on the contrary, is effective only if it is concentrated; it evaporates and is lost when it is dispersed, just as gunpowder scattered on the ground ignites only grain by grain. The least populous countries are thus the most fitted to tyranny; wild beasts reign only in deserts.

CHAPTER 9

The Signs of a Good Government

WHEN, therefore, one asks what in absolute terms is the best government, one is asking a question which is unanswerable because it is indeterminate; or alternatively one might say that there are as many good answers as there are possible combinations in the absolute and relative positions of peoples.

But if it is asked by what signs one can tell whether a given people is well or badly governed, that is another matter; and as a question of fact it could be answered.

Even so, it is not really answered, because everyone will want to answer it in his own way. Subjects prize public tranquillity; citizens the freedom of the individual — the former prefer security of possessions, the latter security of person; subjects think the best government is the most severe, citizens that it is the mildest; the former want crimes to be punished, the latter want them prevented; subjects think it is a good thing to be feared by their neighbours, citizens prefer to be ignored by them; the former are satisfied so long as money circulates, the latter demand that the people shall have bread. But even if there were agreement on these and suchlike points, should we be any more advanced? Moral dimensions have no precise standard of measurement; even if we could agree about signs, how should we agree on their value?

For myself, I am always astonished that people should fail to recognize so simple a sign, or be so insincere as not to accept it as such. What is the object of any political association? It is the protection and the prosperity of its members. And what is the surest evidence that they are so protected and prosperous? The numbers of their population. Then do not look beyond this much debated evidence. All other things being equal, the government under which, without external aids like naturalization and immigration, the citizens increase and multiply most, is infallibly the best government. That under which the people diminishes and wastes away is the worst. Statisticians, this is your problem: count, measure, compare.[【9】]

CHAPTER 10

The Abuse of Government and its Tendency to Degenerate

JusT as the particular will acts unceasingly against the general will, so does the government continually exert itself against the sovereign. And the more this exertion increases, the more the constitution changes for the worse, and, as in this case there is no distinct corporate will to resist the will of the prince and so to balance it, sooner or later it is inevitable that the prince will oppress the sovereign and break the social treaty. This is the inherent and inescapable defect which, from the birth of the political body, tends relentlessly to destroy it, just as old age and death destroy the body of a man.

There are two common ways by which a government degenerates — when it itself contracts and when the state dissolves.

The government contracts when its members pass from a greater to a smaller number, that is, from democracy to aristocracy, or from aristocracy to royal government. This is its natural tendency.[【10】] If it were to move in the other direction from a smaller number to a greater, the government might be said to slacken; but such an inverse progression is impossible.

For indeed, a government never changes its form unless its exhausted energies are too feeble to maintain its original form. If it slackened while expanding, its strength would be absolutely null, and it would be even less likely to survive. It must therefore wind up and tighten the mechanism as it begins to slacken, for otherwise the state which depends on it will fall into ruin.

The dissolution of the state may take place in two ways.

First it takes place when the prince ceases to administer the state according to the law and usurps the sovereign power. Then a remarkable change occurs; for it is not the government but the state which contracts — by which I mean that the state as a whole is dissolved and another is formed inside it, one composed only of members of the government and having no significance for the rest of the people except that of a master and a tyrant, so that the moment the government usurps sovereignty, the social pact is broken, and all the ordinary citizens, recovering by right their natural freedom, are compelled by force, but not morally obliged, to obey.

The same situation occurs when the members of the government separately usurp the power which they ought only to exercise as a body; for this is no less an infraction of the law, and it produces an even greater disorder. For then there are, so to speak, as many princes as there are magistrates, and the state being no less divided than the government, perishes or changes its form.

When the state is dissolved, the abuse of government, whatever it may be, takes the general name of anarchy. More precisely democracy degenerates into ochlocracy, aristocracy into oligarchy, and I would add that royal government degenerates into tyranny, except that this last word is ambiguous and requires explanation.

In the commonly understood sense, a tyrant is a king who governs by force and without regard to justice and the law. In the exact sense, a tyrant is an individual who arrogates to himself royal authority without having any right to it. It is thus that the Greeks understood the word 'tyrant'. They applied it indiscriminately to good and bad princes whenever their authority was not legitimate.[【11】] Thus tyrant and usurper are perfectly syonymous words. To give different names to different things, I call a usurper of royal authority a 'tyrant' and the usurper of the sovereign power a 'despot'. The tyrant is one who intrudes, contrary to law, to govern according to the law; the despot is one who puts himself above the law. Thus the tyrant need not be a despot, but a despot is always a tyrant.

CHAPTER 11

The Death of the Body Politic

SUCH is the natural and inevitable tendency of the best constituted governments. If Sparta and Rome perished, what state can hope to last for ever? If we wish, then, to set up a lasting constitution, let us not dream of making it eternal. We can succeed only if we avoid attempting the impossible and flattering ourselves that we can give to the work of man a durability that does not belong to human things.

The body politic, no less than the body of a man, begins to die as soon as it is born, and bears within itself the causes of its own destruction. Either kind of body may have a constitution of greater or less robustness, fitted to preserve it for a longer or shorter time. The constitution of a man is the work of nature; that of the state is the work of artifice. It is not within the capacity of men to prolong their own lives, but it is within the capacity of men to prolong the life of the state as far as possible by giving it the best constitution it can have. And although even the best constitution will come to an end, it will do so later than any other, unless some unforeseen hazard fells it before its time.

The principle of political life dwells in the sovereign authority. The legislative power is the heart of the state, the executive power is the brain, which sets all the parts in motion. The brain may become paralysed and the individual still live. A man can be an imbecile and survive, but as soon as his heart stops functioning, the creature is dead.

It is not through the law that the state keeps alive; it is through the legislative power. Yesterday's law is not binding today, but silence gives a presumption of tacit consent and the sovereign is taken to confirm in perpetuity the laws it does not abrogate while it has power to abrogate them. Everything which it has once declared to be its will, it wills always — at least until it issues a revocation.

Why then do ancient laws command so much respect? Precisely because they are ancient. We must believe that it is only the excellence of such laws that has enabled them to last so long; if the sovereign had not continually recognized them as salutary, they would have been revoked a thousand times. This is why the laws, far from growing weaker, constantly gain new strength in every well-constituted state; the prejudice in favour of antiquity makes them every day more revered; in those cases, on the other hand, where the laws become weaker with age, this shows that there is no longer any legislative power and that the state is dead.

CHAPTER 12

How the Sovereign Authority Maintains Itself

THE sovereign, having no other force than the legislative power, acts only through the laws, and since the laws are nothing other than authentic acts of the general will, the sovereign can act only when the people is assembled. The people assembled, it will be said — what an illusion! It is indeed an illusion today; but two thousand years ago it was not. Has human nature so much changed?

The boundaries of the possible in the moral realm are less narrow than we think; it is our own weaknesses, our vices and our prejudices that limit them. Base minds do not believe in great men; low slaves jeer in mockery at the word 'freedom'.

In the light of what has been done, let us consider what can be done. I shall not speak of the ancient republics of Greece; but the Roman Republic was, it seems to me, a large state and the town of Rome a large town: the last census gave four hundred thousand men in Rome carrying arms, and the last census calculation under the Empire more than four million citizens without counting subjects, foreigners, women, children or slaves.

One would suppose that it must have been difficult to bring together frequently the numerous people of the capital and its surroundings. In fact, very few weeks passed without the Roman people being assembled, even several times in one week. This people not only exercised the rights of sovereignty, but also a part of the government. It dealt with certain business; it tried certain cases; and the entire people in the public assemblies enacted the role of magistrate almost as often as that of citizen.

Looking back to the earliest history of nations, we notice that the majority of ancient governments, even monarchical ones like those of the Macedonians and the Franks, had similar assemblies. In any case, the one indisputable fact I have cited answers our question; it seems to me good logic to reason from the actual to the possible.

CHAPTER 13

The Same — Continued

IT is not enough that the assembled people should have once determined the constitution of the state by giving sanction to a body of laws; it is not enough that it should set up a perpetual government, or that it should have provided once and for all for the election of magistrates. In addition to the extraordinary assemblies that unforeseen events may necessitate, there must be fixed and periodic assemblies which nothing can abolish or prorogue, so that on the appointed day the people is rightfully summoned by the law itself without any further formal convocation being needed.

But apart from these assemblies which are lawful by their date alone, any assembly of the people which has not been summoned by the magistrate appointed for that duty and according to the prescribed form must be held to be unlawful, and everything it does must be void, for the order to assemble should itself emanate from the law.

As to whether legitimate assemblies should be more or less frequent, this depends on so many circumstances that one cannot lay down in advance any precise rules. One can only say that in general the more strength the government has, the more frequently the sovereign should meet in assemblies.

This, I shall be told, may be good for one single town, but what is to be done if the state consists of several towns? Is the sovereign authority to be divided? Or should it be concentrated in one single town holding the others as subject? I answer that neither the one thing nor the other should be done. In the first place, the sovereign authority is simply one single unit; it cannot be divided without being destroyed. In the second place, a town cannot legitimately be subject to another any more than a nation may be, because the essence of the political body lies in the union of freedom and obedience so that the words 'subject' and 'sovereign' are identical correlatives, the meaning of which is brought together in the single word 'citizen'.

I should answer further that it is always an evil to unite several towns in one nation, and whoever wishes to form such a union should not flatter himself that the natural disadvantages can be avoided. It is no use complaining about the evils of a large state to someone who wants only small ones. But how are small states to be given enough strength to resist large states, as the Greek cities once resisted a great king and as, more recently, Holland and Switzerland resisted the House of Austria?

Nevertheless, if the state cannot be limited to reasonable boundaries, there remains one remedy, and that is to have no fixed capital, but to move the seat of government from one place to another and to assemble the estates of the country in each in turn.

People the territory evenly, extend the same rights to everyone, carry the same abundance and life into every quarter — it is by these means that the state will become at once the strongest and the best governed that is possible. Remember that the walls of towns are made only from the debris of rural houses. Every time I see a mansion being built in the capital I fancy I can see the whole countryside covered with hovels.

CHAPTER 14

The Same — Continued

THE moment the people is lawfully assembled as a sovereign body all jurisdiction of the government ceases; the executive power is suspended, and the person of the humblest citizen is as sacred and inviolable as that of the highest magistrate, for in the presence of the represented there is no longer any representation. Most of the disturbances which took place in the Roman assemblies were the result of this rule being either unknown or neglected. The consuls were no more than the presidents of the people; the tribunes were mere speakers;[【12】] the senate was nothing at all.

These intervals of suspension, when the prince recognizes — or ought to recognize — who is superior, are always alarming for princes; and the assemblies of the people, which are the shield of the body politic and the brake on the government, have always been the nightmare of magistrates; hence the latter spare no effort in raising objections, problems, promises to turn the citizens against assemblies. When the citizens are avaricious, cowardly, pusillanimous, and love repose more than freedom, they do not hold out against the redoubled efforts of the government. It is thus that, as the opposing force increases continuously, the sovereign authority atrophies in the end and the majority of republics fall and perish before their time.

But between the sovereign authority and arbitrary government there is sometimes interposed an intermediate power of which we must now speak.

CHAPTER 15

Deputies or Representatives

As soon as public service ceases to be the main concern of the citizens and they come to prefer to serve the state with their purse rather than their person, the state is already close to ruin. Are troops needed to march to war? They pay mercenaries and stay at home. Is it time to go to an assembly? They pay deputies and stay at home. Thanks to laziness and money, they end up with soldiers to enslave the country and deputies to sell it.

It is the bustle of commerce and the crafts, it is the avid thirst for profit, it is effeminacy and the love of comfort that commute personal service for money. Men give up a part of their profits so as to increase the rest at their ease. Use money thus, and you will soon have chains. The word 'finance' is the word of a slave; it is unknown in the true republic. In a genuinely free state, the citizens do everything with their own hands and nothing by means of money; far from paying for exemption from their duties, they would pay to discharge them in person. I am very far from sharing received ideas: I believe that compulsory service is less contrary to liberty than is taxation.

The better the state is constituted, the more does public business take precedence over private in the minds of the citizens. There is indeed much less private business, because the sum of the public happiness furnishes a larger proportion of each individual's happiness, so there remains less for him to seek on his own. In a well-regulated nation, every man hastens to the assemblies; under a bad government, no one wants to take a step to go to them, because no one feels the least interest in what is done there, since it is predictable that the general will will not be dominant, and, in short, because domestic concerns absorb all the individual's attention. Good laws lead men to make better ones; bad laws lead to worse. As soon as someone says of the business of the state — 'What does it matter to me?' — then the state must be reckoned lost.

The cooling-off of patriotism, the activity of private interest, the vastness of states, conquests, the abuse of government — all these have suggested the expedient of having deputies or representatives of the people in the assemblies of the nation. This is what in certain countries they dare to call the third estate — the private interest of two classes being there given first and second place, and the public interest only third place.

Sovereignty cannot be represented, for the same reason that it cannot be alienated; its essence is the general will, and will cannot be represented — either it is the general will or it is something else; there is no intermediate possibility. Thus the people's deputies are not, and could not be, its representatives; they are merely its agents; and they cannot decide anything finally. Any law which the people has not ratified in person is void; it is not law at all. The English people believes itself to be free; it is gravely mistaken; it is free only during the election of Members of Parliament; as soon as the Members are elected, the people is enslaved; it is nothing. In the brief moments of its freedom, the English people makes such a use of that freedom that it deserves to lose it.

The idea of representation is a modern one. It comes to us from feudal government, from that iniquitous and absurd system under which the human race is degraded and which dishonours the name of man. In the republics and even in the monarchies of the ancient world, the people never had representatives; the very word was unknown. It is remarkable in the case of Rome, where the tribunes were so sacred, that no one ever imagined that they might usurp the functions of the people; and in the midst of such a great multitude, they never attempted to pass on their own authority a single plebiscit-＠ium. One can judge, however, the embarrassment the crowd sometimes caused from what happened at the time of the Gracchi, when a great part of the citizens voted from the rooftops.

Where rights and freedom are everything, inconveniences are nothing. Among these wise people, everything was given its just measure; the lictors were allowed to do what the tribunes would not have dared to do; the people were not afraid that their lictors would wish to represent them.

To explain how, even so, the tribunes did represent the people, it is enough to consider how the government represents the sovereign. Since the law is nothing other than a declaration of the general will, it is clear that there cannot be representation of the people in the legislative power; but there may and should be such representation in the executive power, which is only the instrument for applying the law. This indicates that if we look carefully, we shall find that very few nations have laws. However that may be, it is certain that the tribunes, having no part of the executive power, could never represent the Roman people by the rights of their own office, but only by usurping those of the senate.

Among the Greeks, all that the people had to do, it did itself; it was continuously assembled in the market place. The Greek people lived in a mild climate; it was not at all avaricious; slaves did the work; its chief concern was its freedom. Without the same advantages, how can the same rights be preserved? Your harsher climate creates more necessities;[【13】] six months of the year the public places are uninhabitable; your muted tongues cannot make themselves heard in the open air; you care more for your profits than your freedom; and you fear slavery less than you fear poverty.

What? Is freedom to be maintained only with the support of slavery? Perhaps. The two extremes meet. Everything outside nature has its disadvantages, civil society more than all the rest. There are some situations so unfortunate that one can preserve one's freedom only at the expense of the freedom of someone else; and the citizen can be perfectly free only if the slave is absolutely a slave. Such was the situation of Sparta. You peoples of the modern world, you have no slaves, but you are slaves yourselves; you pay for their liberty with your own. It is in vain that you boast of this preference; I see more cowardice than humanity in it.

I do not mean by all this to suggest that slaves are necessary or that the right of slavery is legitimate, for I have proved the contrary. I simply state the reasons why peoples of the modern world, believing themselves to be free, have representatives, and why peoples of the ancient world did not. However that may be, the moment a people adopts representatives it is no longer free; it no longer exists.

All things carefully considered, I do not see how it will be possible henceforth among people like us for the sovereign to maintain the exercise of its rights unless the republic is very small. But if it is very small, will it not be subjugated? No. I shall show later[【14】] how the defensive strength of a large people can be combined with the free government and good order of a small state.

CHAPTER 16

That the Institution of the Government is not a Contract

ONCE the legislative power is well established, it remains to establish similarly the executive power; for the latter, which operates only by particular acts, is essentially different from the former, and is naturally separate from it. If it were possible for the sovereign, considered as such, to have the executive power, then the de jure and the de facto would be so confused that people would no longer know what was law and what was not; and the body politic, thus perverted, would soon fall prey to that very violence it was instituted to prevent.

The citizens being all equal by the social contract, all may prescribe what all must do, instead of nobody having a right to demand that another shall do what he does not do himself. For it is precisely this right, indispensable for giving life and movement to the body politic, that the sovereign gives to the prince in instituting the government.

Several theorists have claimed that this act of institution is a contract between the people and the magistrates it sets over itself, a contract which stipulates between the two parties the conditions under which the one undertakes to command and the other to obey. It will be admitted, I am sure, that this is a strange way of contracting. But let us see if the theory is tenable.

First, the supreme authority can no more be modified than it can be alienated; to limit it is to destroy it. It is absurd and self-contradictory that the sovereign should give itself a superior; to undertake to obey a master would be to return to absolute freedom.

Furthermore, it is clear that this contract of the people with such or such persons would be a particular act. From this it follows that this contract could not be a law, or an act of sovereignty, and hence that it would be illegitimate.

We see further that the contracting parties would, between themselves, be subject only to natural law, and so without any guarantee of their reciprocal commitments — and this is wholly contrary to the civil state. Since the man who has force in his hand is always the master of what shall be done, this is like giving the name of 'contract' to the act of a man who says to another: 'I give you all my property on condition that you give me back what you please.'

There is only one contract in the state: that of the association itself, and this excludes all others. One cannot imagine any public contract that would not be a violation of the original contract.

CHAPTER 17

The Institution of the Government

IN what conceptual terms then should we think of the act by which the government is instituted? I shall explain first that this act is complex, or composed of two others, namely the establishment of the law and the execution of the law.

By the first, the sovereign enacts that there shall be a body of government established with such or such form; and it is clear that this act is a law.

By the second, the people names the magistrates who are to be invested with the government thus established. Since this nomination is a particular act, it is not a second law, but simply a sequel to the first and a function of government.

The difficulty is to understand how there can be an act of government before the government exists, and how the people, which is only sovereign or subject, can in certain circumstances become prince or magistrate.

Now it is here once more that the body politic reveals one of those astonishing properties by which it reconciles operations that seem to be contradictory. For this operation is accomplished by the sudden transformation of the sovereignty into democracy in such a way that without undergoing any visible change, and simply through a new relation of all to all, the citizens become magistrates and pass from general acts to particular acts, and from the law to its execution.

This change of relation is not a construction of speculative theory without example in practice; it happens every day in the English parliament, where the lower House on certain occasions transforms itself into a committee of the whole House the better to discuss affairs, and so becomes a simple committee of that sovereign court which it was itself a moment before; then later it reports to itself, in its capacity of House of Commons, on what it has just settled as a committee of the whole House, and again debates under one name what it has already decided under another.

It is the advantage peculiar to democratic government that it can be established in fact by a simple act of the general will. After this, the provisional government remains in office if such is the form adopted, or there is established in the name of the sovereign whatever government is prescribed by the law; and everything is then in order. It is not possible to institute the government in any other legitimate manner, without abandoning the principles established in earlier chapters.

CHAPTER 18

Means of Preventing the Usurpation of Government

FROM these explanations, it follows, in confirmation of Chapter 16, that the act which institutes the government is not a contract but a law, and that the holders of the executive power are not the people's masters but its officers; and that the people can appoint them and dismiss them as it pleases; and that there is no question of their contracting, but of obeying; and that in discharging the functions which the state imposes on them, they are only doing their duty as citizens, without having any sort of right to argue terms.

Thus when it happens that the people institutes a hereditary government, whether monarchical in one family, or aristocratic in a class of citizens, it does not enter into any undertaking; hereditary government is simply a provisional form that it gives to the administration until such time as it pleases to arrange it differently.

It is true that such changes are always dangerous, and that one should never touch an established government unless it has become incompatible with the public welfare; but such circumspection is a precept of politics and not a rule of law; and the state is no more bound to leave civil authority to its magistrates than military authority to its generals.

It is true again that in such cases one cannot observe with too great care all the formalities required to distinguish a correct and legitimate act from a seditious tumult, and the will of a whole people from the clamour of a faction. It is here above all that one must avoid yielding to socially harmful claims any more than is required by the strict application of the law; and it is from this obligation too that the prince derives a great opportunity of holding his power in defiance of the people, without it being possible to say that he has usurped it. For while appearing to exercise only his rights it is very easy for him to enlarge those rights and to prevent, on the pretext of public tranquillity, assemblies designed to re-establish good government; thus he exploits the silence which he prevents men breaking, and the irregularities which he makes them commit, to assume in his own favour the tacit consent of those whose mouths are closed by fear and to punish those who dare to speak. It was thus that the decemvirs, having been first elected for one year, and then continued for another, tried to retain their power in perpetuity, by no longer allowing the comitia to assemble. And it is by this simple means that all the governments of the world, once armed with the public force, sooner or later usurp the sovereign authority.

The periodic assemblies of which I have already spoken are the right means to prevent or postpone this evil, above all those assemblies where no formal convocation is needed; for then the prince cannot prevent their meeting without openly proclaiming himself a violator of the laws and an enemy of the state.

At the opening of these assemblies, of which the only purpose is the maintenance of the social treaty, two motions should be put, motions which may never be annulled and which must be voted separately:

The first: 'Does it please the sovereign to maintain the present form of government?'

The second: 'Does it please the people to leave the administration to those at present charged with it?'

I assume here what I believe I have demonstrated, namely, that there is not in the state any fundamental law which may not be revoked, not even the social pact; for if all the citizens assemble to end this pact by a common accord, one cannot doubt that it is very legitimately ended. Grotius indeed thinks that each citizen may renounce his membership of the state, and recover his natural liberty and his goods on withdrawing from the country.[【15】] And it would be absurd if all the citizens united could not do what each of them separately can do.

Note

【1】 Thus in Venice the ruling college is called the Most Serene Prince even when the Doge is not present.

【2】 The Palatine of Posen, father of the King of Poland and Duke of Lorraine.

【3】 Better freedom with danger than peace with slavery.'

【4】 It is clear that the word Optimates, for the ancients, did not mean the best but the strongest.

【5】 It is of the utmost importance that the law should regulate the procedure of election of magistrates, for if this is left to the will of the prince, there will be no avoiding a decline into hereditary aristocracy, as happened in the Republics of Venice and Berne. The first of these two states has long since fallen into decay, while the other preserves itself only by the extreme wisdom of its senate — a very honourable and very dangerous exception to the rule.

【6】 Machiavelli was a gentleman and a good citizen; but being attached to the house of Medici, he was forced during the oppression of his country to disguise his love of liberty. The very choice of an execrable hero reveals his secret intention, and the antithesis between his principles in his book The Prince and those in his Discourses on Livy and The History of Florence proves that this profound political thinker has so far had only superficial or corrupted readers. The Pope's court strictly prohibited his book, which I can well believe, since that was the Court he depicts most plainly.

【7】 'The best as well as the shortest way to find out what is good and what is bad is to consider what you would have wished to happen if someone other than yourself had been Prince.' (Tacitus, History, Book Ⅰ.)

【8】 This does not contradict what I said in Book Ⅱ, Chapter 9, about the disadvantages of a large state, for there I was dealing with the authority of the government over its own members, and here it is a question of the government's strength over the subjects. Its scattered members serve it as so many fulcra to exert pressure on the people from a distance, but it has no such fulcrum to exert pressure on its own members. Thus in the one case the length of the lever is its weakness; in the other, its strength.

【9】 One must judge on the same principle the centuries that merit preference in respect of the prosperity of the human race. People have too much admired those that have witnessed a flourishing of crafts and letters without penetrating the secret purpose of their culture, and without considering its fatal consequences, idque apud imperitos humanitas vocabatur, cum pars servitutis esset. Shall we never see behind the precepts of books the crude self-interest which prompts the authors to speak? No, whatever they may say, when, notwithstanding its brilliance, a country is depopulated, it is simply not true that all is going well; and it is not enough for a poet to have an income of 100,000 livres for his century to be the best of all. It is less important to consider the apparent repose and tranquillity of rulers than the wellbeing of whole nations and above all of the most populous states. A hailstorm may devastate a few cantons, but it rarely causes famine. Riots and civil wars may greatly alarm rulers, but they are not the true misfortunes of peoples, who can at least have a few months' respite during the quarrels as to who is to be the next tyrant. Their calamities and their happiness both arise from their permanent condition. When all remain supine under the yoke, it is then that everything decays, it is then that the rulers can destroy them at their ease, ubi solitudinem faciunt pacem appellant. When the quarrels of the state disturbed the kingdom of France, and the Coadjutor of Paris attended the Parlement with a dagger in his pocket, this did not prevent the French people living happily and multiplying in a free and decent ease. In ancient times, Greece flourished at the height of the cruellest wars; blood flowed in torrents, but the whole country was thickly populated. 'It appeared,' says Machiavelli, 'that in the midst of murder, proscription and civil wars, our republic became stronger than ever; the civil virtue of the citizens, their morals, and their independence, served more effectively to strengthen it than all their dissensions may have done to weaken it.' A little disturbance gives vigour to the soul, and what really makes the species prosper is not peace but freedom.

【10】 The slow formation and progress of the Republic of Venice in its lagoons provides a notable example of this progression; and it is really astonishing that after more than twelve hundred years, the Venetians seem still to be at the second stage, which began with the Serrar di Consiglio in 1198. As for the ancient Doges, for whom the Venetians are reproached, whatever may be said by the squittinio della libertà veneta, there is proof that the Doges were not their sovereigns.

People will not fail to quote against me the case of the Roman Republic, which is said to have followed a reverse sequence, from monarchy to aristocracy and from aristocracy to democracy. But I am very far from sharing this opinion.

The first constitution of Romulus was a mixed government, which promptly degenerated into a despotism. For special reasons, the state perished before its time, just as one sometimes sees an infant die before reaching the age of maturity. The expulsion of the Tarquins was the real moment of the birth of the Republic. But it did not at first assume a fixed form, because the failure to abolish the patriciate left the task half-finished. For the hereditary aristocracy, which is the worst of all legitimate administrations, remained in conflict with democracy, and the form of government, continuously uncertain and wavering, was not fixed (as Machiavelli has proved) until the establishment of the tribunes; only then was there a true government and a true democracy. For indeed the people then was not only sovereign, but also magistrate and judge; and the senate was no more than a subordinate commission to temper and concentrate the government, while the consuls themselves — in spite of their being patricians, chief magistrates and absolute commanders in war — were never more in Rome than presidents of the people.

From that time, the government was seen to follow its natural inclination, and tend strongly towards aristocracy. The patriciate having as it were abolished itself, the aristocracy was no longer seated in the body of the patricians, as in Venice and Genoa, but in the body of the senate composed of patricians and plebeians, even in the body of the tribunes, when they began to usurp the active power. For words do not alter things, and when the people have chiefs who govern on their behalf, this is still an aristocracy no matter what name those persons bear.

The abuse of aristocracy gave birth to civil war and the triumvirate. Sulla, Julius Caesar and Augustus became in fact as good as monarchs, and finally under the despotism of Tiberius the state was dissolved. Roman history, then, does not belie my principle: it confirms it.

【11】 'Omnes enim et habentur et dicuntur Tyranni qui potestate utuntur perpetua, in ea Civitate quae libertate usa est.' ('For all are thought and called tyrants who exercise perpetual power in a city accustomed to freedom.' Cornelius Nepos, Life of Miltiades.) It is true that Aristotle (Nicomachean Ethics, Ⅷ, 10) distinguishes between a tyrant and a king, saying the former governs for his own advantage while the latter governs only for the advantage of his subjects; but in addition to the fact that in general all the Greek authors used the word 'tyrant' in another sense, as we see above all in the Hiero of Xenophon, it would follow from Aristotle's criterion, that there had never yet been a single king since the beginning of the world.

【12】 The word is used here somewhat in the sense it has in the English parliament. The resemblance between these functions would have caused conflict between the Consuls and the Tribunes, even if all jurisdiction had been suspended.

【13】 To adopt in cold countries the luxury and softness of the orientals is to ask to have their chains, to make submission even more inevitable than theirs.

【14】 This is what I intended to do in the remaining part of this work, when, in dealing with foreign relations, I should have come to the subject of confederations. This subject is entirely new, and its principles have yet to be established.

【15】 It being understood that none may leave the country to evade his duty, or avoid saving his country when it needs him. In such a case, flight would be criminal and punishable; it would not be withdrawal but desertion.

Book Ⅳ

CHAPTER 1

That the General Will is Indestructible

So long as several men assembled together consider themselves a single body, they have only one will, which is directed towards their common preservation and general well-being. Then all the animating forces of the state are vigorous and simple; its principles are clear and luminous; it has no incompatible or conflicting interests; the common good makes itself so manifestly evident that only common sense is needed to discern it. Peace, unity, equality are enemies of political sophistication. Upright and simple men are difficult to deceive precisely because of their simplicity; strategems and clever arguments do not prevail upon them; they are not indeed subtle enough to be dupes. When we see among the happiest people in the world bands of peasants regulating the affairs of state under an oak tree, and always acting wisely, can we help feeling a certain contempt for the refinements of other nations, which employ so much skill and mystery to make themselves at once illustrious and wretched?

A state thus governed needs very few laws, and whenever there is a need to promulgate new ones, that need is universally seen. The first man to propose such a law is only giving voice to what everyone already feels, and there is no question either of intrigues or of eloquence to secure the enactment of what each has already resolved to do as soon as he is sure that all the others will do likewise.

What misleads theorists is that, as a result of looking only at states which are badly constituted from the beginning, they are struck by the impossibility of maintaining such a régime there. They laugh at the thought of all the follies that a clever knave or a sly orator could persuade the people of Paris or London to commit. They do not realize that Cromwell would have been put to forced labour by the people of Berne, and the Duc de Beaufort imprisoned by the Genevese.

However, when the social tie begins to slacken and the state to weaken, when particular interests begin to make themselves felt and sectional societies begin to exert an influence over the greater society, the common interest becomes corrupted and meets opposition; voting is no longer unanimous; the general will is no longer the will of all; contradictions and disputes arise; and even the best opinion is not allowed to prevail unchallenged.

In the end, when the state, on the brink of ruin, can maintain itself only in an empty and illusory form, when the social bond is broken in every heart, when the meanest interest impudently flaunts the sacred name of the public good, then the general will is silenced: everyone, animated by secret motives, ceases to speak as a citizen any more than as if the state had never existed; and the people enacts in the guise of laws iniquitous decrees which have private interests as their only end.

Does it follow from this that the general will is annihilated or corrupted? No, that is always unchanging, incorruptible and pure, but it is subordinated to other wills which prevail over it. Each man, in detaching his interest from the common interest, sees clearly that he cannot separate it entirely, but his share of the public evil seems to him to be nothing compared to the exclusive good he seeks to make his own. Where his private good is not concerned, he wills the general good in his own interest as eagerly as anyone else. Even in selling his vote for money, he does not extinguish the general will in himself; he evades it. The fault he commits is to change the form of the question, and to answer something different from what is asked him; so that instead of saying, with his vote, 'It is advantageous to the state', he says, 'It is advantageous to this man or to that party that such or such a proposal should be adopted.' For this reason the sensible rule for regulating public assemblies is one intended not so much to uphold the general will there as to ensure that it is always questioned and always responds.

I might say a great deal here about the simple right of voting in every act of sovereignty, a right of which nothing can deprive citizens, and also about the right of speaking, proposing, dividing and debating — a right which the government always takes great care to assign only to its own members — but this important subject would require a separate treatise, and I cannot put everything in this one.

CHAPTER 2

The Suffrage

IT will be evident from what has been said in the preceding chapter that the manner in which public affairs are conducted gives a sufficiently accurate indication of the moral character and the state of health of the body politic. The greater harmony that reigns in the public assemblies, the more, in other words, that public opinion approaches unanimity, the more the general will is dominant; whereas long debates, dissensions and disturbances bespeak the ascendance of particular interests and the decline of the state.

This will seem less evident when two or several orders enter into the constitution, as in Rome with its patricians and plebeians, whose quarrels often disturbed the comitia even in the finest days of the Republic; but this exception to the rule is more apparent than real, for in Rome, as a result of an inherent defect in the body politic, there were, in a manner of speaking, two states in one, and what is not true of both together is true of each separately. And, indeed, even in the most tumultuous times, the plebiscites of the people always proceeded peacefully when the senate did not interfere, and votes were given with large majorities. The citizens having only one interest, the people had only one will.

At the other extreme of the cycle, unanimity reappears. This is when the citizens, lapsed into servitude, have no longer either freedom or will. Then fear and flattery change voting into acclamation; people no longer deliberate, they worship or they curse. Such was the shameful manner in which the senate gave voice to its opinions under the emperors. Sometimes it did so with absurd precautions. Tacitus mentions that under Otho, the senators covered Vitellius with execrations, but took care at the same time to make a deafening noise, so that Vitellius would not be able to distinguish what each one of them had said, lest he should ever by any chance become master.

These various considerations suggest the principles by which the counting of votes and the comparing of opinions should be arranged, depending on whether the general will is more or less easy to recognize, and on whether the state is more or less in decline.

There is only one law which by its nature requires unanimous assent. This is the social pact: for the civil association is the most voluntary act in the world; every man having been born free and master of himself, no one else may under any pretext whatever subject him without his consent. To assert that the son of a slave is born a slave is to assert that he is not born a man.

If, then, there are opposing voices at the time when the social pact is made, this opposition does not invalidate the contract; it merely excludes the dissentients; they are foreigners among the citizens. After the state is instituted, residence implies consent: to inhabit the territory is to submit to the sovereign.[【1】]

Apart from this original contract, the votes of the greatest number always bind the rest; and this is a consequence of the contract itself. Yet it may be asked how a man can be at once free and forced to conform to wills which are not his own. How can the opposing minority be both free and subject to laws to which they have not consented?

I answer that the question is badly formulated. The citizen consents to all the laws, even to those that are passed against his will, and even to those which punish him when he dares to break any one of them. The constant will of all the members of the state is the general will; it is through it that they are citizens and free.[【2】] When a law is proposed in the people's assembly, what is asked of them is not precisely whether they approve of the proposition or reject it, but whether it is in conformity with the general will which is theirs; each by giving his vote gives his opinion on this question, and the counting of votes yields a declaration of the general will. When, therefore, the opinion contrary to my own prevails, this proves only that I have made a mistake, and that what I believed to be the general will was not so. If my particular opinion had prevailed against the general will, I should have done something other than what I had willed, and then I should not have been free.

This presupposes, it is true, that all the characteristics of the general will are still to be found in the majority; when these cease to be there, no matter what position men adopt, there is no longer any freedom.

When I showed earlier in this essay how particular wills come to take the place of the general will in public deliberations, I made sufficiently clear what practical means may prevent that abuse, and I shall return to this subject later. As for the proportional number of votes required to declare the general will, I have also set forth the principles by which that number can be determined. A difference of a single vote destroys an equal division; a single opposing voice destroys unanimity; but between unanimity and an equal division there are numerous unequal divisions, and the desired proportion can be fixed at any of these points in accordance with the condition and on the needs of the body politic.

Two general maxims may serve to determine these ratios: the first, that the more important and serious the matter to be decided, the closer should the opinion which is to prevail approach unanimity; the second, the swifter the decision the question demands, the smaller the prescribed majority may be allowed to become; and in decisions which have to be given immediately, a majority of one must suffice. The first of these maxims might seem to be more suited to the enactment of laws, the second to the dispatch of administrative business. At all events, it is by a combination of the two maxims that we can determine the right size for the majority that is to decide on any question.

CHAPTER 3

Elections

ELECTIONS of the prince and magistrates, which are, as I have said, complex acts, can be arranged in two ways, by choice or by lot. Both means have been employed in different republics, and a very complicated mixture of the two can still be seen in the election of the Doge of Venice. 'Election by lot,' says Montesquieu, 'is natural to democracy.' I agree. But why is this so? 'Drawing lots,' he continues, 'is a method of election that wounds no one and gives every citizen a reasonable hope of serving his country.' But these are not good reasons.

If we remember that the election of magistrates is a function of government and not of sovereignty, we shall see why the method of lot is natural to democracy, where the administration is all the better in proportion as its acts are fewer.

In every true democracy, magistrature is not a privilege but a heavy responsibility, so that it cannot justly be imposed on one man rather than another. The law alone can impose this burden on the man to whom the lot falls. For in this case, since the conditions are equal for all and the choice does not depend on any human will, the universality of the law is not distorted by any particular application.

In an aristocracy the prince chooses the prince, the government perpetuates itself by its own actions; and then election by choice is appropriate.

The example of the election of the Doge of Venice, far from undermining this distinction, confirms it: such a mixed form suits a mixed government. It is a mistake to regard the government of Venice as a genuine aristocracy. For while the Venetian people has no part in the government, the Venetian nobility is itself a people. A multitude of poor Barnabites never comes near any magistrature, and its nobility rests on the empty title of Excellency and the right to attend the Great Council. And since this Great Council is as numerous as our General Council in Geneva, its illustrious members have no more privileges than our plain citizens. Hence there is no doubt that, apart from the extreme disparity between the two republics, the bourgeoisie of Geneva corresponds precisely to the patriciate of Venice; our natives and inhabitants correspond to the townsmen and the people of Venice, and our peasants to their subjects on the mainland; to sum up, from whatever point of view the Venetian Republic is considered, apart from its size, its government is no more aristocratic than our own. The whole difference lies in the fact that we have no head of state who holds office for life, and so we have not the same need for the method of election by lot.

Election by lot would have few disadvantages in a true democracy, for where all men were equal in character and talent as well as in principles and fortune, it would hardly matter who was chosen. But as I have already said, no true democracy exists.

When election by choice and election by lot are both employed, choice should be used to fill places that call for special skills, such as military commands, and lot for those where common sense, justice and integrity are enough, as in the case of political offices, for in a well-constituted state, such qualities are found among all the citizens.

Under monarchical government, neither election by lot nor election by choice has any place. Since the monarch is by right the sole prince and only magistrate, the choice of his lieutenants belongs to him alone. When the Abbé de St Pierre proposed to increase the Councils of the King of France and have their members elected by ballot, he did not realize that he was proposing to change the form of government!

I have yet to speak of the method of voting and collecting votes in the people's assembly, but perhaps the history of the Roman system would serve to demonstrate more forcefully all the principles that I might myself set forth. It will not be beneath the dignity of a thoughtful reader to consider in some detail how public and private business was conducted in an assembly of two hundred thousand men.

CHAPTER 4

The Roman Comitia

WE have no trustworthy records of the early history of Rome, and there is every likelihood that most of the tales we are told are fables;[【3】] indeed, in general, that most instructive part of the annals of peoples, which is the history of their institution, is the part we most lack. Experience teaches us daily the causes of revolutions in empires, but as peoples are no longer instituted, we have nothing better than conjecture to explain how they were once instituted.

The customs that we find established show at least that such customs must have had an origin. Traditions that recall these origins, that are supported by the best authorities, and confirmed by the best reasons, should pass for the most certain. Such are the principles I have tried to follow in enquiring how the freest and strongest people of the world exercised its supreme power.

After the foundation of Rome, the new-born Republic — that is, the founder's army, made up of Albans, Sabines and foreigners — was divided into three classes, which acquired by this division the name of tribes. Each of these tribes was further divided into ten curiae, and each curia subdivided into decuriae, with chiefs named curiones and decuriones placed at their head.

In addition to this, there was drawn from each tribe a body of a hundred equites or knights, called a century, which indicates that these divisions, hardly necessary in a city, were in the first place purely military. But it seems that an instinct for greatness led this little town of Rome to provide itself from the outset with a system well suited to the capital of the world.

However, this original division soon had one disadvantageous consequence. The tribes of Albans and Sabines remained constant, while the tribe of foreigners grew continuously as more foreigners were recruited, and it soon contained more members than the other two tribes combined. The remedy that Servius found for this dangerous fault was to alter the basis of the division, and in place of the racial distinction, which he abolished, he introduced one based on the district of the town occupied by each of the tribes. Instead of three tribes, he set up four, each occupying one of the hills of Rome and bearing its name. Thus he both corrected an existing inequality and forestalled any future inequality; and to ensure that the division should be one of men and not of places, he forbade the inhabitants of one district to move to another, and so prevented the races from merging together.

He also doubled the three original centuries of equites and added twelve new ones, but he let them keep their former names — a shrewd and simple means by which he succeeded in distinguishing the body of knights from that of the people without making the latter complain.

To these four urban tribes, Servius added fifteen others which were called rustic tribes, because they were formed of inhabitants of the country, arranged in so many cantons. Afterwards as many new tribes were formed, and the Roman people found itself divided into thirty-five tribes, a number which remained unchanged until the end of the Republic.

This distinction between tribes of the town and tribes of the country had one consequence worth noting since there is no other instance of it, and since Rome was indebted to it both for the preservation of her morals and for the growth of her empire. It might have been thought that the urban tribes would have soon monopolized the power and the honours and have been quick to diminish the standing of the rustic tribes. What happened was the contrary. The taste of the early Romans for a country life is well known. This taste came from their wise founder, who made freedom go together with rural labour and military service and, in a manner of speaking, relegated crafts, trades, intrigue, wealth and slavery to the city.

Since all the illustrious men in Rome thus lived in the country and cultivated the land, it became customary to look to the country for the mainstays of the Republic. And as this way of life was that of the most noble patricians, it was honoured by everyone; the simple and laborious life of villagers was preferred to the loose and idle life of the Roman bourgeois, and a man who would have been nothing but a miserable proletarian in the town became as a tiller of the soil a respected citizen. It was not without reason, says Varro, that our magnanimous ancestors established in the village the nursery of those robust and valiant men who defended them in time of war and nourished them in time of peace. Pliny states positively that the rustic tribes were honoured because of the men who belonged to them, and that whenever it was intended to degrade a coward, he was transferred in disgrace to one of the urban tribes. When Appius Claudius, the Sabine, came to set himself up in Rome, he was loaded with honours and inscribed as a member of a rustic tribe which afterwards took the name of his family. Finally, all the freed men joined the urban and never the rustic tribes, and throughout the Republic there was not a single example of any one of these freed men acceding to any magistrature, even though he had become a citizen.

This principle was excellent; but it was pushed so far that it finally produced an alteration, and certainly an abuse in the political system.

First, the censors, having long arrogated to themselves the right arbitrarily to transfer citizens from one tribe to another, allowed most men to enrol in the tribe of their choice, a concession which certainly did no good and which deprived the censorship of one of its great advantages. Moreover, the exalted and powerful men all had themselves enrolled in the rustic tribes, and the freed men remained with the common people in the urban tribes, so that the tribes generally ceased to have any local or territorial bases, and all were so muddled together that it was no longer possible to identify anyone without consulting the register; and this is why the word tribe came to have a personal instead of a territorial meaning, or rather came to be virtually fictitious.

It also came about that the urban tribes, being closer to the centre, often found themselves the strongest group in the comitia, and sold the state to such as deigned to buy the votes of the rabble who composed that assembly.

As for the curiae, since the founder had created ten in each tribe, the whole of the Roman people, at that time enclosed within the walls of the city, was composed of thirty curiae, each with its own temples, its Gods, its officials, its priests and its festivals called compitalia, which resembled the Paganalia later held by the rustic tribes.

When Servius introduced his new division, this number of thirty could not be divided equally between his four tribes, and he did not wish to alter it; in conse quence, the curiae, becoming independent of the tribes, formed another category of inhabitants of Rome. But there was no question of curiae in the rustic tribes or among the people who belonged to them; for after the tribes had become a purely civil institution, and another system introduced for the levying of troops, the military divisions of Romulus proved superfluous. Thus, although each citizen was enrolled in a tribe, there were many who were not members of a curia.

Servius made yet a third division, which had nothing to do with the first two, and which became by reason of its consequences the most important of all. He distributed the whole Roman people into six classes, arranged neither on a personal nor on a residential basis, but according to wealth; so that the first classes were filled with the rich, the last with the poor, and the intermediate classes with men of moderate fortunes. These six classes were subdivided into 193 other bodies called centuries, and these bodies were so distributed that the first class accounted for more than half of them, and the last class for a single one only. Thus it came about that the class with the fewest number of men had the greatest number of centuries, while the last whole class counted only as one single subdivision, although it contained more than half the inhabitants of Rome.

In order that the people should less well perceive the consequences of this division, Servius disguised it in a military form; he put into the second class two centuries of armourers and into the fourth class two centuries of weapon-makers. In each class, except the last, he differentiated between young and old, that is to say, between those liable to bear arms and those legally exempt on grounds of age; and this distinction, more than that of wealth, made it necessary to hold frequent censuses. Finally he prescribed that the assembly should be held in the Campus Martius, and that all those of military age should attend bearing arms.

The reason he did not make the same differentiation between young and old in the last class is simply that the common people who belonged to it did not have the honour of bearing arms in the service of their country; only those who owned hearths had the right to defend them. Among the countless hordes of beggars who ornament the armies of kings today there is perhaps none who would not have been expelled with disdain from a Roman cohort in the days when soldiers were the defenders of liberty.

In the last class, however, a distinction was made between proletarians and those who were called capite censi. The former, not wholly reduced to nothing, at least gave citizens to the state, even sometimes soldiers in times of pressing need. But those who possessed nothing whatever, and could be reckoned only by the counting of heads, were considered to be nonentities, and Marius was the first who condescended to enrol them.

Without deciding here whether this third classification was good or bad in itself, one can, I think, safely say that it was practicable only because of the simple habits of the early Romans, their taste for agriculture, and their contempt alike for commerce and for the pursuit of profit. Where is the modern people, whose devouring greed, unsettled hearts, intrigue, continual movement and constant reversals of fortune would have allowed such a system to last for twenty years without overturning the whole state? It should also be remembered that the morals of the Roman people and the office of censorship had the strength to correct the evils of this system, and that a rich man could find himself relegated to the class of the poor for making too ostentatious a display of his wealth.

From all this it is easy to understand why more than five Roman classes are hardly ever mentioned, even though there were actually six. The sixth, which provided neither soldiers for the army nor voters for the Campus Martius[【4】] and had therefore virtually no function in the Republic, was seldom given any thought.

Such were the different divisions of the Roman people. Let us now consider the effect the divisions had in the assemblies. The assemblies which were lawfully convened were called comitia, and generally met in the Roman forum or in the Campus Martius; they were distinguished as comitia curiata, comitia centuriata and comitia tributa, according to which form was employed. The comitia curiata was founded by Romulus, the comitia centuriata by Servius, and the comitia tributa originated in the tribunes of the people. No law was sanctioned and no magistrate elected except in the comitia, and as there was no citizen who was not enrolled in a curia, century or tribe, it follows that no citizen was excluded from the right to vote, and that the Roman people was truly sovereign, both in law and in fact.

For the comitia to be legally convened and for its decisions to have the force of law, three conditions had to be observed: first, the body or the magistrate convening the assembly had to be vested with the necessary authority; secondly, the assembly had to be held on one of the days permitted by law; thirdly, the auguries had to be favourable.

The reason for the first of these rules needs no explanation. The second was a matter of policy; the assembly was not allowed to meet on holidays or market days, because the country people, who came to Rome to do business, did not have time to spend the day in the forum. The third rule enabled the Senate to keep a restraining hand on a proud and restless people and temper the ardour of seditious tribunes — although the latter found more than one way of evading this check.

Laws and the election of chiefs were not the only matters submitted to the judgement of the comitia. Since the Roman people had usurped the most important functions of government, one could say that the fate of Europe was determined in those assemblies. The variety of public business explains the several forms which the comitia took, according to the matters which had to be decided.

To judge these various forms it is necessary only to compare them. Romulus, in establishing the curiae, aimed to balance the Senate against the people and balance the people against the Senate, while himself dominating both alike. Under this arrangement he gave the people all the authority of numbers to balance the authority of power and wealth which he left to the patricians. But true to the spirit of monarchy, he nevertheless gave the great advantage to the patricians, in that they could buy clients to influence numerical majorities. This admirable institution of patrons and clients was a masterpiece of politics and humanity, without which the patriciate, so contrary to the spirit of the Republic, could not have survived. To Rome alone belongs the honour of giving the world this noble example, from which no abuse has ever come, but which has never been followed elsewhere.

This same form of curiae continued under the kings up to Servius, and as the reign of the last of the Tarquins was not held to be legitimate, the royal laws were generally known by the name of leges curiatae.

Under the Republic, the curiae, which were still limited to the four urban tribes, and still included only the population of Rome, pleased neither the Senate, which led the patricians, nor the tribunes who, in spite of being plebeian, led the more moneyed citizens. Thus the curiae fell into discredit, fell so low indeed that their thirty lictors met to do what the comitia curiae should have done.

The division into centuries was so favourable to the aristocracy that it is not at first easy to see why the Senate did not always carry the day in the comitia which bore that name, and by which the consuls, censors and other cural magistrates were elected. For indeed, of the 193 centuries which formed the six classes of the entire Roman people, the first class contained ninety-eight, and since votes were counted by centuries only, this first class had a majority over all the others. When all these centuries were in agreement, the rest of the votes were not even counted; and what had been decided by a minority passed for a decision of the multitude; so it can be said that in the centuriate assemblies matters were decided by majorities of money rather than of votes.

But this excessive power was tempered in two ways. First, the tribunes ordinarily, and a large number of plebeians always, were in a class with the rich, and balanced the influence of the patricians in the first class.

Secondly, the centuries were not always summoned to vote in their order or rank, which would have meant beginning with the first class; instead, a century was chosen by lot[【5】] and that century alone went on to elect, after which the other centuries were convened on a different day by order of rank to repeat the election, and generally they confirmed it. Thus the authority of example was taken away from rank and given to chance, according to the principle of democracy.

This custom had yet another advantage; it meant that the citizens from the country had time between the elections to inform themselves of the merits of the candidates provisionally nominated, and therefore did not vote in ignorance. But under the pretext of speeding up procedure this custom was finally abolished, and both elections were held on the same day.

The comitia tributa was, strictly speaking, the council of the Roman people. It could be convened only by the tribunes; it was the assembly where the tribunes were elected and it was there that they passed their plebiscites. Not only had the Senate no status in the assembly, but no senator had even the right to attend, and being thus forced to submit to laws in the enactment of which they had no voice, the senators were to that extent less free than the humblest citizen. This injustice was altogether ill conceived, and alone sufficed to invalidate the decrees of a body to which all its members were not admitted. Had all the patricians attended the comitia, according to their rights as citizens, they would not, as simple individuals, have had any great influence on a vote taken by enumerating heads, and in which the humblest proletarian would count for as much as the prince of the Senate.

Thus, it will be seen that besides the order which emerged from the various systems of collecting the votes of so vast a people, these several methods were not in themselves insignificant, but that each had effects connected with the opinions that led to its being chosen.

Without going further into long details, it emerges from the explanation already given, that the comitia tributa was the assembly most favourable to popular government and the comitia centuriata to aristocracy. In the case of the comitia curiata, where the populace of Rome alone formed the majority, their tendency to favour tyranny and evil designs led them to fall into disrepute, so that even the seditious elements avoided these assemblies lest their presence should arouse suspicion concerning their conspiracies. There is no doubt that the whole majesty of the Roman people was to be seen only in the comitia centuriata; this alone was a full assembly, for the comitia curiata excluded the rustic tribes and the comitia tributa excluded the Senate and patricians.

The system of voting used by the Romans was as simple as were their manners and morals, if less simple than that of Sparta. Each man gave his vote by word of mouth, and a clerk recorded it; the majority of individual votes in each tribe determined the decision of that tribe, the majority of tribal votes the decision of the people; and the same thing was done in the curiae and centuriae. This was a good method so long as honesty prevailed among the citizens and everyone was ashamed to give his vote in public to an unjust cause or an unworthy candidate. But when the people grew corrupt and votes were bought, it became expedient for the ballot to be cast in secret, so that the buyers of votes might be restrained by mistrust of the sellers, and scoundrels given the chance of not being traitors also.

I am aware that Cicero condemns this change of method, and holds it partly responsible for the ruin of the Republic. But while I am mindful of the weight which the authority of Cicero ought to bear, I do not agree with him. On the contrary, I think that it was by having too few such changes that the ruin of the state was accelerated. For just as the diet of healthy people is unsuited to the sick, so one should not try to give to a corrupt people the same laws as those which suit a virtuous people. Nothing does more to bear out this principle than the long life of the Republic of Venice, which still retains a simulacrum of existence solely because its laws are uniquely suited to wicked men.

Now the Roman citizens had tablets distributed among them, so that each might cast his vote without anyone's knowing his opinion. New arrangements were also devised for the collection of tablets, the counting of votes, the comparison of numbers, and so forth. This did not prevent the officers entrusted with these functions from being suspected of dishonesty. Finally, edicts designed to prevent intrigue and the buying and selling of votes were passed in such numbers that their very multiplicity proclaims their ineffectiveness.

Towards the last years of the Republic, the Romans were often forced to resort to extraordinary expedients to make up for the inadequacy of the law. Sometimes miracles were invoked, but this device, if it could impose on the people, did not overawe those who ruled them. Sometimes assemblies were hurriedly convened, before candidates had time to pay out their bribes; sometimes a whole session was taken up with filibustering, when it was seen that the people had been seduced and was about to make a wrong decision. But ambition in the end overcame all obstacles; and the most incredible fact of all is that so numerous a people, in the midst of so many abuses, still continued, thanks to its ancient rules of order, to elect magistrates, to enact laws, to judge cases and to conduct private and public business with almost as much facility as the Senate itself might have commanded.

A wisely tempered tribunate is the strongest buttress of a good constitution, but if it has the least degree of power beyond what is necessary, it will overthrow everything. It is not by its nature prone to weakness, and if it is anything at all, it will never be less than it ought to be.

It degenerates into tyranny when it usurps the executive power of which it is only the moderator, and when it tries to make the laws it ought only to protect. The enormous power of the Ephors, which represented no danger so long as Sparta preserved its morale, sped corruption once corruption began. The blood of Agis shed by the tyrants was avenged by his successor; the crimes and the punishments of the Ephors equally hastened the collapse of the Republic, and after Cleomenes, Sparta was nothing. Rome perished in the same way, and the excessive power which the tribunes usurped by degrees finally served, with the aid of laws made to defend liberty, to protect the very emperors who destroyed liberty. As for the Council of Ten in Venice, it is a tribunal of blood, which is baneful as much to the patricians as to the people, and which, far from giving supreme protection to the law, serves only, now that the law has been debased, for the striking of stealthy blows that none dare look upon.

A tribunate, like a government, is weakened by the multiplication of its members. When the tribunes of the Roman people, originally two, then five, sought to double their number, the Senate gave its consent, confident of using one part to check the others; and this it did not fail to effect.

The best method of preventing the usurpations of such a formidable body — though it is a method which no government has ever yet employed — would be not to make the tribunate permanent but to prescribe the intervals during which it should remain suspended. These intervals, which should not be so great as to give abuses time to take root, could be specified by law in such a manner that in case of need they might be shortened by an extraordinary commission.

This method appears to me to have no disadvantages, for since, as I have said, the tribunate is in no sense a part of the constitution, it can be removed without detriment to it; this also seems to me an efficacious method, since a newly established magistrate would not enter office with the power that his predecessors had, but only with that given him by law.

CHAPTER 6

Dictatorship

THE inflexibility of the laws, which prevents them from bending to circumstances, may in certain cases make them injurious, and bring about in a time of crisis the ruin of the state. The ordered and slow procedures of legal formalities require a measure of time that circumstances do not always afford. There may be a thousand eventualities which the lawgiver has not foreseen, and it is a very necessary part of foresight to know that one cannot foresee everything.

For this reason, one should not seek to make political institutions so rigid that one is deprived of the power to suspend their operation. Even Sparta allowed its laws at times to lie dormant.

But it is only the greatest emergency that can counterweigh the dangers of tampering with the public order; and the sacred power of the laws should never be suspended except when the safety of the fatherland is at stake. In these rare and obvious cases, the public security is provided for by a special act making that security the responsibility of the person who is most worthy. This responsibility may be assigned in two ways, according to the nature of the emergency.

If increasing the activity of the government is adequate to counteract the danger, then this activity should be concentrated in the hands of one or two members of the government. In this case, it is not the authority of the laws which is being diminished, but only the form of the administration. But if the danger is such that the apparatus of law is itself an obstacle to safety, then a supreme head must be nominated with power to silence all the laws and temporarily suspend the sovereign authority. In such a case the general will is indubitable; for it is clear that the prime concern of the people is that the state shall not perish. Thus the suspension of the legislative authority does not abolish it; the magistrate who silences it cannot speak for it; he dominates it, without having the power to represent it; he can do everything, except make laws.

The first of these two methods was used by the Roman Senate when, according to a hallowed formula, it entrusted the consuls with the safety of the Republic; the second was used when one of the two consuls nominated a dictator[【6】] — a device that Rome had learned from Alba.

At the beginning of the Republic, the Romans often resorted to dictatorship, because conditions were not yet sufficiently settled for the state to maintain itself by the strength of its constitution. The people's moral character made unnecessary at that time many of the precautions which might have been needed at other times, so men did not fear that a dictator would abuse his position or that he would attempt to prolong his office beyond its term. It seemed, on the contrary, that so much power was a burden to those who wielded it; for they hastened to divest themselves of it, as if standing in the place of the laws made it altogether too onerous and perilous an office.

So it is not because there was a danger of its being abused, but because there was a danger of its being degraded that one condemns the imprudent employment of this supreme magistrature in the early days of the Republic. For while it was wasted on elections, dedications and purely formal things, there was reason to fear that it would become less forceful when it was really needed, and that the people would come to regard dictatorship as an empty title used only to give dignity to idle ceremonies.

Towards the end of the Republic, the Romans, becoming more circumspect, were as sparing in their use of dictatorship as they had once been prodigal, and with as little reason. It was easy to see that their fears were ill founded, and that the weakness of the capital was at that time its protection against the magistrates it had in its midst, that a dictator could in certain cases defend the public freedom without ever being able to invade it, and that the fetters of Rome were not forged in Rome itself, but in the Roman armies; the weak resistance that Marius offered Sulla, and Pompey Caesar, showed plainly what could be expected of internal authority faced with external force.

This mistake led the Romans to commit great wrongs. There was, for example, their failure to nominate a dictator in the Catilina affair; for since this was a matter which concerned only the city itself, or at most some Italian province, the unlimited authority which the law gave a dictator would have facilitated the ready crushing of that conspiracy, which was in fact suppressed only by a concurrence of lucky accidents, such as human prudence could never have expected.

Instead of naming a dictator, the Senate was content to transmit all its powers to the consuls, as a result of which Cicero, in order to act effectively, was obliged to exceed his powers on a crucial point; and though, in a first transport of joy, the Romans approved of his conduct, it was not without justice that he was afterwards asked to account for the blood of citizens shed in violation of the laws — a reproach which could not have been addressed to a dictator. But the consul's eloquence carried everything before him, and he himself, though a Roman, loved his own glory better than his country; and instead of seeking a lawful and certain means of serving the state, he sought all the honour of the affair for himself.[【7】] Thus he was justly honoured as the liberator of Rome, and no less justly punished as the violator of Roman laws. However splendid his recall from exile may have been, it was undoubtedly an act of pardon.

For the rest, in whatever manner this important commission of dictatorship is conferred, it is imperative to limit its duration to one short term that can never be prolonged; in the emergencies which call for its institution, the state is soon lost or saved, and once the urgent need is over, dictatorship becomes either tyrannical or useless. In Rome, where the term was of six months, most of the dictators abdicated before that time had expired. If the term had been longer, they might have been tempted to prolong it still further, like the decemvirs, who held office for a year. The dictator, having only the time to meet the need which had prompted his appointment, had none in which to meditate on further projects.

CHAPTER 7

The Censorial Tribunal

JUST as the general will is declared by the law, so is the public judgement declared by the censorial office; public opinion is that form of law of which the censor is the minister, and which he, on the model of the prince, merely applies to particular cases.

Far, then, from the censorial tribunal being the arbiter of the people's opinion, it is only the spokesman; and as soon as it departs from this, its decisions are void and without effect.

It is useless to separate the morals of a nation from the objects of its esteem; for both spring from the same principle and both necessarily merge together. Among all the peoples of the world, it is not nature but opinion which governs the choice of their pleasures. Reform the opinions of men, and their morals will be purified of themselves. Men always love what is good or what they think is good, but it is in their judgement that they err; hence it is their judgement that has to be regulated. To judge morals is to judge what is honoured; to judge what is honoured, is to look to opinion as law.

The opinions of a people spring from its constitution; although the law does not regulate morals, it is legislation that gives birth to morals; when legislation weakens, morals degenerate; and then the rulings of the censors will not accomplish what the law has failed to achieve.

From this it follows that the censorial office may be useful in preserving morals, but never in restoring morals. Set up censors while the laws are still vigorous; for as soon as the vigour is lost, everything is hopeless; nothing legitimate has any force once the laws have force no longer.

The censorial office sustains morals by preventing opinions from being corrupted, by preserving their integrity with wise rulings, and sometimes even by settling points on which opinion is uncertain. The use of seconds in duels, carried to an impassioned extreme in the kingdom of France, was abolished by a single edict of the King: 'as for those who are cowardly enough to name seconds'. This judgement anticipated that of the public, and settled it with one stroke. But when the same edicts sought to declare that it was also cowardice to fight duels — which is very true, but at variance with popular opinion — the public scoffed at this decision on a matter about which its mind was made up.

I have said elsewhere that since public opinion is not subject to constraint, there should be no vestige of constraint in the tribunal established to represent it. We cannot too greatly admire the skill with which this device, entirely alien to the moderns, was put into effect by the Romans and even better by the Lacedaemonians.

Once when a man of bad character put forward a good idea in the council of Sparta, the Ephors, ignoring him, had the same thing proposed by a virtuous citizen. What an honour for the one, what a disgrace for the other; yet neither praise nor blame was given to either. Certain drunkards from Samos once defiled the tribunal of the Ephors; the following day the Samians were given permission by public edict to be filthy. An actual punishment would have been less severe than such a form of impunity. When Sparta has pronounced on what is and what is not decent, Greece does not dispute its judgements.

CHAPTER 8

The Civil Religion

AT first men had no kings but the Gods, and their only government was theocratic. They reasoned like Caligula, and in the circumstances they reasoned rightly. A prolonged modification of feelings and ideas was needed before man could make up his mind to accept one of his own kind as master, and to persuade himself that in doing so he had done well.

From this single fact, that a God was placed at the head of every political society, it follows that there were as many Gods as peoples. Two peoples alien to one another, and nearly always enemies, could not long recognize the same master: two armies going into battle could not obey the same commander. Thus national divisions produced polytheism, and this in turn produced religious and civil intolerance, which are naturally the same, as I shall explain later.

The fanciful idea of the Greeks that they had discovered their own Gods being worshipped by barbarian peoples originated in the Greek habit of regarding themselves as the natural sovereigns of those same peoples. But in our own times, it is a ludicrous parody of learning which studies the identity of the Gods of different nations, as if Moloch, Saturn and Chronos could be the same God, as if the Baal of the Phoenicians, the Zeus of the Greeks, and the Jupiter of the Romans could be identical; as if there could be anything in common between chimerical beings with different names!

But if it is asked why under paganism, when each state had its own religious cult and its own Gods, there were no wars of religion, I answer that it was due to this very fact that each state, having its own faith as well as its own government, did not distinguish between its Gods and its laws. Political war was just as much theological war; the provinces of the Gods were determined, so to speak, by the frontiers of nations. The God of one people had no rights over other peoples. The Gods of the Pagans were in no sense jealous Gods; they divided the empire of the world between them; even Moses and the Hebrew people sometimes countenanced this idea by speaking of the God of Israel. It is true that they did not recognize the Gods of the Canaanites, a proscribed people who were doomed to destruction, and whose country they were to occupy; but consider how they spoke of the divinities of neighbouring peoples, whom they were forbidden to attack: 'Is not the possession of that which belongs to Chamos your God lawfully your due?' says Jephthah to the Ammonites. 'By the same title we possess the lands which our conquering God has taken.'[【8】]

But when the Jews, subject to the Kings of Babylon, and afterwards to the Kings of Syria, stubbornly sought to recognize no other God but their own, this refusal was regarded as a rebellion against their conquerors, and it brought on the Jews those persecutions of which we read in their history, and of which we find no other example before the coming of Christianity.[【9】]

Since each religion was thus attached exclusively to the laws of the state which prescribed it, and since there was no means of converting people except by subduing them, the only missionaries were conquerors; and since the obligation to change faith was part of the law of conquest, it was necessary to conquer before preaching conversion. Far from men fighting for the Gods, it was, as in Homer, the Gods who fought for men; each people asked its own God for victory, and paid for it with new altars. The Romans, before taking a town, called upon its Gods to abandon it; when they allowed the Tarentines to keep their angry Gods, it was in the belief that those Gods were subject to their own and obliged to pay them homage. They let the vanquished keep their own Gods just as they let them keep their own laws. A crown dedicated to Jupiter of the Capitol was often the only tribute they exacted.

In the end, when the Romans had spread their faith and their Gods with their empire, and often themselves adopted those of the vanquished in giving all and sundry the rights of citizenship, the peoples of this vast empire gradually found themselves with a multitude of Gods and faiths, which were everywhere almost the same; and this is how paganism became one and the same religion throughout the known world.

It was in these circumstances that Jesus came to establish a spiritual kingdom on earth; this kingdom, by separating the theological system from the political, meant that the state ceased to be a unity, and it caused those intestine divisions which have never ceased to disturb Christian peoples. Now as this new idea of a kingdom of another world could never have entered the minds of pagans, they always regarded the Christians as true rebels who, under the cloak of hypocritical submission, only awaited the moment to make themselves independent and supreme, and cunningly to usurp that authority which they made a show of respecting while they were weak. Such was the cause of the persecutions.

What the pagans feared did indeed happen; then everything altered its countenance; the humble Christians changed their tune and soon the so-called kingdom of the other world was seen to become, under a visible ruler, the most violent despotism of this world.

However, since princes and civil laws continued to exist, the consequence of this dual power has been an endless conflict of jurisdiction, which has made any kind of good polity impossible in Christian states, where men have never known whether they ought to obey the civil ruler or the priest.

Many peoples, even in Europe or nearby, have tried to preserve or re-establish the ancient system, but without success: the spirit of Christianity has won completely. The religious cult has always kept, or recovered, its independence of the sovereign, and has lacked its necessary connexion with the state. Mahomet had very sound opinions, taking care to give unity to his political system, and for as long as the form of his government endured under the caliphs who succeeded him, the government was undivided and, to that extent, good. But the Arabs, in becoming prosperous, cultured, polite, effeminate and soft, were subjugated by the barbarians; then the division between the two powers was started afresh, and even though the division is less apparent among the Moslems than among the Christians, it nevertheless exists, above all in the sect of Ali and in states like Persia where it has never ceased to make itself felt.

Among us, the Kings of England have established themselves as heads of the church and the Czars have done the same. But with this title they have made themselves not so much masters as ministers, and have acquired not so much the right to change the church as the power to preserve it; they are not legislators, they are only princes. Wherever the clergy constitutes a body,[【10】] it is master and legislator in its own house. Thus there are two powers, two sovereigns, in England and in Russia, just as there are elsewhere.

Of all Christian authors, the philosopher Hobbes is the only one who saw clearly both the evil and the remedy, and who dared to propose reuniting the two heads of the eagle and fully restoring that political unity without which neither the state nor the government will ever be well constituted. But he should have seen that the dominant spirit of Christianity was incompatible with his system, and that the interest of the prince will always be stronger than that of the state. It is not so much the horrible and false parts of Hobbes's system that have made it hated, but the parts which are just and true.[【11】]

I believe that if the historical facts were analysed from this point of view, we could easily refute the opposing beliefs of both Bayle and Warburton, the one holding that no religion is useful to the body politic, the other that Christianity is its best support. We could refute the first by showing that no state has ever been founded without religion as its base; and we could refute the second by showing that the Christian law is at bottom more injurious than serviceable to a robust constitution of the state. For this to be clearly understood, I think I have only to give a little more precision to the exceedingly vague idea of religion, as it bears upon my subject.

Religion, considered in connexion with societies, whether general or particular, can be divided into two categories, the religion of the man and the religion of the citizen. The first, without temples, altars or rituals, and limited to inward devotion to the supreme God and the eternal obligations of morality, is the pure and simple religion of the Gospel, the true theism, and might be called the divine natural law. The religion of the citizen is the religion established in a single country; it gives that country its Gods and its special tutelary deities; it has its dogmas, its rituals, its external forms of worship laid down by law; and to the one nation which practises this religion, everything outside is infidel, alien, barbarous; and it extends the rights and duties of man only so far as it extends its altars. Such were the religions of all the early peoples; and we might give it the name of civil or positive divine law.

There is a third and more curious kind of religion, which, giving men two legislative orders, two rulers, two homelands, puts them under two contradictory obligations, and prevents their being at the same time both churchmen and citizens. Such is the religion of the Lamas, such is that of the Japanese, and such is Catholic Christianity. One might call this the religion of the priest. It produces a kind of mixed and anti-social system of law which has no name.

From the political point of view, each of these three kinds of religion has its defects. The third kind is so manifestly bad that the pleasure of demonstrating its badness would be a waste of time. Everything that destroys social unity is worthless; and all institutions that set man at odds with himself are worthless.

The second kind of religion is good in that it joins divine worship to a love of the law, and that in making the homeland the object of the citizens' adoration, it teaches them that the service of the state is the service of the tutelary God. This is a kind of theocracy, in which there can be no pontiff other than the prince, and no priests except the magistrates. Then to die for one's country is to become a martyr, to break the law to be impious, and to subject a guilty man to public execration is to hand him over to the wrath of God: sacer esto.

But this kind of religion is also bad; since it is based on error and lies, it deceives men, and makes them credulous and superstitious; it buries the true worship of God in empty ceremonials. It is bad, again, when it becomes exclusive and tyrannical, and makes a people bloodthirsty and intolerant, so that men breathe only murder and massacre, and believe they are doing a holy deed in killing those who do not accept their Gods. This puts the people concerned into a natural state of war with all others, and this is something destructive of its own security.

There remains the religion of humanity, or Christianity, not the Christianity of today, but that of the Gospel, which is altogether different. Under this holy, sublime and true religion, men, as children of the same God, look on all others as brothers, and the society which unites them is not even dissolved by death.

But this religion, having no specific connexion with the body politic, leaves the law with only the force the law itself possesses, adding nothing to it; and hence one of the chief bonds necessary for holding any particular society together is lacking. Nor is this all: for far from attaching the hearts of the citizens to the state, this religion detaches them from it as from all other things of this world; and I know of nothing more contrary to the social spirit.

It is said that a people of true Christians would form the most perfect society imaginable. I see but one great flaw in this hypothesis, namely that a society of true Christians would not be a society of men.

I would even say that this imagined society, with all its perfection, would be neither the strongest nor the most durable. Being perfect, it would be without bonds of union; its ruinous defect would lie in its very perfection.

Everyone would do his duty; the people would obey the law; the rulers would be just and moderate; the magistrates would be honest and incorruptible; the soldiers would scorn death; there would be neither vanity nor luxury; and all that is very fine. But let us look further.

Christianity is a wholly spiritual religion, concerned solely with the things of heaven; the Christian's homeland is not of this world. The Christian does his duty, it is true, but he does it with profound indifference towards the good or ill success of his deeds. Provided that he has nothing to reproach himself for, it does not matter to him whether all goes well or badly here on earth. If the state prospers, he hardly dares to enjoy the public happiness; he fears lest he become proud of his country's glory; if the state perishes, he blesses the hand of God that weighs heavily on His people.

For such a society to be peaceful and for harmony to prevail, every citizen without exception would have to be an equally good Christian. If, unhappily, there should appear one ambitious man, one hypocrite, one Catilina, for example, or one Cromwell among them, that man would readily exploit his pious compatriots. Christian charity does not allow us readily to think ill of our neighbours. When a man is cunning enough to master the art of imposing on others, and gains a part of the public authority, there, behold, is a man who is given honours; and God wills that he be respected; soon, we see a man of power, and God wills that he be obeyed. Suppose he abuses the power of which he is the trustee? Then he is the scourge with which God chastises his children. Christians would have scruples about expelling the usurper; for that would mean disturbing the public peace, using violence, shedding blood, and all this accords ill with Christian mildness. And after all what does it matter whether one is free or a slave in this vale of tears? The essential thing is to go to paradise, and resignation is but one more means to that end.

Suppose a foreign war breaks out. The citizens will march without reluctance to war; no one among them will think of flight; all will do their duty — but they will do it without passion for victory; they know better how to die than to conquer. It does not matter to them whether they are victors or vanquished. Does not providence know better than they what is needful? One can imagine what advantage a proud, impetuous and passionate enemy would draw from their stoicism. Set them at war against a generous people whose hearts are devoured by an ardent love of glory and their country; imagine your Christian republic confronted by Sparta or Rome, and your pious Christians will be beaten, crushed, destroyed before they have time to collect their wits, or they will owe their salvation only to the contempt which their enemy feels for them.

I myself think it was an excellent oath that was taken by the soldiers of Fabius; they did not swear to conquer or die, but to return as conquerors, and they kept their word. Christians would never have dared to do this; they would have felt that it was tempting God.

But I err in speaking of a Christian republic; for each of these terms contradicts the other. Christianity preaches only servitude and submission. Its spirit is too favourable to tyranny for tyranny not to take advantage of it. True Christians are made to be slaves; they know it and they hardly care; this short life has too little value in their eyes.

It is said that Christian troops are excellent. I deny it. Show me these Christian troops. Personally I know of none. You may mention the crusades. But without disputing the valour of the crusaders, I shall say that they were far from being Christians. They were soldiers of the priests. They were citizens of the Church; they were fighting for its spiritual homeland, which it had in some strange way made temporal. Strictly speaking, this comes under the heading of paganism; for since the Gospel never sets up any national religion, holy war is impossible among Christians.

Under the pagan Emperors, Christian soldiers were brave. All the Christian authors tell us this, and I believe them; but those soldiers were competing for honour against pagan troops. Once the Emperors became Christian, this emulation ceased; and once the cross had driven out the eagle, all Roman valour disappeared.

But leaving aside considerations of politics, let us return to those of right; and settle the principles which govern this important question. The right which the social pact gives the sovereign over the subjects does not, as I have said, go beyond the boundaries of public utility.[【12】] Subjects have no duty to account to the sovereign for their beliefs except when those beliefs are important to the community. Now it is very important to the state that each citizen should have a religion which makes him love his duty, but the dogmas of that religion are of interest neither to the state nor its members, except in so far as those dogmas concern morals and the duties which everyone who professes that religion is bound to perform towards others. Moreover, everyone may hold whatever opinions he pleases, without the sovereign having any business to take cognizance of them. For the sovereign has no competence in the other world; whatever may be the fate of the subjects in the life to come, it is nothing to do with the sovereign, so long as they are good citizens in this life.

There is thus a profession of faith which is purely civil and of which it is the sovereign's function to determine the articles, not strictly as religious dogmas, but as expressions of social conscience, without which it is impossible to be either a good citizen or a loyal subject.[【13】] Without being able to oblige anyone to believe these articles, the sovereign can banish from the state anyone who does not believe them; banish him not for impiety but as an anti-social being, as one unable sincerely to love law and justice, or to sacrifice, if need be, his life to his duty. If anyone, after having publicly acknowledged these same dogmas, behaves as if he did not believe in them, then let him be put to death, for he has committed the greatest crime, that of lying before the law.

The dogmas of the civil religion must be simple and few in number, expressed precisely and without explanations or commentaries. The existence of an omnipotent, intelligent, benevolent divinity that foresees and provides; the life to come; the happiness of the just; the punishment of sinners; the sanctity of the social contract and the law — these are the positive dogmas. As for the negative dogmas, I would limit them to a single one: no intolerance. Intolerance is something which belongs to the religions we have rejected.

In my opinion, those who distinguish between civil and theological intolerance are mistaken. These two forms of intolerance are inseparable. It is impossible to live in peace with people one believes to be damned; to love them would be to hate the God who punishes them; it is an absolute duty either to redeem or to torture them. Wherever theological intolerance is admitted, it is bound to have some civil consequences,[【14】] and when it does so, the sovereign is no longer sovereign, even in the temporal sphere; at this stage the priests become the real masters, and kings are only their officers.

Now that there is not, and can no longer be, an exclusive national religion, all religions which themselves tolerate others must be tolerated, provided only that their dogmas contain nothing contrary to the duties of the citizen. But anyone who dares to say 'Outside the church there is no salvation' should be expelled from the state, unless the state is the church and the prince the pontiff. Such a dogma is good only in a theocratic government; in any other, it is pernicious. The reason for which Henri Ⅳ is said to have embraced the Catholic religion is one which should make all honest men abandon it, above all any prince who knows how to reason.

CHAPTER 9

Conclusion

AFTER setting out the true principles of political right, and trying to establish the state on the basis of those principles, I should complete my study by considering the foreign relations of the state, including international law, commerce, the rights of war and conquest, public law, leagues, negotiations, treaties and so forth. But all this would represent a new subject too vast for my weak vision; and I ought always to keep my eyes fixed on matters more within my range.

Note

【1】 This should always be understood to refer only to free states, for elsewhere family, property, lack of asylum, necessity or violence may keep an inhabitant in the country unwillingly, and then his mere residence no longer implies consent either to the contract or to the violation of the contract.

【2】 In Genoa the word Libertas may be seen on the doors of all the prisons and on the fetters of the galleys. This use of the motto is excellent and just. In fact, it is only the malefactors of all states who prevent the citizens from being free. In a country where all such people were in the galleys, the most perfect liberty would be enjoyed.

【3】 The name 'Rome', which is said to derive from Romulus, is really Greek, and it means force; the name 'Numa' is also Greek, and it means law. Is it very probable that the first two kings of that city should have borne before they reigned names so clearly related to what they did?

【4】 I say 'Campus Martius' because this was where the comitia centuriata met. In the other two forms of assembly, the people met in the forum or elsewhere, and then the capite censi had as much influence and authority as the leading citizens.

【5】 The century thus drawn was called praerogativa because it was the first required to cast its vote; and this is the origin of our word 'prerogative'.

【6】 This nomination took place by night and in secret, as if they were ashamed to put a man above the law.

【7】 He could not have been sure of this if he had proposed appointing a dictator, for he did not dare to name himself, and he could not be sure that his colleagues would name him.

【8】 Nonne ea quae possidet Chamos deus tuus, tibi jure debentur? Such is the text of the Vulgate. Father de Carrières translates it thus: 'Do you not believe that you have a right to possess that which belongs to your God Chamos?' I do not know the bearing of the Hebrew text, but I notice that in the Vulgate, Jephthah positively recognizes the rights of the God Chamos, and that the French translation weakens this recognition by adding an 'according to you' which is not in the Latin.

【9】 It is clear beyond dispute that the Phocian war, called the Holy War, was not a war of religion. Its object was to punish sacrilege, and not to make unbelievers submit.

【10】 It should be noted that it is not so much the formal assemblies, like those of France, which bind the clergy together in a body, but rather the communion of churches. Communion and excommunication are the social compact of the clergy, one through which they will always be masters of both peoples and kings. All the priests who communicate together are fellow citizens, even though they are at opposite ends of the earth. This invention is a masterpiece of politics. There was nothing like it among the pagan priests; hence they never constituted a body of clergy.

【11】 See, among other things, in a letter of Grotius to his brother dated 11 April 1643, what that learned man approved of and what he disapproved of in Hobbes's De Cive. It is true that, being inclined to indulgence, he forgives that author the good points for the sake of the bad, but not everyone is so merciful.

【12】 'In the republic,' says the M(arquis) d'A(rgenson), 'everyone is perfectly free to do what does not injure others.' Here is the invariable boundary; one could not express it more exactly. I have not been able to deny myself the pleasure of quoting sometimes from this manuscript, although it is not known to the public, in order to pay homage to the memory of an illustrious and honourable man, who, even as a Minister of State, kept the heart of a true citizen, together with just and sound opinions on the government of his country.

【13】 Caesar pleading for Catilina tried to establish the dogma of the mortality of the soul. Cato and Cicero, to refute it, did not waste time with philosophy; they were content to show that Caesar was speaking like a bad citizen and advancing a doctrine that was injurious to the state. And this was what the Senate had to give judgement on, not any question of theology.

【14】 Marriage, for example, being a civil contract, has civil consequences without which it would be impossible for society itself to subsist. Let us suppose that in a given country the clergy reached the point of gaining the sole right of permitting marriage, a right which it is bound to usurp under any intolerant religion. Is it not then clear that in making the authority of the church supreme in this matter, it will nullify that of the prince, who will then have no subjects other than those the clergy allow him to have? Enable priests to decide whether to marry people according to their assent to this or that doctrine, their assent to this or that formula, or according to their being more or less devout, then is it not clear that if the clergy acts shrewdly and holds firm, it will in time alone dispose of inheritances, offices, the citizens and the state itself, since the latter could not endure if composed only of bastards? But, you may say, men will call upon the temporal power, issue summonses and warrants, seize church properties. What a sorry sight! If the clergy has even a little, I do not say courage, but common sense, it will allow everything to go its own way; it will quietly let the summonses, the warrants and seizures take place and still end up as master. It is no great sacrifice, I feel, to give up a part when you are sure of securing the whole.

人类幸福

21　太年轻会影响人的判断，太老也一样。

考虑欠周或者过虑，都会使人固执己见，痴迷不悟。

完成一项工作，马上去审视，我们仍然深陷其中；太久，又断了线索。

这就像欣赏离得太远或太近的画。唯有那么一个不可分割的点，是合适的位置。

其他的点，要么太近或太远，要么太高或太低。在绘画中，这个点取决于透视原理，那么就真理和道德而言，这个点又取决于什么？

22　苍蝇很强大，能战胜我们，麻痹我们的大脑，吞噬我们的肌体。

23　科学的无助。苦恼之际，自然科学知识无法安慰我对道德观的无知，而道德观方面的知识却可以安慰我对自然科学的无知。

24　人类的境况。反复无常，厌倦无聊，焦躁不安。

25　君王出行总是伴以侍卫、鼓乐、臣仆，以及所有其他随身用具，这种情景使人敬畏之情油然而生，因此，即使他们独处时的神态，也足以令臣民们满怀敬畏。这是因为，我们的大脑无法将君王本人和总是陪伴君王的随从区分开来。世人不知这是习惯使然，却相信是来自某种自然的力量，因此，有俗语道：“神相刻在脸上。”

26　建立王权的基础是臣民的理性和愚昧，尤其是他们的愚昧。世间最伟大、最重要的事物皆建立在臣民软弱无能的基础上。这是可以牢牢把握的根基，因为没有什么能比臣民的软弱无能更牢靠了。完全建立于理性之上的事物，比如对智慧的崇尚，根基不牢。

30　我们不会选择船上出身最高贵的人做船长。

31　我们只是城市的过客，不会顾及留在那里的声誉，但要待上一段时间就会在意。这一段时间是多长呢？它同我们虚荣琐碎的生活成正比。

33　最令我惊异的是，世人不惊异于自己的无能。我们行为严肃，人人遵循内心的意愿，但不是因为这样做真正有益，符合风气，而好像人人都确切地知道什么是理性，什么是品行正直。我们不断地失望，荒唐的谦卑使我们自责，却不将此归咎于我们总是引以为豪的本领。周围有相当一部分人不是怀疑论者，他们表明，人可以发表最极端的见解，既然他确信人不是生来无能而是天生智慧，这对维护怀疑论的声望倒是件好事。

36　谁看不到世界的空虚，谁就是空虚的人。那么，除了喧哗、消遣、憧憬未来的年轻人，还有谁看不到世界的空虚？

但不消遣的话，他们会无聊得要命。他们感到自己无足轻重，却不了解这种状态。这是因为，人一旦被迫反省，没有消遣，马上会沮丧得不堪忍受，这种感觉糟糕透顶。

42　有多少王国对我们一无所知！

43　琐事让人感到宽慰，因为琐事能使人感到烦恼。

44　想象。想象是人的主要天赋，因为人是谬误和谎言高手，如果不总是这样的话，欺骗性就更强；因为如果想象是判断谎言的绝对可靠标准的话，它也是判断真理的绝对可靠标准。然而，由于它总是虚假的，显示不出品质如何，因此给真理和谎言打上相同的印记。

我不是在谈论傻瓜，而是在谈论聪明绝顶之人，他们的想象富于感染力。理性的反对无济于事，不能决定事物的价值。

这股傲慢的力量阻碍、支配它的敌人理性，乐意到处显示它的势力，证实了人具有第二天性。想象拥有快乐的人和不快乐的人，患病的人和健康的人，也拥有富人和穷人；它使我们相信、怀疑、否定理性；它麻痹感官，又唤醒它们；它款待傻瓜，也款待贤能，它让宾客心满意足，而理性永远望尘莫及，这让我们无比恼火。善于想象的人比小心谨慎、理智地愉悦自己的人对自己更满意。他们神态傲慢，睥睨他人，辩论时胆大自信，而别人却羞怯犹疑；他们神采飞扬，常常能赢得听众的有利裁决，因为具有想象的智慧的人能赢得具有同样素质的法官的好感。想象力不会使傻瓜变得聪明，但能使他们高兴，理性就相反，只能让朋友沮丧：一个令朋友荣耀，另一个使他们蒙羞。

谁来分配声望？谁使我们尊敬他人、工作、法律、伟人？除了想象力，还能有谁？没有它的恩准，世上的财富就微不足道。那位地方法官一大把年纪让大家肃然起敬，你难道能不说他是在纯粹、高度的理性支配下，是在公正但不拘细枝末叶地断案吗？而照顾小节只会得罪弱者的想象力。看看他去听布道时虔诚、热忱的样子，流露出的仁爱之情更显得他判案公正，他正怀着值得效仿的崇敬心情等待布道开始。如果布道者出现时带着一副天生嘶哑的嗓音、一张奇怪的面孔，胡须被理发师刮得马马虎虎，恰好又衣冠不整，那么我敢打赌，不管他宣讲什么真理，我们的元老院议员都无法板着脸。

把世界上最伟大的哲学家放到一块木板上，木板比实际需要的要宽一些；如果脚下是峭壁，虽然理性可能使他相信自己是安全的，但想象仍会占上风。很多人只需想一下这个情景都会脸色发白，浑身冒汗。

我不想罗列出想象力的所有效果。谁都知道，看到猫或老鼠，听到煤块刺耳的爆裂声，等等，够使理智失常的。说话的腔调能影响最明智的人，能影响一篇演讲或一首诗的效果。

爱或憎改变正义的面目。如果辩护律师事先拿到了优厚的报酬，他会觉得自己辩护的诉讼案更合理。他的举止充满魄力，法官们被这种表面的东西所蒙蔽，觉得他的诉讼更正当。随风倒的理性多么荒唐！我应该列出人的几乎全部行为，除了想象，没有什么能让他激动，因为理性不得不屈服，明智地采纳人类的想象力在每个转折关头草率订立的原则。一味执着于追随理性的人会证明自己是傻瓜。既然理性这样合人心意，我们必须从早到晚工作，以得到想象中的好处，然后，睡眠消除了理性带来的疲劳，一觉醒来，神清气爽，我们要马上跳起身来，去追寻这个世界统治者的幽灵，忍受它制造的印象。这是错误的渊源，但不是唯一的一个。

让这两股力量结盟是对的，虽然在这种和平态势下想象占有很大优势，但在对立状态下它占有更绝对的优势。理性永远不会彻底战胜想象，相反的情况倒是常见。

我们的地方法官们表明他们深谙这一奥秘，他们的红色法袍、他们像毛绒绒的猫咪一样蜷缩在里面的白貂皮、他们端坐判案的法庭、鸢尾花旗帜[1]，所有这些，庄严的场面必不可少。如果医生不穿大褂，不骑骡子，如果满腹经纶的博士不戴方帽，不穿四倍于合适尺寸的肥大袍子，他们永远也不会蒙骗世人，而世人觉得他们这种样子真实可信，无法抗拒。如果他们拥有纯粹的公正，如果医生掌握真正的医术，他们就不必戴方帽；庄严的科学本身就会赢得尊敬。但是，因为只掌握想象的科学，他们只能借助这些无用的装备来激发想象，这才是他们真正关心的东西，实际上，这也正是他们如何赢得尊敬的东西。

唯有士兵不用这种方式掩饰自己，因为他们更具有实质性的作用；他们用武力证实自己，其他人却用外在的样子证明自己。

这就是为什么国王从来不设法掩饰自己。他们不必用非同寻常的衣装打扮自己，以显示身份，不过，他们有侍卫和伤痕累累的老兵保护。这支武装队伍的人员只有双手和力量是属于他们自己的，有鼓号在行进队伍的最前列奏响，还有千军万马在四周围绕，这千军万马够使最坚毅的人发抖。他们身上没有官阶佩饰，只是散发出一股威力。看到土耳其皇帝住在富丽堂皇的宫殿里，有四万禁卫军把守，还觉得他跟其他人一样，这需要多么强健的理智。

只要看到律师戴着帽子，穿着长袍，就尽可以相信其能力。

想象决定一切；它创造美丽、正义、幸福这些世界上最美好的东西。我非常想读那本意大利语的书，但我只看得懂书名，Dell’opinione regina del mondo仅这书名就比几本书都有价值。我不了解这本书，但支持书里的观点，不论里面有什么样的邪恶。

这样的情况或多或少都是这种骗人的本领导致的结果，显然别有用心地赋予我们这种本领，让我们必犯错误。我们还有很多犯错误的其他信念。

不仅长期存有的印象误导我们；新奇事物也具有相同的魔力，所以才产生了辩论，人们要么谴责对方追随儿时的假象，要么谴责对方草率地追随新的印象。如果谁发现了中庸之道，那就让他出来证明吧。任何信念，不管有多自然，即使儿时就埋在心底，也可能会被当成教育或感官造成的假象。

他们说：“因为你自幼相信，如果看不到盒子里的东西，里面就是空的。你相信真空可能存在。这只是感官的幻觉，被习惯强化，要由科学来更正。”其他人则说：“学校里教你没有真空这种东西，你违背了常识；在产生错误印象之前，这一点明白无误，现在，要回到你最初的状态才能更正这种印象。”那么究竟谁骗了你，是感官还是教育？

我们还有一种针对疾病的错误信念，它妨碍我们判断和感觉。如果重病确实危及健康，我毫不怀疑，不那么重的病对健康的危害程度可以相应减小。

自身利益是另一个使我们情愿盲目的绝好工具。世上最公正的人，也不容许他判自己的案子。我知道一种人，为避免偏袒自己的危险，适得其反地倒向极不公正的一边。想让一个原本合理的诉讼案败诉，最保险的办法是将它委托给近亲打理。正义和真理是两个微妙的点，我们粗糙的工具无法精确地量到。就算能碰得着，也会把点弄得模糊，处处量到虚假，而不是真相。

那么，人类对真理没有确切的信念，对虚伪倒是有几个极好的信念。现在让我们来看看有多少。

然而，犯错误最荒唐的信念是感性和理性之间的争斗。

46　虚荣。爱的因与果。克利奥佩特拉[2]。

47　我们从来不活在当下。我们回忆过去；我们预见未来，好像嫌它来得太慢，催它快些；或者回忆过去，好像要留住它飞逝的时光。我们愚蠢得在不属于自己的时光里徜徉，不理会唯一属于我们的一刻。我们枉然地向往逝去的时光，又盲目地逃离唯一存在的一刻。这样，当下往往使我们痛楚。把它丢到视线以外是因为它使我们忧伤；觉得它令人愉悦就会惋惜地看着它消逝。我们设法给予它未来的支持，思量如何安排无法掌控的事情，安排到一个我们从没有把握企及的时间。

让我们每个人审视一下自己的想法；他会发现，他只关心过去和未来。我们几乎从不考虑当下，真正考虑的时候，也只是看看它对未来的计划有什么帮助。当下从来不是我们的目标。过去和当下是我们的工具，只有未来是我们的目标。因此，我们从没有真正生活过，只是渴望生活，而且，既然我们总是计划如何快乐，就必然不会。

49　在我看来，恺撒[3]用征服世界取悦自己时，年事已高，这种消遣对奥古斯都[4]和亚历山大[5]还可以；他们是年轻人，不那么容易被遏制。恺撒应该表现得更为成熟一些。

53　人类向禽兽屈服，甚至崇拜禽兽，真是无耻之尤。

54　反复无常。事物的性质多样，心灵的意向纷呈。这是因为呈送给心灵的都不是简单的事情，心灵也从不简单地凡事劳神。这就是为什么同一件事情，可以让我们发笑，也可以使我们哭泣。55反复无常。我们以为摆弄人就像摆弄一架普通的风琴。他确实是架风琴，但离奇、变换、不定。只会弹奏普通风琴的人，永远不会在这架风琴上弹出和谐的曲调。你得知道琴键在哪里。

56　一件事情，可以让我们快活，出了差错时，也可以让我们烦恼，这令人郁闷。成千上万的事情都可能，也确实经常碰到这种情况。事情顺利时愉快，不顺利时也不烦恼，能发现这个奥秘的人就是找到了诀窍。这是一种恒动。

57　太自由不好。

应有尽有不好。

58　专制在于妄图统治一切，无视秩序。

强壮的人、标致的人、聪明的人、虔诚的人，在这些人所处的各个不同领域里，每个人都只是他自己房间的主人，不涉及其他地方。有时他们相遇，强壮的人和英俊的人便相互争夺优势。这很愚蠢，因为他们拥有不同的优势。他们彼此不了解，又错误地妄图到处统治。不能这样做，即使是力量：它在学术界就行不通，因为它只能统治表面行为。——因此，这些论点是错误的……

专制。专制在于妄图以一种方式获得只能以另一种方式获得的东西。我们为不同的功绩支付不同的代价；我们肯定喜欢魅力，害怕力量，相信知识。

为获得这些功绩必须付出代价，拒绝付出是错误的，要求获得其他功绩也是错误的。因此，下面这些论点是错误、专横的：“我漂亮，所以你要怕我。我强壮，所以你要爱我。我……”同样认为：“他不强壮，所以我不尊敬他。他不聪明，所以我不怕他。”也是错误、专横的。

65　多样性。神学是一门科学，但同时又是多少门科学？人是一种物质，但如果将其解剖，他又是什么？头颅、心脏、腹部、血管、每一根血管、每一节血管、血、血的汁液？

一个市镇或一道风景，从远处看是一个市镇或一道风景，但待走近就变成了房舍、树木、瓦片、树叶、小草、蚂蚁、蚂蚁的腿等，无穷无尽。所有这些都包含在“风景”这个词里。

68　我短暂的一生会溶入其前后的无边岁月——像对一位只逗留了一日的客人的回忆——我看到自己占有的狭小空间被广袤无垠的空间吞没，而我对这空间一无所知，空间对我也是如此，每当想到这些时，我便会恐惧，且惊诧地看到自己在这里，而不是那里；我没有理由在这里，而不是那里，没有理由是这时，而不是那时。是谁把我放置在这里？是谁的旨意和行动，把此时、此地分配给了我？

69　悲惨。约伯[6]和所罗门[7]。

70　如果我们处于真正幸福的状态，就不必回避考虑它。

71　对立性。骄傲抵消了所有的悲惨境遇；人类要么藏起它们，要么展示它们，并为自己意识到这种悲惨境遇而自豪。

72　人要了解自己，即使这样做无助于发现真理，但至少有助于经营自己的日子，这样做很妥帖。

73　反复无常的原因是，人认识到眼前的快乐是虚假的，同时还有一个原因是，他认识不到不存在的快乐是虚幻的。

77　骄傲。好奇心只不过是虚荣心。我们通常只是为了有谈资才想了解点什么；换句话说，如果不是想谈论海的话，就不会作海上旅行，这只不过是因为热衷于向别人描述而去见识点什么。

78　对人的描述。依赖、独立的欲望、需求。

79　放弃痴迷上的东西很累人。一个人家庭生活美满，但只要碰到一个赏心悦目的女人，或是去赌博，快活五六天，再回到先前的日子时，他会满心遗憾。这样的事情每天都有。

80　尊敬意味着：让自己退场。这可能看起来毫无意义，但很有道理，因为这等于说：如果你需要，我当然应该让自己退场，因为你不退出的时候，我才这样做；另外，尊敬是用来彰显伟人的。如果尊敬意味着坐在扶手椅上，那是向所有人表示尊敬，也就无法显示区别。我们让自己退场后，就凸显出区别来了。

81　唯一能被普遍接受的法则，在日常事务中是一国之法，在其他事务中是大多数人的意愿。为什么会这样？因为其中蕴含着权力问题。

这就是为什么君王由于另有权力来源，不听从多数大臣的意见。

毫无疑问，平均占有财富是公平的，但是，人无法让权势服从权利，就只好让权利服从权势。因为不能强化公平，就只好让势力公平化。这样，权利和权势共处，天下太平，这是至善。

82　智慧将我们带回童年，除非你变回幼童。

83　世界是个事物的好裁判，因为它处于一种天然的蒙昧状态，人类确实处于这种状态。知识有两极，两极可以相遇。一极是每个人出生时那种纯粹、天然的蒙昧状态；另一极是才智之士领略了人类整个知识范畴后达到的境界，但达到后却发现自己一无所知，回到了出发时的蒙昧状态，然而这是一种明智的蒙昧，一种自知之明。有的人停在半路，他们脱离了天生的蒙昧，但并没有达到另一极；他们对一些必须掌握的知识略知一二，却装作什么都懂。他们让世界烦恼，把一切都弄错。

平庸的人和比他们聪明的人构成世界的趋势；前者鄙视世界，也被世界鄙视。他们的判断有失公允，而世界对他们的判断却公正无误。

84　笛卡尔。总之我们一定会说：“那是数字和运动的结果。”因为事实就是这样，但说出它们究竟是什么，并把机器装配起来，就显得可笑了，这样做没有意义，靠不住，也很辛苦。即使真的是这样，整个哲学也不值得我们付出哪怕一小时的努力。

86　论真正的公允。我们不再拥有，如果有，也不应该像一个人应该遵守一国习俗那样，把它当作公正原则来接受。

这就是为什么找不到权利的时候，我们会找到权势。

87　大法官神情庄重，身着精致长袍，因为他的职位是虚幻的；国王就用不着这样，他享有权力，用不着想象。法官、医生，等等，除了享有想象力，其他一无所有。

88　是能力的结果，而不是习惯，因为富有独创性的人很少。大多数人只会亦步亦趋，并拒绝认可那些希望自己的独创性得到认可的人。如果这些人坚持要别人认可，又看不起没有独创性的人，别人就会给他们安上可笑的骂名嘲弄他们，甚至施以拳脚。因此，不要傲气夺人，偷偷地沾沾自喜吧。

94　人民的忠告。最大的祸害是内讧。

如果要奖励优点的话，必然会带来祸害，因为人人都会申明自己值得奖励。如果傻瓜生来就有继承权，带来的祸害就没有那么可怕，也未必要怕。

95　人民的忠告。优雅不仅仅是虚荣，因为它能表明很多人在为你效劳。你的头发表明你有仆人，有香水制作者，等等，领饰、配线、镶边，等等，表明……很多人服侍一个人，并不仅仅意味着肤浅的炫耀或穿着。

雇佣的人手越多，就越有权力。优雅是展示权力的手段。

98　为什么跛脚的人不会惹怒我们，而蹩脚的头脑却会？因为跛脚的人承认我们是昂首挺胸走路，而蹩脚的头脑却说瘸着走路的是我们。不过，我们应该为此感到遗憾，而不是生气。

埃皮克提图[8]问得更深刻：为什么有人说我们头痛时，我们不生气，可当有人说我们的论点或选择有问题时，我们却会生气？

99　原因是我们确信自己不头痛，不跛脚，但不敢确定是否作出了正确的选择。由于我们只对自己掌握的证据有把握，当别人掌握的证据得出相反结论的时候，我们便犹豫不决，措手不及。当有一千人嘲笑我们的选择时，情况就更是如此，因为我们应该更看重自己的判断，而不是众人的，但这样做需要胆识，所以很难。对于跛脚的人从来没有观点上的冲突。

人就是这样：如果反复跟他说他是个傻瓜，他就相信。这样说多了，他就会说服自己相信。这是因为，人独处时在内心跟自己对话，所以有必要恰当地控制这种对话。有害的交流败坏风度。我们必须尽可能远离沉默，只在内心谈论上帝。因为我们知道上帝是真实的，所以能说服自己相信这一点。

103　权利、权势。追随权利正确无疑，追随权势确有必要。

没有权势的权利无助，没有权利的权势专横。

没有权势的权利要经受挑战，因为恶人总是无处不在。没有权利的权势要遭受指责。因此，我们必须将权利和权势结合在一起，为着这个目的，我们将权利铸进权势，或将权势铸进权利。

权利易受争论，权势易被认可，所以没有争论的余地。因此，权利不可能变成权势，因为权势会挑战权利，宣称权利不公正而自己是公正的。

由此而来，无法将权利铸进权势，我们就把权势铸进了权利。

104　生为贵族享有多么优越的地位，它赋予一个十八岁的人身份、认可和尊敬，而别人五十岁之前都可能无法赢得。这意味着他毫不费力地赢得三十年的领先优势。

105　如果在狩猎时，动物理智地作出了凭本能才能做的事，理智地说出了凭本能才能说的话，或者警告同伴错过或发现了猎物，它当然接着就会谈起对它影响更大的话题，比如它会说：“咬段这根绳子，它弄疼我了，我够不着。”

106　伟大。因果关系表明，人因为自己的贪欲创造出这么杰出的秩序，有多么伟大。

107　鹦鹉擦拭嘴巴，即使已经很干净。

108　我们身体的哪个部位能体会到快乐？是手、胳膊、肌肉，还是血液？显然是一种非物质的东西。

109　反对怀疑论。很奇怪，我们不把问题弄得模糊不清，便无法下定义；我们总是没完没了地纠缠在这些问题上。我们假设，每个人都以相同的方式推测这些问题，但这是无端的假设，因为不能得到证明。我确实看到大家在一些相同的场合使用某些词句；每当两个人看到一个物体移动位置时，都会用相同的词句表达看到的现象，每个人都会说，那个物体移动了。这种用词的一致性导致人们断言说，思想也具有一致性，但这种断言根本没有说服力，虽然奇怪的是，情况确实如此，因为我们知道，不同的假设经常得出相同的结论。

至少这足以把问题弄得模糊不清，虽然没有完全遮挡住自然之光，而在这些问题上自然之光倒能提供确定性。柏拉图主义者会为此打赌，但这会使光线更暗，惹怒教条主义者，把荣耀归于怀疑论者的小集团，它代表含混不清的模糊和费解的晦涩，我们的疑虑无法遮挡住其中的所有光亮，就像自然之光不能驱散所有黑暗。

110　我们不仅仅凭借理性掌握真理，也凭借心灵。正是凭借后者，我们才掌握了第一原理；理性与此无关，只是枉然地驳斥这些原理。除了这一点，怀疑论者没有其他攻击的目标，只是漫无目标地白费力气。我们知道自己不是在做梦，但可能无法理智地证明这一点；我们的无能除了证明理性的无能，别的什么也证明不了，也证明不了我们所掌握的全部知识的不确定性，而且这种不确定性会一直存在下去。关于第一原理的知识，如空间、时间、物体的运动、数量，正如其他凭借理性获得的知识一样可靠，正是基于这些凭借心灵和本能获得的知识，理性才得以使用和建立论据。心灵感到，存在三维空间，存在一个无穷数列；理性接着证明，没有两个平方数，其中的一个是另一个的两倍。原理感觉到了，命题证明了，双方都得到了肯定，虽然是通过不同手段。如果理性在同意接受来自于心灵的第一原理以前，要求先证明它们，这既毫无意义，又荒谬可笑。如同心灵在同意接受所有命题以前，要求获得经过理性证明的关于命题的直觉知识，一样荒谬可笑。

我们的无能因此只效力于谦卑的理由，可它却想做万物的判官，但又不能驳倒我们的确凿事实。好像只有通过理性才能学习知识！对于上帝，则恰恰相反，我们从来不需要理性，我们凭直觉和感觉了解一切！但是大自然拒绝赋予我们这样的福祉，它赐予我们的这类知识微不足道；其他一切知识都要凭理性去获取。

这就是为什么有些人很幸运，因为上帝感动了他们的心，赋予其宗教信仰，使他们感到完全有理由信从上帝。而对那些没有信仰的人，我们只能通过推理让其获得信仰，直到上帝感化了他们，赋予其信仰；不为上帝感化而获得的信仰只是世俗的，对救赎毫无用处。

111　我诚然可以想象一个人没有手，没有脚，或没有头，因为只有经验告诉我们，头比脚更重要。但我无法想象一个人没有思想，那他将是一块石头或一个动物。

112　本能和理性，两种天性的标志。

113　思想的芦苇。我无须从空间寻求人的尊严，而是寻求我思想的秩序。拥有土地对我毫无益处。凭借空间，宇宙会像对一个微粒那样掌握我，吞噬我；凭借思想，我却可以掌握宇宙。

114　人的伟大在于他知道自己可悲：一棵树不知道自己可悲。

因此，知道自己可悲，这本身就可悲，但知道自己可悲，是伟大的。

115　灵魂的非物质性。当哲学家压抑了自己的激情时，是什么物质取得了这个效果？

116　所有这些悲惨的例子证明了他的伟大。这是一个圣明的主的悲惨，一个被废黜的王的悲惨。

117　人的伟大。人的伟大是如此之明显，甚至可以从他的悲惨推断出来，因为在动物身上是天性的东西，在人身上便称作悲惨，承认这一点的话，如果如今人的天性同动物的一样，他一定已经从曾经所处的更高境界堕落了。

除了被废黜的君主，谁真的会为自己不在王位而闷闷不乐？有谁认为保罗·哀米利乌斯[9]为自己不是执政官而不快吗？相反，人人认为他很高兴自己曾经担任这一职务，因为这个职务不是永久的。人们认为珀修斯[10]被废黜时很不高兴，因为王位是永久的，对他能够忍受不在王位的生活感到惊讶。谁会为只有一张嘴而不高兴？谁不会为只有一只眼睛而不高兴？也许从来没有人为自己没有三只眼睛而苦恼，但一只眼睛也没有的人就无以慰藉了。

118　人的伟大，甚至在于他的贪欲。他以此建立了如此杰出的体系，从而树立起真正仁爱的形象。

119　对立性。（在展示了人是如何邪恶、如何伟大以后。）现在，让人来判断自己的价值，让他自爱，因为他天生具有行善的能力；但这不是他爱自身的卑劣的理由。让他鄙视自己，因为他仍然缺乏这种能力；但这不是他鄙视这种本能的理由。让他恨自己，让他爱自己；他本身具有掌握真理，保持幸福的能力，但他并不拥有恒久不变，或令人满意的真理。

因此，我应当激起人寻求真理的欲望，明白自己的知识如何被情绪蒙上了阴影，从而随时准备抛弃情绪，追随真理，无论在何处找到它。我想让他讨厌自身的贪欲，因为贪欲会替他做主，这样，他抉择时就不会被贪欲蒙蔽，而一旦作出抉择，也不会被贪欲妨碍。

120　我们如此狂妄，我们要全世界知道自己，甚至是那些在我们身后才来到世上的人。周围几个人的溢美之词就能让我们心满意足，这就是我们的虚荣心。

121　太明确地向人解释他如何等同于动物而不指出他的伟大之处，这是危险的；过多地说他的伟大之处，而不指出他的卑劣，这也是危险的。两种情况都不让他了解，就更危险；而两种情况都向他表明，则最为重要。

不能让人相信，他要么等同于动物，要么等同于天使；也不能让他认为，自己既不等同于动物，也不等同于天使；但他必须知道，自己既等同于动物，又等同于天使。

122　伟大和可悲。由于可悲和伟大可以互为推断出来，有些人更倾向于得出这样的结论，即人是可悲的，因为他用自己的伟大证明了这一点。而另一些人则用可悲的证据得出更中肯的结论，即人是伟大的。一方称作伟大性的证明，在另一方只不过是推断可悲的论据，因为堕落得越深，就越是可悲；反之亦然。在无休无止的循环中，一个紧跟另一个，因为可以肯定的是，人的洞见越来越深刻，所以他发现自身同时存在着可悲和伟大之处。总之，人知道自己可悲，因而，他是可悲的，因为事实如此。而正因为他知道这一点，他是真正伟大的。

123　对立性。蔑视我们的存在，无谓的死亡，憎恨我们的存在。

124　对立性。人天生轻信、怀疑、羞怯、大胆。

125　天然的信念，除了说它是习惯性的信念，还能意味着什么？对于儿童，是从父辈那里继承下来的习惯性信念，如同笼中捕兽。

习惯的改变，会产生不同的天然信念，这可由经验证明。如果存在一些习惯所不能根除的信念，就会存在其他既是习惯性的，又是非天然的信念，天性或新习惯都无法将其根除。这一切都取决于一个人的性情。

126　父辈唯恐子女天然的爱心会泯灭。那么，这种可泯灭的天性是什么？

习惯是第二天性，可以摧毁第一天性。但什么是天性？为什么习惯不是天生的？恐怕天性本身不过是第一习惯，就像习惯是第二天性一样。

127　人的天性，可以用两种方式考虑：要么以他的结局来考虑，那他就是伟大的，不可媲美的；要么以大众的品评来考虑，因为马和狗的天性是大众根据其奔跑和驱赶陌生人的能力来评判的，这样的话，人是下贱又邪恶的。这两种方式导致了不同的看法，引起了哲学家之间的争论，因为个人都否认别人的假说。

有人说：“人不是为这种结局而生的，因为他的所作所为辜负了这种结局。”其他人说：“人的行为如此卑鄙，他离这种结局相去甚远。”

128　有两样东西教导人什么是他的全部天性：本能和经验。

129　行业。思想。一切为一个整体，又变化万千。

人的天性中又有多少种天性！有多少种职业！多么偶然，多么平淡，大家听到赞许便选择了职业。善于转向的脚跟。

130　如果他颂扬自己，我便鄙视他。

如果他鄙视自己，我便颂扬他。

我不断地否定他，直到他明白自己是一个怪物，不可理喻。

131　怀疑论者最有力的论点，暂且不提次要的论点，就是，除了能肯定这些信念是通过某种天生的直觉获得的，我们无法肯定这些信念真实可靠（信仰和神启除外）。现在这种天生的直觉没有提供令人信服的证据，证明这些信念真实可靠。除了信仰，还不能确定人是由一个仁慈的上帝创造的，还是由一个恶魔创造的，或者只是出于偶然。这样的话，根据我们的由来，这些固有的信念究竟是正确的，还是错误的，还是含糊不定，总是一个疑问。

此外，除信仰以外，没有人可以肯定他是睡着还是醒着，因为我们入眠时，我们也同样坚信我们像现在一样醒着。正如我们经常梦到我们在做梦，一个梦里又套着另一个梦，有没有可能我们的前半生不过是一场梦，其他的梦移植在里面，当我们死后，才能从中醒来呢？有没有可能在这场持续的梦境里，我们对真理和美德准则的掌握，会像在平常的睡眠里掌握得那么少呢？所有这些时间和生命的流逝、所有这些我们能感觉得到的各式各样的身体、令我们激动的种种想法，都可能只不过是幻觉，如同时间的流逝，和梦境里虚无的魅影。我们认为，我们看见了空间、形状、物体的运动，我们感觉到时间在流逝，我们计量它的流逝，事实上，我们的行为像醒着的时候一样。结果，因为前半生在睡眠中度过，我们自己承认，除了表面现象，我们对真理茫然不知，因为所有的直觉都是那段时间里的幻觉。有谁知道我们的后半生不过又是一觉，虽然自己认为是醒着，同第一觉稍有区别，睡着以后，一个个梦移植上去，然后从中醒来，虽然自己以为还睡着？又有谁会怀疑，如果我们和别人一起做梦，大家的梦又碰巧相同，这倒是常事，如果醒来时孤单一人，我们会觉得事情颠三倒四？

这些就是各方的要点，暂且不提那些次要的论点，比如那些怀疑论者用来反对习惯、教育和当地习俗等的影响的论点，怀疑论呼一小口气就能将其推翻，虽然这种影响说服了大多数普通人，但这些人的信条是建立在这种虚假的基础之上的。你只需看看怀疑论者的书；如果你没有被彻底说服，很快就会了，也许会被过分说。

我暂且停在教条主义者唯一的可取之处，即，平心而论，我们不能怀疑天然的信念。

怀疑论者对此的简短答复是，我们由来的不确定性，必然导致我们天性的不确定性。教条主义者自从世界的开端就一直在试图回应这一说法。

（若有人想获得更多的有关怀疑论者的情况，应该去读读他们的书；他很快就会被说服，也许会被过分说服。）

这意味着人们之间的公开战争，其中每个人都必须采取立场，要么站在教条主义一边，要么站在怀疑论者一边，因为谁想象他能保持中立的话，就是一个出类拔萃的怀疑论者。这种中立性就是他们那个小集团的本质。只要不反对他们，就是他们的坚定支持者，这正是他们的优势所在。他们甚至不顾自己的利益，中立，冷漠，不再评判任何事情，包括他们自己。

那么，在这种事态下人应该何去何从？去怀疑一切，怀疑他是否醒着，是否被挤压或被焚烧？怀疑他是否在怀疑，怀疑他是否存在？

没有人会这么过分，而且我坚持认为，从来没有十足真诚的怀疑论者。是天性支撑着无可奈何的理性，防止它太失控，误入歧途。

另外，他会说他确实拥有真理，可稍有压力就不能证明自己的说法，而被迫放弃吗？

那么，人是个什么样的怪物啊！多么奇异、多么可恶、多么混乱、多么自相矛盾、多么惊心动魄！万物的判官、软弱的小人、真理的宝库、怀疑和谬误的巢穴、宇宙的荣耀和糟粕！

谁来解除这个困惑？这当然是教条主义和怀疑论望尘莫及的，是所有人类哲学望尘莫及的。人类超越了人类的理性范围。那么就让我们向怀疑论者所一贯倡导的让步，他们认为真理超出了我们力所能及的范围，是无法企及的目标，真理不是尘世的居民，它以天堂为家，躺在上帝的膝上，只有当它取悦上帝时，上帝才揭示它，让我们了解它。让我们从尚未创造出的真理和真理的化身来了解自己的真实天性吧。

如果凭借理性寻求真理，我们就无法回避这三个学派中的任何一个。没有沉闷的天性，你就不能做一个怀疑论者，或柏拉图主义者；不背叛理性，你就不能做一个教者。

天性使柏拉图主义者和怀疑论者困惑，理性使教条主义者困惑。那么，凭借天然的理性探寻自己的真实情况的你，作为人，会怎么样？你不能回避这三个学派中的一个，也不可能在三者中任何一个里面生存。

那么就知道了，骄傲的人，你自身是一个什么样的悖论。谦卑吧，无能的理性！沉默吧，软弱的天性！要明白人无限地超越人类的理性范围，要倾听你的主人讲述你的真实情况，你对此一无所知。

倾听上帝的声音吧。

人的境况具有双重性，这难道不像白昼一样清晰明了吗？问题是，如果人从未堕落过，他会清白无辜、心安理得地享有真理和幸福，而且，如果人除了堕落没有做过别的，他就不懂得什么是真理，什么是幸福。因为我们这么不幸福（而且如果我们的境况中没有伟大的因素的话，我们应该没有这么不幸福），我们便懂得什么是幸福，但没法得到它。我们觉察得到真理的形象，但除了谎言我们一无所有，对真理我们不是绝对无知，也不是绝对了解；因此，很显然，我们曾经拥有一定程度的完美，又不幸地从中堕落。

那么，让我们设想，人的境况具有双重性。让我们设想，人类无限地超越人类的理性范围，而没有信仰相助，他仍将认为自己是不可揣测的，因为谁也看不到，除非我们认识到人类的双重性，不然我们将仍旧对自己的真相一无所知，无可奈何？

然而，令人惊骇的是，没有远离我们知识领域的奥秘，没有罪恶转嫁说，我们对自己就一无所知。

毫无疑问，能让我们的理性震惊的莫过于说，始祖的罪行牵连了后人，而他们离原罪那么遥远，似乎不可能是同犯。这个罪恶的渊源在我们看来不仅是不可能的，诚然也是最不公正的。因为在一个小孩子存在之前六千年犯下的罪行中，他的角色微不足道，也根本无法行使自己的意愿，却把他罚入永久的地狱，还有什么比这更有悖于我们可怜的正义规则？没有什么比这更粗野地震惊我们，然而，恰恰因为这个谜，这个最令人费解的谜，我们仍然令自己费解。我们的境况纠缠成一个结，给抛进那个深渊，结果，在不存在这个谜的情况下揣摩人，比人自己揣摩这个谜更难。

这表明，上帝希望我们无法理解因存在而面临的重重困难，所以才把那个结藏得那么高，或者更准确地说，藏得那么低，使我们无法够得到。因此，我们真正了解自己，不是凭借理性骄傲的活动，而是凭借它简单的顺从。

这些基本事实牢固地树立在神圣不可侵犯的宗教权威之上，告诫我们，确实存在着两个同样永恒不变的真理。一个是人被创造出来，或者说，他沐浴着神的恩典，高高地屹立于整个自然之上，生而仰望上帝，共享他的神性；另一个是人从第一状态堕落，陷于罪恶之中，变成了野兽。这两个命题同样确定无疑。

《圣经》在一些地方公开宣布了这一点：喜悦归于人子——我要将我的灵浇灌凡有血气的——你们是神；而在另一些地方却说：凡有血气的尽都如草——人如死亡的畜类一样——我心里说，这乃为世人的缘故。

这清楚地表明，人从神恩而造，对上帝心向往之，分享他的神性，没有神恩，他将被视为田野之诸兽。

136　消遣。有时，当我开始思考人从事的各种活动，在宫廷里或争战中面临的危险和麻烦，由此引起的诸多争吵和狂怒，狂妄而常为邪恶的野心等。我就常说，人不快乐的唯一原因是他不知道如何安静地待在屋里。一个人如果一生富足，就不会离家去航海；如果懂得享受居家生活，就不会去围攻什么堡垒；如果能消受得了城里的生活，终其一生，人们都不会付出那么大的代价去买军职，而只会寻机赌博消遣，找人做伴，因为不喜欢待在家里。

但寻找引起所有不快乐的具体原因后，仔细想想，既然我了解大概的原因，我发现了一个非常切实的理由，人对自己软弱的凡人境况存有天然的不满，这境况太悲惨，认真地思索一下，便觉得无以慰藉。

想象你喜欢的任何情形，总括你可能得到的所有祝福，称王仍然是世上最美妙的事情；但是，如果你想象，一个人拥有这个地位带来的一切好处，却没办法消遣，只能苦思冥想自己生为何人，这种虚伪的福气让他过不下去；他必将开始考虑面临的所有威胁、犯上作乱的可能，最后要考虑不可避免的死亡和疾病，结果是，如果被剥夺了所谓的消遣，他就不快乐，实在是比他最卑微的臣民还不快乐，而他们是可以享受运动和消遣的。

因此，唯一对人有好处的，是不去思索自己生为何人，方式可以是要么谋一份差事，权且忘掉这个问题；要么用新奇、惬意的嗜好让自己忙碌起来，比如赌博、狩猎、观看饶有趣味的表演，简而言之，是用消遣的方式。

这就是为什么人如此热衷于赌博和女性朋友圈子、战争和要职。这并不是说它们真正给人带来了幸福，也没有任何人指望真正的幸福在于拥有赌博赢来的钱，或猎获的野兔：谁也不会将其当作礼物。人们想要的，不是会使人想起自己不幸境况的惬意平静的生活，不是战争的危险，也不是工作的负担，而是鼓动自己停止思考，娱乐自己。这就是为什么我们喜欢狩猎胜过捕获。

这就是为什么人如此喜欢热闹；这就是为什么监禁的惩罚如此可怕；这就是为什么独处的快乐如此不可理喻。事实上，这就是为国王最大的快乐，因为人们总是试图让他消遣，让他尽情欢乐。围绕在国王身边的人唯一想做的就是让他消遣，不让他想到自己，因为尽管身为国王，一想到自己便会闷闷不乐。

这就是人为获得幸福而作的全部谋划；从哲学的观点考虑这种谋划的人坚持认为，人整天追逐野兔，但它却又不是自己想买的东西，实在是不理智。持有这种看法的人对我们的天性了解太少。野兔本身不会让我们免于思考死亡和苦难这些令人苦恼的话题，但狩猎本身却有这样的作用。因此，当有人建议皮拉斯[11]休息时，他也一直在努力争取休息，却很难做到。[12]

让一个人去休息，如同让他愉快地生活。这意味着建议他享受一种充分快乐的状态，在其中悠闲地思考，有苦恼。这意味着不了解人的天性。

因此，人们回避休息胜过回避其他事情，因为他们生来明白自己是怎么回事；为找麻烦，他什么都可做。

那么，责怪他们就不对了；他们寻求刺激没有错——如果只是为消遣。麻烦的是，他们寻求刺激，好像一旦寻求的东西到手，就不会不由衷地快乐。这就是为什么有理由说他们的寻求是枉然的。所有这一切表明，无论是批评者还是被批评者，他们都不了解人的真正天性。

人们因急切追求永远无法满足自己的东西而受到责备时，如果认真地考虑一下，最恰当的回答应该是，他们只不过是在寻求一份激烈的、充满活力的工作，以占据自己的头脑，这就是为什么他们选择的目标足以诱惑自己，能怂恿自己热切地追求。他们的对手找不到答案，（名利，炫耀的乐趣。舞蹈，考虑好往哪里放脚。）

而他们也不那样回答，因为他们不了解自己。他们不知道，自己最需要的是狩猎，而不是捕获的猎物。贵族诚然知道，狩猎是一项伟大的运动，是王者的运动，但他的猎人没有这种感受。他们设想，如果能获得某项任命，过后就可以享受休息了，他们没有意识到天性的疯狂和贪婪。当他们真正需要的不过是活动的时候，却以为自己真心希望休息。

他们有一种秘密本能，驱使他们寻找外部的消遣和工作，这是挥之不去的苦难感带来的结果。他们还有一种秘密本能，源自天性中的伟大，他们会告诉自己，唯一真正的幸福在于休息而不是神经兴奋。这两个对立的本能搞乱藏在灵魂深处的计划，使得他们用活动的方式寻求休息，而又使得他们总是设想，一旦克服了某些明显的困难，能打开房门欢迎休息时，错失的满足感自然会到。

我们的日子都是这样度过的：我们挣扎着克服某些障碍以寻求休息，一旦克服了，休息却显得无法忍受，因为它招致无聊。我们必须摆脱它，去渴望兴奋。

我们不考虑当下，也不考虑可能来临的苦难，而且即使我们在各方面都感到很安全，无聊也不会不从我们内心深处浮出——那是它自然扎根的地方，然后毒害我们的整个大脑。

人真是不高兴，即使没有理由也会感到百无聊赖，这是他天然的性情所致；他也真是不可救药，即使有一千零一个基本的理由让他无聊，哪怕最微不足道的事情，比如用台球杆推动一只球，也足以让他消愁解闷。

你会说：“但是，他做这些的目的究竟是什么？”正因为这样做了，他明天才能向朋友们夸耀，说自己比别人打得好。同样，其他人在书房里埋头苦干，这样就可以向学者证明，他们解决了一些迄今无法解决的代数问题。许多人在我看来也一样愚蠢，他们甘冒最大的风险，这样过后就可以自诩，攻下了某个要塞。还有一些人疲于奔命，观察上面这些现象，不是为变得更明智，只是为表明他们认识那些人。这些人是地段上最大的傻瓜，因为他们明白自己在做什么，但是人人都看得出来，如果他们也明白的话，别人就不会再愚蠢下去了。

假设一个人每天赌一点小钱日子就不会乏味。如果每天早上给他一笔钱，这笔钱的数目是他当天会赢到的，但前提是他不去赌博，那你会令他闷闷不乐。或许可以这样辩解，他想要的是赌博的乐趣，而不是赢到的钱。那么就让他玩，但不赢什么，可是这样就激不起他的兴趣，会让他感到无聊，因此他想要的不仅是娱乐。让人三心二意、不能兴奋起来的娱乐会使人变得无聊。他需要刺激，他必须哄骗自己去想象：放弃赌博得到的礼物自己并不想要，而赌博赢到了才会开心。他必须为自己的爱好设定某个目标，然后为这个既定目标激起欲望、愤怒、恐惧，像小孩子涂抹出一副面孔，却吓着自己。

这就是为什么，一个人数月前失去了独子，今早又因为诉讼案和与人争吵而烦躁郁闷，可这会儿他的思绪全然不在丧子之痛。不要惊讶；他的注意力都集中在野猪将向哪个方向逃跑，他的狗已经猛烈地追逐了六个小时。这就是他所需要的。虽然一个人可能悲伤不已，但如果你能说服他做点什么来消遣一下，做的过程中他会很快乐；虽然一个人可能心情舒畅，但如果没有消遣，没有让他沉醉的激情或娱乐去摆脱无聊，他很快就会闷闷不乐。没有消遣就没有快乐；有了消遣就没有悲伤。这就是构成达官显贵快乐的东西，因为有一大批人为其提供消遣，而且他们有能力保持这种状态。

请不要误会。做总监、大法官、首席法官，其中很多人每天早上从各地赶来，不留出一个小时考虑自己，这除了说明他们享有地位，还意味着什么？而一旦失宠，被贬到乡下的房子里，没有财富享用，也没有仆人伺候，无法满足其需要，这时他们必然凄惨、沮丧，因为没有人阻止他们想到自己的惨境。

139　消遣。人自幼便有责任照应自己的荣誉、自己的财产、自己的朋友，甚至朋友的财产和荣誉，他们担负着履行职责、参加语言培训和运动的重任，并要自己懂得，如果他们或他们朋友的身体、荣誉、财产不是一切正常的话，自己就决不会快乐。他们还要懂得，只要有一件事出了差错，自己就会不快乐。因此，他们背负着责任和义务，从每天的第一刻起就开始烦恼。你会说，这个让人快乐的办法实在是奇怪；能想出更高明的办法让人不快乐吗？不然人又能做什么？你只需消除他所有的牵挂，这样他们就会看到自己，想想自己是谁、从何处来、往何处去。这就是为什么人不能太忙碌、太苦恼，这就是为什么当他们有空闲从纷繁的事物中解脱出来的时候，会有人建议他们花些时间去消遣和参加体育活动，总是让自己忙碌着。

人心是多么虚伪而险恶！

148　没有信仰的人不懂得至善，也不懂得公正。

所有人都谋求幸福，概莫能外。虽然使用的手段不同，他们都朝着这一目标努力。之所以一些人去征战，一些人却没有，其实是出于相同的愿望，只不过是用两种不同的方式表达。不是为了这个目标，愿望一小步都不肯挪动。这就是每个人采取每项行动的动机，包括那些绞死自己的人。

然而，多年以来，没有一个没有信仰的人能达到那个目标，那个人人都在不断瞄准的目标。所有人都怨声载道：王子、臣民、贵族、平民、老人、青年，精壮的、虚弱的、有学问的、无知的、健康的、生病的，在每一个国度、在每一时刻、在所有年龄段、在所有情形下。

一项持续已久、从没有停顿或变化的试验应该能说服我们相信，我们无法凭自己的努力达到至善。不过能说服我们的实例很少。没有两个例子相像得连微妙的区别都不存在，而正是这一点让我们猜想，我们的期望这次不会落空，不像上次。因此，现实从没有满足我们，经验却欺骗了我们，引导我们从一个不幸走向另一个不幸，直到死亡来临，那是终极的、永恒的高潮。

这种渴望，这种无助，除了宣布人曾经拥有真正的幸福，而现在只剩下其空空的脚印和踪迹，还有什么可宣布的？他徒劳地试图用周围的一切填补空虚，从不存在的东西里寻求从存在的东西里寻求不到的补救办法，虽然一切都爱莫能助，因为这无底的深渊只能用一个无限、永恒不变的东西填补；换句话说，就是用上帝本人。

只有上帝是人的至善，而奇怪的事实是，自从人抛弃了他，还没有发现大自然中有什么东西接替了他的位置：星辰、天空、地球、化学元素、植物、白菜、韭菜、动物、昆虫、牛、蛇、发热、瘟疫、战争、饥荒、堕落、通奸、乱伦。自从失去了他的至善，人能够从任何东西里，甚至从他的自我毁灭里，发现他的至善，虽然这同时有悖于上帝、理性和天性。

有的人从权威中求善，有的求之于脑力研究和知识，有的求之于欢愉。

还有一些人，确实更接近至善，他们发现，人人所期盼的这个众所周知的善不可能存在于任何一个特定的物体中，因为这个物体只能由一个人独占，一旦共享，拥有者对缺失部分的哀伤，大于他对独占部分的满足。他们意识到，至善应该是这样的：它可以同时被大家拥有，不会因此而缩小，也没人嫉妒，没有人因失去它而违反自己的意愿。他们的理由是，人有这种愿望是自然的，因为所有的人必然能感觉到至善，人不能没有它，他们因此得出结论……

151　依赖伙伴的陪伴是荒唐的，跟我们自己一样可悲，无可救药；他们不会帮助我们，我们将孤独地死去。

那么，我们必须孑身一人那样去行动。如果是这样，我们会去建造精巧的房子等吗？我们应该毫不迟疑地去寻求真理。不过如果我们拒绝的话，就表明我们对人的声望的尊敬，胜过对追求真理的尊敬。

152　生命仅处于半路，在我们和天堂或地狱之间，是世界上最脆弱的东西。

153　除了十年的自爱（因为下的赌注为十年），你究竟许诺我什么了，那么努力地讨好都没用，更不要说那些痛苦了？

155　心灵

本能

信念。

156　怜悯那些正在寻觅的无神论者，是因为他们不够快乐吗？痛骂那些以此夸耀的人。

157　无神论显示精神力量，但只限于某种程度。

158　选择的时候，你必须甘愿麻烦而寻求真理，因为没有尊奉真正的原则就死去，你将迷失自己。你说：“但是，如果他要我尊奉他，他会给我留下一些迹象昭示他的旨意。”他是这样做的，你却没有理会。那么就去寻找吧；非常值得。

159　如果我们应该放弃自己一周的生命，就应该放弃一年。

160　世界上只有三种人：发现了上帝，并侍奉他的人；忙于寻觅他，但还没有寻觅到的人；活着，但既不寻觅也没有寻觅到的人。第一类人合乎情理而幸福，最后一类人愚蠢而不幸福，中间一类人不幸福但合乎情理。

161　无神论者应该谈论十分明确的事情。现在还不十分明确说灵魂是物质的。

162　以怜悯不信者开始；他们的状况足以使自己不幸福。

他们不应该遭到辱骂，除非对他们有好处，但实际上有害。

163　囚禁在牢里的人不知道对他的判决是否已宣布，只有一个小时的时间弄清楚，而一旦知道已经判决了，一个小时也足以把它推翻。如果他不利用那一小时弄清楚是否判决已宣布，却去打牌，那就太不正常了。

因此，如果人，……，就违背了所有天性。这拖累了上帝之手。

因此，这是那些寻求证明上帝存在的人的热情，也是不寻求他的人的愚昧。

164　开始。牢狱。我同意不必深究哥白尼的意见。而是这样：

了解灵魂可朽还是不朽，这影响我们一生。

165　剧的最后一幕很血腥，不过其余部分还不错。他们把泥土撒到你头上，这样就永远结束了。

166　我们把东西挡在面前，以防自己看到深渊，然后又懵头懵脑地跳进去。

193　偏见导致谬误。可悲的是看到大家争论手段，却从不争论结局。人人都考虑如何在事业上出人头地，但到了选择职业或国家的时候，却是命运为我们做主。

真是可怜，看到这么多的土耳其人、异教徒、不信从者追随着父辈的脚印，只是因为他们在成长过程中就相信这是最好的道路。这就是为什么我们每个人选择了锁匠、军人等作为自己的职业。

这就是为什么野蛮人不在乎普罗旺斯。

194　为什么要把我的知识、身高、寿命的限度设在一百年，而不是一千年？自然为什么把一切造就成这样，因为没有一个中数比另一个更引人注目，可是在没有更多的理由去选择一个中数而不选择另一个的时候，却从所有的无穷数里选择了这个，而不是那个？

195　每样一点点。因为我们不可能成为全才，知道应该知道的每样事情的全部，所以必须每样事情知道一点，因为每一样事情都知道一些，远远胜过知道一些事情的每一样。这种通才是最好的。两方面都做得到，那就更好，但是，如果要选择的话，就这样选择。世人都知道这一点，也是这样做的，因为世人常常是优秀的裁判。

196　某种癖好使我讨厌声音沙哑的人，或一边吃东西一边喷气的人。癖好举足轻重。这对我们有什么好处？我们放纵癖好是因为它是天生的吗？不，是因为我们抗拒癖好。

197　想证明人类的虚荣心，最好的办法是考虑爱情的因与果，因为整个世界可以因它而改变。克利奥佩特拉的鼻子。

198　每当我看到人盲目和悲惨的处境，每当我探究整个无言的世界和没有光明的人，他好像被遗失在宇宙的这个角落，不知道是谁把他放置在那里，他来做什么，死后会怎么样，对这些一无所知，每当这时，我就感慨得惊恐，如同人在睡梦里被送到某个可怕的荒岛，醒来后倍感迷惘，走投无路。于是，我感到惊讶，如此悲惨的境地竟不能逼人绝望。我看到周围的人处境跟我一样。我问他们，是否比我更了解情况，他们说不是。然后，这些茫然可怜的人儿环顾四周，被一些东西吸引，接着便沉溺于其中。至于我，就从未沉于这种东西，而且，考虑到极有可能存在着我所看不见的东西，我曾尝试弄清楚上帝是否留下过任何踪迹。

我看到一些宗教之间发生冲突，因此，除了一种宗教，其余的都是假的。每个宗教都希望人们信从自己的权威，并威胁不信从者。我不相信他们的说法。任何人都可以这样说。任何人都可以自称为先知，但我发现了基督教，寻到了它的预言，不是所有人都有这种预言的能力。

199　人的失衡。这是我们从纯粹的知识中得出的。如果它不正确，人就不具备真理；如果正确，他就有充分的理由感到羞耻；这两种情况下他都要谦卑。

而且，由于他不相信这个知识就不能生存，在对自然进行更广泛的探究之前，我希望他认真、从容地考虑一下自然，而且也看看他自己，把自己和自然作个比较，再判断两者之间是否存在着均衡。

让人深思整个大自然丰富崇高的伟大，让他把目光掠过身边微不足道的物体；让他注目凝视那耀眼的光芒，它像点亮的灯盏，永远照耀着整个宇宙，让他把地球看作一个小点，由这颗恒星划出的巨大轨道衬托下的一颗微粒，这让他惊讶地看到，由在苍穹中运行的众多恒星划出的轨道衬托下，这个巨大的轨道只不过是其中最微小的一个点。如果我们就此收住目光，那就放开想象吧；趁大自然还没有厌倦创造，想象一下她能创造出什么产物，连想象力也会疲惫。整个可见的世界只是大自然宽广怀抱里一个觉察不到的点点。没有什么想象可以接近它；没有必要将概念延伸到可想象的空间以外，我们只消将现实世界比作原子。自然是个无边无际的球体，其中心无处不在，圆周不见踪迹。总之，它是展示上帝全能的最伟大的可见标志，我们的想象会迷失于这个想法中。

让人回头思索自己本身，把自己与存在的物体相比较；让他暂且认为自己迷失了，让他从自己寄居的这个小小牢笼里，我指的是宇宙，学会以其应有的价值接受地球、地球的疆域、地球的城邦、地球的房舍，以及他自己。

人在苍穹中的角色是什么？

为了再向他展示一个同样令其震惊的奇观，让他探究已知的最微小的东西。让一只螨虫向他展示自己小小身躯里小得无与伦比的各个部分——带关节的腿、腿里的血管、血管里的血、血里的汁液、汁液里的血滴，血滴里的水汽；让他继续把这些东西分割下去，直到想象力穷尽，并让最后一样物质作为我们讨论的话题。他也许会认为这是自然界最最细微的物质。

我想向他展示一个新的深渊。我不仅想向他描绘这个可见的宇宙，还要描绘包含在这个微小原子里可以想象的广袤自然的一切。让他看到有众多无边的宇宙，每个都有自己的苍穹、自己的行星、自己的地球，比例和可见世界里的相同，那个地球上有各种动物，最后是螨虫，从这些螨虫身上得出和第一只一样的结果；从其他螨虫身上也发现了同样的东西，无穷无尽，他将迷失在这些奇迹中，惊异于它们的细微，像惊异于其他物体的广阔。谁能不惊诧，我们的身体，片刻之前在一个宇宙里还感觉不到，因为它处在一个整体的怀抱里，细微得让人感觉不到，现在，同无法企及的虚无相比，它却应该是一个巨人、一个世界，或者说一个整体？用这样的方式思索自身的人会被自己吓着，而且，看到自然赋予他的质量将他维系在无限和虚无这两个深渊之间，他将面对这奇迹发抖。我相信，随着好奇心变成赞叹，他将更倾向于默默地思考，而不是带着假设去探究这些奇迹。

人在自然中的角色究竟是什么？与无限相比，是一种虚无，与虚无相比，是一个整体，是一切和虚无之间的中间点，无限地远离认识的极限；事情的结局和本源不可企及，深藏于无法破解的秘密之中。

看不到他出自于其中的虚无，也看不到他淹没于其中。

那么，除了感知些微中间状态的表象，而永远没有希望知道其本源或结局，他还有什么可为？一切出自虚无，归于无限。谁能懂得这些惊人的过程？只有奇迹的创造者，没有他人。

由于没有考虑到这些无限性，人们贸然承诺探索自然，好像他们和大自然之间存在着某种均衡。

奇怪的是，他们被一个像自己探究的对象一样无限的假设激励着，想了解事物的本源，然后从那里出发继续去探究一切。毫无疑问，没有无限的假设，或没有像自然一样无限的能力，就发现不了这个计划。

我们认识得更清楚时，我们就会理解，既然自然雕刻出自己及其所有产物的创造者的形象，它们就几乎都拥有大自然的双重无限性。因此，我们看到，各门科学都具有无限的研究范围，因为，以数学为例，谁能怀疑数学阐释无限命题的无限性？科学的无限性也体现于其原则的多重性和细微性，因为任何人都可以看到，那些应该是终极的东西，却不能自圆其说，而要依赖其他学说，其他学说又依赖其他学说，因此永远也没有结局。

在理性看来是终极的东西我们才将其看作是终极的，如同对物质的东西，由于我们的感官感觉不到一个点以外的东西，我们便称其为不可分割的点，虽然根据其性质是可以无限分割下去的。

科学的这两个无限性当中，范围的无限广阔更为明显，这就是为什么几乎没有人声称他们无所不知。“我要论及一切。”德谟克利特[13]常常这样说。

但是无限的细微却难以觉察。哲学家们却很轻率地声明已经达到了细微的程度，而这正是他们犯错误之处。那些人们熟悉的标题便来源于此，像《事物的原则》《哲学原理》等，这些题目实在是自命不凡，虽然看起来不像《可知的一切》这个言过其实的题目一样。

我们自然相信，我们掌握事物核心的能力比掌握其外表要大，世界的可见程度显然比我们所见的要大。由于从我们来看，比小的东西大，我们便认为自己更有能力驾驭它们，然而，企及虚无需要的能力并不比企及整体需要的小。无论哪种情况下，都需要一种无限的能力，而且在我看来，任何人理解了事物的终极原则，就会成功地领会无限。一个依赖于另一个，由一个通向另一个。这些极端从相反的方向接触，会合，它们相会于上帝，也只有相会于上帝。

那么，让我们来认识自身的局限。我们是某物，但不是万物。我们的自身存在对我们隐瞒了来自于虚无的第一原理的知识，我们自身存在的渺小使我们的视线无法触及无限性。

我们的智慧在智力序列中所处的顺序，等同于我们的身体在整个自然领域中所处的位置。

因为各方面的局限，我们发现这一个反映在我们各项能力上的两个极端间的中间状态。我们的感官感觉不到极端；喧哗过度使人耳聩，光线太亮令人目眩；太远或太近，都看不清楚；论据过长或过短都含糊不清，真理过多让我们困惑。我知道有人弄不懂为什么零减四等于零。第一原理对我们来说太过直白；太多的快乐导致苦恼；乐曲里和弦太多惹人心烦，过分的好意使我们恼怒；我们希望能超额偿还债务。好意在能偿还的条件下才受欢迎。太过分时，感激变成了仇恨。

我们感觉不到极度的热，也感觉不到极度的冷。过度的高品质并不好，让人觉察不到；我们再也感觉不到，反而受罪。太年轻和太老都影响思考；学识太多和太少也一样。

总之，极端好像不为我们存在，我们也不为极端存在；极端逃离了我们，或者我们逃离了极端。

这就是我们的真实状态。它使得我们无法获得确凿的知识，也无法绝对地无知。我们漂浮在一个范围广阔的中间状态里，总是行踪不定，给吹来吹去；每当我们认为有个固定的点可以抓住安身时，它却转身离开我们。我们跟上去，它就躲避我们，挣脱我们的抓握，永远逃离我们。没有什么因我们而一成不变。这就是我们的自然状态，但最有悖于我们的意愿。我们热切地希望找到一个坚固的立足点，一个终极、持久的基座，在上面建立一个直达无限的高塔，但我们的基座整个塌陷，大地裂开，变为深渊。

那么，让我们不追求确定也不追求稳定；我们的理性总是被表象的不一致所欺骗。没有什么可以确定两个无限之间的有限，因为这两个无限包含有限，又回避有限。

一旦清楚地认识到这一点，我觉得每个人就可以安静地停留在一种状态里，就是大自然把我们安置于其中的状态。既然分配给我们的中间站总是远离极端，如果别人对事物的理解略高一筹又有何妨？如果他是这样，而且理解得更深刻一点，他不是仍然无限地远离目标吗？我们融入永恒的生命即使延长十年，不也是同样短暂吗？

从这些无限性的角度来看，所有的有限都地位平等，于是我认为没有理由把想象力放于其中的一个而不是另一个之上。仅仅把我们自己同有限相比较就令人痛苦。

如果人探究自己，他将看到自己是多么无力取得进展。部分怎么可能知道整体？也许他会渴望至少知道跟自己有关的那些部分，然而，世界的各部分紧密相连，我觉得不可能只知道一部分，而不知道其他或整体。

例如，一个人和他已知事物之间的关系。他需要容纳他的空间、他存活的时间、生存的动机、构成他的元素、滋养他的温度和食物、呼吸的空气。他看得见光线，感觉得到身体，总之一切都与他有关。因此要了解人，一个人必须知道他为什么要靠空气生存，要了解空气，一个人必须知道它与人的生命有怎样的关系，等等。

没有空气，火焰就不能燃烧，所以，想了解一样，就必须了解另一样。

因此，既然一切事物都既是结果，也是原因，既是接受援助的，也是提供援助的，既是间接的，也是直接的，将一个链条上最远、最迥异的东西无形中自然地联结在一起，相互支持，那么，我认为不了解整体就不可能了解各个部分，如同不了解各个部分就不了解整体。

事物本身的永恒，或存在于上帝的永恒，一定仍然使我们惊奇，贯穿短暂的一生。

大自然固定、始终如一的不动性，相比我们自身的不断变化，一定会产生同样的效果。

我们之所以无法完全地认识事物是因为它们本身简单，而我们却是由两个不同、对立的性质构成的，即灵魂和肉体。这是因为，我们能推理的那个部分，除了是精神的，不可能是别的，即使它被宣布为完全是肉体的，而这会更加妨碍我们了解事物，因为，说物质了解自己，没有比这更不可思议的。我们不可能知道它如何了解自己。

因此，如果我们完全是物质的，我们就一无所知，而且，如果我们是由精神和物质构成的，我们就不能完全了解那些仅仅是精神的，或仅仅是肉体的东西。

这就是为什么几乎所有的哲学家都混淆了对事物的看法。他们从精神的角度谈论物质的东西。从物质的角度谈论精神的东西，因为他们敢于断言，肉体趋向于堕落，追求自己的核心，逃离毁灭，害怕空虚，有自己的爱好、同情、反感等一切只跟精神有关的东西。谈到精神时，他们认为精神处于一个地方，有从一个地方运动到另一个地方的属性，然而这些东西只跟肉体有关。

我们不接受这些事物纯正的概念，却用我们自己的品质给它们涂上色彩，把我们混合而成的自我存在刻印在所考虑的简单事物上。

看见我们把精神和物质混为一谈，谁能不认为这种混合体对我们来说其实有多么清晰明了？然而这正是我们最不了解的事物；人对自己来说是自然界最伟大的奇迹，因为他无法想象肉体为何物，更无法想象精神为何物，最无法想象肉体何以能联结到精神上。这是他最大的难题，然而这却是他的自身存在。精神何以寄居到肉体上，这是人所无法理解的，然而这正是人的构成。

最后，为完成对我们自身无能的证明，我就以对这两个问题的考虑结束……

200　人只是棵芦苇，自然界中最脆弱的东西，但却是棵思想的芦苇。整个宇宙没有必要挥拳将其粉碎：蒸汽、水滴就足以将其扼杀。即使宇宙要将其粉碎，它仍然比刽子手高贵，因为它知道自己行将死去，知道宇宙比它强大，然而宇宙对这些却毫不知情。

因此，我们所有的尊严都在于思想。正是思想，我们要依靠其复兴，而不是依靠空间和时间，因为我们永远无法将其填补。那么让我们力求深思熟虑，这是基本的道德原则。

201　无限空间的永恒沉默让我充满恐惧。

202　尽管放心；你并不求它来自于你本身，正相反，你要以对自己无所求的方式去求它。

271　耶稣的所作所为是教人爱自己，教人知晓自己是奴仆、盲人、患者，悲苦不幸、罪孽深重，教人知晓他必须传播福音，启迪心灵，洗清罪过，治愈病痛，教人知晓他的痛苦和十字架上的殉难，他们会悔过自新，追随自己，这样他的教导便会如愿以偿。

273　那些难以信从的人寻找借口，说犹太人不信从。他们说：“如果是那么清晰的话，他们为什么不信从？”他们几乎想让自己信从，这样他们就不会因犹太人拒绝信从的例子而断了皈依的念头，然而，正是他们的拒绝才成全了我们的信念。如果他们站在我们的立场，我们就不会这么心甘情愿地信从；那样的话，我们应该找个更好的借口。

让犹太人喜欢预言，仇视应验，这是件非常好的事情。

281　永恒。这个宗教信仰在于，相信人类已经从荣耀和与神交流的状态堕落到暗淡无光、悔过自新、与神疏远的地步，但此生之后，我们会蒙应许的弥赛亚而再生，这信仰一直存在于世。

一切均已消逝，只有让万物蒙恩的信仰永世长存。

在世界初期，人受引诱犯下各种罪行，但有像以诺、拉麦等那样的圣人，他们自世界开端便耐心祈盼应许给他们的基督。诺亚看透了人的邪恶，他用自己的美德拯救世界，对他所预示的弥赛亚满怀希望。亚伯拉罕蒙上帝展示弥赛亚的奥秘，从远处欢呼，那时他正被偶像崇拜者包围。以撒和雅各的时代，世人彼此憎恶，但这些圣人坚守信念，雅各临终前停下给孩子的祝福，满怀喜悦地呼喊：“主啊，我祈盼着你应许的救世主。”

埃及人盛行偶像崇拜和魔术，即使是上帝的子民也被他们的做法冲昏了头脑。然而，摩西和其他人仰望到埃及人无法看到的上帝，并尊奉他，期待着他为他们准备的永恒的礼物。

其次，希腊人和拉丁人顶礼膜拜假神。诗人发明了一百门神学，哲学家将其划分成一千个教派。然而，在犹太人的内心，总是有上帝的选民预言弥赛亚的降临，只有他们获此晓谕。他终于在时机成熟之际降临，从那以后，我们经历了频繁的分裂和异端邪说、众多国家的倾覆、纷繁的变化，而教会对他的尊奉从没有停止。这个宗教肇始就饱受攻击，却得以生存下来，这足以显示其美妙绝伦的神圣。它无数次面临毁灭，每一次都有上帝昭显非凡的力量，挽救其于彻底毁灭的边缘。它没有向专制统治者卑躬屈膝却延续了下来，这足以让世人惊奇；这是因为在一个尚存的国度里，法律有时要向需求让步，这不足为怪，但是……（见《蒙田》中圈出的部分）

284　唯一违背天性、违背常识、违背我们欢悦的宗教，是唯一永存的那个。

308　肉体和精神间的无限距离，象征着精神和仁慈之间更无限的距离，因为仁慈是超自然的。

伟大所具有的全部辉煌，都不足以供给那些追求精神的人们所需的光亮。

智力佼佼者的伟大对君王、富人、将领来说是看不见的，因为后者的伟大属于肉体意义上的。

智慧的伟大，如果不是来自神明，便一无是处，肉体的人或心智非凡的人看不到它。这三者是性质不同的三个秩序。

伟大的天才自有自己的力量、自己的辉煌、自己的伟大、自己的胜利和自己的荣耀，他们不需要肉体的伟大，因为肉体的伟大与他们毫不相干。他们由精神而不是眼睛认可，这对他们足矣。

圣人自有圣人的力量、圣人的辉煌、圣人的胜利、圣人的荣耀，不需要肉体的或心智的伟大，这与他们毫不相干，因为这既不增加什么，也不减少什么。他们由上帝和他的使者而不是肉体或好奇心认可。上帝对他们足矣。

阿基米德即便令人费解也让人心怀崇敬。他从未在有形的战场作战，但他的发现丰富了每一个心灵。他照亮了人心！

耶稣既不富有，也没有外在的学识，但自有其圣洁的秩序。他没有发明创造，也不实行君主统治，但他谦逊、耐心，对神明虔诚，令魔鬼畏惧，又纯洁无瑕。在感知智慧的心灵里，他的降临是多么伟大、辉煌、壮丽的盛况！

阿基米德用不着在其数学专著里扮演王子的角色，虽然他就是王子。

我们的主耶稣基督用不着以王者的身份，闪耀着他神圣统治的光辉降临，而千真万确，他是披载着自己秩序的辉煌降临人间。

为耶稣的卑微而震惊，实在荒唐，好像他的卑微同他的降临彰显的伟大为同一秩序。

如果我们考虑到他的伟大彰显于他的一生、他的激情、他的默默无闻、他的死、他选择使徒的方式、使徒对他的遗弃、他的秘密复活，以及一切的一切之中，我们没有理由为一种毫不相干的卑微感到震惊。能认识到这一点就了不起。

但有些人只能欣赏肉体的伟大，好像不存在精神的伟大。而其他人只钦佩精神的伟大，好像不存在更加无限崇高的智慧的伟大。

所有的肉体、苍穹、星辰、地球和它上面的王国，都比不上一点点精神，因为精神了解它们，也了解自己，而肉体却一无所知。

把所有的肉体放在一起，把所有的精神放在一起，创造出的产物也不值得仁慈产生一丝冲动。这是一个无限至高无上的秩序。

用所有的肉体也不能创造出一丝思想。这是不可能的，这是一个不同的秩序。用所有的肉体和精神也无法让真正的仁慈产生一丝冲动。这是不可能的，这是一个不同的、超自然的秩序。

310　耶稣基督存在的证明。认为使徒是恶棍的假设实在是荒诞不经。顺着这个假设一直想下去，设想这十二个人在耶稣遇难后聚会，密谋对外宣称他复活了，这意味着向一切权势发起进攻。人心容易因浮躁、变化、承诺、贿赂产生动摇，这简直不可思议。其中一个使徒在这些诱惑下只好否定自己的过去，或因可能的监禁、折磨和死亡而作出更过分的举动，使徒们会迷惘失落。顺着这个假设一直想下去。

332　预言。如果一个人写了本书，预言耶稣降临的时间和方式，而且耶稣的降临应验了这些预言，其意义将无限深远。

它的意义也远不止于此。在四千年的岁月里，人一代又一代，始终如一地预言着同一个降临，这是整个民族的宣言，在其生存的四千年岁月里，在一个身体上验证他们的信念，而且无论什么样的威胁和迫害，他们都百折不挠。其深远意义有着不同的秩序。

335　对耶稣最有力的证据是预言。上帝为这些预言作了最好的安排，因为预言的应验是个奇迹，从教会诞生直到最终都是如此。因此，在一千六百年的时间里，上帝哺育了先知，在此后的四百年岁月里，他将预言传播给所有犹太人，他们把预言带到世界的每一个角落。这是为耶稣诞生所作的准备，而且，由于他的福音必由举世仰望，预言不仅让人信奉福音，还要把这些预言传遍全世界，让全世界都信奉福音。

351　基督教很奇怪；它要人认识到自己有多么卑鄙，甚至是恶毒，它要人希望能像神明一样行事。如果没有这个制衡，得意会让人沦入可怕的虚荣，自卑会让人陷入可怕的低贱。

352　苦难让人绝望。

得意让人自负。

耶稣化身成人是用所求的救赎的伟大，向世人显示他苦难的伟大。

356　就服从性来说，一个士兵和一个天主教加尔都西会教士有什么区别？他们都顺从、依赖、隐忍于苦行，但是，士兵始终渴望成为自己的主人，却从未实现这一愿望。即使是将领和王子也始终都是奴仆，依赖于他人，但他一直渴望着，始终努力实现这一目标，而教士则发誓要永远依赖。因此，他们都处于永久的被奴役地位，这始终是他们的共同命运，不过，一个总是抱有希望，另一个却从没有一丝念头。373我们必须只爱上帝，只恨自己。

如果脚从来不知道它属于身体，有身体可以依赖，如果它只知道自己，只爱自己，如果它后来知道自己其实属于身体，并依赖身体，它将为过去的岁月感到多么遗憾，多么羞愧啊，因为身体为它注入了生命，它却对其毫无用处；如果身体拒绝它，割掉它，像脚把自己从身体上割断，它将不复存在！它该如何祈求把自己保留下来！它该如何顺从地让掌管身体的意愿来统治自己，甚至必要的话可以接受截肢！不然的话，它就不是其中的一员，因为每个成员都必须为主体而心甘情愿地消亡，因为一切都为主体而生。

378　他们说：“如果我看到了神迹，我就会皈依主。”他们何以这么肯定会做自己不懂的事情？他们设想，这种皈依在于对上帝的尊崇，像他们勾画的那样，如同一种交流或对话。真正的皈依在于面对万能的神的自我毁灭，为这个神我们经常争论不休，而他完全有权在任何时候摧毁我们，也在于承认没有他我们将一事无成，而且除了失宠于他，我们不配得到任何东西。真正的皈依在于知晓神和我们之间的对抗不可调和，而没有调解者，就没有我们和他的交流。

392　象征。上帝希望为自己创造一个神圣的民族，与所有其他民族区别开来，将他们从敌人手中解救出来，将他们带到一个休憩的处所。上帝许诺了这一切，并由其先知预言他降临的时间和方式。为坚定他各个时代的选民的信念，他向他们昭示了这一切会是怎样一番景象，他向他们保证他有拯救他们的力量和意愿，然后才离开。上帝创造人类时亚当可以为此作证，他得到应许，一位女子会诞生出救世主。

离上帝创世不久，世人还不会忘怀上帝如何创造他们，自己如何堕落；当见过亚当的人不在人世时，上帝便派来了挪亚，他用神迹彰显他救世的力量和意愿，从而拯救了挪亚，淹没了整个世界，并让那位感孕的女子诞生出他许诺的人子。

这个奇迹足以让他的选民更加坚定地期盼那一天的到来。

世人对那场洪水还记忆犹新。当挪亚还活着时，上帝向亚伯拉罕许诺；当闪还活着时，上帝派来了摩西……

403　悲惨。所罗门和约伯最懂得人的苦难，也作了最好的诠释：

一个是最幸福的人，一个是最不幸福的人；一个凭经验懂得享乐的空虚，另一个了解痛苦的现实。

412　人的疯狂如此不可避免，不疯也等于疯狂地扭动疯狂。

414　悲惨。唯一能慰藉我们苦难境况的是消遣，然而，这才是我们最大的苦难，因为它最能阻止我们思索自己，无形中把我们引向毁灭。我们会厌倦消遣，迫使我们寻求更可靠的手段去逃避。消遣会消磨时间，使我们在不知不觉中走向死亡。

418　无限——虚无。我们的灵魂给投进身体，它在那里发现了数量、时间、尺度；它将这一切理性化，称其为天生的，或必要的，除此以外，它不相信任何东西。

把单一添加到无限，无限丝毫不会增加，就像把一英尺添加到无限的长度上：有限消逝于无限之中，成为纯粹的虚无。因此，这就像我们的心智之于上帝，我们的公义之于神的公义。我们的公义和神的公义之间，正像单一和无限之间，并没有多么大的不对称。

上帝的公义一定像他的慈悲情怀一样宽广无边。如今，他对被诅咒之人的公义，我们对此的惊诧，就不及他对他的选民的慈悲情怀了。

我们知道存在着无穷，却无从了解它的本质，正如我们知道，说数字是有限的，这不是事实。因此，确实存在一个无穷数，但我们不知道它是什么。说它是偶数，不对，说它是奇数，不对，因为增加一个单位，也不会改变其性质。然而，它是一个数字，每个数字不是偶数就是奇数。（的确，这适用于每一个有穷数。）

因此，我们可以清楚地知道神的存在，却无从知道他是怎么回事。

看到存在这么多真实的事情，本身却并不确切，难道就不存在真正的真理吗？

因此，我们知道存在着有限，也了解它的本质，因为我们自己也是有限的，在空间延伸。

我们知道存在着无限，却不了解它的本质，因为虽然它也延伸，但不像我们，它无可限量。

我们既不知道是否存在上帝，也不了解他的本质，因为他既不延伸，也无可限量。

我们凭信念相信他的存在，凭荣耀了解他的本质。

现在，我已经证明，很有可能知道存在某个东西，但不了解其本质。

现在让我们借着自然之光讲话。

如果有上帝，他就无限地超出我们的理解范围，因为他的不可分割和无可限量说明他与我们无关。因此，我们无从了解他是怎么回事，或他是否存在。既然如此，谁还敢来试图回答这个问题？当然不是我们，与他无关的人。

那么，谁还会谴责基督徒无法对自己的信仰作出理智的解释，扬言他们不是出于理智信仰一个宗教？他们宣布，向世人阐释这样的信仰是愚蠢之举，然后你抱怨说，他们无从证明这一点。如果他们真的证明了，反倒说明他们没有信用。没有证据才表明他们不是没有理由。“是的，尽管这能给人们提供借口信仰这样的宗教，并为受到的无理指责开脱，可并不能为接受信仰的人开脱。”那么就让我们来考察一下这个问题，让我们说：“上帝存在，或者不存在。”然而我们应该倾向于哪个观点？理性不能判定这个问题。无限的混乱将我们隔开。在这个无穷距离的尽头，一枚硬币在旋转，然后会正面朝上，或反面朝上地落下来。你将赌什么？理性不能驱使你选择任何一面，也不能证明选择任何一面是错的。

那么，就不要谴责有所选择的人做错了事，因为你对此一无所知。“不，我谴责他们，不是因为他们作出了这样的选择，而是不管作任何选择，因为，虽然一个选择正面，另一个同样错了，他们确实都错了：稳妥起见，什么都别赌。”

是的，但你必须赌。没有任何选择，你已经作出承诺。那么你会选择哪一面呢？让我们来看一下：既然必须作出选择，让我们来看看哪个带来的好处最小。你会失去两样东西：真与善；有两样东西可做赌注：你的理性和你的意愿，你的知识和你的幸福；你的天性想避免两件事情：错误和悲惨。既然你必然要选择，选择一个而不是另一个，就不会冒犯你的理性。这一点已经确定无疑，但你的幸福呢？让我们权衡一下选正面赌上帝存在的得失。我们估计一下这两种情况：如果赢了，你将赢得一切；如果输了，你什么也不会损失。那么，就不要犹豫，赌他存在。“太好了。是的，我必须下赌注，但也许我押得太多了。”让我们看看：既然是一个得失参半的机会，如果你敢以一个生命赌两个生命，这个赌注仍然可以下，但假设你能赢得三个生命呢？

你将不得不赌（因为你必然要赌），而一旦要赌，不在一场输赢机会参半的赌博里拿自己的生命冒险，去赌三个生命，你就是不明智的。生命和幸福是永恒的。这样的话，尽管无限的机会中只有一个偏爱你，以一个生命赌两个，仍然是对的；因为不得不赌，而在那场赌博的无数次机会里，只有一次对你有利，可一旦赢了，赢得的无限幸福的生命又是无限的，在这种情况下，如果拒绝以一个生命去赌三个，你就错了。这里，因为赢得无限幸福的生命是无限的，一个赢的机会对应有限输的机会，所以你押上的赌注是有限的。这样，就没有选择的余地；哪里有无限，不是无限输的机会对应一个赢的机会，哪里就没有犹豫的余地，你必须押上一切。因此，既然你必然要赌，你却贮藏生命，不拿它去赌一个无限的收益，就像蒙受的损失可能等于零一样，如果是这样的话，你就是宣布放弃理性。

因为不能说：还不确定你是否能赢，你肯定在冒险，而且在你所冒风险的确定性和你所赢得收益的不确定性之间，存在着无限的距离，这距离使你确定地押作赌注的有限利益等于你不确定得的益。并非如此，每一个赌徒都押上一个确定的赌注，去赢得一个不确定的利益，但他是在押上确定的有限赌注，去赢得不确定的有限收益，这不违背理性。确定的赌注和不确定的收益之间不存在无限的距离：情况不是这样。确实，在赢的确定性和输的确定性之间，存在着无限的距离，但赢的不确定性和押上的赌注的确定性之间的比例，同赢或输相对应的机会是对称的。因此，一方面的机会等同于另一方面时，你输赢的机会相等。在这种情况下，你押上的赌注的确定性，等于你会赢得的收益的不确定性；它们之间绝没有无限远的距离。在一场赌博中，当赌注有限，输赢机会参半，而且会赢得无限的奖赏时，我们的辩论便有着无限深远的意义。

这已成定论，而且如果人能获得真理的话，这便是真理。

“我忏悔，我承认，但确实没办法看到底牌吗？”——“有。有《圣经》和其他东西，等等”——“是的，但我的手被捆住，我的嘴被封住；我被迫打赌，没有自由；我被驱赶着；我天生就是这样，没法信从。你要我怎么样呢？”——“这是事实，但你至少要明白，如果你不能信从，那是情绪在作怪，既然理性没法逼你信从。那么就集中精力逐渐消除这股情绪，而不是成倍地放大上帝存在的证明，以说服自己信从。你想寻求信仰，但不知道路在何方。你想治愈没有信仰的病痛，而且寻求治疗的方法：向那些曾经像你一样被束缚，现在却押上了一切的人学习吧。这些人知道你要走的路，他们的苦恼已经被治愈，也正是你想治愈的苦恼：沿着他们的路走下去吧。他们蘸了圣水，做了弥撒，等等，所作所为看起来真的是信从了。这会使你十分自然地信从，会使你更顺服。”——“但这正是我害怕的。”——“为什么？难道会失去什么吗？只是指给你那条路，这确实会抑制你的情绪，因为情绪已成为你的巨大障碍……”

“那么，选择这条道路究竟对你何害之有？你会忠诚、可靠、谦逊、感恩、多结善果，是一个诚挚、真正的朋友……的确，你将无法享受害人的欢乐，无法享受荣耀及安逸的生活，但你不会获得其他东西吗？

“我来告诉你，你今生就将获益，在这条道路上每迈出一步，你都会看到收益是如此确定无疑，赌注是如此无足轻重，最终你会发现，你赌的东西确切而无限，而你什么也没有付出。”

“这些话让我充满了喜乐！——”

“如果我的话让你心悦诚服，你要知道这些话出自这样一个人之口，他始终在跪求一个无限而不可分割的生命，向他交付出自己的生命，而且为了你好，为了他的荣耀，而可能把你的生命也交付给他：卑贱者由此获得了力量。”

427　[反对冷漠]让他们至少在攻击这个宗教之前了解它究竟怎样。如果这个宗教自诩清楚地看到了上帝及其存在的清晰而明显的证据，那么反对者说在这个世界看不到他存在的明显证据，这样反对很有效。但是，正相反，这个宗教认为，人处于黑暗之中，远离上帝；而上帝把自己隐匿起来，不让人了解他，在《圣经》里他就将自己称为：Deus absconditus[隐匿的上帝]；总之，如果这个宗教同样努力去证明两个事实：上帝在教会中确定了明显的标志，这样，真诚地寻求他的人才会认出他；他依然把标志隐藏起来，只有一心寻求他的人才会察觉到他，那么，人们并不像自己表白的那样关心寻求真理，却抗议没有把迹象显示给他们，这样做有什么意义？他们发现自己处于这种幽晦之中，又利用幽晦反对教会，而这幽晦恰恰使教会坚持的一样东西得到承认，而不会影响到其他，从而使这个宗教得到确认，而远远谈不上证明它是谬误。

为了全力攻击真理，他们会抗议说，他们竭尽全力，到处寻求它，甚至是在教会提供的训导里，但遍寻不到。如果这样说的话，他们就确实是在攻击基督教的某一个主张了。我希望在此表明，通情达理的人不会这样讲话。我甚至敢说，从来没有人这样说过。我们十分清楚人们在这种思想框架下如何行事。他们认为自己付出了巨大努力去学习，可实际上却只花了几个小时阅读经书，向神职人员询问问题，了解信仰的真相，之后，他们就声称，他们在书里，在人群中寻找，但都没有找到。可我的确应该对他们说我常说的话：这种漫不经心是不能容忍的。这不是某个陌生人微不足道的兴趣导致行为的问题：这是我们自己的问题，我们所有人的问题。

灵魂永生，这一点对我们意义极其重大，影响极其深远，一个人要完全失去感觉才会不关注对其真相的了解。我们的行动和思想遵循的路径特别不同，因此，根据能否有希望获得永恒的祝福，凭感觉和判断行事的唯一可行方法就是根据这一点决定我们的路径，这应当是我们的最终目标。

因此，我们主要关心的以及我们的主要职责是，寻求神明对这一问题的启示，我们所有的行为也依赖于此。这就是为什么在那些不信从的人当中，我把两种人完全区分开：一种是竭尽全力去探寻的人；一种是活着，但不给自己找麻烦，或不思考的人。

一些人真诚地哀叹自己的疑虑，将它视为最大的不幸，但又不努力摆脱它，把寻求当作主要的、最严肃的事情。对这些人，除了怀有怜悯，我没有其他感觉。

一些人了此一生，却从未想过寻找生活的最终目标，他们在自身找不到信仰之光，也不屑到别处寻找，也不深究一下，人们接受这个观点是出于轻信和幼稚，还是因为这个观点虽然本身幽晦，其基础却牢不可破：对这些人，我持有完全不同的看法。

对他们自己、他们的永恒、他们的一切都处于危险之中的问题漠不关心，这让我愤怒，远过于怜悯，也让我震惊、恐惧、难以置信。这并非出于我精神信仰的虔诚热情，我的意思恰恰相反，人类的利益和自尊原则就应该使我们产生这种感情。因此，我们只要具有最不开化者的见识就可以了。

人的一生没有真正、确切的满足，一切欢悦毫无价值，烦闷苦恼无边无际，最后一点是，死亡每时每刻都威胁着我们，数年之后就会确定无疑地到来，我们面临无法逃避的骇人选择，要么毁灭，要么陷入永恒的悲惨。认识到上面这些，不需要具有伟大高尚的灵魂。

没有比这更真实，或更可怕的。让我们权且大胆地面对：那就是最后的结局，它等待着世上最杰出的生命。让我们仔细想想这些问题，然后问，是不是毫无疑问，我们今生所做的唯一善事就是盼望来生，我们快乐是因为我们接近来生，而且，就像就一些人而言，前面没有更多的忧愁等着，是因为他们十分确定永恒的存在，就另一些人而言，前面没有幸福等着，是因为他们没有得到暗示。

存有这样的疑虑确实是一大罪恶，但有疑虑而去寻求答案，至少是履行不可推卸的义务；因此怀疑者不寻求答案，同时也就不会幸福，就是错误的。如果他还公开宣称自己平静满足，甚至因此寻欢作乐，满足虚荣心，我就找不到任何辞藻来描述如此放肆的东西了。

何以产生这样的感受？除了期待无可奈何的悲惨结局，其他无可期待，还有什么理由能找到欢乐？为什么让虚荣陷入不可逾越的黑暗？一个理性的人又如何能这样辩解？

“我不知道是谁把我投放到这个世界，不知道世界是什么，也不知道我自己是谁。我简直一无所知。我不知道我的肉体是什么，我的感官是什么，或者我的灵魂是什么，甚至不了解在考虑我讲话的那部分，它反映一切，也反映自身，但对它自己了解的程度，不及对其他的了解。

“我看到宇宙可怕的空间将我包围起来，我发现我附着在这个广袤苍穹的一角，却不知道为什么把我放置于此地，而不是彼地，或者为什么把我短暂的生命分配到先我而往，继我而来的无边岁月中的此刻，而不是其他时刻。我只看到周围的无限，它吞没了我，像吞没一个原子，或一个瞬间飞逝的影子。我只知道我行将死去，但对无法回避的死亡，我知之甚少。

“正如不知道我从哪里来，我也不知道我要到哪里去。我所知道的是，当我离开这个世界的时候，我将永远陷入虚无，或落入愤怒的上帝手中，但我不知道这两个状态中哪个是我永恒的归宿。这就是我的状态，软弱而不确定。我从所有这一切中得出的结论是，别想探究什么会来临，就这样了此一生。我的疑惑也许会得到某种启示，但我不想自找麻烦，也没有费半点努力去寻找；然后，因为我嘲笑那些人向这个目标努力，——不论他们多么确定，最后都会绝望，而不是空虚——我自己则无忧无虑地得过且过，预见不到会面临一件大事，结果让自己软绵绵地走向死亡，不知道我将来在永恒里是个什么样子。”

谁愿意自己的朋友这样辩解？有谁会选择他做知己？谁会在逆境中向他求助？生活中他能有什么用处？

与这么不理智的人为敌，真是宗教的荣耀：他们的攻击对我们构成的威胁微不足道，相反，恰恰有助于证明宗教的真相。对基督教的信仰几乎完全在于证明这两样东西：人性的腐败和基督的救赎。现在，我坚持认为，如果他们不用圣洁的行为证明救赎的真相，至少是以这么不人性的态度完美地证明了人性的腐败。

就人来说，状态无比重要：永恒无比可怕。因此，有人不理会丧失自我，不理会面临永恒悲惨的危险，这是违反天性的。在所有其他事情上，他们则大不相同：他们担心区区小事，能预见到和感觉到这种小事；那个人为失去官职，或为丢失所谓的面子，而日日夜夜愤怒、绝望，就是他，明明知道将在死亡中失去一切，却没有一丝一毫的焦虑或感伤。看到一个人，还有他的心，对微不足道的事情如此敏感，对极端伟大的事物如此奇怪地麻木，真是可怕。这是一种不可思议的魔力，是一种被无限的力量支配着的超自然的迟钝。

人性一定经历过一种奇怪的逆转，才使人为处于某种状态而得意洋洋，而一个人竟该处于这种状态，简直是不可思议。经验告诉我，很多人都喜欢这样，如果我们不知道有关的人大部分都在装腔作势，不是他们真实的样子，这倒不可思议了。这些人听说，言行放肆是礼貌的举止。这就是他们所谓的摆脱枷锁，是他们正试图效仿的样子，但是，让他们知道用这种方式获取声名是错误的，这并不困难。即使凡夫俗子都不用这种方式沽名钓誉，因为他们处事理智，知道成功的唯一途径是要显得真诚、可靠、明智，可以给朋友帮上忙，因为出于天性，人都喜欢别人能为其所用。听到有人说他已经摆脱了枷锁，说他不相信有上帝在监视自己的行动，说他是自己行为的唯一主人，准备为自己的行为负责而不靠别人，听到这些对我们有什么好处？他以为这样做，从此以后就赢得了我们的充分信任，使我们今生一有需求便期待他的安慰、忠告、帮助？他们告诉我们，而且是以一种得意洋洋、津津乐道的腔调说的，我们的灵魂不过是一阵风、一缕烟，他们以为告诉我们这些会给我们带来极大的快乐吗？这是快乐地诉说的事情吗？正相反，这是世界上最大的悲哀，要伤心地诉说的吗？

如果他们认真想一想，就会发现这样做其实是误入歧途，违背良知，有碍体面，无论如何离自己追求的礼貌举动相距甚远，本来更有可能将有意追随他们的人改造过来，而不是使其堕落。确实，让他们形容一下致使自己怀疑宗教的感受和理由：他们的话拙劣而空洞，劝你相信却适得其反。正如有一天有人得体地对他们说：“如果你一直那样说服我，你真的会让我皈依主呢。”他说得没错，看到自己跟那么卑劣的人有同感，谁能不退而避之？

因此，装腔作势的人如果强行压抑自己的天性，让自己成为最傲慢的人，确实会不幸福。如果因为不能看清真相而内心苦闷，他们就不应该装出另外一副面孔：承认这一点并不羞耻。除了没有信仰，其他的没有什么好羞愧的。没有认识到不信上帝就不幸福，这是精神极端软弱最确定的标志；不期盼永恒的许诺会实现，这是邪恶之心最确定的标志；厚颜无耻地与上帝对峙，这是最怯懦的表现。那么就让他们把这种对神不敬的罪名，留给那些粗野得能够竭尽不敬之能事的人；如果不能做基督徒，让他们至少做个体面人；简单地说，让他们承认只有两种人合乎情理：一种人尽心尽力地侍奉上帝，因为他们认识他；另一种人尽心尽力地寻觅他，因为他们不认识他。

至于那些活着，但既不知道他，也不寻觅他的人，他们认为只值得麻烦自己稍作尝试，也就根本不屑去麻烦别人，而且，要想不鄙视这些鄙视宗教的人，不抛弃他们，而任其愚蠢，这个宗教要倾其所有怜悯才能做到。一方面，宗教要求我们，要在他们的有生之年始终尊重他们，要相信他们会得到神启的恩典，相信在短时间内他们可能会比我们更有信仰；另一方面，现在蒙蔽他们的也可能会蒙蔽我们自己。因此，把我们想要的，也赋予他们，呼吁他们怜悯自己，至少向前迈出几步努力寻求光明。让他们花几个小时研读，否则会把时间浪费在其他事情上：他们可能会不情愿于此，但有可能会发现点什么，至少不会损失太多。对那些精诚寻求，真正渴望寻求到真理的人，我希望他们如愿以偿，信服于我在这里收集的，表明这一宗教是如此神圣的证据，或多或少地按照这个顺序……

429　这就是我所看到并困惑我的东西。我环顾四周，看到的都是黑暗。除了怀疑和焦虑，我从大自然一无所获。如果没看到神祇的迹象，我会作出相反的决定：如果造物主的迹象处处可见，我会安然信主。因为看到太多要否定的东西，而看不到足够可以肯定的东西，所以我的境况令人同情，我千百次地渴望，如果有神明维系着大自然，大自然会毫不含糊地将神明宣布出来，如果大自然显示的迹象都是骗人的，则应该彻底清除；大自然应该要么畅所欲言，要么一言不发，这样我就知道何去何从。相反，处于这种不知道自己是谁，也不知道自己应该做什么的状态，我对自己的境况和职责都一无所知。为追求至善，我用整个身心去认识至善：为永恒付出的代价不会过高。

我羡慕那些忠心耿耿的人漠然地活着，不好好享用馈赠，如果是我就会别有他用。

430　其他人没有意识到，人是最优秀的生物。一些人充分意识到他的优秀有多么真实，把软弱怯懦、忘恩负义当作人卑微的天然情感；而另一些人，充分意识到这种卑微有多么真实，傲慢地嘲讽人天生的伟大情怀。

一些人说：“抬起头来看上帝，看看他，你与他相似，他把你创造出来崇拜他。你可以把自己造就得像他一样：如果你想追寻他，你就会因智慧和他平等。”——“昂起头，自由的人。”埃皮克提图[14]说。

其他人则说：“低下头来看地面，你是蛆虫，再看看那些禽兽，你与它们为伍。”

那么，人究竟是什么？人会等同于上帝，还是等同于禽兽？多么可怕的距离！那么，人究竟应是什么？谁能不从这一切看出，人已经迷失了，从原来的位置堕落了，他在急切地寻找原来的位置，但再也找不回去了？那么，谁能把他引领到原处？最伟大的人都无可奈何。

434　设想一下，一些人戴着镣铐，已经被判处死刑，每天都有一些人在其他人的注视下死去；留下来的从同伴那里看到了自己的命运，他们面面相觑，充满悲伤和绝望，等待着轮到自己。这是人类状况的反映。

450　真正的宗教信仰会教人什么是伟大和悲惨，会激发自尊与自卑，热爱与憎恨。

470　人最卑鄙的特点是沽名钓誉，但也正是这一点，最清楚地表明了他的卓越。无论他在这个世界上拥有什么样的财富，享有什么样的健康或必不可少的安逸，都不及他享受同类的赞誉带来的满足感。他高度重视人的理性，不管在这个世界上拥有什么样的特权，如果不能同时在人的理性上占有优越的地位，他就不幸福。这是世界上最好的位置，没有任何东西可以使他偏离这一愿望，这是人内心最无法改变的品质。

有些人极端鄙视人类，把人看作禽兽，但仍然希望得到他们的敬佩和信任，感受同自己背道而驰，因为他们的天性无比强势，能更有力地说服他们相信人的伟大，胜过理性说服他们相信自己的卑劣。

474　当创世记开始隐入往昔，上帝提供了一个近代史学家，并责成整个民族保管这本书，这样，这本书就是世界上最权威的历史，所有的人都可以从中学习必须掌握的知识，也只能从这本书学习。

477　傲慢是一切形式的苦难的平衡力和解毒剂。这里有一个怪物，犯了明显的过失。他从原来的位置堕落到这里，急切地想寻找回去。所有人都在做这件事。让我们看看谁找到了。

480　在所有的宗教中真诚都必不可少：真正的异教徒，真正的犹太人，真正的基督徒。

499　什么人曾经拥有更大的荣耀？

整个犹太民族在他降临前预言他。外邦人在他降临后尊崇他。

外邦人和犹太人都把他作为自己的中心。然而，什么人曾经享有这么小的荣耀？

在三十三年的生命中，他三十年没有露面，三年被视为骗子。祭司和当权者排斥他，最亲近的人鄙视他，最终他因被一门徒背叛，被另一个门徒否认，被所有人抛弃而死去。

他从这荣耀中得到了什么好处？没有人享有过如此巨大的荣耀，也没有人蒙受过更大的耻辱。这一切荣耀归我们受用，使我们能够认识他，而他自己却没有享受过一丝一毫。

505　权威性。道听途说远远不是信仰的标准，只有把自己放入一种似乎闻所未闻的状态才能相信。

内心认同，符合自己而不是他人的理智，才能相信。

信仰至关重要。

一百个异义都有可能是对的。

如果年代久远是信仰的标准，那么古人就没有标准。

如果要依据普遍赞同的标准，那么如果人死了呢……

惩罚罪人：错误。

虚假的谦逊，傲慢。

揭露真相。

你在浪费时间，一个人要么相信，要么否定，要么怀疑。

那么我们就没有标准了吗？

动物做事时，我们可以判断他们是否做得好，对人就没有评判的标准了吗？

否定、相信和怀疑之于人，像奔跑之于马。

510　人愈聪明，就愈多地发现有独创性的人。普通人看不到人与人之间的差异。

511　正确的思维有不同的形式，有些人遵守事物的特定顺序，如果按其他顺序的话，就会误入歧途。

有些人从少量原理中得出正确的结论，这是正确思维方式的一种。

还有人从涉及大量原理的事物中得出正确的结论。

例如，一些人很好地掌握了水的性质，其中涉及很少几个原理，但其结论是如此微妙，只有极为精准的头脑才能得出这些结论。这些人可能都不是大数学家，因为数学包含了大量原理，而且一个人的智力可能是这样的，它可以轻易、正确地掌握少数几个原理，但对涉及众多原理的事物却一筹莫展。

因此，有两种才智：一种迅速地从原理中得出深刻的结论，这是精准的头脑；另一种可以把握大量原理，并将其区分开来，这是数学头脑。第一种是功能强大而又精准的头脑，第二种显示出才智的广度。现在，很可能是二者不可兼得的状态，因为一个头脑可能是功能强大而思路狭窄，也可能是思路宽广而功能弱小。

513　数学。直觉。真正的雄辩没有时间雄辩，真正的道德标准没有时间遵守道德标准。换言之，判断的道德标准没有时间判断任意发挥的心智的道德标准。

判断建立在本能之上，就像知识建立在心智之上。直觉充当判断的角色，数学充当心智的角色。

没有时间从事哲学的人是真正的哲学家。

517　如果圣奥古斯丁[15]出现在今天，像他的现代捍卫者那样仅享有一点点权力，他将一事无成。上帝有效地统治他的教会，把他早早地派来，并赋予他权力。

518　怀疑论。——极度聪明被谴责为愚蠢得极度缺乏聪明；只有适度才恰如其分。这是大多数人的规则，谁偏离了这一点，有任何极端的倾向，就会受到攻击。我不会很别扭，非常同意给放在中间，但拒绝在底端，不是因为它在最下面，而是因为那是终结，因为我也同样会拒绝被在顶部。放弃中庸就是放弃人性。

人类灵魂的伟大在于懂得如何保持这个方向；伟大并不意味着偏离这个方向，而是保持在这个方向上。

526　作恶容易；作恶有无数的形式，而行善几乎是独一无二的。某种恶行很难发现，就像善行一样，由于这个缘故，这种特定的恶行往往冒充善行。确实，做这种恶需要具有异常伟大的灵魂，就像达到至善一样。

532　怀疑论。我会在此让我的思绪见诸笔端，因为思绪涌来了，而且也许并非呈一种毫无目的的混乱状态。这是真正的秩序，总是杂乱无章地显示我的目的。

我如果按顺序写下去，题目就太荣幸了，因为我在设法证明它是无法享受顺序的。

533　我们总是想象柏拉图、亚里士多德身着长长的袍服，其实他们跟普通的体面人一样，也会跟朋友谈笑风生。他们撰写《法律篇》和《政治学》用以消遣，以此为乐。这是他们生活中最没有哲理、最不严肃的一部分：最富有哲理的部分是生活简单，不小题大做。

如果撰写政治著作，他们仿佛是在为疯人院制订规章制度。

如果他们假装把它当成真正的要事来处理，这是因为他们知道，正在与之对话的疯子相信自己是帝王。他们迁就这些信念，以便使疯子冷静下来，又尽可能少受伤害。

535　一些恶习通过其他恶习纠缠我们，把主干除掉，它们就会像树枝一样散落下来。

540　所有的好格言都已存在于世：我们只是不加以运用。

例如，没有人怀疑，为保卫共同利益，应该拿生命冒险，许多人都是这样做的，但不是为宗教信仰。

人与人之间必然存在着不平等，的确如此；但是，一旦准许这种现象存在，大门不仅向最有权威的规则敞开，也向最有权威的专制敞开。

有必要稍微放松一下精神，却为极度过分敞开了大门。

让我们给限度下个定义。事物没有界限，法律试图强行设定一些，但精神不能忍受。

542　思绪随意来，随意去。没有器具可以捕获或拥有它们。

一个思绪逃走了：我试图将它见诸文字：可是我却写道，它逃离了我。

545　“凡世界上的事，都是肉体的欲望、眼目的欲望，或今生的骄傲。”悲惨的境况是受诅咒之地，被这三条火河侵蚀，而远非灌溉！岸边的人有福了，因为不受火河浸泡，不被洪流卷走，他们坐着，而不是站着，处于低又安全的位置，在河边稳固不动。他们不会在火光中起身，而是平静地休息后，向他伸出手，由他扶起，昂首挺胸，沉稳坚定地站在耶路撒冷神圣的门廊前，骄傲不能把他们打垮；不过，他们哭泣，不是因为看到急流卷走终将腐朽消亡的东西，而是因为想起他们心爱的家园，天堂般的耶路撒冷，在流离失所的漫长岁月里，他们常常想念它。

551　想象以奇怪的夸张把微小的物体放大，直到满足我们的灵魂，又以大胆的傲慢把伟大的事物缩小到自己的大小，就像谈及上帝时那样。

561　他们说，日食、月食是灾难的征兆，因为灾难频繁，足以证明对厄运的预测准确；但如果他们说，日食、月食是好运的征兆，他们往往是错的。他们只将好运归于罕见的天体现象，所以预测很少有误。

562　只有两种人：正直的人，认为自己是罪人；罪人，认为自己是正直的。

577　如果不孤注一掷的话，对宗教就什么也别做，因为对它还不确定。我们碰了多少次运气啊：航海，征战。我认为，觉得它不确定，就什么也别做。宗教所具有的可确定之处，多于我们活到明天会见到的东西。

虽然不能肯定我们明天还能看得见，但可以肯定，我们有可能看不见。对于宗教，我们不能这样说。不能肯定它是真的，但谁敢说，可以肯定它有可能不是真的？

现在，当我们为明天而努力，去碰运气时，所作所为顺理成章，因为我们应该根据已经证实的概率法则去冒险。

圣奥古斯丁看到，我们在海上冒险，在征战中冒险，等等，——但他没有见过概率法则，证明我们应该冒险。蒙田看到，糊涂的头脑会惹怒我们，习惯可以为所欲为，但他不知其原因。

这些人都只看到结果，没有看到原因。他们与发现了原因的人相比，就像只有眼睛的人同有头脑的人相比，因为在某种程度上结果可以为感官所感觉到，而原因只能由头脑觉察到。尽管头脑可以看到这些结果，这种头脑同能看到原因的头脑相比，就像肉体的感官有可能同头脑相比。

585　在人性间的某种关系中存在某种形式的或强或弱的魅力和审美倾向，以及让我们感到惬意的某种东西。

一切符合这一形式的东西都吸引我们，它可能是一座房舍、一首歌曲、一次演讲、一首诗歌、一篇散文、一位女子、鸟类、河流、树木、房间、衣物等。

一切不符合这个形式的东西都会使有品位的人不悦。

基于这种美好的形式，一首歌和一座房舍之间存在着一种确切的关系，因为两者各代表一种形式，虽然是各自的方式；同样，基于拙劣的形式，事物也同样存在着一种确切的关系。并不是只有一种拙劣的形式，其实其数是数不清的，但是，以十四行诗为例，每一首拙劣的十四行诗，不管它以什么样的错误形式写就，都酷似一位女子照着这一形式装扮自己。

理解一首拙劣的十四行诗如何荒谬，再好不过的办法是，考虑一下其特点和形式，然后想象套在这种形式里的一位女子或一座房舍。

595　除非我们知道自己骄傲自大、充满野心、贪欲横流、虚弱无能、悲惨可怜和不仁不义，不然就真的是瞎了眼睛。如果有人知道这一切，还不希望被拯救，还有什么可说的？

那么我们又怎能不崇敬对人的缺陷了如指掌的宗教？除了渴望一个千真万确的宗教，因为它许诺了我们所渴求的救赎，我们还能渴望什么？

607　象征。救世主、天父、献身者、献祭、食物、国王、智者、立法者、受折磨的人、穷人，注定要诞生出一个民族，由他引领和哺育，并带到乐土。

620　人显然是为思考而生。他所有的尊严和价值就在于思考；他全部的义务就是像他应该的那样去思考。现在，思想的顺序从我们自己开始，从我们的造物主和我们的结局开始。

如今世人都在考虑些什么？从来没有别的，只是舞蹈、弹琴、唱歌、作诗、跑马挑圈，等等，还有搏斗、称王，却不思索做一个国王或一个人意味着什么。

622　厌倦。人处于完全的休息状态，没有激情、没有工作、没有消遣、没有努力，会忍无可忍。

然后，他就会面对无足轻重、孤独、无能、依赖、无助、空虚。

接着，立刻由灵魂深处生出无聊、沮丧、抑郁、懊恼、愤恨、绝望。

623　活在世上但不试图弄懂自己是怎么回事，如果这是非天然的盲目的话，那么过着罪恶的生活，同时又信奉上帝，就是可怕的盲目。

627　虚荣顽固地扎根于人的内心，一个士兵，一个随军杂役，一个厨师，或一个搬运工都会自夸，期待有人崇拜，甚至哲学家也期待拥有崇拜者；用文字反对哲学家的人，想享有写得好的声望，读的人想享有读过的声望，也许我本人写了这些文字，也想获得同样的东西，也许我的读者……

631　寻求至善却毫无结果，弄得疲惫憔悴，这是件好事，这样就可以向救世主伸出双手。

632　人对琐碎小事的敏感和对最伟大事物的漠然，是怪异混乱的标志。

633　尽管满目的苦难打动了我们，扼住了我们的喉咙，我们却具有一种无法抑制的本能，让自己振作起来。

634　人生最重要的是选择职业，它取决于机遇。是习惯的势力造就了泥瓦匠、士兵、屋顶建筑工。他们说：“他是个很好的屋顶建筑工。”谈到士兵时他们说：“他们疯了。”而相反，其他人则说：“战争的伟大无可比拟，其他人毫无价值。”幼年时听到对这些职业的溢美之词，就把其他职业排除在外，我们便这样选择了职业。因为我们天生热爱美德，憎恨愚蠢；某些字眼起决定性作用，只是我们运用这些字眼时出了问题。

习惯极其强大，天性只造就了人，而我们自己则造就了各式各样的人和各种各样的情况。

一些地区出泥瓦匠，一些地区出士兵，毫无疑问，天性是不尽一致的：是习惯造成了这种情况，因为它支配天性，但有时天性会战胜习惯，让人服从本能，无论是什么样的习惯，好的或坏的。

638　我们健康时想知道，如果生病了该怎么办。生病时，我们兴高采烈地服药；疾病帮我们解决了问题。我们不再怀有对消遣和远足的激情和欲望，因为消遣和远足只跟健康的身体有关，同生病时的危机不协调。天性激发出的激情和欲望是符合我们目前状态的。是我们自己的担心，而不是天性扰乱了我们，因为担心将我们现在所处的状态同我们不处于其中的状态所具有的激情联结在一起。

649　蒙田。蒙田本身具有的优点，别人要费尽周折才能具备。如果有人警告过他，他小题大做，谈论自己过多的话，他本身具有的缺点——我指的是除品行以外的——本可以在瞬间得到改正。

668　每个人对自己都意味着一切，因为一旦他死了，对他来说一切都消逝了。这就是为什么我们每个人都认为他对每个人意味着一切。我们不要根据自己而要根据人性的标准判断人性。

674　我们不以自己的力量，而是凭两个对立的罪恶之间的抗衡保持美德，正如我们在两股相向的逆风吹动下能保持直立。除掉一种罪恶，我们便跌入另一种罪恶。

685　荣耀。动物不互相钦佩。马匹不佩服它的伙伴。这并不是说它们不互相竞赛，而是这样没有意义，因为回到马厩时，更笨重的那匹马不会由于那个缘故把自己的燕麦让给别人的马，像人希望他人对自己那样。对它们来说，美德是它对自己的奖赏。

688　什么是自我？

一个人走到窗口看路过的人，如果我路过，我能说他是去看我吗？不，因为他没有特别地想到我。如果有人因一位女子的美貌而爱她呢，他爱她吗？不，因为天花会破坏她的美貌虽然不会毁掉她本人，这会结束他对她的爱情。

如果有人因为我的判断力或记忆力爱我，他们真的爱我吗？我，我本身？不，因为我可能会失去这些素质而不会失去我自己。如果这个自我既不在肉体上也不在灵魂里，它到底在哪里？除了爱这些素质，一个人怎么能爱躯体或灵魂，因为素质并不构成自我，而且是会消失的？我们会抽象地爱人的灵魂的实质，无论它包含什么样的素质吗？这是不可能的，这将是错误的。因此，我们永远不会爱任何人，而只爱素质。

让我们停止嘲笑那些因得到任命和官职而感到荣耀的人，因为除了借来的素质，我们从来没有爱过任何人。

693　世人认为最安逸的生活条件，在上帝看来最为艰苦；反之亦然。世人认为宗教生活最为艰苦，因为在上帝看来没有比它更安逸的事情。按照凡夫俗子的生活方式，享受高官或财富最为安逸，什么艰苦也比不过按上帝的方式生活，因为毫无兴趣，也不以此为乐。

696　别让人说我的话没有什么新意；素材的布局是新的。打网球时，双方使用同一个球，但其中一个人打得更好。

马上就会有人告诉我说，我用的是旧词。同样的想法但布局不同不会形成新的论据，正像同样的文字但布局不同却会形成新的想法！

697　生活放荡的人告诉规矩的人，说他们违背了天性，而认为自己遵循天性；这就像船上的人认为，岸上的人在移动。不管在何处，对一件事情的说法也是这样：我们需要一个固定的点来判断说法。港湾是船上乘客的裁判，但道德的港湾在哪里？

699　当所有的东西在同时移动，就显得没有什么在动，就像在船上。当每个人都在走向堕落时，就看不出有人在走向堕落，但如果有人站住，就会显出别人倏忽而过，自己就成了固定的点。

709　我们对自己知之甚少，许多人身体健康却以为自己快要死了，而许多人濒临死亡，没有感觉到自己马上就要发热或长脓，却以为自己身体健康。

711　力量。缘何要服从大多数人？是不是因为他们更正确？否，是因为他们更强大。

缘何要遵循远古的律法和主张？是不是因为它们最健全？否，是因为它们独一无二，没有争论的余地。

712　一天有人告诉我，他忏悔后觉得快乐，充满自信。别人告诉我，他仍然恐惧。我的反应是，这两种感受合起来可以造就一个好人，因为他们当中的一个如果不具备另一种感受的话，就会缺失什么。同样的情况也常常发生在其他相关联的事物上。

739　如今真理是如此模糊不定，谎言是如此确定无疑，除非我们热爱真理，不然永远都认不出它的面目。

740　懦夫了解真理，但只是在对自己有好处时才坚持真理，不然就放弃它。

741　加法机产生的效果比动物的任何行为都更接近思想，但它没有理由断言，会像动物一样有意愿。

742　即使他们说的不影响大家的利益，也不能肯定地推断他们没有说谎，因为有些人只是为说谎而说谎。

743　怒海行船，但肯定不会丧生，是可以乐在其中的。这就像教会受到迫害那样的情况。

744　我们不了解事情真相时，有个常出错的问题供人琢磨也是件好事，比如，月亮造成的季节变化、病情的发展，等等。因为人的主要毛病是，对无法了解的事物抱有无尽的好奇心，与其无谓地好奇，还不如犯错误。

746　事实上，无论是约瑟夫[16]、塔西佗[17]，还是其他历史学家，都没有谈及耶稣基督。

这绝不是反对他，相反，是对他有利。可以肯定，耶稣基督存在，他的宗教引起了轰动，所以很明显，他们是故意不提，或者他们提到了，但隐瞒或篡改了真相。

749　有一种判断，就是没有人不把自己凌驾于世人之上，没有人不希望自己好、自己永远幸福、永远生存下去超过希望世人如此。这种判断实在是歪曲事实。

750　克伦威尔想摧毁整个基督教世界，要不是一粒小小的砂子窜进他的膀胱，他就推翻王室，建立了自己长久的强权政治；甚至罗马也将在他的脚下颤栗。而他正是死于这粒砂子，家人蒙羞，天下太平，君主复位。

751　习惯于凭感觉判断的人对涉及推理的问题全然不知。因为他们想一眼就看清问题，而不习惯于探寻原则。其他人就相反，习惯于从原则进行推理，对涉及感觉的问题毫不了解，因为他们探寻原则，不能一眼就看清问题。

752　两种人使一切等同，如节假日和工作日，基督徒和牧师，他们自身的所有罪孽。由此，有人得出结论说，对牧师不好的，对基督徒也不好；而另一些人得出结论说，对基督徒不错的，对牧师也是许可的。

753　当奥古斯都听说希律王处死的两岁以下儿童中有自己的儿子时，他说，做希律王的猪胜过做他的儿子。（麦克洛比乌斯[18]的《农神节》，第二卷，第四章）

754　第一度：被责怪做得不好或被赞扬做得好。第二度：不受赞扬也不受责怪。

755　他制造出一个假神。

令人恶心。

756　思想。人所有的尊严都在于他的思想，但这个思想是什么？多么愚蠢！

那么思想从本质看，是令人赞叹的，不可媲美的。它一定是具有离奇的缺陷才应受到蔑视，但它确实有缺陷，这真是可笑之至。由于本质它是多么伟大，由于缺陷它又是多么卑微啊。

757　流失。感觉到一个人拥有的全都流失掉了，真是匪夷所思。

758　光明。黑暗。如果没有明显的真理的迹象，就会有太多的黑暗。真理令人赞叹的一个标志是，它始终存在于有形的教会和会众之间。教会里只有一种主张的话，就有更多的光明。一直存在的那个是真正的宗教，因为真正的一直存在，从没有存在过假的。

759　思想构成了人的伟大。

764　所有大型的消遣都有害于基督徒的生活，但在世人发明的所有消遣形式中，剧场最为可怕。那里自然、巧妙地上演着激情，从而唤醒、激发出我们内心的激情，特别是爱的激情；尤其是当它表现贞洁和美德时。因为它表现得越纯洁，就越能打动纯洁的灵魂，所以它热烈的气氛吸引着我们的自尊，使它立即产生一种欲望，想制造出生动的表演所产生的效果。与此同时，我们的良心适应了我们所看到的无可指责的感情，因为这感情消除了纯洁心灵的恐惧，他们想象以爱去爱别人，纯洁之心就不会受到伤害，是慎重之举。

因此，当我们离开剧场时，心里充满了爱情的美好和甜蜜，内心相信自己的纯洁，完全准备好接受爱的第一次感觉，或者寻找机会，在别人的内心唤起这样的感觉，这样我们就可以享受到在剧场里观看到的、精心表演的那种欢悦和牺牲。

765　如果雷电袭击低洼的地方，等等，诗人和只能争论这类事情的民众得不到证据。

767　因为公爵、国王和地方法官的头衔是真实而必要的（因为权力统治一切），所以它们存在于任何时代，任何地方，如果仅仅是心血来潮才册封出这样或那样的人，头衔没有一贯性，也就容易变异。

768　理性的命令必须服从，胜过服从主人的命令，因为不服从这个命令的话，会令我们不快，但如果不服从另一个的话，则是愚蠢的。

773　只是竞技本身，而不是胜利吸引我们。

我们喜欢看动物搏斗，而不是将一方征服后的胜利。除了最终的胜利，我们还希望看到什么？一旦决出胜负，我们就看够了。赌博和追求真理也是这样。我们希望看到辩论中不同的意见互相冲突，但一旦发现了真理，我们还会对它作一番深思吗？绝对不会。如果要享受真理，就必须看到它在辩论中产生。感情也一样，看到两种对立的感情发生碰撞是种愉悦，而当一方声称自己处于优势时，就变得残忍了。

我们从来不设法获得什么东西，而是追求过程。因此，剧场里无遮无拦的幸福场景不好看，好不过极度而无奈的痛苦，或冷酷的爱情，或野蛮的行径。

802　时间治愈痛苦，平息争吵，因为我们在变化。我们已不再是原来的自己；既不是冒犯者，也不是被冒犯者。这就好像一个人惹怒了一个民族，两代以后回来拜访他们。他们仍然是法兰西人，但已是不同的法兰西人。

803　如果我们每天夜里做同样的梦，梦会像我们每天看到的物体那样影响我们。如果一个工匠能每晚十二个小时梦到他是国王，我相信他会像一个国王每晚十二个小时梦到他是个工匠那样高兴。

如果我们每晚梦到被敌人追杀，为这些幻象所困扰，白天又做其他事情，就像旅行时的情况，我们会像确有其事似地受罪，会害怕去睡觉，因为害怕醒来时真的会遭遇不测。实际上这种梦魇带来的痛苦，几乎和现实带来的一样。

因为梦各不相同，而且即使在同一个梦中梦境也会变化，因为连续性的原因，梦中看到的东西比醒着时看到的影响要小一些。除极少数情况以外，这种连续性并非连续、平稳得没有变化，只是变化得不那么突然，就像在旅途中，我们说：“这就像一场梦。”因为人生就是一场梦，但似乎没有那么多变。

804　难道说，人承认原罪是因为他们说公义已经离开了这个世界？没有人称得上幸福，直到他死去。这是否意味着他们知道，永恒、绝对的幸福从死亡开始？

805　了解一个人的主要兴趣，就可以取悦他，但人的喜好可能有悖于自己的利益，这个利益是他自己概念中的利益，这个怪事令人不安。

806　我们不满意自己的生活，想过一种想象的、别人眼里的生活，所以就设法制造一种印象。我们不断地努力美化和维护想象中的自我，而忽视了真实的自我。如果我们冷静、大方或忠诚可靠的话，就渴望别人知道，这样就能将这些美德同我们的其他自我联系起来；我们想让美德脱离真正的自我，使之与其他自我统一起来。如果能赢得勇敢的声望，需要做懦夫我们也兴高采烈。这清楚地表明，我们的自我是多么微不足道，它会因为缺失了一样，就不满足于另一样，常常拿一个换另一个！因为不为挽救荣誉而死的人，就不会声名远扬。

808　有三种方法信从：理性、习惯、灵感。基督教本身就具有理性。基督教不承认不是因灵感而信从的人为其真正的孩子。这并不是说它排斥理性和习惯，恰恰相反，但我们必须接受那些证据，通过习惯坚定自己对它的信心，同时因蒙羞而获得灵感，只有这样，才能产生真正、有益的效果。免得基督的十字架毫无意义。

812　福音书的风格在许多方面都引人注目，其中包括从没有抨击过基督的刽子手和他的敌人。因为历史学家的著作从没有抨击过犹大[19]、彼拉多[20]或任何犹太人。

如果福音书显示出作者的这种克制，以及这种优秀品质的其他众多特点，如果他们写出来只是为了引起别人注意，而自己不作这样评论的话，不会没有朋友为他们说话。正是由于他们不虚伪，不偏激，才没有引来任何评论。我相信，这样的事情有很多以前都没有评论过。这表明这件事干得有多妙。

813　出于良知作恶，会作得充分而愉快。

814　我们滥用自己的感情，就像滥用自己的思想。

我们的思想和感情是我们交往的人训练的，也被我们交往的人滥用，我们交往的好人或坏人分别训练或滥用我们的思想和感情。因此，重要的是能够作出正确的选择，使我们对其进行训练，而不是滥用。除非这种选择能力已经被训练出来，而不是被滥用，否则我们作不出这种选择。这是个恶性循环，但任何人都能有幸逃脱。

815　普通人有能力不去考虑自己不想考虑的事。“不要考虑那些有关弥赛亚的段落。”犹太人对儿子说。我们自己人也经常这样，这就是虚伪的宗教是如何保存下来的，就大多数人而言，即使真正的宗教也是这样。

但是有些人无力阻止自己思考，越是被禁止，就越要思考。这些人摆脱了虚伪的宗教，甚至真正的宗教，除非能找到确凿的论据。

816　他们说：“如果我有信仰的话，我会很快放弃寻欢作乐的生活。”但是我告诉你：“如果放弃寻欢作乐的生活，你很快就会有信仰。现在，由你决定是否开始。如果我可以给你信仰，我会给的。但我不能，也不能证实你说的是真的，不过你可以轻而易举地放弃寻欢作乐，证实我是否在说真话。”

817　无可否认；人必须承认，基督教蕴含惊心动魄的东西。他们会说：“这是因为你出身于基督教家庭。”远非如此；我态度强硬地反对这个理由，因为害怕被偏见腐蚀。纵然我出身于基督教家庭，我仍然情不自禁地感到惊心动魄。

937　我们因爱好而做事的时候，便忘记了责任。例如，如果喜欢一本书，我们就会读这本书，而这时我们本应该做别的事情。但要记住我们的责任，无非是要决定做我们不喜欢的事情；这样我们就有借口做别的事情，从而也就记住了责任。

938　福音书中用于形容病态灵魂的是患病的肌体。由于一个肌体不能生出那么多的病症，用以恰当形容病态的灵魂，就需要有多个肌体，因此，我们看到聋子、哑巴、瞎子、瘫子、麻风病患者、魔鬼附体的人。所有这些都一起给放到病态的灵魂里。

939　“仆人不知道主人做什么”，因为主人只告诉他要做什么，而不告诉他目的。这就是他为什么盲目地服从，又往往与目的背道而驰。但是耶稣基督向我们晓谕了目的。

而你却破坏了那个目的。

940　耶稣不想以不公义的形式被处死，因为死于公义之手远比死于不公义的反抗更蒙羞。

[1]法国波旁王室鸢尾花国旗。——译者注

[2]克利奥佩特拉（Cleopatra），古埃及艳后，公元前69年10月—公元前30年8月12日，古埃及托勒密王朝的最后一任法老。——译者注

[3]盖乌斯·尤利乌斯·恺撒（Gaius Julius Caesar），公元前100年7月13日—公元前44年3月15日，或称恺撒大帝，罗马共和国末期杰出的军事统帅、政治家。曾征服高卢全境（大约是现在的法国），袭击日耳曼和不列颠。——译者注

[4]原名盖·屋大维·图里努斯（Gaius Julius Caesar Octavianus），公元前63年9月23日—公元14年8月19日，又名奥古斯都（Augustus），是恺撒大帝的甥孙和养子、罗马帝国的开国君主，统治罗马四十三年。曾出兵消灭了古埃及的托勒密王朝。——译者注

[5]马其顿国王亚历山大三世（Alexander III of Macedon），公元前356年7月22日—公元前323年6月10日，他维持了以马其顿为领导的统一的希腊诸城邦，并征服了波斯及其他亚洲王国，直至攻击到印度，被认为是历史上重要的军事家之一。——译者注

[6]约伯（Job），《旧约全书·约伯记》中的主角，被描述为一个受祝福的人，行为正直。由于撒旦指控约伯只为了物质利益才侍奉上帝，于是上帝一步步撤去保护，容许撒旦夺去约伯的财富、子女、健康。约伯受难，但保持了忠诚，没有诅咒上帝。上帝后来对约伯加倍祝福，使他晚景昌盛。——译者注

[7]所罗门（Solomon），根据《旧约全书·列王记》记载，是古以色列国王大卫之子，王国的第三任君主，以智慧著称；因崇信多神，偏离上帝，耶和华向他发怒，导致他死后叛乱爆发，王国分裂为北方的以色列王国和南方的犹大王国。——译者注

[8]埃皮克提图（Epictetus），公元前一世纪时的希腊斯多噶派哲学家、教师。——译者注

[9]保罗·哀米利乌斯（Paulus Emilius），公元前182年和公元前168年曾两度任罗马执政官，第二任时击败马其顿王珀修斯。——译者注

[10]珀修斯（Perseus），马其顿末代国王，公元前179年至公元前168年在位，公元前168年被保罗·哀米利乌斯击败，被俘。——译者注

[11]皮拉斯（Pyrrhus），公元前318—公元前272年，伊庇鲁斯国王（公元前306—公元前301年，公元前297—公元前272年），Molosso国王（公元前297—公元前272年），马其顿国王（公元前288—公元前284年，公元前273—公元前272年），罗马称霸亚平宁半岛的主要敌人之一，一生为王位征战。——译者注

[12]有人让皮拉斯说出计划征服世界的理由，据说他回答道：他的最终目的是心满意足地休息，但要在实现了征服的梦想以后。

[13]德谟克利特（Democritus），约公元前460—公元前370年，古希腊哲学家。——译者注

[14]埃皮克提图（Epictetus），公元前一世纪时的希腊斯多噶派哲学家、教师。——译者注

[15]圣奥古斯丁（Aurelius Augustinus），354年11月13日—430年8月28日，古罗马帝国时期基督教思想家，欧洲中世纪基督教神学、教父哲学的重要代表人物。——译者注

[16]约瑟夫（Josephus），耶稣时期犹太最著名的历史学家、犹太教徒。——译者注

[17]普布里乌斯·克奈里乌斯·塔西佗（Publius Cornelius Tacitus，50—120），古代罗马最伟大的历史学家、古罗马元老院议员。——译者注

[18]麦克洛比乌斯（Ambrosius Theodosius Macrobius），五世纪罗马文法家、新柏拉图主义哲学家。——译者注

[19]犹大（Judas），《圣经》中耶稣的十二门徒之一，他出卖了耶稣。——译者注

[20]彼拉多（Pilate），《圣经》中下令处死耶稣的犹太总督。——译者注

Human Happiness

PENGUIN BOOKS—GREAT IDEAS

Human Happiness

Blaise Pascal

1623-1662

Blaise Pascal

Human Happiness

TRANSLATED BY A. J. KRAILSHEIMER

PENGUIN BOOKS—GREAT IDEAS

In this selection of extracts the numbering system for theindividual pensées is that used in the Penguin Classics edition.

21 If we are too young our judgement is impaired, just as it is if we are too old.

Thinking too little about things or thinking too much both make us obstinate and fanatical.

If we look at our work immediately after completing it, we are still too involved; if too long afterwards, we cannot pick up the thread again.

It is like looking at pictures which are too near or too far away. There is just one indivisible point which is the right place.

Others are too near, too far, too high, or too low. In painting the rules of perspective decide it, but how will it be decided when it comes to truth and morality?

22 Flies are so mighty that they win battles, paralyse our minds, eat up our bodies.

23 Vanity of science. Knowledge of physical science will not console me for ignorance of morality in time of affliction, but knowledge of morality will always console me for ignorance of physical science.

24 Man's condition. Inconstancy, boredom, anxiety.

25 The fact that kings are habitually seen in the company of guards, drums, officers and all the things which prompt automatic responses of respect and fear has the result that, when they are sometimes alone and unaccompanied, their features are enough to strike respect and fear into their subjects, because we make no mental distinction between their person and the retinue with which they are normally seen to be associated. And the world, which does not know that this is the effect of habit, believes it to derive from some natural force, hence such sayings as: 'The character of divinity is stamped on his features.'

26 The power of kings is founded on the reason and the folly of the people, but especially on their folly. The greatest and most important thing in the world is founded on weakness. This is a remarkably sure foundation, for nothing is surer than that the people will be weak. Anything founded on sound reason is very ill-founded, like respect for wisdom.

30 We do not choose as captain of a ship the most highly born of those aboard.

31 We do not care about our reputation in towns where we are only passing through. But when we have to stay some time we do care. How much time does it take? A time proportionate to our vain and paltry existence.

33 What amazes me most is to see that everyone is not amazed at his own weakness. We behave seriously, and everyone follows his calling, not because it is really a good thing to do so, in accordance with fashion, but as if everyone knew for certain where reason and justice lie. We are constantly disappointed and an absurd humility makes us blame ourselves and not the skill we always boast of having. But it is a good thing for the reputation of scepticism that there are so many people about who are not sceptics, to show that man is quite capable of the most extravagant opinions, since he is capable of believing that he is not naturally and inevitably weak, but is, on the contrary, naturally wise.

36 Anyone who does not see the vanity of the world is very vain himself. So who does not see it, apart from young people whose lives are all noise, diversions, and thoughts for the future?

But take away their diversion and you will see them bored to extinction. Then they feel their nullity without recognizing it, for nothing could be more wretched than to be intolerably depressed as soon as one is reduced to introspection with no means of diversion.

42 How many kingdoms know nothing of us!

43 A trifle consoles us because a trifle upsets us.

44 Imagination. It is the dominant faculty in man, master of error and falsehood, all the more deceptive for not being invariably so; for it would be an infallible criterion of truth if it were infallibly that of lies. Since, however, it is usually false, it gives no indication of its quality, setting the same mark on true and false alike.

I am not speaking of fools, but of the wisest men, amongst whom imagination is best entitled to persuade. Reason may object in vain, it cannot fix the price of things.

This arrogant force, which checks and dominates its enemy, reason, for the pleasure of showing off the power it has in every sphere, has established a second nature in man. Imagination has its happy and unhappy men, its sick and well, its rich and poor; it makes us believe, doubt, deny reason; it deadens the senses, it arouses them; it has its fools and sages, and nothing annoys us more than to see it satisfy its guests more fully and completely than reason ever could. Those who are clever in imagination are far more pleased with themselves than prudent men could reasonably be. They look down on people with a lofty air; they are bold and confident in argument, where others are timid and unsure, and their cheerful demeanour often wins the verdict of their listeners, for those whose wisdom is imaginary enjoy the favour of judges similarly qualified. Imagination cannot make fools wise, but it makes them happy, as against reason, which only makes its friends wretched: one covers them with glory, the other with shame.

Who dispenses reputation? Who makes us respect and revere persons, works, laws, the great? Who but this faculty of imagination? All the riches of the earth are inadequate without its approval. Would you not say that this magistrate, whose venerable age commands universal respect, is ruled by pure, sublime reason, and judges things as they really are, without paying heed to the trivial circumstances which offend only the imagination of weaker men? See him go to hear a sermon in a spirit of pious zeal, the soundness of his judgement strengthened by the ardour of his charity, ready to listen with exemplary respect. If, when the preacher appears, it turns out that nature has given him a hoarse voice and an odd sort of face, that his barber has shaved him badly and he happens not to be too clean either, then, whatever great truths he may announce, I wager that our senator will not be able to keep a straight face.

Put the world's greatest philosopher on a plank that is wider than need be: if there is a precipice below, although his reason may convince him that he is safe, his imagination will prevail. Many could not even stand the thought of it without going pale and breaking into sweat.

I do not intend to list all the effects of imagination. Everyone knows that the sight of cats, or rats, the crunching of a coal, etc., is enough to unhinge reason. The tone of voice influences the wisest of us and alters the force of a speech or a poem.

Love or hate alters the face of justice. An advocate who has been well paid in advance will find the cause he is pleading all the more just. The boldness of his bearing will make it seem all the better to the judges, taken in by appearances. How absurd is reason, the sport of every wind! I should list almost all the actions of men, who hardly stir except when jolted by imagination. For reason has had to yield, and at its wisest adopts those principles which human imagination has rashly introduced at every turn. Anyone who chose to follow reason alone would have proved himself a fool. We must, since reason so pleases, work all day for benefits recognized as imaginary, and, when sleep has refreshed us from the toils of our reason, we must at once jump up to pursue the phantoms and endure the impressions created by this ruler of the world. Here is one of the principles of error, but not the only one.

Man has been quite right to make these two powers into allies, although in this peace imagination enjoys an extensive advantage; for in conflict its advantage is more complete. Reason never wholly overcomes imagination, while the contrary is quite common.

Our magistrates have shown themselves well aware of this mystery. Their red robes, the ermine in which they swaddle themselves like furry cats, the law-courts where they sit in judgement, the fleurs de lys, all this august panoply was very necessary. If physicians did not have long gowns and mules, if learned doctors did not wear square caps and robes four times too large, they would never have deceived the world, which finds such an authentic display irresistible. If they possessed true justice, and if physicians possessed the true art of healing, they would not need square caps; the majesty of such sciences would command respect in itself. But, as they only possess imaginary science, they have to resort to these vain devices in order to strike the imagination, which is their real concern, and this, in fact, is how they win respect.

Soldiers are the only ones who do not disguise themselves in this way, because their role is really more essential; they establish themselves by force, the others by masquerade.

That is why our kings have not attempted to disguise themselves. They have not dressed up in extraordinary clothes to show what they are, but they have themselves escorted by guards, scarred veterans. These armed troops whose hands and strength are theirs alone, the drums and trumpets that march before them, and these legions which surround them make the most resolute tremble.

They do not wear the trappings, they simply have the power. It would take reason at its most refined to see the Grand Turk, surrounded in his superb seraglio by 40,000 janissaries, as a man like any other.

We have only to see a lawyer in cap and gown to form a favourable opinion of his competence.

Imagination decides everything: it creates beauty, justice and happiness, which is the world's supreme good. I should dearly like to see the Italian book, of which I know only the title, worth many books in itself, Dell’opinione regina del mondo. Without knowing the book, I support its views, apart from any evil it may contain.

Such, more or less, are the effects of this deceptive faculty, apparently given to us for the specific purpose of leading us inevitably into error. We have plenty of other principles of error.

Longstanding impressions are not the only ones that can mislead us; the charms of novelty have the same power. Hence all the debate among men, who accuse each other either of following the false impressions of childhood or of rashly pursuing new ones. If anyone has found the golden mean, let him appear and prove it. Any principle, however natural it may be, even implanted in childhood, may be treated as a false impression either of education or of the senses.

'Because,' they say, 'you have believed since you were a child that a box was empty when you could not see anything in it, you believed that a vacuum could exist. This is just an illusion of your senses, strengthened by habit, and it must be corrected by science.' Others say: 'When you were taught at school that there is no such thing as a vacuum, your common sense was corrupted; it was quite clear about it before being given the wrong impression, and now it must be corrected by reverting to your original state.' Who then is the deceiver, the senses or education?

We have another principle of error in illnesses, which impair our judgement and sense. If serious illnesses do considerable harm, I have no doubt that the less serious ones have a proportionate effect.

Our own interest is another wonderful instrument for blinding us agreeably. The fairest man in the world is not allowed to be judge in his own cause. I know of men who, to avoid the danger of partiality in their own favour, have leaned over to the opposite extreme of injustice. The surest way to lose a perfectly just case was to get close relatives to commend it to them. Justice and truths are two points so fine that our instruments are too blunt to touch them exactly. If they do make contact, they blunt the point and press all round on the false rather than the true.

Man, then, is so happily constituted that he has no exact principle of truth, and several excellent ones of falsehood. Let us now see how many.

But the most absurd cause of his errors is the war between the senses and the reason.

46 Vanity. The cause and effect of love. Cleopatra.

47 We never keep to the present. We recall the past; we anticipate the future as if we found it too slow in coming and were trying to hurry it up, or we recall the past as if to stay its too rapid flight. We are so unwise that we wander about in times that do not belong to us, and do not think of the only one that does; so vain that we dream of times that are not and blindly flee the only one that is. The fact is that the present usually hurts. We thrust it out of sight because it distresses us, and if we find it enjoyable, we are sorry to see it slip away. We try to give it the support of the future, and think how we are going to arrange things over which we have no control for a time we can never be sure of reaching.

Let each of us examine his thoughts; he will find them wholly concerned with the past or the future. We almost never think of the present, and if we do think of it, it is only to see what light it throws on our plans for the future. The present is never our end. The past and the present are our means, the future alone our end. Thus we never actually live, but hope to live, and since we are always planning how to be happy, it is inevitable that we should never be so.

49 Caesar was too old, it seems to me, to go off and amuse himself conquering the world. Such a pastime was all right for Augustus and Alexander; they were young men, not easily held in check, but Caesar ought to have been more mature.

53 Man is vile enough to bow down to beasts and even worship them.

54 Inconstancy. Things have various qualities and the soul various tendencies, for nothing presented to the soul is simple, and the soul never applies itself simply to any subject. That is why the same thing makes us laugh and cry.

55 Inconstancy. We think playing upon man is like playing upon an ordinary organ. It is indeed an organ, but strange, shifting and changeable. Those who only know how to play an ordinary organ would never be in tune on this one. You have to know where the keys are.

56 We are so unhappy that we can only enjoy something which we should be annoyed to see go wrong, and that can and does constantly happen to thousands of things. Anyone who found the secret of rejoicing when things go well without being annoyed when they go badly would have found the point. It is perpetual motion.

57 It is not good to be too free.

It is not good to have all one needs.

58 Tyranny consists in the desire to dominate everything regardless of order.

In the various departments for men of strength, beauty, sense and piety, each man is master in his own house but nowhere else. Sometimes they meet and the strong and the handsome contend for mastery, but this is idiotic because their mastery is of different kinds. They do not understand each other and their mistake lies in wanting to rule everywhere. Nothing can do that, not even strength: it is of no effect in the learned world and only governs external actions. -So these arguments are false...

Tyranny. Tyranny is wanting to have by one means what can only be had by another. We pay different dues to different kinds of merit; we must love charm, fear strength, believe in knowledge.

These dues must be paid. It is wrong to refuse them and wrong to demand any others. So these arguments are false and tyrannical: 'I am handsome, so you must fear me. I am strong, so you must love me, I am...' In the same way it is false and tyrannical to say: 'He is not strong, so I will not respect him. He is not clever, so I will not fear him.'

65 Diversity. Theology is a science, but at the same time how many sciences? A man is a substance, but if you dissect him, what is he? Head, heart, stomach, veins, each vein, each bit of vein, blood, each humour of blood?

A town or a landscape from afar off is a town and a landscape, but as one approaches it becomes houses, trees, tiles, leaves, grass, ants, ants' legs, and so on ad infinitum. All that is comprehended in the word 'landscape'.

68 When I consider the brief span of my life absorbed into the eternity which comes before and after - as the remembrance of a guest that tarrieth but a day - the small space I occupy and which I see swallowed up in the infinite immensity of spaces of which I know nothing and which know nothing of me, I take fright and am amazed to see myself here rather than there: there is no reason for me to be here rather than there, now rather than then. Who put me here? By whose command and act were this time and place allotted to me?

69 Wretchedness. Job and Solomon.

70 If our condition were truly happy we should not need to divert ourselves from thinking about it.

71 Contradictions. Pride counterbalances all these miseries; man either hides or displays them, and glories in his awareness of them.

72 One must know oneself. Even if that does not help in finding truth, at least it helps in running one's life, and nothing is more proper.

73 What causes inconstancy is the realization that present pleasures are false, together with the failure to realize that absent pleasures are vain.

77 Pride. Curiosity is only vanity. We usually only want to know something so that we can talk about it; in other words, we would never travel by sea if it meant never talking about it, and for the sheer pleasure of seeing things we could never hope to describe to others.

78 Description of man. Dependence, desire for independence, needs.

79 How tiresome it is to give up pursuits to which we have become attached. A man enjoying a happy home-life has only to see a woman who attracts him, or spend five or six pleasant days gambling, and he will be very sorry to go back to what he was doing before. It happens every day.

80 Respect means: put yourself out. That may look pointless, but it is quite right, because it amounts to saying: I should certainly put myself out if you needed it, because I do so when you do not; besides, respect serves to distinguish the great. If respect meant sitting in an armchair we should be showing everyone respect and then there would be no way of marking distinction, but we make the distinction quite clear by putting ourselves out.

81 The only universal rules are the law of the land in everyday matters and the will of the majority in others. How is that? Because of the power implied.

That is why kings, who have another source of power, do not follow the majority of their ministers.

Equality of possessions is no doubt right, but, as men could not make might obey right, they have made right obey might. As they could not fortify justice they have justified force, so that right and might live together and peace reigns, the sovereign good.

82 Wisdom leads us back to childhood. Except ye become as little children.

83 The world is a good judge of things, because it is in the state of natural ignorance where man really belongs. Knowledge has two extremes which meet; one is the pure natural ignorance of every man at birth, the other is the extreme reached by great minds who run through the whole range of human knowledge, only to find that they know nothing and come back to the same ignorance from which they set out, but it is a wise ignorance which knows itself. Those who stand half-way have put their natural ignorance behind them without yet attaining the other; they have some smattering of adequate knowledge and pretend to understand everything. They upset the world and get everything wrong.

Ordinary people and clever people make up the run of the world; the former despise it and are despised in their turn. All their judgements are wrong and the world judges them rightly.

84 Descartes. In general terms one must say: 'That is the result of figure and motion,' because it is true, but to name them and assemble the machine is quite ridiculous. It is pointless, uncertain, and arduous. Even if it were true we do not think that the whole of philosophy would be worth an hour's effort.

86 Of true justice. We no longer have any. If we had, we should not accept it as a rule of justice that one should follow the customs of one's country.

That is why we have found might when we could not find right.

87 The chancellor is a grave man, dressed in fine robes because his position is false; not so the king. He enjoys power, and has no use for imagination. Judges, doctors, etc., enjoy nothing but imagination.

88 It is the effect of power, not of custom, for those capable of originality are rare. Those who are strongest in numbers only want to follow, and refuse recognition to those who seek it for their originality. If they persist in wanting recognition and despising those who are not original, the others will call them ridiculous names and may even beat them. So do not be conceited about your subtlety, or keep your satisfaction to yourself.

94 Sound opinions of the people. The greatest of evils is civil war.

It is bound to come if people want to reward merit, because everyone will claim to be meritorious. The evil to be feared if the succession falls by right of birth to a fool is neither so great nor so certain.

95 Sound opinions of the people. It is not mere vanity to be elegant, because it shows that a lot of people are working for you. Your hair shows that you have a valet, a perfumer, etc., bands, thread, braid, etc., show ... It means more than superficial show or mere accoutrement to have many hands in one's service.

The more hands one employs the more powerful one is. Elegance is a means of showing one's power.

98 How is it that a lame man does not annoy us while a lame mind does? Because a lame man recognizes that we are walking straight, while a lame mind says that it is we who are limping. But for that we should feel sorry rather than angry.

Epictetus goes much further when he asks: Why do we not lose our temper if someone tells us that we have a headache, while we do lose it if someone says there is anything wrong with our arguments or our choice?

99 The reason for that is that we are quite certain that we have not got a headache, and are not limping, but we are not so sure we are making the right choice. Consequently, since the only thing that makes us sure is the evidence available to us, we hesitate and are taken aback when the evidence available to someone else makes him see just the opposite. All the more so when a thousand other people scoff at our choice, because we are obliged to prefer our judgement to that of so many others, and that is a bold and difficult thing to do. There is never such a clash of views over a lame man.

Man is so made that if he is told often enough that he is a fool he believes it. By telling himself so often enough he convinces himself, because when he is alone he carries on an inner dialogue with himself which it is important to keep under proper control. Evil communications corrupt good manners. We must keep silence as far as we can and only talk to ourselves about God, whom we know to be true, and thus convince ourselves that he is.

103 Right, might. It is right to follow the right, it is necessary to follow the mighty.

Right without might is helpless, might without right is tyrannical.

Right without might is challenged, because there are always evil men about. Might without right is denounced. We must therefore combine right and might, and to that end make right into might or might into right.

Right is open to dispute, might is easily recognized and beyond dispute. Therefore right could not be made mighty because might challenged right, calling it unjust and itself claiming to be just.

Being thus unable to make right into might, we have made might into right.

104 What a great advantage to be of noble birth, since it gives a man of eighteen the standing, recognition and respect that another man might not earn before he was fifty. That means winning thirty years' start with no effort.

105 If an animal did rationally what it does by instinct, and if it spoke rationally what it speaks by instinct when hunting, or warning its fellows that the prey has been lost or found, it would certainly go on to talk about matters which affect it more seriously, and it would say, for instance: 'Bite through this cord; it is hurting me and I cannot reach it.'

106 Greatness. Causes and effects show the greatness of man in producing such excellent order from his own concupiscence.

107 The parrot wipes its beak although it is clean.

108 What part of us feels pleasure? Is it our hand, our arm, our flesh, or our blood? It must obviously be something immaterial.

109 Against Scepticism. It is odd that we cannot define these things without making them obscure; we talk about them all the time. We assume that everyone conceives of them in the same way, but that it is a quite gratuitous assumption, because we have no proof that it is so. I see indeed that we apply these words on the same occasions; every time two men see a body change its position they both use the same word to express what they have seen, each of them saying that the body has moved. Such conformity of application provides a strong presumption of conformity of thought, but it lacks the absolute force of total conviction, although the odds are that it is so, because we know that the same conclusions are often drawn from different assumptions.

That is enough to cloud the issue, to say the least, though it does not completely extinguish the natural light which provides us with certainty in such matters. The Platonists would have wagered on it, but that makes the light dimmer and upsets the dogmatists, to the glory of the sceptical clique which stands for ambiguous ambiguity, and a certain dubious obscurity from which our doubts cannot remove every bit of light any more than our natural light can dispel all the darkness.

110 We know the truth not only through our reason but also through our heart. It is through the latter that we know first principles, and reason, which has nothing to do with it, tries in vain to refute them. The sceptics have no other object than that, and they work at it to no purpose. We know that we are not dreaming, but, however unable we may be to prove it rationally, our inability proves nothing but the weakness of our reason, and not the uncertainty of all our knowledge, as they maintain. For knowledge of first principles, like space, time, motion, number, is as solid as any derived through reason, and it is on such knowledge, coming from the heart and instinct, that reason has to depend and base all its argument. The heart feels that there are three spatial dimensions and that there is an infinite series of numbers, and reason goes on to demonstrate that there are no two square numbers of which one is double the other. Principles are felt, propositions proved, and both with certainty though by different means. It is just as pointless and absurd for reason to demand proof of first principles from the heart before agreeing to accept them as it would be absurd for the heart to demand an intuition of all the propositions demonstrated by reason before agreeing to accept them.

Our inability must therefore serve only to humble reason, which would like to be the judge of everything, but not to confute our certainty. As if reason were the only way we could learn! Would to God, on the contrary, that we never needed it and knew everything by instinct and feeling! But nature has refused us this blessing, and has instead given us only very little knowledge of this kind; all other knowledge can be acquired only by reasoning.

That is why those to whom God has given religious faith by moving their hearts are very fortunate, and feel quite legitimately convinced, but to those who do not have it we can only give such faith through reasoning, until God gives it by moving their heart, without which faith is only human and useless for salvation.

111 I can certainly imagine a man without hands, feet, or head, for it is only experience that teaches us that the head is more necessary than the feet. But I cannot imagine a man without thought; he would be a stone or an animal.

112 Instinct and reason, signs of two natures.

113 Thinking reed. It is not in space that I must seek my human dignity, but in the ordering of my thought. It will do me no good to own land. Through space the universe grasps me and swallows me up like a speck; through thought I grasp it.

114 Man's greatness comes from knowing he is wretched: a tree does not know it is wretched.

Thus it is wretched to know that one is wretched, but there is greatness in knowing one is wretched.

115 Immateriality of the soul. When philosophers have subdued their passions, what material substance has managed to achieve this?

116 All these examples of wretchedness prove his greatness. It is the wretchedness of a great lord, the wretchedness of a dispossessed king.

117 Man's greatness. Man's greatness is so obvious that it can even be deduced from his wretchedness, for what is nature in animals we call wretchedness in man, thus recognizing that, if his nature is today like that of the animals, he must have fallen from some better state which was once his own.

Who indeed would think himself unhappy not to be king except one who had been dispossessed? Did anyone think Paulus Emilius was unhappy not to be consul? On the contrary, everyone thought he was happy to have been so once, because the office was not meant to be permanent. But people thought Perseus so unhappy at finding himself no longer king, because that was meant to be a permanent office, that they were surprised that he could bear to go on living. Who would think himself unhappy if he had only one mouth and who would not if he had only one eye? It has probably never occurred to anyone to be distressed at not having three eyes, but those who have none are inconsolable.

118 Man's greatness even in his concupiscence. He has managed to produce such a remarkable system from it and make it the image of true charity.

119 Contradictions. (After showing how vile and how great man is.) Let man now judge his own worth, let him love himself, for there is within him a nature capable of good; but that is no reason for him to love the vileness within himself. Let him despise himself because this capacity remains unfilled; but that is no reason for him to despise this natural capacity. Let him both hate and love himself; he has within him the capacity for knowing truth and being happy, but he possesses no truth which is either abiding or satisfactory.

I should therefore like to arouse in man the desire to find truth, to be ready, free from passion, to follow it wherever he may find it, realizing how far his knowledge is clouded by passions. I should like him to hate his concupiscence which automatically makes his decisions for him, so that it should not blind him when he makes his choice, nor hinder him once he has chosen.

120 We are so presumptuous that we should like to be known all over the world, even by people who will only come when we are no more. Such is our vanity that the good opinion of half a dozen of the people around us gives us pleasure and satisfaction.

121 It is dangerous to explain too clearly to man how like he is to the animals without pointing out his greatness. It is also dangerous to make too much of his greatness without his vileness. It is still more dangerous to leave him in ignorance of both, but it is most valuable to represent both to him.

Man must not be allowed to believe that he is equal either to animals or to angels, nor to be unaware of either, but he must know both.

122 Greatness and wretchedness. Since wretchedness and greatness can be concluded each from the other, some people have been more inclined to conclude that man is wretched for having used his greatness to prove it, while others have all the more cogently concluded he is great by basing their proof on wretchedness. Everything that could be said by one side as proof of greatness has only served as an argument for the others to conclude he is wretched, since the further one falls the more wretched one is, and vice versa. One has followed the other in an endless circle, for it is certain that as man's insight increases so he finds both wretchedness and greatness within himself. In a word man knows he is wretched. Thus he is wretched because he is so, but he is truly great because he knows it.

123 Contradictions. Contempt for our existence, dying for nothing, hatred of our existence.

124 Contradictions. Man is naturally credulous, incredulous, timid, bold.

125 What are our natural principles but habitual principles? In children it is the principles received from the habits of their fathers, like hunting in the case of animals.

A change of habit will produce different natural principles, as can be seen from experience, and if there are some principles which habit cannot eradicate, there are others both habitual and unnatural which neither nature nor a new habit can eradicate. It all depends on one's disposition.

126 Fathers are afraid that their children's natural love may be eradicated. What then is this nature which is liable to be eradicated?

Habit is a second nature that destroys the first. But what is nature? Why is habit not natural? I am very much afraid that nature itself is only a first habit, just as habit is a second nature.

127 Man's nature may be considered in two ways; either according to his end, and then he is great and beyond compare, or according to the masses, as the nature of horses and dogs is judged by the masses from seeing how they run or ward off strangers, and then man is abject and vile. These are the two approaches which provoke such divergent views and such argument among philosophers, because each denies the other's hypothesis.

One says: 'Man was not born for this end, because everything he does belies it.' The other says: 'He is falling far short of his end when he acts so basely.'

128 Two things teach man about his whole nature: instinct and experience.

129 Trade. Thoughts. All is one, all is diversity.

How many natures lie in human nature! How many occupations! How fortuitously in the ordinary way each of us takes up the one that he has heard others praise. A well-turned heel.

130 If he exalts himself, I humble him.

If he humbles himself, I exalt him.

And I go on contradicting him

Until he understands

That he is a monster that passes all understanding.

131 The strongest of the sceptics' arguments, to say nothing of minor points, is that we cannot be sure that these principles are true (faith and revelation apart) except through some natural intuition. Now this natural intuition affords no convincing proof that they are true. There is no certainty, apart from faith, as to whether man was created by a good God, an evil demon, or just by chance, and so it is a matter of doubt, depending on our origin, whether these innate principles are true, false or uncertain.

Moreover, no one can be sure, apart from faith, whether he is sleeping or waking, because when we are asleep we are just as firmly convinced that we are awake as we are now. As we often dream we are dreaming, piling up one dream on another, is it not possible that this half of our life is itself just a dream, on to which the others are grafted, and from which we shall awake when we die? That while it lasts we are as little in possession of the principles of truth and goodness as during normal sleep? All this passage of time, of life, all these different bodies which we feel, the different thoughts which stir us, may be no more than illusions like the passage of time and vain phantoms of our dreams. We think we are seeing space, shape, movement, we feel time pass, we measure it, in fact we behave just as we do when we are awake. As a result, since half our life is spent in sleep, on our own admission and despite appearances we have no idea of the truth because all our intuitions are simply illusions during that time. Who knows whether the other half of our lives, when we think we are awake, is not another sleep slightly different from the first, on to which our dreams are grafted as our sleep appears, and from which we awake when we think we are sleeping? And who can doubt that, if we dreamed in the company of others and our dreams happened to agree, which is common enough, and if we were alone when awake, we should think things had been turned upside-down?

These are the main points on each side, to say nothing of minor arguments, like those the sceptics direct against the influences of habit, education, local customs, and so on, which the slightest puff of scepticism overturns, though they convince the majority of ordinary people, who have only this vain basis for their dogmas. You have only to look at their books; if you are not sufficiently persuaded you soon will be, perhaps too much so.

I pause at the dogmatists' only strong point, which is that we cannot doubt natural principles if we speak sincerely and in all good faith.

To which the sceptics reply, in a word, that uncertainty as to our origin entails uncertainty as to our nature. The dogmatists have been trying to answer that ever since the world began.

(Anyone wanting ampler information about scepticism should look at their books; he will soon be persuaded, perhaps too much so.)

This means open war between men, in which everyone is obliged to take sides, either with the dogmatists or with the sceptics, because anyone who imagines he can stay neutral is a sceptic par excellence. This neutrality is the essence of their clique. Anyone who is not against them is their staunch supporter, and that is where their advantage appears. They are not even for themselves; they are neutral, indifferent, suspending judgment on everything, including themselves.

What then is man to do in this state of affairs? Is he to doubt everything, to doubt whether he is awake, whether he is being pinched or burned? Is he to doubt whether he is doubting, to doubt whether he exists?

No one can go that far, and I maintain that a perfectly genuine sceptic has never existed. Nature backs up helpless reason and stops it going so wildly astray.

Is he, on the other hand, to say that he is the certain possessor of truth, when at the slightest pressure he fails to prove his claim and is compelled to loose his grasp?

What sort of freak then is man! How novel, how monstrous, how chaotic, how paradoxical, how prodigious! Judge of all things, feeble earthworm, repository of truth, sink of doubt and error, glory and refuse of the universe!

Who will unravel such a tangle? This is certainly beyond dogmatism and scepticism, beyond all human philosophy. Man transcends man. Let us then concede to the sceptics what they have so often proclaimed, that truth lies beyond our scope and is an unattainable quarry, that it is no earthly denizen, but at home in heaven, lying in the lap of God, to be known only in so far as it pleases him to reveal it. Let us learn our true nature from the uncreated and incarnate truth.

If we seek truth through reason we cannot avoid one of these three sects. You cannot be a sceptic or a Platonist without stifling nature, you cannot be a dogmatist without turning your back on reason.

Nature confounds the sceptics and Platonists, and reason confounds the dogmatists. What then will become of you, man, seeking to discover your true condition through natural reason? You cannot avoid one of these three sects nor survive in any of them.

Know then, proud man, what a paradox you are to yourself. Be humble, impotent reason! Be silent, feeble nature! Learn that man infinitely transcends man, hear from your master your true condition, which is unknown to you.

Listen to God.

Is it not as clear as day that man's condition is dual? The point is that if man had never been corrupted, he would, in his innocence, confidently enjoy both truth and felicity, and, if man had never been anything but corrupt, he would have no idea either of truth or bliss. But unhappy as we are (and we should be less so if there were no element of greatness in our condition) we have an idea of happiness but we cannot attain it. We perceive an image of the truth and possess nothing but falsehood, being equally incapable of absolute ignorance and certain knowledge; so obvious is it that we once enjoyed a degree of perfection from which we have unhappily fallen.

Let us then conceive that man's condition is dual. Let us conceive that man infinitely transcends man, and that without the aid of faith he would remain inconceivable to himself, for who cannot see that unless we realize the duality of human nature we remain invincibly ignorant of the truth about ourselves?

It is, however, an astounding thing that the mystery furthest from our ken, that of the transmission of sin, should be something without which we can have no knowledge of ourselves.

Without doubt nothing is more shocking to our reason than to say that the sin of the first man has implicated in its guilt men so far from the original sin that they seem incapable of sharing it. This flow of guilt does not seem merely impossible to us, but indeed most unjust. What could be more contrary to the rules of our miserable justice than the eternal damnation of a child, incapable of will, for an act in which he seems to have so little part that it was actually committed 6,000 years before he existed? Certainly nothing jolts us more rudely than this doctrine, and yet, but for this mystery, the most incomprehensible of all, we remain incomprehensible to ourselves. The knot of our condition was twisted and turned in that abyss, so that it is harder to conceive of man without this mystery than for man to conceive of it himself.

This shows that God, in his desire to make the difficulties of our existence unintelligible to us, hid the knot so high, or more precisely, so low, that we were quite unable to reach it. Consequently it is not through the proud activity of our reason but through its simple submission that we can really know ourselves.

These fundamental facts, solidly established on the inviolable authority of religion, teach us that there are in faith two equally constant truths. One is that man in the state of his creation, or in the state of grace, is exalted above the whole of nature, made like unto God and sharing in his divinity. The other is that in the state of corruption and sin he has fallen from that first state and has become like the beasts. These two propositions are equally firm and certain.

Scripture openly declares this when it says in certain places: My delights were with the sons of men - I will pour out my spirit upon all flesh - Ye are gods, while saying in others: All flesh is grass - Man is like the beasts that perish - I said in my heart concerning the estate of the sons of men.

Whence it is clearly evident that man through grace is made like unto God and shares his divinity, and without grace he is treated like the beasts of the field.

136 Diversion. Sometimes, when I set to thinking about the various activities of men, the dangers and troubles which they face at Court, or in war, giving rise to so many quarrels and passions, daring and often wicked enterprises and so on, I have often said that the sole cause of man's unhappiness is that he does not know how to stay quietly in his room. A man wealthy enough for life's needs would never leave home to go to sea or besiege some fortress if he knew how to stay at home and enjoy it. Men would never spend so much on a commission in the army if they could bear living in town all their lives, and they only seek after the company and diversion of gambling because they do not enjoy staying at home.

But after closer thought, looking for the particular reasons for all our unhappiness now that I knew its general cause, I found one very cogent reason in the natural unhappiness of our feeble mortal condition, so wretched that nothing can console us when we really think about it.

Imagine any situation you like, add up all the blessings with which you could be endowed, to be king is still the finest thing in the world; yet if you imagine one with all the advantages of his rank, but no means of diversion, left to ponder and reflect on what he is, this limp felicity will not keep him going; he is bound to start thinking of all the threats facing him, of possible revolts, finally of inescapable death and disease, with the result that if he is deprived of so-called diversion he is unhappy, indeed more unhappy than the humblest of his subjects who can enjoy sport and diversion.

The only good thing for men therefore is to be diverted from thinking of what they are, either by some occupation which takes their mind off it, or by some novel and agreeable passion which keeps them busy, like gambling, hunting, some absorbing show, in short by what is called diversion.

That is why gaming and feminine society, war and high office are so popular. It is not that they really bring happiness, nor that anyone imagines that true bliss comes from possessing the money to be won at gaming or the hare that is hunted: no one would take it as a gift. What people want is not the easy peaceful life that allows us to think of our unhappy condition, nor the dangers of war, nor the burdens of office, but the agitation that takes our mind off it and diverts us. That is why we prefer the hunt to the capture.

That is why men are so fond of hustle and bustle; that is why prison is such a fearful punishment; that is why the pleasures of solitude are so incomprehensible. That, in fact, is the main joy of being a king, because people are continually trying to divert him and procure him every kind of pleasure. A king is surrounded by people whose only thought is to divert him and stop him thinking about himself, because, king though he is, he becomes unhappy as soon as he thinks about himself.

That is all that men have been able to devise for attaining happiness; those who philosophize about it, holding that people are quite unreasonable to spend all day chasing a hare that they would not have wanted to buy, have little knowledge of our nature. The hare itself would not save us from thinking about death and the miseries distracting us, but hunting it does so. Thus when Pyrrhus was advised to take the rest towards which he was so strenuously striving, he found it very hard to do so.[①]

Telling a man to rest is the same as telling him to live happily. It means advising him to enjoy a completely happy state in which he can contemplate at leisure without cause for distress. It means not understanding nature.

Thus men who are naturally conscious of what they are shun nothing so much as rest; they would do anything to be disturbed.

It is wrong then to blame them; they are not wrong to want excitement - if they only wanted it for the sake of diversion. The trouble is that they want it as though, once they had the things they seek, they could not fail to be truly happy. That is what justifies calling their search a vain one. All this shows that neither the critics nor the criticized understand man's real nature.

When men are reproached for pursuing so eagerly something that could never satisfy them, their proper answer, if they really thought about it, ought to be that they simply want a violent and vigorous occupation to take their minds off themselves, and that is why they choose some attractive object to entice them in ardent pursuit. Their opponents could find no answer to that,

(Vanity, pleasure of showing off. Dancing, you must think where to put your feet.)

but they do not answer like that because they do not know themselves. They do not know that all they want is the hunt and not the capture. The nobleman sincerely believes that hunting is a great sport, the sport of kings, but his huntsman does not feel like that. They imagine that if they secured a certain appointment they would enjoy resting afterwards, and they do not realize the insatiable nature of cupidity. They think they genuinely want rest when all they really want is activity.

They have a secret instinct driving them to seek external diversion and occupation, and this is the result of their constant sense of wretchedness. They have another secret instinct, left over from the greatness of our original nature, telling them that the only true happiness lies in rest and not in excitement. These two contrary instincts give rise to a confused plan buried out of sight in the depths of their soul, which leads them to seek rest by way of activity and always to imagine that the satisfaction they miss will come to them once they overcome certain obvious difficulties and can open the door to welcome rest.

All our life passes in this way: we seek rest by struggling against certain obstacles, and once they are overcome, rest proves intolerable because of the boredom it produces. We must get away from it and crave excitement.

We think either of present or of threatened miseries, and even if we felt quite safe on every side, boredom on its own account would not fail to emerge from the depths of our hearts, where it is naturally rooted, and poison our whole mind.

Man is so unhappy that he would be bored even if he had no cause for boredom, by the very nature of his temperament, and he is so vain that, though he has a thousand and one basic reasons for being bored, the slightest thing, like pushing a ball with a billiard cue, will be enough to divert him.

'But,' you will say, 'what is his object in all this?' Just so that he can boast tomorrow to his friends that he played better than someone else. Likewise others sweat away in their studies to prove to scholars that they have solved some hitherto insoluble problem in algebra. Many others again, just as foolishly in my view, risk the greatest dangers so that they can boast afterwards of having captured some stronghold. Then there are others who exhaust themselves observing all these things, not in order to become wiser, but just to show they know them, and these are the biggest fools of the lot, because they know what they are doing, while it is conceivable that the rest would stop being foolish if they knew too.

A given man lives a life free from boredom by gambling a small sum every day. Give him every morning the money he might win that day, but on condition that he does not gamble, and you will make him unhappy. It might be argued that what he wants is the entertainment of gaming and not the winnings. Make him play then for nothing; his interest will not be fired and he will become bored, so it is not just entertainment he wants. A half-hearted entertainment without excitement will bore him. He must have excitement, he must delude himself into imagining that he would be happy to win what he would not want as a gift if it meant giving up gambling. He must create some target for his passions and then arouse his desire, anger, fear, for this object he has created, just like children taking fright at a face they have daubed themselves.

That is why this man, who lost his only son a few months ago and was so troubled and oppressed this morning by lawsuits and quarrels, is not thinking about it any more. Do not be surprised; he is concentrating all his attention on which way the boar will go that his dogs have been so hotly pursuing for the past six hours. That is all he needs. However sad a man may be, if you can persuade him to take up some diversion he will be happy while it lasts, and however happy a man may be, if he lacks diversion and has no absorbing passion or entertainment to keep boredom away, he will soon be depressed and unhappy. Without diversion there is no joy; with diversion there is no sadness. That is what constitutes the happiness of persons of rank, for they have a number of people to divert them and the ability to keep themselves in this state.

Make no mistake about it. What else does it mean to be Superintendent, Chancellor, Chief Justice, but to enjoy a position in which a great number of people come every morning from all parts and do not leave them a single hour of the day to think about themselves? When they are in disgrace and sent off to their country houses, where they lack neither wealth nor servants to meet their needs, they infallibly become miserable and dejected because no one stops them thinking about themselves.

139 Diversion. From childhood on men are made responsible for the care of their honour, their property, their friends, and even of the property and honour of their friends; they are burdened with duties, language-training and exercises, and given to understand that they can never be happy unless their health, their honour, their fortune and those of their friends are in good shape, and that it needs only one thing to go wrong to make them unhappy. So they are given responsibilities and duties which harass them from the first moment of each day. You will say that is an odd way to make them happy: what better means could one devise to make them unhappy? What could one do? You would only have to take away all their cares, and then they would see themselves and think about what they are, where they come from, and where they are going. That is why men cannot be too much occupied and distracted, and that is why, when they have been given so many things to do, if they have some time off they are advised to spend it on diversion and sport, and always to keep themselves fully occupied.

How hollow and foul is the heart of man!

148 Man without faith can know neither true good nor justice.

All men seek happiness. There are no exceptions. However different the means they may employ, they all strive towards this goal. The reason why some go to war and some do not is the same desire in both, but interpreted in two different ways. The will never takes the least step except to that end. This is the motive of every act of every man, including those who go and hang themselves.

Yet for very many years no one without faith has ever reached the goal at which everyone is continually aiming. All men complain: princes, subjects, nobles, commoners, old, young, strong, weak, learned, ignorant, healthy, sick, in every country, at every time, of all ages, and all conditions.

A test which has gone on so long, without pause or change, really ought to convince us that we are incapable of attaining the good by our own efforts. But example teaches us very little. No two examples are so exactly alike that there is not some subtle difference, and that is what makes us expect that our expectations will not be disappointed this time as they were last time. So, while the present never satisfies us, experience deceives us, and leads us on from one misfortune to another until death comes as the ultimate and eternal climax.

What else does this craving, and this helplessness, proclaim but that there was once in man a true happiness, of which all that now remains is the empty print and trace? This he tries in vain to fill with everything around him, seeking in things that are not there the help he cannot find in those that are, though none can help, since this infinite abyss can be filled only with an infinite and immutable object; in other words by God himself.

God alone is man's true good, and since man abandoned him it is a strange fact that nothing in nature has been found to take his place: stars, sky, earth, elements, plants, cabbages, leeks, animals, insects, calves, serpents, fever, plague, war, famine, vice, adultery, incest. Since losing his true good, man is capable of seeing it in anything, even his own destruction, although it is so contrary at once to God, to reason and to nature.

Some seek their good in authority, some in intellectual inquiry and knowledge, some in pleasure.

Others again, who have indeed come closer to it, have found it impossible that this universal good, desired by all men, should lie in any of the particular objects which can only be possessed by one individual and which, once shared, cause their possessors more grief over the part they lack than satisfaction over the part they enjoy as their own. They have realized that the true good must be such that it may be possessed by all men at once without diminution or envy, and that no one should be able to lose it against his will. Their reason is that this desire is natural to man, since all men inevitably feel it, and man cannot be without it, and they therefore conclude...

151 It is absurd of us to rely on the company of our fellows, as wretched and helpless as we are; they will not help us; we shall die alone.

We must act then as if we were alone. If that were so, would we build superb houses, etc.? We should unhesitatingly look for the truth. And, if we refuse, it shows that we have a higher regard for men's esteem than for pursuing the truth.

152 Between us and heaven or hell there is only life half-way, the most fragile thing in the world.

153 What after all do you promise me but ten years of self-love (for ten years is the stake), trying hard to please without succeeding, not to speak of certain anguish?

155 Heart

Instinct

Principles.

156 Pity the atheists who seek, for are they not unhappy enough? Inveigh against those who boast about it.

157 Atheism indicates strength of mind, but only up to a certain point.

158 As far as the choices go, you must take the trouble to seek the truth, for if you die without worshipping the true principle you are lost. 'But', you say, 'if he had wanted me to worship him, he would have left me some signs of his will.' So he did, but you pay no heed. Look for them then; it is well worth it.

159 If we ought to give up one week of our life, we ought to give up a hundred years.

16o There are only three sorts of people: those who have found God and serve him; those who are busy seeking him and have not found him; those who live without either seeking or finding him. The first are reasonable and happy, the last are foolish and unhappy, those in the middle are unhappy and reasonable.

161 Atheists should say things that are perfectly clear. Now it is not perfectly clear that the soul is material.

162 Begin by pitying unbelievers; their condition makes them unhappy enough.

They ought not to be abused unless it does them good, but in fact it does them harm.

163 A man in a dungeon, not knowing whether sentence has been passed on him, with only an hour left to find out, and that hour enough, once he knows it has been passed, to have it revoked. It would be unnatural for him to spend that hour not finding out whether sentence has been passed but playing piquet.

So it is beyond all nature that man, etc.... It is weighing down the hand of God.

So it is not only the zeal of those who seek him that proves God's existence, but also the blindness of those who do not seek him.

164 Beginning. Dungeon. I agree that Copernicus' opinion need not be more closely examined. But this:

It affects our whole life to know whether the soul is mortal or immortal.

165 The last act is bloody, however fine the rest of the play. They throw earth over your head and it is finished for ever.

166 We run heedlessly into the abyss after putting something in front of us to stop us seeing it.

193 Prejudice leading to error. It is deplorable to see everybody debating about the means, never the end. Everyone thinks about how he will get on in his career, but when it comes to choosing a career or a country it is fate that decides for us.

It is pitiful to see so many Turks, heretics, unbelievers follow in their fathers' footsteps, solely because they have all been brought up to believe that this is the best course. This is what makes each of us pick his particular career as locksmith, soldier, etc.

That is why savages do not care about Provence.

194 Why have limits been set upon my knowledge, my height, my life, making it a hundred rather than a thousand years? For what reason did nature make it so, and choose this rather than that mean from the whole of infinity, when there is no more reason to choose one rather than another, as none is more attractive than another?

195 Little of everything. As we cannot be universal by knowing everything there is to be known about everything, we must know a little about everything, because it is much better to know something about everything than everything about something. Such universality is the finest. It would be still better if we could have both together, but, if a choice must be made, this is the one to choose. The world knows this and does so, for the world is often a good judge.

196 Some fancy makes me dislike people who croak or who puff while eating. Fancy carries a lot of weight. What good will that do us? That we indulge it because it is natural? No, rather that we resist it.

197 There is no better proof of human vanity than to consider the causes and effects of love, because the whole universe can be changed by it. Cleopatra's nose.

198 When I see the blind and wretched state of man, when I survey the whole universe in its dumbness and man left to himself with no light, as though lost in this corner of the universe, without knowing who put him there, what he has come to do, what will become of him when he dies, incapable of knowing anything, I am moved to terror, like a man transported in his sleep to some terrifying desert island, who wakes up quite lost and with no means of escape. Then I marvel that so wretched a state does not drive people to despair. I see other people around me, made like myself. I ask them if they are any better informed than I, and they say they are not. Then these lost and wretched creatures look around and find some attractive objects to which they become addicted and attached. For my part I have never been able to form such attachments, and considering how very likely it is that there exists something besides what I can see, I have tried to find out whether God has left any traces of himself.

I see a number of religions in conflict, and therefore all false, except one. Each of them wishes to be believed on its own authority and threatens unbelievers. I do not believe them on that account. Anyone can say that. Anyone can call himself a prophet, but I see Christianity, and find its prophecies, which are not something that anyone can do.

199 Disproportion of man. This is where unaided knowledge brings us. If it is not true, there is no truth in man, and if it is true, he has good cause to feel humiliated; in either case he is obliged to humble himself.

And, since he cannot exist without believing this knowledge, before going on to a wider inquiry concerning nature, I want him to consider nature just once, seriously and at leisure, and to look at himself as well, and judge whether there is any proportion between himself and nature by comparing the two.

Let man then contemplate the whole of nature in her full and lofty majesty, let him turn his gaze away from the lowly objects around him; let him behold the dazzling light set like an eternal lamp to light up the universe, let him see the earth as a mere speck compared to the vast orbit described by this star, and let him marvel at finding this vast orbit itself to be no more than the tiniest point compared to that described by the stars revolving in the firmament. But if our eyes stop there, let our imagination proceed further; it will grow weary of conceiving things before nature tires of producing them. The whole visible world is only an imperceptible dot in nature's ample bosom. No idea comes near it; it is no good inflating our conceptions beyond imaginable space, we only bring forth atoms compared to the reality of things. Nature is an infinite sphere whose centre is everywhere and circumference nowhere. In short it is the greatest perceptible mark of God's omnipotence that our imagination should lose itself in that thought.

Let man, returning to himself, consider what he is in comparison with what exists; let him regard himself as lost, and from this little dungeon, in which he finds himself lodged, I mean the universe, let him learn to take the earth, its realms, its cities, its houses and himself at their proper value.

What is a man in the infinite?

But, to offer him another prodigy equally astounding, let him look into the tiniest things he knows. Let a mite show him in its minute body incomparably more minute parts, legs with joints, veins in its legs, blood in the veins, humours in the blood, drops in the humours, vapours in the drops: let him divide these things still further until he has exhausted his powers of imagination, and let the last thing he comes down to now be the subject of our discourse. He will perhaps think that this is the ultimate of minuteness in nature.

I want to show him a new abyss. I want to depict to him not only the visible universe, but all the conceivable immensity of nature enclosed in this miniature atom. Let him see there an infinity of universes, each with its firmament, its planets, its earth, in the same proportions as in the visible world, and on that earth animals, and finally mites, in which he will find again the same results as in the first; and finding the same thing yet again in the others without end or respite, he will be lost in such wonders, as astounding in their minuteness as the others in their amplitude. For who will not marvel that our body, a moment ago imperceptible in a universe, itself imperceptible in the bosom of the whole, should now be a colossus, a world, or rather a whole, compared to the nothingness beyond our reach? Anyone who considers himself in this way will be terrified at himself, and, seeing his mass, as given him by nature, supporting him between these two abysses of infinity and nothingness, will tremble at these marvels. I believe that with his curiosity changing into wonder he will be more disposed to contemplate them in silence than investigate them with presumption.

For, after all, what is man in nature? A nothing compared to the infinite, a whole compared to the nothing, a middle point between all and nothing, infinitely remote from an understanding of the extremes; the end of things and their principles are unattainably hidden from him in impenetrable secrecy.

Equally incapable of seeing the nothingness from which he emerges and the infinity in which he is engulfed.

What else can he do, then, but perceive some semblance of the middle of things, eternally hopeless of knowing either their principles or their end? All things have come out of nothingness and are carried onwards to infinity. Who can follow these astonishing processes? The author of these wonders understands them: no one else can.

Because they failed to contemplate these infinities, men have rashly undertaken to probe into nature as if there were some proportion between themselves and her.

Strangely enough they wanted to know the principles of things and go on from there to know everything, inspired by a presumption as infinite as their object. For there can be no doubt that such a plan could not be conceived without infinite presumption or a capacity as infinite as that of nature.

When we know better, we understand that, since nature has engraved her own image and that of her author on all things, they almost all share her double infinity. Thus we see that all the sciences are infinite in the range of their researches, for who can doubt that mathematics, for instance, has an infinity of infinities of propositions to expound? They are infinite also in the multiplicity and subtlety of their principles, for anyone can see that those which are supposed to be ultimate do not stand by themselves, but depend on others, which depend on others again, and thus never allow of any finality.

But we treat as ultimate those which seem so to our reason, as in material things we call a point indivisible when our senses can perceive nothing beyond it, although by its nature it is infinitely divisible.

Of these two infinites of science, that of greatness is much more obvious, and that is why it has occurred to few people to claim that they know everything. 'I am going to speak about everything,' Democritus used to say.

But the infinitely small is much harder to see. The philosophers have much more readily claimed to have reached it, and that is where they have all tripped up. This is the origin of such familiar titles as Of the principles of things, Of the principles of philosophy, and the like, which are really as pretentious, though they do not look it, as this blatant one: Of all that can be known.

We naturally believe we are more capable of reaching the centre of things than of embracing their circumference, and the visible extent of the world is visibly greater than we. But since we in our turn are greater than small things, we think we are more capable of mastering them, and yet it takes no less capacity to reach nothingness than the whole. In either case it takes an infinite capacity, and it seems to me that anyone who had understood the ultimate principles of things might also succeed in knowing infinity. One depends on the other, and one leads to the other. These extremes touch and join by going in opposite directions, and they meet in God and God alone.

Let us then realize our limitations. We are something and we are not everything. Such being as we have conceals from us the knowledge of first principles, which arise from nothingness, and the smallness of our being hides infinity from our sight.

Our intelligence occupies the same rank in the order of intellect as our body in the whole range of nature.

Limited in every respect, we find this intermediate state between two extremes reflected in all our faculties. Our senses can perceive nothing extreme; too much noise deafens us, too much light dazzles; when we are too far or too close we cannot see properly; an argument is obscured by being too long or too short; too much truth bewilders us. I know people who cannot understand that 4 from o leaves o. First principles are too obvious for us; too much pleasure causes discomfort; too much harmony in music is displeasing; too much kindness annoys us: we want to be able to pay back the debt with something over. Kindness is welcome to the extent that it seems the debt can be paid back. When it goes too far gratitude turns into hatred.

We feel neither extreme heat nor extreme cold. Qualities carried to excess are bad for us and cannot be perceived; we no longer feel them, we suffer them. Excessive youth and excessive age impair thought; so do too much and too little learning.

In a word, extremes are as if they did not exist for us nor we for them; they escape us or we escape them.

Such is our true state. That is what makes us incapable of certain knowledge or absolute ignorance. We are floating in a medium of vast extent, always drifting uncertainly, blown to and fro; whenever we think we have a fixed point to which we can cling and make fast, it shifts and leaves us behind; if we follow it, it eludes our grasp, slips away, and flees eternally before us. Nothing stands still for us. This is our natural state and yet the state most contrary to our inclinations. We burn with desire to find a firm footing, an ultimate, lasting base on which to build a tower rising up to infinity, but our whole foundation cracks and the earth opens up into the depth of the abyss.

Let us then seek neither assurance nor stability; our reason is always deceived by the inconsistency of appearances; nothing can fix the finite between the two infinites which enclose and evade it.

Once that is clearly understood, I think that each of us can stay quietly in the state in which nature has placed him. Since the middle station allotted to us is always far from the extremes, what does it matter if someone else has a slightly better understanding of things? If he has, and if he takes them a little further, is he not still infinitely remote from the goal? Is not our span of life equally infinitesimal in eternity, even if it is extended by ten years?

In the perspective of these infinites, all finites are equal and I see no reason to settle our imagination on one rather than another. Merely comparing ourselves with the finite is painful.

If man studied himself, he would see how incapable he is of going further. How could a part possibly know the whole? But perhaps he will aspire to know at least the parts to which he bears some proportion. But the parts of the world are all so related and linked together that I think it is impossible to know one without the other and without the whole.

There is, for example, a relationship between man and all he knows. He needs space to contain him, time to exist in, motion to be alive, elements to constitute him, warmth and food for nourishment, air to breathe. He sees light, he feels bodies, everything in short is related to him. To understand man therefore one must know why he needs air to live, and to understand air one must know how it comes to be thus related to the life of man, etc.

Flame cannot exist without air, so, to know one, one must know the other.

Thus, since all things are both caused or causing, assisted and assisting, mediate and immediate, providing mutual support in a chain linking together naturally and imperceptibly the most distant and different things, I consider it as impossible to know the parts without knowing the whole as to know the whole without knowing the individual parts.

The eternity of things in themselves or in God must still amaze our brief span of life.

The fixed and constant immobility of nature, compared to the continual changes going on in us, must produce the same effect.

And what makes our inability to know things absolute is that they are simple in themselves, while we are composed of two opposing natures of different kinds, soul and body. For it is impossible for the part of us which reasons to be anything but spiritual, and even if it were claimed that we are simply corporeal, that would still more preclude us from knowing things, since there is nothing so inconceivable as the idea that matter knows itself. We cannot possibly know how it could know itself.

Thus, if we are simply material, we can know nothing at all, and, if we are composed of mind and matter, we cannot have perfect knowledge of things which are simply spiritual or corporeal.

That is why nearly all philosophers confuse their ideas of things, and speak spiritually of corporeal things and corporeally of spiritual ones, for they boldly assert that bodies tend to fall, that they aspire towards their centre, that they flee from destruction, that they fear a void, that they have inclinations, sympathies, antipathies, all things pertaining only to things spiritual. And when they speak of minds, they consider them as being in a place, and attribute to them movement from one place to another, which are things pertaining only to bodies.

Instead of receiving ideas of these things in their purity, we colour them with our qualities and stamp our own composite being on all the simple things we contemplate.

Who would not think, to see us compounding everything of mind and matter, that such a mixture is perfectly intelligible to us? Yet this is the thing we understand least; man is to himself the greatest prodigy in nature, for he cannot conceive what body is, and still less what mind is, and least of all how a body can be joined to a mind. This is his supreme difficulty, and yet it is his very being. The way in which minds are attached to bodies is beyond man's understanding, and yet this is what man is.

Finally to complete the proof of our weakness, I shall end with these two considerations ...

200 Man is only a reed, the weakest in nature, but he is a thinking reed. There is no need for the whole universe to take up arms to crush him: a vapour, a drop of water is enough to kill him. But even if the universe were to crush him, man would still be nobler than his slayer, because he knows that he is dying and the advantage the universe has over him. The universe knows none of this.

Thus all our dignity consists in thought. It is on thought that we must depend for our recovery, not on space and time, which we could never fill. Let us then strive to think well; that is the basic principle of morality.

201 The eternal silence of these infinite spaces fills me with dread.

202 Be comforted; it is not from yourself that you must expect it, but on the contrary you must expect it by expecting nothing from yourself.

271 All Jesus did was to teach men that they loved themselves, that they were slaves, blind, sick, unhappy and sinful, that he had to deliver, enlighten, sanctify and heal them, that this would be achieved by men hating themselves and following him through his misery and death on the Cross.

273 Those who find it hard to believe seek an excuse in the fact that the Jews do not believe. 'If it is so clear,' they say, 'why do they not believe?' They would almost like them to believe so that they should not be deterred by the example of the Jews' refusal. But it is the very fact of their refusal that is the basis of our belief. We should be much less inclined to believe if they were on our side; we should then have a much better excuse.

It is a wonderful thing to have made the Jews so fond of prophecies and so hostile to their fulfilment.

281 Perpetuity. This religion consists in believing that man has fallen from a state of glory and communion with God into a state of gloom, penitence and estrangement from God, but that after this life we shall be restored by a promised Messiah, and it has always existed on earth.

All things have passed away, but this, through which all things are, has endured.

In the first age of the world men were led into all kinds of misdeeds, and yet there were holy men like Enoch, Lamech and others who patiently awaited the Christ promised since the world began. Noah saw men's wickedness at its height, and he had the merit to save the world in his person, through hoping in the Messiah, whom he prefigured. Abraham was surrounded by idolaters when God showed him the mystery of the Messiah whom he hailed from afar. In the time of Isaac and Jacob abomination spread over the whole earth but these holy men lived in their faith, and Jacob on his deathbed, as he was blessing his children, cried out in a rapture which made him interrupt his speech: 'I await the saviour whom thou hast promised, O Lord.'

The Egyptians were riddled with idolatry and magic, and even the people of God were carried away by their example. Yet Moses and others saw him they did not see, and worshipped as they looked to the eternal gifts he was preparing for them.

Next the Greeks and Latins set up false gods. The poets invented a hundred different theologies, the philosophers split up into a thousand different sects. And yet in the heart of Judaea there were always chosen men foretelling the coming of the Messiah who was known only to them. He came at last in the fullness of time, and since then we have seen so many schisms and heresies arise, so many states overthrown, so many changes of every kind, while the Church which worships him who has always been has continued without a break. What is wonderful, incomparable and wholly divine is that this religion which has always survived has always been under attack. Times without number it has been on the verge of total destruction, and every time it has been in such a state God has rescued it by extraordinary manifestations of his power. For what is amazing is that it has continued without bending and bowing to the will of tyrants, for there is nothing strange in a state still surviving when its laws are sometimes made to give way to necessity, but that ... (See the circle in Montaigne.)

284 The only religion which is against nature, against common sense and against our pleasures is the only one which has always existed.

308 The infinite distance between body and mind symbolizes the infinitely more infinite distance between mind and charity, for charity is supernatural.

All the splendour of greatness lacks lustre for those engaged in pursuits of the mind.

The greatness of intellectual people is not visible to kings, rich men, captains, who are all great in a carnal sense.

The greatness of wisdom, which is nothing if it does not come from God, is not visible to carnal or intellectual people. They are three orders differing in kind.

Great geniuses have their power, their splendour, their greatness, their victory and their lustre, and do not need carnal greatness, which has no relevance for them. They are recognized not with the eyes but with the mind, and that is enough.

Saints have their power, their splendour, their victory, their lustre, and do not need either carnal or intellectual greatness, which has no relevance for them, for it neither adds nor takes away anything. They are recognized by God and the angels, and not by bodies or by curious minds. God is enough for them.

Archimedes in obscurity would still be revered. He fought no battles visible to the eyes, but enriched every mind with his discoveries. How splendidly he shone in the minds of men!

Jesus without wealth or any outward show of knowledge has his own order of holiness. He made no discoveries; he did not reign, but he was humble, patient, thrice holy to God, terrible to devils, and without sin. With what great pomp and marvellously magnificent array he came in the eyes of the heart, which perceive wisdom!

It would have been pointless for Archimedes to play the prince in his mathematical books, prince though he was.

It would have been pointless for Our Lord Jesus Christ to come as a king with splendour in his reign of holiness, but he truly came in splendour in his own order.

It is quite absurd to be shocked at the lowliness of Jesus, as if his lowliness was of the same order as the greatness he came to reveal.

If we consider his greatness in his life, his passion, his obscurity, his death, in the way he chose his disciples, in their desertion, in his secret resurrection and all the rest, we shall see that it is so great that we have no reason to be shocked at a lowliness which has nothing to do with it.

But there are some who are only capable of admiring carnal greatness, as if there were no such thing as greatness of the mind. And others who only admire greatness of the mind, as if there were not infinitely higher greatness in wisdom.

All bodies, the firmament, the stars, the earth and its kingdoms are not worth the least of minds, for it knows them all and itself too, while bodies know nothing.

All bodies together and all minds together and all their products are not worth the least impulse of charity. This is of an infinitely superior order.

Out of all bodies together we could not succeed in creating one little thought. It is impossible, and of a different order. Out of all bodies and minds we could not extract one impulse of true charity. It is impossible, and of a different, supernatural, order.

310 Proofs of Jesus Christ. The hypothesis that the Apostles were knaves is quite absurd. Follow it out to the end and imagine these twelve men meeting after Jesus's death and conspiring to say that he had risen from the dead. This means attacking all the powers that be. The human heart is singularly susceptible to fickleness, to change, to promises, to bribery. One of them had only to deny his story under these inducements, or still more because of possible imprisonment, tortures and death, and they would all have been lost. Follow that out.

332 Prophecies. If a single man had written a book foretelling the time and manner of Jesus's coming and Jesus had come in conformity with these prophecies, this would carry infinite weight.

But there is much more here. There is a succession of men over a period of 4,000 years, coming consistently and invariably one after the other, to foretell the same coming; there is an entire people proclaiming it, existing for 4,000 years to testify in a body to the certainty they feel about it, from which they cannot be deflected by whatever threats and persecutions they may suffer. This is of a quite different order of importance.

335 The most weighty proofs of Jesus are the prophecies. It is for them that God made most provision, for the event which fulfilled them is a miracle, continuing from the birth of the Church to the end. Thus God raised up prophets for 1,600 years and for 400 years afterwards dispersed all the prophecies with all the Jews, who carried them into every corner of the world. Such was the preparation for the birth of Christ, and, since his Gospel had to be believed by the whole world, there not only had to be prophecies to make men believe it, but these prophecies had to be spread throughout the world so that the whole world should embrace it.

351 Christianity is strange; it bids man to recognize that he is vile, and even abominable, and bids him want to be like God. Without such a counterweight his exaltation would make him horribly vain or his abasement horribly abject.

352 Wretchedness induces despair.

Pride induces presumption.

The Incarnation shows man the greatness of his wretchedness through the greatness of the remedy required.

356 What difference is there between a soldier and a Carthusian as regards obedience? For they are equally obedient and dependent and engaged in equally arduous exercises. But the soldier always hopes to become his own master, and never does, for even captains and princes are always slaves and dependent, but he always hopes, and always strives to achieve his object, whereas the Carthusian vows never to be anything but dependent. Thus they do not differ in their perpetual servitude, which is always their common lot, but in the hope that one always and the other never entertains.

373 We must love God alone and hate ourselves alone.

If the foot had never known it belonged to the body, and that there was a body on which it depended, if it had only known and loved itself, and if it then came to know that it belonged to a body on which it depended, what regret, what shame it would feel for its past life, for having been useless to the body which poured life into it, and would have annihilated it if it had rejected and cut it off as the foot cut itself off from the body! How it would pray to be kept on! How submissively it would let itself be governed by the will in charge of the body, to the point of being amputated if necessary! Otherwise it would cease to be a member, for every member must be willing to perish for the sake of the body, for whose sake alone everything exists.

378 'If I had seen a miracle,' they say, 'I should be converted.' How can they be positive that they would do what they know nothing about? They imagine that such a conversion consists in a worship of God conducted, as they picture it, like some exchange or conversation. True conversion consists in self-annihilation before the universal being whom we have so often vexed and who is perfectly entitled to destroy us at any moment, in recognizing that we can do nothing without him and that we have deserved nothing but his disfavour. It consists in knowing that there is an irreconcilable opposition between God and us, and that without a mediator there can be no exchange.

392 Figures. God wishing to create for himself a holy people, whom he would keep apart from all other nations, whom he would deliver from their enemies, whom he would bring to a place of rest, promised to do so and foretold by his prophets the time and manner of his coming. And yet to strengthen the hope of his chosen people in every age he showed them an image of all this, never leaving them without assurances of his power and will for their salvation, for in the creation of man Adam was witness to this and received the promise of a saviour who should be born of woman.

When men were still so close to Creation that they had not been able to forget their creation and their fall; when those who had seen Adam were no longer in this world, God sent Noah, saving him and drowning the whole earth by a miracle which clearly showed his power to save the world, and his will to do so, and to cause to be born from the seed of woman the one he had promised.

This miracle was sufficient to strengthen the hope of the elect.

The memory of the Flood being still so fresh among men, while Noah was still alive, God made his promises to Abraham, and while Shem was still alive, God sent Moses ...

403 Wretchedness. Solomon and Job have known and spoken best about man's wretchedness, one the happiest, the other the unhappiest of men; one knowing by experience the vanity of pleasure, and the other the reality of afflictions.

412 Men are so inevitably mad that not to be mad would be to give a mad twist to madness.

414 Wretchedness. The only thing that consoles us for our miseries is diversion. And yet it is the greatest of our miseries. For it is that above all which prevents us thinking about ourselves and leads us imperceptibly to destruction. But for that we should be bored, and boredom would drive us to seek some more solid means of escape, but diversion passes our time and brings us imperceptibly to our death.

418 Infinity — nothing. [THE WAGER] Our soul is cast into the body where it finds number, time, dimensions; it reasons about these things and calls them natural, or necessary, and can believe nothing else.

Unity added to infinity does not increase it at all, any more than a foot added to an infinite measurement: the finite is annihilated in the presence of the infinite and becomes pure nothingness. So it is with our mind before God, with our justice before divine justice. There is not so great a disproportion between our justice and God's as between unity and infinity.

God's justice must be as vast as his mercy. Now his justice towards the damned is less vast and ought to be less startling to us than his mercy towards the elect.

We know that the infinite exists without knowing its nature, just as we know that it is untrue that numbers are finite. Thus it is true that there is an infinite number, but we do not know what it is. It is untrue that it is even, untrue that it is odd, for by adding a unit it does not change its nature. Yet it is a number, and every number is even or odd. (It is true that this applies to every finite number.)

Therefore we may well know that God exists without knowing what he is.

Is there no substantial truth, seeing that there are so many true things which are not truth itself?

Thus we know the existence and nature of the finite because we too are finite and extended in space.

We know the existence of the infinite without knowing its nature, because it too has extension but unlike us no limits.

But we do not know either the existence or the nature of God, because he has neither extension nor limits.

But by faith we know his existence, through glory we shall know his nature.

Now I have already proved that it is quite possible to know that something exists without knowing its nature.

Let us now speak according to our natural lights.

If there is a God, he is infinitely beyond our comprehension, since, being indivisible and without limits, he bears no relation to us. We are therefore incapable of knowing either what he is or whether he is. That being so, who would dare to attempt an answer to the question? Certainly not we, who bear no relation to him.

Who then will condemn Christians for being unable to give rational grounds for their belief, professing as they do a religion for which they cannot give rational grounds? They declare that it is a folly, stultitiam, in expounding it to the world, and then you complain that they do not prove it. If they did prove it they would not be keeping their word. It is by being without proof that they show they are not without sense. 'Yes, but although that excuses those who offer their religion as such, and absolves them from the criticism of producing it without rational grounds, it does not absolve those who accept it.' Let us then examine this point, and let us say: 'Either God is or he is not.' But to which view shall we be inclined? Reason cannot decide this question. Infinite chaos separates us. At the far end of this infinite distance a coin is being spun which will come down heads or tails. How will you wager? Reason cannot make you choose either, reason cannot prove either wrong.

Do not then condemn as wrong those who have made a choice, for you know nothing about it. 'No, but I will condemn them not for having made this particular choice, but any choice, for, although the one who calls heads and the other one are equally at fault, the fact is that they are both at fault: the right thing is not to wager at all.'

Yes, but you must wager. There is no choice, you are already committed. Which will you choose then? Let us see: since a choice must be made, let us see which offers you the least interest. You have two things to lose: the true and the good; and two things to stake: your reason and your will, your knowledge and your happiness; and your nature has two things to avoid: error and wretchedness. Since you must necessarily choose, your reason is no more affronted by choosing one rather than the other. That is one point cleared up. But your happiness? Let us weigh up the gain and the loss involved in calling heads that God exists. Let us assess the two cases: if you win you win everything, if you lose you lose nothing. Do not hesitate then; wager that he does exist. 'That is wonderful. Yes, I must wager, but perhaps I am wagering too much.' Let us see: since there is an equal chance of gain and loss, if you stood to win only two lives for one you could still wager, but supposing you stood to win three?

You would have to play (since you must necessarily play) and it would be unwise of you, once you are obliged to play, not to risk your life in order to win three lives at a game in which there is an equal chance of losing and winning. But there is an eternity of life and happiness. That being so, even though there were an infinite number of chances, of which only one were in your favour, you would still be right to wager one in order to win two; and you would be acting wrongly, being obliged to play, in refusing to stake one life against three in a game, where out of an infinite number of chances there is one in your favour, if there were an infinity of infinitely happy life to be won. But here there is an infinity of infinitely happy life to be won, one chance of winning against a finite number of chances of losing, and what you are staking is finite. That leaves no choice; wherever there is infinity, and where there are not infinite chances of losing against that of winning, there is no room for hesitation, you must give everything. And thus, since you are obliged to play, you must be renouncing reason if you hoard your life rather than risk it for an infinite gain, just as likely to occur as a loss amounting to nothing.

For it is no good saying that it is uncertain whether you will win, that it is certain that you are taking a risk, and that the infinite distance between the certainty of what you are risking and the uncertainty of what you may gain makes the finite good you are certainly risking equal to the infinite good that you are not certain to gain. This is not the case. Every gambler takes a certain risk for an uncertain gain, and yet he is taking a certain finite risk for an uncertain finite gain without sinning against reason. Here there is no infinite distance between the certain risk and the uncertain gain: that is not true. There is, indeed, an infinite distance between the certainty of winning and the certainty of losing, but the proportion between the uncertainty of winning and the certainty of what is being risked is in proportion to the chances of winning or losing. And hence if there are as many chances on one side as on the other you are playing for even odds. And in that case the certainty of what you are risking is equal to the uncertainty of what you may win; it is by no means infinitely distant from it. Thus our argument carries infinite weight, when the stakes are finite in a game where there are even chances of winning and losing and an infinite prize to be won.

This is conclusive and if men are capable of any truth this is it.

'I confess, I admit it, but is there really no way of seeing what the cards are?' — 'Yes. Scripture and the rest, etc.' — 'Yes, but my hands are tied and my lips are sealed; I am being forced to wager and I am not free; I am being held fast and I am so made that I cannot believe. What do you want me to do then?' — 'That is true, but at least get it into your head that, if you are unable to believe, it is because of your passions, since reason impels you to believe and yet you cannot do so. Concentrate then not on convincing yourself by multiplying proofs of God's existence but by diminishing your passions. You want to find faith and you do not know the road. You want to be cured of unbelief and you ask for the remedy: learn from those who were once bound like you and who now wager all they have. These are people who know the road you wish to follow, who have been cured of the affliction of which you wish to be cured: follow the way by which they began. They behaved just as if they did believe, taking holy water, having masses said, and so on. That will make you believe quite naturally, and will make you more docile.' — 'But that is what I am afraid of.' — 'But why? What have you to lose? But to show you that this is the way, the fact is that this diminishes the passions which are your great obstacles ...'

'Now what harm will come to you from choosing this course? You will be faithful, honest, humble, grateful, full of good works, a sincere, true friend ... It is true you will not enjoy noxious pleasures, glory and good living, but will you not have others?

'I tell you that you will gain even in this life, and that at every step you take along this road you will see that your gain is so certain and your risk so negligible that in the end you will realize that you have wagered on something certain and infinite for which you have paid nothing.'

'How these words fill me with rapture and delight! —'

'If my words please you and seem cogent, you must know that they come from a man who went down upon his knees before and after to pray this infinite and indivisible being, to whom he submits his own, that he might bring your being also to submit to him for your own good and for his glory: and that strength might thus be reconciled with lowliness.'

427 [AGAINST INDIFFERENCE] Let them at least learn what this religion is which they are attacking before attacking it. If this religion boasted that it had a clear sight of God and plain and manifest evidence of his existence, it would be an effective objection to say that there is nothing to be seen in the world which proves him so obviously. But since on the contrary it says that men are in darkness and remote from God, that he has hidden himself from their understanding, that this is the very name which he gives himself in Scripture: Deus absconditus [the hidden God]; and, in a word, if it strives equally to establish these two facts: that God has appointed visible signs in the Church so that he shall be recognized by those who genuinely seek him, and that he has none the less hidden them in such a way that he will only be perceived by those who seek him with all their heart, then what advantage can they derive when, unconcerned to seek the truth as they profess to be, they protest that nothing shows it to them? For the obscurity in which they find themselves, and which they use as an objection against the Church, simply establishes one of the things the Church maintains without affecting the other, and far from proving her teaching false, confirms it.

In order really to attack the truth they would have to protest that they had made every effort to seek it everywhere, even in what the Church offers by way of instruction, but without any satisfaction. If they talked like that they would indeed be attacking one of Christianity's claims. But I hope to show here that no reasonable person could talk like that. I even venture to say that no one has ever done so. We know well enough how people in this frame of mind behave. They think they have made great efforts to learn when they have spent a few hours reading some book of the Bible, and have questioned some ecclesiastic about the truths of the faith. After that they boast that they have sought without success in books and among men. But, in fact, I should say to them what I have often said: such negligence is intolerable. It is not a question here of the trifling interest of some stranger prompting such behaviour: it is a question of ourselves, and our all.

The immortality of the soul is something of such vital importance to us, affecting us so deeply, that one must have lost all feeling not to care about knowing the facts of the matter. All our actions and thoughts must follow such different paths, according to whether there is hope of eternal blessings or not, that the only possible way of acting with sense and judgement is to decide our course in the light of this point, which ought to be our ultimate objective.

Thus our chief interest and chief duty is to seek enlightenment on this subject, on which all our conduct depends. And that is why, amongst those who are not convinced, I make an absolute distinction between those who strive with all their might to learn and those who live without troubling themselves or thinking about it.

I can feel nothing but compassion for those who sincerely lament their doubt, who regard it as the ultimate misfortune, and who, sparing no effort to escape from it, make their search their principal and most serious business.

But as for those who spend their lives without a thought for this final end of life and who, solely because they do not find within themselves the light of conviction, neglect to look elsewhere, and to examine thoroughly whether this opinion is one of those which people accept out of credulous simplicity or one of those which, though obscure in themselves, none the less have a most solid and unshakeable foundation: as for them, I view them very differently.

This negligence in a matter where they themselves, their eternity, their all are at stake, fills me more with irritation than pity; it astounds and appals me; it seems quite monstrous to me. I do not say this prompted by the pious zeal of spiritual devotion. I mean on the contrary that we ought to have this feeling from principles of human interest and self-esteem. For that we need only see what the least enlightened see.

One needs no great sublimity of soul to realize that in this life there is no true and solid satisfaction, that all our pleasures are mere vanity, that our afflictions are infinite, and finally that death which threatens us at every moment must in a few years infallibly face us with the inescapable and appalling alternative of being annihilated or wretched throughout eternity.

Nothing could be more real, or more dreadful than that. Let us put on as bold a face as we like: that is the end awaiting the world's most illustrious life. Let us ponder these things, and then say whether it is not beyond doubt that the only good thing in this life is the hope of another life, that we become happy only as we come nearer to it, and that, just as no more unhappiness awaits those who have been quite certain of eternity, so there is no happiness for those who have no inkling of it.

It is therefore quite certainly a great evil to have such doubts, but it is at least an indispensable obligation to seek when one does thus doubt; so the doubter who does not seek is at the same time very unhappy and very wrong. If in addition he feels a calm satisfaction, which he openly professes, and even regards as a reason for joy and vanity, I can find no terms to describe so extravagant a creature.

What can give rise to such feelings? What reason for joy can be found in the expectation of nothing but helpless wretchedness? What reason for vanity in being plunged into impenetrable darkness? And how can such an argument as this occur to a reasonable man?

'I do not know who put me into the world, nor what the world is, nor what I am myself. I am terribly ignorant about everything. I do not know what my body is, or my senses, or my soul, or even that part of me which thinks what I am saying, which reflects about everything and about itself, and does not know itself any better than it knows anything else.

'I see the terrifying spaces of the universe hemming me in, and I find myself attached to one corner of this vast expanse without knowing why I have been put in this place rather than that, or why the brief span of life allotted to me should be assigned to one moment rather than another of all the eternity which went before me and all that which will come after me. I see only infinity on every side, hemming me in like an atom or like the shadow of a fleeting instant. All I know is that I must soon die, but what I know least about is this very death which I cannot evade.

'Just as I do not know whence I come, so I do not know whither I am going. All I know is that when I leave this world I shall fall for ever into nothingness or into the hands of a wrathful God, but I do not know which of these two states is to be my eternal lot. Such is my state, full of weakness and uncertainty. And my conclusion from all this is that I must pass my days without a thought of seeking what is to happen to me. Perhaps I might find some enlightenment in my doubts, but I do not want to take the trouble, nor take a step to look for it: and afterwards, as I sneer at those who are striving to this end － (whatever certainty they have should arouse despair rather than vanity) － I will go without fear or foresight to face so momentous an event, and allow myself to be carried off limply to my death, uncertain of my future state for all eternity.'

Who would wish to have as his friend a man who argued like that? Who would choose him from among others as a confidant in his affairs? Who would resort to him in adversity? To what use in life could he possibly be turned?

It is truly glorious for religion to have such unreasonable men as enemies: their opposition represents so small a danger that it serves on the contrary to establish the truths of religion. For the Christian faith consists almost wholly in establishing these two things: The corruption of nature and the redemption of Christ. Now, I maintain that, if they do not serve to prove the truth of the redemption by the sanctity of their conduct, they do at least admirably serve to prove the corruption of nature by such unnatural sentiments.

Nothing is so important to man as his state: nothing more fearful than eternity. Thus the fact that there exist men who are indifferent to the loss of their being and the peril of an eternity of wretchedness is against nature. With everything else they are quite different; they fear the most trifling things, foresee and feel them; and the same man who spends so many days and nights in fury and despair at losing some office or at some imaginary affront to his honour is the very one who knows that he is going to lose everything through death but feels neither anxiety nor emotion. It is a monstrous thing to see one and the same heart at once so sensitive to minor things and so strangely insensitive to the greatest. It is an incomprehensible spell, a supernatural torpor that points to an omnipotent power as its cause.

Man's nature must have undergone a strange reversal for him to glory in being in a state in which it seems incredible that any single person should be. Yet experience has shown me so many like this that it would be surprising if we did not know that most of those concerned in this are pretending and are not really what they seem. They are people who have heard that it is good form to display such extravagance. This is what they call shaking off the yoke, and what they are trying to imitate. But it would not be difficult to show them how mistaken they are to court esteem in this way. That is not how to acquire it, not even, I would say, among worldly people, who judge things sensibly and who know that the only way to succeed is to appear honest, faithful, judicious and capable of rendering useful service to one's friends, because by nature men only like what may be of use to them. Now what advantage is it to us to hear someone say he has shaken off the yoke, that he does not believe that there is a God watching over his actions, that he considers himself sole master of his behaviour, and that he proposes to account for it to no one but himself? Does he think that by so doing he has henceforth won our full confidence, and made us expect from him consolation, counsel and assistance in all life's needs? Do they think that they have given us great pleasure by telling us that they hold our soul to be no more than wind or smoke, and saying it moreover in tones of pride and satisfaction? Is this then something to be said gaily? Is it not on the contrary something to be said sadly, as being the saddest thing in the world?

If they thought seriously, they would see that this is so misguided, so contrary to good sense, so opposed to decency, so remote in every way from the good form they seek, that they would be more likely to reform than corrupt those who might feel inclined to follow them. And, indeed, make them describe the feeling and reasons which inspire their doubts about religion: what they say will be so feeble and cheap as to persuade you of the contrary. As someone said to them very aptly one day: 'If you go on arguing like that,' he said, 'you really will convert me.' And he was right, for who would not shrink from finding himself sharing the feelings of such contemptible people?

Thus those who only pretend to feel like this would be indeed unhappy if they did violence to their nature in order to become the most impertinent of men. If they are vexed in their inmost heart at not seeing more clearly, they should not try to pretend otherwise: it would be no shame to admit it. There is no shame except in having none. There is no surer sign of extreme weakness of mind than the failure to recognize the unhappy state of a man without God; there is no surer sign of an evil heart than failure to desire that the eternal promises be true; nothing is more cowardly than to brazen it out with God. Let them then leave such impiety to those ill-bred enough to be really capable of it; let them at least be decent people if they cannot be Christians; let them, in short, acknowledge that there are only two classes of persons who can be called reasonable: those who serve God with all their heart because they know him and those who seek him with all their heart because they do not know him.

As for those who live without either knowing or seeking him, they consider it so little worthwhile to take trouble over themselves that they are not worth other people's trouble, and it takes all the charity of that religion they despise not to despise them to the point of abandoning them to their folly. But as this religion obliges us always to regard them, as long as they live, as being capable of receiving grace which may enlighten them, and to believe that in a short time they may be filled with more faith than we are, while we on the contrary may be stricken by the same blindness which is theirs now, we must do for them what we would wish to be done for us in their place, and appeal to them to have pity on themselves, and to take at least a few steps in an attempt to find some light. Let them spend on reading about it a few of the hours they waste on other things: however reluctantly they may approach the task they will perhaps hit upon something, and at least they will not be losing much. But as for those who approach it with absolute sincerity and a real desire to find the truth, I hope that they will be satisfied, and convinced by the proofs of so divine a religion which I have collected here, following more or less this order ...

429 This is what I see and what troubles me. I look around in every direction and all I see is darkness. Nature has nothing to offer me that does not give rise to doubt and anxiety. If I saw no sign there of a Divinity I should decide on a negative solution: if I saw signs of a Creator everywhere I should peacefully settle down in the faith. But, seeing too much to deny and not enough to affirm, I am in a pitiful state, where I have wished a hundred times over that, if there is a God supporting nature, she should unequivocally proclaim him, and that, if the signs in nature are deceptive, they should be completely erased; that nature should say all or nothing so that I could see what course I ought to follow. Instead of that, in the state in which I am, not knowing what I am nor what I ought to do, I know neither my condition nor my duty. My whole heart strains to know what the true good is in order to pursue it: no price would be too high to pay for eternity.

I envy those of the faithful whom I see living so unconcernedly, making so little use of a gift which, it seems to me, I should turn to such different account.

430 No other has realized that man is the most excellent of creatures. Some, fully realizing how real his excellence is, have taken for cowardice and ingratitude men's natural feelings of abasement; while others, fully realizing how real this abasement is, have treated with haughty ridicule the feelings of greatness which are just as natural to man.

'Lift up your eyes to God,' say some of them, 'look at him whom you resemble and who created you to worship him. You can make yourself like him: wisdom will make you his equal, if you want to follow him.' — 'Hold your heads high, free men,' said Epictetus. And others say, 'Cast down your eyes towards the ground, puny worm that you are, and look at the beasts whose companion you are.'

What then is to become of man? Will he be the equal of God or the beasts? What a terrifying distance! What then shall he be? Who cannot see from all this that man is lost, that he has fallen from his place, that he anxiously seeks it, and cannot find it again? And who then is to direct him there? The greatest men have failed.

434 Imagine a number of men in chains, all under sentence of death, some of whom are each day butchered in the sight of the others; those remaining see their own condition in that of their fellows, and looking at each other with grief and despair await their turn. This is an image of the human condition.

450 The true religion would have to teach greatness and wretchedness, inspire self-esteem and self-contempt, love and hate.

470 The vilest feature of man is the quest for glory, but it is just this that most clearly shows his excellence. For whatever possession he may own on earth, whatever health or essential amenity he may enjoy, he is dissatisfied unless he enjoys the good opinion of his fellows. He so highly values human reason that, however privileged he may be on earth, if he does not also enjoy a privileged position in human reason he is not happy. This is the finest position on earth, nothing can deflect him from this desire, and this is the most indelible quality in the human heart.

And those who most despise men, and put them on the same level as the beasts, still want to be admired and trusted by them, and contradict themselves by their own feelings, for their nature, which is stronger than anything, convinces them more strongly of man's greatness than reason convinces them of their vileness.

474 When the creation of the world began to recede into the past, God provided a single contemporary historian, and charged an entire people with the custody of this book, so that this should be the most authentic history in the world and all men could learn from it something which it was so necessary for them to know and which could only be known from it.

477 Pride is a counterweight and antidote for all forms of wretchedness. Here is a strange monster, and a very palpable aberration. Here he is, fallen from his place, looking anxiously for it. That is what all men do. Let us see who has found it.

480 In all religions sincerity is essential: true heathens, true Jews, true Christians.

499 What man ever had greater glory?

The entire Jewish people foretells him before his coming. The Gentiles worship him after his coming.

Both the Gentile and Jewish peoples regard him as their centre.

And yet what man ever enjoyed such glory less?

For thirty of his thirty-three years he lives without showing himself. For three years he is treated as an impostor. The priests and rulers reject him. Those who are nearest and dearest to him despise him, finally he dies betrayed by one of his disciples, denied by another and forsaken by all.

What benefit then did he derive from such glory? No man ever had such great glory, no man ever suffered greater ignominy. All this glory has only been of use to us, to enable us to recognize him, and he had none of it for himself.

505 Authority. Hearsay is so far from being a criterion of belief that you should not believe anything until you have put yourself into the same state as if you had never heard it.

It is your own inner assent and the consistent voice of your reason rather than that of others which should make you believe.

Belief is so important.

A hundred contradictions might be true.

If antiquity was the criterion of belief, then the ancients had no criterion.

If general consent, if men had died ...?

Punishment of sinners: error.

False humility, pride.

Raise the curtain.

You are wasting your time, one must either believe, deny or doubt.

Are we then to have no criterion?

When animals do something we can judge whether they are doing it well; is there to be no criterion for judging men?

Denying, believing and doubting are to men what running is to horses.

510 The more intelligent one is, the more men of originality one finds. Ordinary people find no difference between men.

511 Different kinds of right thinking, some in a particular order of things but not in others where they go quite astray.

Some draw correct conclusions from a small number of principles, and this is one kind of right thinking.

Others draw correct conclusions from things involving numerous principles.

For example, some have a good grasp of the properties of water, which involve few principles, but whose conclusions are so subtle that only an extremely accurate mind can reach them. These people might all the same not be great mathematicians, because mathematics comprises a large number of principles, and a mind may well be such that it can easily get right to the bottom of a few principles without being able to make the least advance in things involving many.

Thus there are two kinds of mind: one goes rapidly and deeply into the conclusions from principles, and this is the accurate mind. The other can grasp a large number of principles and keep them distinct, and this is the mathematical mind. The first is a powerful and precise mind, the second shows breadth of mind. Now it is quite possible to have one without the other, for a mind can be powerful and narrow, as well as broad and weak.

513 Mathematics. Intuition. True eloquence has no time for eloquence, true morality has no time for morality. In other words the morality of judgement has no time for the random morality of mind.

For judgement is what goes with instinct, just as knowledge goes with mind. Intuition falls to the lot of judgement, mathematics to that of the mind.

To have no time for philosophy is to be a true philosopher.

517 If St Augustine were to appear today and enjoy as little authority as his modern defenders he would not accomplish anything. God has ruled his Church well by sending him earlier, and endowed with authority.

518 Scepticism. — Extreme intelligence is accused of being as foolish as extreme lack of it; only moderation is good. The majority have laid this down and attack anyone who deviates from it towards any extreme whatever. I am not going to be awkward, I readily consent to being put in the middle and refuse to be at the bottom end, not because it is bottom but because it is the end, for I should refuse just as much to be put at the top. It is deserting humanity to desert the middle way.

The greatness of the human soul lies in knowing how to keep this course; greatness does not mean going outside it, but rather keeping within it.

526 Evil is easy; it has countless forms, while good is almost unique. But a certain sort of evil is as hard to find as what is called good, and this particular evil is often on that account passed off as good. Indeed it takes as much extraordinary greatness of soul to attain such evil, as to attain good.

532 Scepticism. I will write down my thoughts here as they come and in a perhaps not aimless confusion. This is the true order and it will always show my aim by its very disorder.

I should be honouring my subject too much if I treated it in order, since I am trying to show that it is incapable of it.

533 We always picture Plato and Aristotle wearing long academic gowns, but they were ordinary decent people like anyone else, who enjoyed a laugh with their friends. And when they amused themselves by composing their Laws and Politics they did it for fun. It was the least philosophical and least serious part of their lives: the most philosophical part was living simply and without fuss.

If they wrote about politics it was as if to lay down rules for a madhouse.

And if they pretended to treat it as something really important it was because they knew that the madmen they were talking to believed themselves to be kings and emperors. They humoured these beliefs in order to calm down their madness with as little harm as possible.

535 There are some vices which only keep hold on us through other ones, and if we take the trunk away they come off like the branches.

54o All the good maxims already exist in the world: we just fail to apply them.

For example, no one doubts that one should risk his life in defence of the common good, and many people do so, but not for religion.

Inequality must necessarily exist among men, it is true: but that once granted the door is open not only to the most absolute rule but to the most absolute tyranny.

It is necessary to relax the mind a little, but that opens the door to the greatest excesses.

Let us define the limits. There are no boundaries in things. Laws try to impose some, and the mind cannot bear it.

542 Thoughts come at random, and go at random. No device for holding on to them or for having them.

A thought has escaped: I was trying to write it down: instead I write that it has escaped me.

545 'All that is in the world is lust of the flesh, lust of the eyes or pride of life.' Libido sentiendi, libido sciendi, libido dominandi. Wretched is the cursed land consumed rather than watered by these three rivers of fire! Happy are those who are beside those rivers, neither immersed, nor carried away, but immovably steady beside these rivers, not standing but sitting, in a low and safe position. They will not rise thence before the light, but, after resting in peace, stretch out their hands to him who shall raise them to stand upright and steady in the porches of Jerusalem the blessed, where pride shall no more be able to fight against them and lay them low; and yet they weep, not at the sight of all the perishable things swept away by these torrents, but at the memory of their beloved home, the heavenly Jerusalem, which they constantly remember through the long years of their exile.

551 Imagination magnifies small objects with fantastic exaggeration until they fill our soul, and with bold insolence cuts down great things to its own size, as when speaking of God.

561 They say that eclipses are portents of disaster, because disasters are so common, and misfortune occurs often enough for these forecasts to be right, whereas if they said that eclipses were portents of good fortune they would often be wrong. They ascribe good fortune only to rare conjunctions of heavenly bodies and thus seldom guess wrong in their forecasts.

562 There are only two kinds of men: the righteous who think they are sinners and the sinners who think they are righteous.

577 If we must never take any chances we ought not to do anything for religion, for it is not certain. But how many chances we do take: sea voyages, battles. Therefore, I say, we should have to do nothing at all, for nothing is certain. And there is more certainty in religion than that we shall live to see tomorrow.

For it is not certain that we shall see tomorrow but it is certainly possible that we shall not. We cannot say the same of religion. It is not certain that it is true, but who would dare to say that it is certainly possible that it is not?

Now when we work for tomorrow and take chances we are behaving reasonably, for we ought to take chances, according to the rule of probability already demonstrated.

St Augustine saw that we take chances at sea, in battle, etc. — but he did not see the rule of probability which proves that we ought to. Montaigne saw that we are offended by a lame mind and that habit can do anything, but he did not see the reason for this.

All these people saw the effects but did not see the causes. In comparison with those who have discovered the causes they are like those who have only eyes compared to those who have minds. For the effects can, as it were, be felt by the senses but the causes can only be perceived by the mind. And, although these effects can be seen by the mind, this mind can be compared to that which sees the causes as the bodily senses may be compared to the mind.

585 There is a certain model of attractiveness and beauty consisting in a certain relation between our nature, weak or strong as it may be, and the thing which pleases us.

Everything that conforms to this model attracts us, be it a house, a song, a speech, verse, prose, a woman, birds, rivers, trees, rooms, clothes, etc.

Everything which does not conform to this model is displeasing to people of good taste.

And as there is an exact relation between a song and a house based on this good model, because both resemble a single model, though each in its own way, there is in the same way an exact relation between things based on bad models. It is not that there is only one bad model, because they are innumerable, but every bad sonnet, for example, whatever the false model it is based on, is exactly like a woman dressed according to that model.

Nothing gives a better idea of the absurdity of a bad sonnet than to consider its nature and its model and then to imagine a woman or a house conforming to that model.

595 Unless we know ourselves to be full of pride, ambition, concupiscence, weakness, wretchedness and unrighteousness, we are truly blind. And if someone knows all this and does not desire to be saved, what can be said of him?

How then can we have anything but respect for a religion which knows man's faults so well? What desire but that a religion which promises such desirable remedies should be true?

607 Figures. Saviour, father, sacrificer, sacrifice, food, king, wise, lawgiver, afflicted, poor, destined to produce a people whom he should lead and feed, and bring into the land.

620 Man is obviously made for thinking. Therein lies all his dignity and his merit; and his whole duty is to think as he ought. Now the order of thought is to begin with ourselves, and with our author and our end.

Now what does the world think about? Never about that, but about dancing, playing the lute, singing, writing verse, tilting at the ring, etc., and fighting, becoming king, without thinking what it means to be a king or to be a man.

622 Boredom. Man finds nothing so intolerable as to be in a state of complete rest, without passions, without occupation, without diversion, without effort.

Then he faces his nullity, loneliness, inadequacy, dependence, helplessness, emptiness.

And at once there wells up from the depths of his soul boredom, gloom, depression, chagrin, resentment, despair.

623 If it is unnatural blindness to live without trying to find out what one is, it is a fearful blindness to lead an evil life while believing in God.

627 Vanity is so firmly anchored in man's heart that a soldier, a camp follower, a cook or a porter will boast and expect admirers, and even philosophers want them; those who write against them want to enjoy the prestige of having written well, those who read them want the prestige of having read them, and perhaps I who write this want the same thing, perhaps my readers ...

631 It is good to be tired and weary from fruitlessly seeking the true good, so that one can stretch out one's arms to the Redeemer.

632 Man's sensitivity to little things and insensitivity to the greatest things are marks of a strange disorder.

633 Despite the sight of all the miseries which affect us and hold us by the throat we have an irrepressible instinct which bears us up.

634 The most important thing in our lives is the choice of a trade, and chance decides it.

Custom makes masons, soldiers, roofers. 'He is an excellent roofer,' they say, and, speaking of soldiers: 'They are quite mad,' while others on the contrary say: 'There is nothing as great as war, everyone else is worthless.' From hearing people praise these trades in our childhood and running down all the others we make our choice. For we naturally love virtue and hate folly; the very words will decide, we only go wrong in applying them.

So great is the force of custom that where naturehas merely created men, we create every kind and condition of men.

For some regions are full of masons, some of soldiers etc. There is no doubt that nature is not so uniform: it is custom then which does all this, for it coerces nature, but sometimes nature overcomes it and keeps man to his instincts despite all customs, good or bad.

638 When we are well we wonder how we should manage if we were ill. When we are ill we take our medicine cheerfully; our illness settles that problem for us. We no longer have the passions, and the desires for diversions and outings, which went with good health and are incompatible with the exigencies of our illness. Nature then inspires the passions and desires appropriate to our present state. It is only the fears that we owe to ourselves, and not to nature, which disturb us by linking the state in which we are with the passions of that in which we are not.

649 Montaigne. What is good in Montaigne can only be acquired with difficulty. What is bad in him, I mean apart from morals, could have been corrected in a moment if someone had warned him that he was making too much of things and talking too much about himself.

668 Each man is everything to himself, for with his death everything is dead for him. That is why each of us thinks he is everything to everyone. We must not judge nature by ourselves, but by its own standards.

674 We do not keep ourselves virtuous by our own power, but by the counterbalance of two opposing vices, just as we stay upright between two contrary winds. Take one of these vices away and we fall into the other.

685 Glory. Animals do not admire each other. A horse does not admire its companion. It is not that they will not race against each other, but this is of no consequence, for, back in the stable, the one who is heavier and clumsier does not on that account give up his oats to the other, as men want others to do to them. With them virtue is its own reward.

688 What is the self?

A man goes to the window to see the people passing by; if I pass by, can I say he went there to see me? No, for he is not thinking of me in particular. But what about a person who loves someone for the sake of her beauty; does he love her? No, for smallpox, which will destroy beauty without destroying the person, will put an end to his love for her.

And if someone loves me for my judgement or my memory, do they love me? me, myself ? No, for I could lose these qualities without losing my self. Where then is this self, if it is neither in the body nor the soul? And how can one love the body or the soul except for the sake of such qualities, which are not what makes up the self, since they are perishable? Would we love the substance of a person's soul, in the abstract, whatever qualities might be in it? That is not possible, and it would be wrong. Therefore we never love anyone, but only qualities.

Let us then stop scoffing at those who win honour through their appointments and offices, for we never love anyone except for borrowed qualities.

693 The easiest conditions to live in from the world's point of view are the hardest from that of God; and vice versa. Nothing is so hard from the world's point of view as the religious life, while nothing is easier from that of God. Nothing is easier than to enjoy high office or great wealth in a worldly way, nothing harder than to live such a life in God's way, without taking interest or pleasure in it.

696 Let no one say that I have said nothing new; the arrangement of the material is new. In playing tennis both players use the same ball, but one plays it better.

I would just as soon be told that I have used old words. As if the same thoughts did not form a different argument by being differently arranged, just as the same words make different thoughts when arranged differently!

697 Those who lead disorderly lives tell those who are normal that it is they who deviate from nature, and think they are following nature themselves; just as those who are on board ship think that the people on shore are moving away. Language is the same everywhere: we need a fixed point to judge it. The harbour is the judge of those aboard ship, but where are we going to find a harbour in morals?

699 When everything is moving at once, nothing appears to be moving, as on board ship. When everyone is moving towards depravity, no one seems to be moving, but if someone stops he shows up the others who are rushing on, by acting as a fixed point.

709 We know so little about ourselves that many people think they are going to die when they are quite well, and many think they are quite well when they are on the point of death, not sensing the approach of fever or the abscess ready to form.

711 Strength. Why do we follow the majority? Is it because they are more right? No, but they are stronger.

Why do we follow ancient laws and opinions? Is it because they are the soundest? No, but they are unique and leave us no basis for disagreement.

712 Someone told me one day that he felt full of joy and confidence when he had been to confession. Someone else told me that he was still afraid. My reaction was that one good man could be made by putting these two together, for each of them lacked something in not sharing the feelings of the other. The same thing often happens in other connexions.

739 Truth is so obscured nowadays and lies so well established that unless we love the truth we shall never recognize it.

740 Weaklings are those who know the truth, but maintain it only as far as it is in their interest to do so, and apart from that forsake it.

741 The adding-machine produces effects closer to thought than anything done by the animals, but it does nothing to justify the assertion that it has a will like the animals.

742 Even if people's interests are not affected by what they say, it must not be definitely concluded that they are not lying for there are some people who lie simply for the sake of lying.

743 There is some pleasure in being on board a ship battered by storms when one is certain of not perishing. The persecutions buffeting the Church are like this.

744 When we do not know the truth about something, it is a good thing that there should be some common error on which men's minds can fix, as, for example, the attribution to the moon of changes of seasons, progress of diseases, etc. For man's chief malady is restless curiosity about things he cannot know, and it is not so bad for him to be wrong as so vainly curious.

746 On the fact that neither Josephus, nor Tacitus, nor other historians, spoke of Jesus Christ.

Far from telling against him, this is on the contrary in his favour. For it is certain that Jesus Christ existed, that his religion made a great stir, and so it is obvious that they simply concealed it on purpose, or that they spoke about it and that it was suppressed or changed.

749 How warped is the judgement by which there is nobody who does not put himself above the rest of the world, and who does not prefer his own good, and continuing happiness and survival to that of the rest of the world!

750 Cromwell was about to ravage the whole of Christendom; the royal family was lost and his own set for ever in power, but for a little grain of sand getting into his bladder. Even Rome was about to tremble beneath him. But, with this bit of gravel once there, he died, his family fell into disgrace, peace reigned and the king was restored.

751 Those who are accustomed to judge by feeling have no understanding of matters involving reasoning. For they want to go right to the bottom of things at a glance, and are not accustomed to look for principles. The others, on the contrary, who are accustomed to reason from principles, have no understanding of matters involving feeling, because they look for principles and are unable to see things at a glance.

752 Two sorts of people make everything equal, for example holidays and working days, Christians and priests, all the sins amongst themselves. And from this some people conclude that what is bad for priests is also bad for Christians, while others conclude that what is not bad for Christians is permissible for priests.

753 When Augustus learned that among the children under two put to death by Herod was his own son, he said that it was better to be Herod's pig than his son. (Macrobius, Saturnalia, lib. ii, ch. iv.)

754 First degree: to be blamed for doing badly or praised for doing well.

Second degree: to be neither praised nor blamed.

755 He maketh a vain god.

Disgust.

756 Thought. All man's dignity consists in thought, but what is this thought? How silly it is!

Thought, then, is admirable and incomparable by its very nature. It must have had strange faults to have become worthy of contempt, but it does have such faults that nothing is more ridiculous. How great it is by its nature, how vile by its faults! 757 Draining away. It is an appalling thing to feel all one possesses drain away.

758 Light. Darkness. There would be too much darkness if there were no visible signs of the truth. One admirable sign of it is that it has always resided in a visible Church and congregation. There would be too much light if there were only one opinion in the Church. That which has always existed is the true one, for the true one has always been there, but no false one has always been there.

759 Thought constitutes man's greatness.

764 All the major forms of diversion are dangerous for the Christian life, but among all those which the world has invented none is more to be feared than the theatre. It represents passions so naturally and delicately that it arouses and engenders them in our heart, especially that of love; above all when it is represented as very chaste and virtuous. For the more innocent it seems to innocent souls, the more liable they are to be touched by it; its violence appeals to our self-esteem, which at once conceives the desire to produce the same effects which we see so well represented. At the same time our conscience is conditioned by the irreproachable sentiments to be seen there, which remove the fear of pure souls, who imagine that purity is not offended by loving with a love which seems to them so prudent.

Thus we leave the theatre with hearts so full of all the beauty and sweetness of love, and our mind so convinced of its innocence, that we are quite prepared to receive our first impressions of it, or rather to seek the opportunity of arousing them in someone else's heart, so that we may enjoy the same pleasures and sacrifices as those which we have seen so well depicted in the theatre.

765 If lightning struck low-lying places, etc., poets and people who can only argue about things of this kind would be without proofs.

767 As the ranks of duke, king and magistrate are real and necessary (because power governs all things) they exist at all times and in all places, but, since it is mere whim that makes it this or that person, there is no consistency about it, it is liable to variation, etc.

768 The commands of reason are much more imperative than those of any master, for if we disobey the one we are unhappy, but if we disobey the other we are foolish.

773 Only the contest appeals to us, not the victory.

We like to watch animals fighting, but not the victor falling upon the vanquished. What did we want to see but the final victory? And once it has happened we have had enough. It is the same with gaming, with the pursuit of truth. We like to see the clash of opinions in debate, but do we want to contemplate the truth once it is found? Not at all. If we are to enjoy it, we must see it arising from the debate. It is the same with passions; there is some pleasure in seeing the collision of two opposites, but when one asserts its mastery it becomes mere brutality.

We never go after things in themselves, but the pursuit of things. Thus in the theatre scenes of unclouded happiness are no good, any more than extreme and hopeless misery, or brutal love affairs, or harsh cruelty.

802 Time heals pain and quarrels because we change. We are no longer the same persons; neither the offender nor the offended are themselves any more. It is as if one angered a nation and came back to see them after two generations. They are still Frenchmen, but not the same ones.

803 If we dreamed the same thing every night, it would affect us as much as the objects we see every day. And if an artisan was sure of dreaming for twelve hours every night that he was king, I believe he would be almost as happy as a king who dreamed for twelve hours every night that he was an artisan.

If we dreamed every night that we were being pursued by enemies and troubled by these distressing apparitions, and spent every day doing something different, as one does on a journey, we should suffer almost as much as if it were true, and would dread going to sleep as we dread waking up when we are afraid of really encountering some misfortune. And this would in fact cause almost as much pain as reality.

But because dreams are all different, and there is variety even within each one, what we see in them affects us much less than what we see when we are awake, because of the continuity. This, however, is not so continuous and even that it does not change too, though less abruptly, except on rare occasions, as on a journey, when we say: 'It seems like a dream.' For life is a dream, but somewhat less changeable.

804 Are we to say that men recognized original sin because they said that justice had left the earth? Call no man happy until he is dead. Does that mean that they knew that eternal and absolute happiness begins at death?

805 By knowing each man's ruling passion, we can be sure of pleasing him, and yet each has fancies contrary to his own good, in the very idea he has of good, and this oddity is disconcerting.

806 We are not satisfied with the life we have in ourselves and our own being. We want to lead an imaginary life in the eyes of others, and so we try to make an impression. We strive constantly to embellish and preserve our imaginary being, and neglect the real one. And if we are calm, or generous, or loyal, we are anxious to have it known so that we can attach these virtues to our other existence; we prefer to detach them from our real self so as to unite them with the other. We would cheerfully be cowards if that would acquire us a reputation for bravery. How clear a sign of the nullity of our own being that we are not satisfied with one without the other and often exchange one for the other! For anyone who would not die to save his honour would be infamous.

808 There are three ways to believe: reason, habit, inspiration. Christianity, which alone has reason, does not admit as its true children those who believe without inspiration. It is not that it excludes reason and habit, quite the contrary, but we must open our mind to the proofs, confirm ourselves in it through habit, while offering ourselves through humiliations to inspiration, which alone can produce the real and salutary effect. Lest the Cross of Christ be made of none effect.

812 The style of the Gospels is remarkable in so many ways; among others for never putting in any invective against the executioners and enemies of Christ. For there is none in any of the historians against Judas, Pilate or any of the Jews.

If this restraint of the Evangelists had been put on, together with many other features of such fine character, and if they had only put it on in order to draw attention to it, not daring to remark on it themselves, they would not have failed to acquire friends to make such remarks for their benefit. But, since they acted as they did without affectation and quite disinterestedly, they did not cause anyone to remark on it. And I believe that many of these things have never been remarked on before. That shows how coolly the thing was done.

813 We never do evil so fully and cheerfully as when we do it out of conscience.

814 We pervert our feelings just as we pervert our minds.

Our minds and feelings are trained by the company we keep, and perverted by the company we keep. Thus good or bad company trains or perverts respectively. It is therefore very important to be able to make the right choice so that we train rather than pervert. And we cannot make this choice unless it is already trained, and not perverted. This is thus a vicious circle from which anyone is lucky to escape.

815 Ordinary people have the ability not to think about things they do not want to think about. 'Do not think about the passages concerning the Messiah,' said the Jew to his son. Our own people often behave like this, and this is how false religions are preserved, and even the true one as far as many people are concerned.

But there are some without this ability to stop themselves thinking, who think all the more for being forbidden to do so. These people rid themselves of false religions, and even of the true one, unless they find solid arguments for them.

816 'I should soon have given up a life of pleasure,' they say, 'if I had faith.' But I tell you: 'You would soon have faith if you gave up a life of pleasure. Now it is up to you to begin. If I could give you faith, I would. But I cannot, nor can I test the truth of what you say, but you can easily give up your pleasure and test whether I am telling the truth.'

817 There is no denying it; one must admit that there is something astonishing about Christianity. 'It is because you were born in it,' they will say. Far from it; I stiffen myself against it for that very reason, for fear of being corrupted by prejudice. But, though I was born in it, I cannot help finding it astonishing.

937 When our passions impel us to do something we forget our duty. For example, if we like a book, we read it when we ought to be doing something else. But to remember our duty we need only decide to do something we dislike; we then make the excuse of something else to be done, and thus remember our duty.

938 The figure used in the Gospel for the state of the soul that is sick is that of sick bodies. But, because one body cannot be sick enough to express it properly, there had to be more than one. Thus we find the deaf man, the dumb man, the blind man, the paralytic, dead Lazarus, the man possessed of a devil. All these put together are in the sick soul.

939 'The servant knoweth not what his lord doeth,' because the lord only tells him what to do and not the purpose of it. That is why he obeys slavishly and often sins against the purpose. But Jesus Christ has told us the purpose.

And you destroy that purpose.

940 Jesus did not want to be killed without the forms of justice, for it is much more ignominious to die at the hands of justice than in some unjust insurrection.

NOTE

①　[Pyrrhus, pressed to justify his plans for world conquest, reputedly answered that his ultimate purpose was to rest content, but not before realizing his dreams of conquest.]

导读

列夫·尼古拉耶维奇·托尔斯泰（1828—1910），俄国小说家、哲学家、政治思想家，也是非暴力的基督教无政府主义者和教育改革家。他出生于贵族家庭，1844年入喀山大学，1847年退学回到故乡尝试农奴制改革。1851年至1854年在高加索军队中服役并开始写作。1854年至1855年参加克里米亚战争。这几年的军旅生活让他看到了上流社会的腐化，也为其后来的巨著《战争与和平》打下了基础。

1855年11月，托尔斯泰到彼得堡进入文学界，并发表其成名小说《童年》。十多年后又创作了长篇历史小说《战争与和平》。在《忏悔录》中，托尔斯泰回忆起这段时光，他写道：“在此期间，我出于虚荣、自私和自负而涉身写作。我在写作时的所作所为竟和生活中一模一样。为了猎取写作带来的名利，我不得不隐藏起自己真善美的一面，把罪恶的一面展示在世人面前。如今，每当我想起那段时光、忆及我自己和周围的人们（很不幸，如今这样的人更是成千上万）当时的思想状态，我都会感到悲哀、恐惧和荒谬，它在我身上所激发的情感就像人们在疯人院中看到的那样疯狂和荒诞。”（第二章）

以上只是托尔斯泰对自己过往的一小段评价，实际上，在其成长和写作的生涯中，一直都在剖析和检视自我：“撒谎、偷盗、放荡、烂醉、暴力、谋杀……没有一项恶事我未曾染指，尽管这样，我的作为还是赢得了他人的赞赏，同辈人也认为相对而言我是个品德高尚的人。”（第二章）同时，不断尝试从科学、哲学等各种角度去追寻生命的意义，但都宣告失败：“如果你活着而又无法了解生命的意义，就结束生命，而不要到处大放厥词或制造文字垃圾，说什么你不了解生命。”（第七章）随后，他将目光投向了宗教信仰，但宗教的门派之争很快让他认清现实：“当我注意到这些口口声声基督仁爱的教徒的所作所为时，我不禁不寒而栗。”（第十五章）最终，他把对生命意义的执著追求的落脚点转向了劳动人民：“如果我希望继续活着并了解生命的意义的话，就不能够在那些已经失去生命或希望自杀的人们身上寻找，而应该看看那些创造过生命且愿意为自己和他人的生命负责的人，无论他们仍然活着还是已经逝去。于是我环顾四周，仔细观察简朴的普通大众，他们多半没受过什么教育，也没有钱，却一直活着且仍在活着，我看到了全然不同的东西。”（第八章）“就在我倾听一个没有文化的农民信仰者讲述上帝、宗教、生命和救赎时，我突然知晓了信仰的意义。我于是开始接近那些普通人，倾听他们关于生命和宗教的争论，也越来越接近真理。”（第十四章）

托尔斯泰的《忏悔录》，与古罗马奥古斯丁和法国卢梭的《忏悔录》，并称世界三大《忏悔录》。在三本《忏悔录》中，托尔斯泰的《忏悔录》篇幅最短，但却以人生思索与探寻的深度见长。托尔斯泰在文中深刻的思想剖析与严苛的自我检视，对生命意义何在的不断追问，对生命和人生的洞察，即使在今天，依然可以给读者以启发与感悟。

第一章

1.我一出生便接受了东正教的洗礼，并在信仰该教派的家庭环境中长大。我在东正教的谆谆教诲下度过了整个童年、少年和青年时期。然而在十八岁那年，大学二年级的我离开学校，不再相信他们教给我的任何教义。

2.忆及诸多往事，我觉得自己根本未曾笃信过宗教，只是信赖长辈们的言传身教，而这种信赖极不稳固。

3.记得十一岁那年的一个周日，一个名叫沃洛迪亚的高中生（此人如今已去世多年）来家中看望我们，向我们宣布了当时学校里的最新发现——世上根本没有上帝，我们所学到的关于上帝的一切纯属人们的编造（那是1838年）。我记得我的哥哥们对这一发现产生了极大的兴趣，甚至允许我参加他们的讨论。我记得当时大家都十分激动，觉得这个消息切实可信而令人神往。

4.我还记得当时正在上大学的哥哥德米特里突然间以性格中特有的激情，狂热地信起宗教来，并开始参加所有的宗教仪式，诸如奉行斋戒、崇尚纯洁而道德的生活等。我们大家（包括家中的大人）于是时常拿他取笑，出于众所周知的原因，大伙还给他起了个绰号叫“诺亚”。我记得那时喀山大学[1]的图书馆馆长穆西金·普希金先生有一次邀请大家参加舞会，在遭到德米特里的拒绝后，开玩笑地劝告我的这位哥哥说，就连大卫王也在方舟前跳过舞[2]。那时我常常被大人们的玩笑逗乐，从中也得出一个结论，那就是学习教义和去教堂做礼拜都是必要的，但无须过于认真。也曾记得很小的时候读过伏尔泰的作品，当时不仅没有为他那些抨击教会的犀利幽默感到震惊，反倒觉得相当有趣。

5.我的宗教热情日渐减退的过程和大多数同样背景的人差不多，时代进步了，这一过程却基本没有变化。在我看来，绝大多数情况大致如下：每个人经历的生活没有什么区别，但人们生活所依据的原则却不仅与教旨毫无关系，且大体上背道而驰。宗教教义丝毫不能应用于生活和人际关系，我们在自己的个人生活中也无须按照宗教教义行事。宗教教义是在另外一个境界中存在和传播的，它与生活本身有着一段距离，且超然独立于生活。我们所面对的宗教只是一种外部现象，和生活本身毫无关系。

6.一直以来，从一个人的生活或举止根本无法判断他是不是信徒。如果说公开宣称信仰东正教的人和拒绝入教的人有所不同，似乎算不上是对前者的夸赞之词。一直以来，公开声明和宣誓信仰东正教的通常都是愚钝呆滞、生性残暴、道德败坏和自视甚高的人。反之，聪慧、诚实、坦率、温厚以及美德则往往是声称自己并非信徒的人们所具备的品质。国家虽规定学校里必须讲授教义、必须送孩子们去教堂做礼拜，官员们也必须出具参加圣餐仪式的证据；然而现在（在过去更是如此），如果你既不在学校读书也不在政府部门任职，则可以数十年无所顾忌地生活在一个基督教国家，无须顾忌自己的周围都是基督徒。

7.因此如今和以往一样，人们在年少时怀着信任之心接受宗教教义，后来又迫于外界压力继续信仰。渐渐地，由于与知识和生活经验相悖，宗教教条的可信度最终在此二者的影响下不断衰减；当现实生活中已经完全没有宗教的印迹之时，人们可以认为幼时接受的宗教教诲仍然存在，此二者并行不悖，对个人的生活也不会产生什么影响。

8.有一个聪明诚实的人（姑且称之为S.），曾给我讲述过他自己不再信仰宗教的经历。二十六岁那年一次外出狩猎，他在夜间休息时遵循幼年养成的习惯，跪下来祈祷。当时他哥哥也在场，躺在稻草垫子上看着他。当S.祈祷完毕准备躺下睡觉时，他听到哥哥说：“你到现在还在祈祷？”之后一夜无语。从那天起，迄今三十多年过去了，S.再也没有祈祷、做礼拜或领圣餐，也没有去过教堂。之所以如此，并不是因为他了解了哥哥对于信仰的看法并希望与哥哥意见一致，也不是因为他内心已然作出决定，而恰恰是因为S.内心对宗教的信奉如同一面摇摇欲坠的断壁残垣。哥哥的话就仿佛手指轻轻一弹，整面墙便轰然倒塌。哥哥的话只是挑明了S.内心中被宗教占据的那一隅其实早已变成虚无的空洞，他的祈祷词、胸前画下的十字以及祈祷时的屈膝跪拜全都变成了毫无意义的肢体动作。一旦认识到这一切毫无意义，S.便再也不能够继续这些无谓的信仰了。

9.因此我相信，对绝大多数人而言，情况基本上就是这样，过去和现在没有什么不同。我这里提到的大多数人，是指与我们有着相同背景的人。这些人真诚地对待自己，不将立誓信教作为达到某种世俗目的的手段。（那些人才是最根本的非教徒：既然信仰在他们看来只是用于达到某种世俗目的的工具，那就根本不再有什么信仰可言了）和我们成长背景相同的人们会陷入这样一种境地：知识和生活的光辉会逐渐消融人为建立的宗教信仰，他们要么在不知不觉中把信仰忘得一干二净；要么迄今也未曾注意到这一点，对信仰听之任之。

10.我年幼时接受的宗教教诲后来大多消逝了，这一点和其他人一样。与其他人不同的是，我自幼开始读书思考，因而很早便摒弃了宗教。十六岁时我便不再主动祈祷、做礼拜或斋戒。我不再相信年幼时被灌输的教义，但是我的确一直信仰着，尽管我也说不清自己信仰的东西究竟是什么。我相信上帝，或者更确切地说，我不否认上帝的存在，但是当时的我说不清楚自己信仰的上帝是什么样子；我也不否认耶稣的存在抑或他的教义，而当时的我也同样说不清楚自己对耶稣教义的领悟。

11.回首前尘往事，我可以清楚地看到，除了出于动物本能而激发的对生活的欲望之外，我当时拥有的唯一真实的信念，就是自我修养和完善。但是这种自我修养包含哪些内容，又有着怎样的目标，当时的我不得而知。我尝试着在知识上完善自我，研习生活中的一切经历。我尝试着锻炼自己的意志，给自己制定各种规则并努力遵守。我尝试着健全自己的体格，通过各种运动来增强力量和身体的灵活性。我还试图克服各种困难，培养自己的韧性和耐心。我将所有这一切视为自我完善。当然，其开端乃是道德修养，然而没过多久，所有这些都烟消云散，被一种更具概括性的完善所取代，我不再关注是否在自己或上帝眼中做得更好，而开始在乎自己在他人看来是否完美无缺。很快这种攀比的决心变成比其他人更具影响力的强烈愿望：我要拥有比他人更多的声名、权力和财富。

第二章

1.有一天，我会向人们讲述自己的生活经历，以及在我年轻时代的十年间，生活给了我怎样的震撼和启示。想必很多人都曾有类似的经历。我真心诚意地希望做到尽善尽美，但那时的我年轻气盛、孤身一人，在追求尽善尽美的道路上孤立无援。每当我试图展示自己内心深处的渴望——做一个道德高尚的人时，总会招来鄙视和嘲笑；而一旦我屈服于低俗的欲望，却总是能够得到人们的赞赏和鼓励。野心、权力欲、自私自利、放荡、骄傲、愤怒、复仇，这些倒成了令人敬仰的品质。于是我渐渐臣服于这些私欲和贪念，变成我长辈的模样，并被他们悦纳。生活中接触到的最为纯洁的人乃是一个可敬的老姑妈，她总说她别无所求，只愿我能够和一位已婚妇女来一段风流韵事。“还有什么比和一位少妇交欢更美妙的呢？”她常常用优雅的法文发出这样的感叹。她还祝愿我能成为一名副官，最好能够为沙皇服务。诸多祈福中最令她兴奋的，莫过于我能迎娶一位富有的女孩，并通过婚姻拥有很多农奴，越多越好。

2.每忆及当年往事，我内心无不充满恐惧、厌恶和悲叹。在战争中我杀过人，给别人下过战书并想在决斗中杀死对方，也赌过纸牌，我压榨雇农，还惩罚他们；我与人私通、行事虚伪、面目丑恶。撒谎、偷盗、放荡、烂醉、暴力、谋杀……没有一项恶事我未曾染指，尽管这样，我的作为还是赢得了他人的赞赏，同辈人也认为相对而言我是个品德高尚的人。他们至今也没有改变这种观点。

3.这样的生活持续了整整十年。

4.在此期间，我出于虚荣、自私和自负而涉身写作。我在写作时的所作所为竟和生活中一模一样。为了猎取写作带来的名利，我不得不隐藏起自己真善美的一面，把罪恶的一面展示在世人面前。我也正是这么做的。我总是在作品中设法假借冷漠和漫不经心来掩盖使生命充满意义的、对于善的追求。我成功了，并得到人们的赞赏。

5.战争结束[3]那年，二十六岁的我回到圣彼得堡，并开始结交那里的作家。那个圏子欣然接受了我，还对我大肆奉承。我来不及停下思考，就被结交的这群作家同化，采纳了他们的生活态度。没过多久，我自己年轻时所有自我修养的尝试荡然无存。那些作家的生活态度无疑为我毫无节制的生活提供了理论依据和借口。

6.我的这些作家朋友们的人生观可以总结如下：一般来说，生活是一个不断发展的过程，在这个过程中扮演最重要的角色的就是我们这些思想者，而在诸多思想者中，我们这群艺术家和诗人最具影响力。我们的使命是传道授业。为了避免为“我知道些什么，又能教些什么”这类浅薄的问题所迷惑，他们解释说根本没必要知道这个问题的答案，因为诗人和艺术家在无意识中成就了其作为人类导师的使命。我既然是大家公认的杰出艺术家兼诗人，便自然而然地接受了这一理论。作为一个艺术家和诗人，我在写作时不必知道我要向人们传授什么。我做这些是有偿的。作为交换，我得到了美味的食物、舒适的住所、女人的陪伴、令人向往的社交圏和名望。既然如此，想必我教授的东西一定十分出色。

7.相信诗歌的意义以及生活的渐进发展也是一门信仰，而我就是这门教派中的一名“牧师”。作为这样一位“牧师”是件颇有裨益和令人愉悦的事，因而在相当长的一段时间，我都生活在这样的信念当中，从来没有质疑过其正确性。但是在第二年，我开始怀疑它的正确性，并开始了对它的质疑和审视，第三年更是如此。最初引起我怀疑的，是我注意到该教派内部的“牧师”们意见不一。有人说：“我们是最出色、最有价值的老师，我们教授的才是人们最需要的，而其他人教授的都是错误的东西。”有人说：“不对！我们才是真正的老师，你们错了！”他们为此辩论、争吵，彼此蒙蔽和欺诈。更有甚者，我们之中很多人对谁是谁非漠不关心，而只是冷眼观望，从中渔利。所有这一切迫使我对这门信仰产生了怀疑。

8.此外，一旦我开始质疑作家这门信仰的正确性，我便开始密切关注这里的“牧师”们，并愈加确信该教派内部几乎所有的“牧师”——那些作家们——都是不道德的。他们绝大多数都有着邪恶而卑劣的人格，还远不及我早年在放荡的军旅生活中遇到的那些人。但是他们又都颇为自鸣得意和孤芳自赏——那种自负要么表明他们是真正的圣徒，要么表明他们对虔诚和圣洁一无所知。他们开始显示出对我的厌恶和不满，我也开始对自己厌恶和不满，并最终意识到这门信仰原来是一个骗局。

9.但奇怪的是，尽管我很快认识到这些教条乃是纯粹的谎言，应该尽快抛弃，我却并没有放弃这些人赋予我的地位：没有放弃艺术家、诗人和传道授业者的头衔。我天真地幻想自己是个诗人和艺术家，能够在自己不明所以的情况下教授他人。我也确实是这么做的。

10.在和这些作家的交往中，我染上一种新的恶习，认为自己的使命就是在不明所以的情况下为人传道解惑，并对此抱有病态盲目的自傲和荒唐的自信。

11.如今，每当我想起那段时光、忆及我自己和周围的人们（很不幸，如今这样的人更是成千上万）当时的思想状态，我都会感到悲哀、恐惧和荒谬，它在我身上所激发的情感就像人们在疯人院中看到的那样疯狂和荒诞。

12.那时，我们都坚信自己必须滔滔不绝、笔耕不辍，坚信我们应该尽多尽快地发表作品——那可是全人类的福祉。就这样，成千上万的文人一面彼此相轻、口诛笔伐，一面著书立说、传道授业。没有人意识到自己的无知，我们连生活中最基本的问题——善恶是非的问题——都回答不了。人人高谈阔论、口若悬河，从不会谦虚地倾听他人说些什么。有时我们彼此纵容、互相夸赞，甚是享受；有时又怒气冲天、恶言相向，整个情形就仿佛我们全都生活在疯人院。

13.成千上万的工人日夜劳作，印成的铅字堆积如山，再邮寄分发至俄国各地。我们以传道授业为天降己任，却未曾真正向人们揭示出所有这些道业的真理，还总是觉得自己没有受到应有的重视并为此烦恼不已。

14.这一切真是非常奇怪，不过现在我全都懂了。我们真正关心的本是如何沽名钓誉。为达到这一目的，我们所知的唯一办法就是著书立说——那正是我们的所为。然而为了完成这一全然无用的任务，说服人们相信我们都是不可或缺的重要人物，就需要一种理论来为自己的所作所为进行辩解。由此我们编造出如下理论：凡是存在的都是合理的，万事都在不断发展变化。发展需要教化，而教化是以书刊的发行量来衡量的。既然这些书刊让我们得到了金钱和人们的尊敬，我们当然是最最重要、最有价值的一群人。如果我们大家意见一致，这个理论应该是非常合情合理的；但是既然我们中任何一个人表达的想法都会有人以截然相左的观点予以反对，我们就应该被迫重新思考该理论的正确性。然而没有人注意到这一点，我们得到了金钱的回报，得到了观点一致的人的赞美和夸奖，自然都觉得自己才是代表正义的一方。

15.如今我明白，我们的举止和疯人院里疯子的行为没有任何分别；但是那时我只是隐约地怀疑到这一点。和所有的疯子一样，我也认为除了我之外，其他人都是疯子。

第三章

1.就这样，我又在这种疯狂的状态下生活了六年，直到后来结婚。在此期间我还出过国。在欧洲的生活，以及与那些博学多才、见多识广的欧洲人的交往，加深了我继续自我修养的信念。因为我发现，那些人也持有同样的信念。这种信念在我身上的表现形式和我们那个时代所有的有识之士差不多，可以用一个词来表达，那就是“进步”。当时的我觉得这个词寓意颇深。我虽过着不错的生活，却和所有人一样，整日被“人类如何能够过上更好的生活”这样的问题所困扰。当时的我还不大了解在探讨如何“与时代共同进步”这个问题时，我就像一个人坐在一只随波逐流的小船上，每当被问及那个最基本、最重要的问题“我掌着生活的舵，驶向哪里”，总是试图逃避问题，而只是说，“我们被时代裹挟着前行”。

2.当时的我并未意识到这些。只是偶尔，我会出于本能（而不是理性）地抗拒在我生活的年代盛极一时的迷信，在那个年代，人们惯于用那样的迷信来掩饰自己对生活的无知。接下来，在巴黎逗留期间见到的一次处决让我意识到，社会进步这一迷信的根基是多么不牢靠。当我看到人们的首级与身体分离之后砰然落入木箱时，我忽然明白——不仅在理性上了解，也全身心地感受到——没有哪个关于人类生存和进步的理论能够为这样的暴行开脱。我意识到，哪怕自创世以来每一个人都根据这样或那样的理论认定这一暴行是必要的，我仍然认为这样做既不必要也不合理。如此看来，每个人都应该有自己关于是非和社会进步的判断，绝不能对他人言听计从、人云亦云，而应该听从自己内心最本真的声音。还有一个瞬间也让我感受到关于进步的迷信无益于人们彻底了解生命，那就是我哥哥的死。他是一个聪明、善良、庄重的人，生病的时候还很年轻，辗转病榻一年多，最终在痛苦中死去。死时他尚不知道自己为何生，更不知道自己为何死。没有什么理论能够回答这些问题，在哥哥那漫长而备受煎熬的濒死时日，我和他对生命和死亡的意义一样茫然。

3.然而这些只是偶尔出现的瞬间，事实上我仍然继续着我的生活，除了进步之外没有其他信仰。“一切都在发展，我也在进步；至于为什么我能够同万事万物共同进步，总有一天我会知晓原因。”当时的我就这样阐述自己的信仰。

4.回国后，我在乡下创办农民学校，并终日为此奔波忙碌。我之所以对这一职业情有独钟，是因为它没有我此前做文学教师时日益明显而强烈地感受到的虚伪。我在这里也是以进步之名办学，但我已经开始采取一种批判的态度来看待所谓的进步了。我告诉自己，进步的某些表现方式是错误的，而当我在乡下与那些农村孩子相处时，进步则必然体现为一种自由的精神，让他们得以根据自己的意愿选择任何进步的道路。

5.事实上，那时的我仍然面对着同样无法解决的问题：如何在我自己不明所以的情况下传道、授业、解惑。在较高级的文学圏子，我显然无法在自己不明所以的时候教授他人，基于我发现大家的教法各不相同，且我们在争论时总是尽可能地掩饰自己的无知。而在教这些农民孩子的时候，我可以让孩子们学习自己喜欢的任何东西，避开这个难题了。为了实现自己为师授道的抱负，当年的我走了一条多么迂回的道路，想来不免觉得好笑，然而我内心深处非常清楚，我始终无法教授人们真正需要的东西，因为我自己也不知道人们究竟需要什么。花费一年处理学校的各项事务后，我又去了国外，希望了解如何将我自己不明所以的东西教授给他人。

6.在农奴解放那一年，我重回俄国，我以为我终于找到了这个问题的答案并理解个中奥义。这一次我以正义的公断者自居，在学校里给无知的人们传授知识，并开始在报纸杂志上发表檄文，向有识之士传播思想。这一切似乎进展得不错，但是我感到自己的精神状态不是很健康，因而这一切不会持续太久。在我五十岁的时候，若不是我还能从尚未经历的人生另一面家庭生活中看到一丝救赎之光，或许我会陷入同样不可自拔的绝望之中。

7.整整一年，我忙于自己的仲裁工作、忙于学校的事务和在报纸杂志上发表文章，不久便筋疲力尽。这在很大程度上归咎于我思想上的紊乱，作为仲裁者所要处理的争端太过烦琐、学校的事务太过芜杂、我自己在报纸杂志上的搪塞支吾又令人厌恶，因为所有这些都可以最终归结到同一件事上：我想成为天下人之师，同时又始终力图掩盖一个事实，那就是我根本不知道自己教的是什么。我病了，与其说是身体上的疾病，不如说是精神上的煎熬。我中断手头所有的事情去了西伯利亚大草原，在那里我呼吸着新鲜的空气、喝着香甜的马奶酒，过着一种原始朴素的生活。

8.再次回到俄国时，我结婚了。快乐的家庭生活让我拥有了全新的活力，我彻底摆脱了所有对生命意义的追求。此时，我全部的生活都和我的家庭、妻子和孩子们联系在一起，我最关心的，就是如何改善我们的生活质量。从最初痴迷于自我完善，到后来代之以追求全人类的完善也就是社会进步，那一切都被一种更直接的欲望所战胜，就是如何让我的家庭和我本人过上最好的生活。

9.就这样又过了十五年。

10.尽管在那十五年间我觉得作家的工作无关紧要，我仍然没有间断写作。我已经尝到了身为作家的甜头，它让我在经济上获利甚丰，也为自己微不足道的工作获得了许多掌声。我将投身于写作看成提升自己物质地位的一种手段，与此同时，我也依赖于对写作的专注来压制自己灵魂深处始终缠绕的问题，就是我自己的生命乃至所有人生命的意义。

11.在写作中我试图传递自己认定的唯一真理：我们必须活着，为我们自己和家人创造最好生活的可能性。

12.这样的生活又过去了许多年，直到五年前，一种非常奇怪的现象发生在我身上。起初我开始经历时断时续的迷乱，仿佛生命静止了，仿佛我并不知道应该怎样活着，应该做些什么，我陷入茫然，进而陷入绝望。不过这样的迷乱很快就过去了，一切又恢复了先前的样子。之后这种迷乱发生得越来越频繁，出现的模式也一模一样。每到这时，当生命在一瞬间突然静止，总会有同样的问题出现在我的脑际：“为什么会这样？接下来会发生什么？”

13.起初我觉得这些问题毫无意义，也毫不相干。我觉得这些问题的答案，人所共知，只要我愿意解决，不会花费很大的力气；我觉得我一时没有时间考虑这些问题，不过只要我愿意认真思考，总会找到所有的答案。可是问题总是反复出现在我的脑海，越来越迫切地要求我给出答案。它们就像圆圆的句号，总是回到原点，仿佛转了一个大圏，形成一个更大的黑洞。

14.随后，那种常见的致命的心理疾病在我身上爆发。一开始只是一些不舒服的小迹象，一般病人都会忽视这些迹象；后来，症状出现得越来越频繁，最终变成了一段时间的持续煎熬。痛苦日益加重，在病人终于意识到问题的严重性时，他发现最初忽视的那些不舒服的迹象，事实上要比世间的一切都更为重要：那就是死亡。

15.当时的我就是这样。我意识到那并不是偶尔出现的不舒服，而是非常严重的疾病。如果同样的问题不断反复出现，就必须找到答案。我试图为它们寻找答案。那些问题显得如此愚蠢、无知和傻气。然而一旦我开始思考并试图解决这些问题，便立即认定：首先，它们并不傻气而愚蠢，而是生命中最重要、最有意义的问题；其次，无论我怎样绞尽脑汁，仍然找不到答案。在我忙于在萨马拉置办房产、着手教育儿子或投身写作之前，我必须知道自己做这些事情的意义何在；如果不能了解它们的意义，我什么也做不下去。当时我正忙着考虑农场的事儿，有时突然有一个问题出现在脑中：“啊，很好，这样你就拥有了萨马拉省六千俄亩[4]的农场和三百匹马了，但那又怎么样呢？”这让我觉得茫然，不知道接下来应该想些什么。只要一开始教育孩子们，我就会问自己“为什么”，或者正在思考如何让农民们走向富裕，我会突然问自己“那跟我有什么关系”，或者正想着写作带给我的显赫声名，我会对自己说：“啊，不错，这样你就比果戈理、普希金、莎士比亚、莫里哀更有名了，你会比世界上所有的作家都有名，但那又怎么样呢？”

16.对于这些问题，我根本找不到答案。

第四章

1.我的生活陷入了静止状态。我呼吸如常，吃喝入睡都像是例行公事；但是我已经没有生命力，因为没有什么现实的欲望让我觉得值得去实现。如果预先我就知道我的渴望能被满足，那我就都不会从中获得快乐。

2.假如有一位魔法师站在我面前，对我说他可以满足我的愿望，我不知道该对他说什么。在我偶尔很兴奋的时候，还会有出于习惯的欲望而不是真正的欲望的话，在我清醒的时候，我知道那些不过是幻觉。事实上，我什么也不想得到。我甚至不想知道真相，因为我已经猜到了真相是什么——真相是，生命毫无意义。

3.就仿佛我一直继续着自己的生活之路，就会来到了一个悬崖边，在那里我可以清楚地看到，前方除了毁灭之外什么也没有。然而我已经不可能停下来，不可能回头，或者闭上眼睛假装对此一无所知。人生在世，原来面对的除了关于生命和快乐的谎言，就是煎熬至死的现实——生命，原本是彻底的虚无。

4.我开始厌恶生活，开始感受到有一种不可逾越的力量，它带着我寻求解脱，不管以什么方式，我一定要从这样的虚无中解脱出来。我不能说自己想自杀，那向我招手、让我远离生命的，是一种更强大、更彻底、更宏阔的欲望，就像曾经指引我不懈地追求更好的生活的那种力量。只是如今，指引我向着相反的方向。我用尽全力与生命抗争，自杀的想法出现得如此自然，就像之前那些不断进步、完善自我的想法一样自然。这个想法强烈地吸引着我，以至于我不得不动用一些小伎俩，以免自己太仓促地作出决定。我不想莽撞，希望能够尽量看清整个事情的真相。我告诉自己，如果当时无法揭开真相，我还有的是时间。就在那时，将在更衣室单间的绳子拿了出来，避免自己在壁橱间的横梁上上吊；每次前去打猎时，我也不再像往常那样随身带一支手枪，以防自己克制不住自杀的念头，那么轻易地结束一切。我也不知道自己想要什么。我害怕生命，全力与它抗争，又仍然希望从生命中得到一些什么。

5.这一切发生在我被常人眼中无比完美和快乐的生活包围着的时候：我还不到五十岁，有一个善良、忠实又深深为我所爱的妻子，孩子们活泼可爱，我还有很大的一片地产，即使我本人没有费什么力气，它也运转良好并有不断扩大之势。亲戚朋友比以往更加尊重我，陌生人也对我赞誉有加，我可以毫不脸红地说，自己已经是一个名人了。此外，我的精神和身体都还健康，有着同龄人少有的充沛精力和体力：在体力上我可以和农民一起在田间耕种；在脑力上我可以连续工作八九个小时也不觉得累，之后也不会出现什么不舒服的反应。而就在这样近乎完满的生活状态下，我觉得自己简直有些活不下去了，同时又因为害怕死亡，我不得不自欺欺人，以防自己真的选择自杀。

6.这种精神状态是以下面这种方式呈现在我脑海中的：生活是某人跟我开的一个愚蠢而邪恶的玩笑。尽管我不知道这位“某人”是谁——他或许是带我来到世间的造物主——这种我被某人带到这个世界上、此人以此种方式跟我开了一个愚蠢而又邪恶的玩笑的想法，在我看来，成为表达自己当时那种精神状态的最自然的方式。

7.我不禁感到，在我身外的某一个空间，那人正一边笑着一边看我的好戏，看我如何生活了三四十年；看我徒劳地学习、长大、达到所谓的身心成熟；看我此时心智成熟地站在生命自我揭示意义的悬崖，像个傻瓜一样，如此坚信生命的虚无：生命毫无意义，过去没有，将来也不会有。那人嘲笑着我。

8.即使那个观察我的生活并以此为乐的人不存在，也不会让我感到丝毫的轻松。哪怕是一个小小的举动，我都无法为它找到理性的意义，更不要说整个生命了。我只是感到震惊，为什么我一开始竟没有意识到这一点，在如此漫长的生命中，这样的问题一直存在，根本就应该是常识。今天或明天，疾病和死亡就会降临到我最心爱的人们身上，也会降临到我自己身上（或许它们已经来了）。之后除了尸骨渐寒，什么也不会留下。早晚有一天，无论我曾经立下怎样的丰功伟业，它们都会被世人遗忘，荡然无存。那么我们又在这里斤斤计较些什么呢？人，怎么可以一直活着，却看不到这样的真相？这真是太让人震惊了！只有当我们对生活迷迷糊糊时，才有可能这样活着；一旦清醒，就不可能看不到所有这一切都只是一个玩笑，一个愚蠢的恶作剧！那就是真相：没有什么诙谐幽默，一切都显得残酷而愚蠢。

9.有一个古老的东方寓言，讲述一个旅人在没有防备的情况下被一个残暴的野兽驱赶到一片空旷的大草原。为了躲开野兽，旅人藏身于一口已经干涸的深井中，但他朝下一看，井底有一条巨龙正张着大口，准备吞掉他。可怜的旅人不敢爬出深井，因为害怕被残暴的野兽吃掉，也不敢落到井底，怕那条巨龙一口吞掉他。于是他抓住井壁的石头缝里长出的一根灌木枝，整个身子吊在那里。他的胳膊渐渐没劲儿了，知道无论是上还是下，死亡就在不远处等待着他，他别无选择。然而他还是紧紧抓住手中的那颗救命稻草。他四处看看，发现有一黑一白两只老鼠，正在啃噬着他手中抓着的灌木枝的根茎，那根茎已经摇摇欲坠了。不久老鼠就会把它彻底啃断，他就会落入巨龙的大口。旅人看到这个，知道自己注定难逃一死了。然而他吊在那里的时候有几滴蜂蜜落在灌木树叶上，他伸出舌头，舔食蜂蜜。我也像这样吊在生命之树上，我太清楚，死亡的巨龙就在下面等待着我，准备把我撕成碎片，我也不知道自己何以落入这样一口受尽折磨的深井。我试着舔食那曾经让我觉得甘甜和安慰的蜂蜜，但已经从中得不到任何快乐。白色和黑色的老鼠——白天和黑夜——无休止地啃噬着我紧紧抓住的树枝。我清楚地看到那只张着大口的巨龙，蜂蜜吃到嘴里也不再甘甜了。视线所及，只有那条让我无以逃遁的巨龙和那两只老鼠，我无法转移视线不去看它们。这不是寓言而是真相，是每个人都无法辩驳又能清楚看到的真相。

10.生命中快乐的幻觉曾一度抑制住我对巨龙的恐惧，如今我不再自欺欺人。无论我多少次听到这样的话：你根本无法理解生命的意义，过自己的生活，不要再想了——我仍然无法顺从，因为我已经顺从太久了。现在我总是看到自己被白天和黑夜交替追赶着，走向死亡。这就是我所看到的一切，因为这是唯一的真相，其他的全都是谎言。

11.那两滴蜂蜜，一是对家庭的眷恋，二是对写作——也就是我称之为“艺术”的事业的热爱，曾经是引领我的目光远离残酷真相的最重要的力量，如今却已不再让我感到甜蜜了。

12.“家庭……”我自言自语道。但是我的家庭，我的妻子和孩子也都是凡俗的肉身啊。他们的处境和我一模一样：要么生活在谎言中，要么直面可怕的真相，他们也别无选择。那么他们又是为什么而活着呢？为什么我会爱他们，照顾他们，造就他们，时刻关注着他们？是为了让他们向我一样被绝望笼罩，还是为了让他们对这一切无知无觉？如果我爱他们，就不能向他们隐瞒真相。在知识的海洋，每前进一步，就离真相更进一步，而那真相就是死亡。

13.“艺术，诗歌……”在很长一段时间里，因为成功，因为他人的赞美，我说服自己说那是一件可为之事。尽管日渐走近死亡会将那一切湮没在废墟中：我自己和我的作品，以及人们对这一切的记忆。然而我很快意识到这也是假象。我清楚地看到，艺术只不过是生活的装点和修饰，然而既然它在我看来已全无魅力，我又如何用它去感染他人呢？我并没有真正地生活过，只是一具徒有躯壳的行尸走肉，只要我认为生命是有意义的，哪怕我说不清楚它究竟有何意义，任何诗歌和艺术中所反映的生命都会让我感受到快乐。我通过艺术的镜子观察生活，这让我无比享受。但是当我开始探寻生命的意义，当我开始感受到活着原来是不得已，这面镜子就变得无关紧要、累赘多余而荒谬可笑，甚至干脆变成了令人痛苦的折磨。在镜中，我看到的只有自己愚蠢而令人绝望的处境，就再也不能奢望从中得到安慰了。当我在自己的灵魂深处认定生命是有意义的时候，镜中的一切会带给我愉悦。那时，光影的跃动，世间的悲喜剧，生命中令人感动、令人赞叹、令人恐惧的方方面面都会给我以慰藉。然而当我发现生命没有意义，根本就是一个可怕的恶作剧时，就不再能够从镜中光影里得到娱乐了。无论蜂蜜有多甘甜，一旦我看到身子下面张着大口的巨龙和头顶上啃噬着支撑我的根茎的老鼠，就再也感受不到任何甘甜的滋味了。

14.还不止如此。如果我只是了解到生命全无意义，或许会平静地接受这一现实，觉得那是我不得不接受的宿命。然而我无法这样冷静。如果我是一个在森林里迷了路的人，知道根本没有出路，或许也就安然地活下去了；但是我像一个莽撞之徒，在森林里迷了路，明知道没有路却又为寻找出路而四处奔跑，这让我倍感恐惧。因为我知道，每往前一步都会更深地迷失，然而又无法停下脚步。

15.这是非常可怕的。于是，为了摆脱这样的恐惧，我想到了自杀。我感到未来等待着我的东西比眼前的处境更可怕，而我既无法将它驱赶开来，又没有足够的耐心平静地等待结局。无论科学界怎么说心脏的血管会在一瞬间崩裂，或者会有什么东西突然爆炸，一切都会在瞬间结束，我仍然无法平心静气地等待那一瞬间的到来。对黑暗的恐惧太强烈，我想要逃离那种恐惧，越快越好，不管是用绳子还是子弹。正是这种感觉无比强烈地引诱我走向自杀的道路。

第五章

1.有好几次我对自己说：“或许我忽略了什么，或者我对某些知识不够了解？不可能人人都会陷入这样的绝望啊。”于是我开始在人类各个分支的知识中找寻答案，之后的很长时间，我一直在苦苦求索。我可不是三心二意地敷衍了事，也绝非出于好奇一时兴起，而是拿出自己全部的耐性和毅力，就像一个垂死的人寻求解脱那样，日夜不停地寻找，最终一无所获。

2.我企图在所有的知识中一探究竟，最终不仅一无所获，反而坚信，所有和我一样在知识中寻找答案的人，必定都和我一样一无所获。他们不仅一无所获，还不无痛苦地认识到同样令我陷入绝望的现实：生命毫无意义。这是人类所能获得的最无可辩驳的知识。

3.我到处寻找，幸亏我一直在学术圏里生活，在学术界交游甚广，可以接触到各个学科的学者。我可以通过著作或通过和他们谈话，洞察这些学者的博学广识，因而关于知识能够回答生命的所有问题，我都一一通晓。

4.在很长一段时间，我不相信知识回答不了生命的问题，而只能回答它本身提出的问题。在很长一段时间，我看到科学在提出自己的主张（那些主张多半与人类生活无关）时那一副自以为是的严肃劲儿，却并没有觉得它们加深了我对世界的理解。在很长一段时间，我在知识面前自惭形秽，觉得自己之所以没有找到问题的答案，一定是因为幼稚无知，而不是知识的错误。不过这对我来说可不是什么好笑的事情，它不是玩笑，而是我生命中一个非常重要的课题。最后我不得不得出结论，我的问题是唯一合理的问题，是所有知识学科的基础。我本人和我的问题都没有错，如果科学一度伪装自己能够回答这些问题，那就是科学的错。

5.那个让我在五十岁时几近自杀的问题乃是每个人灵魂深处最重要的问题，无论是懵懂无知的少年还是饱读诗书的智叟。根据我的经验，没有这个问题就不可能有生命。这个问题就是：我今天或明天的行为将产生什么样的后果。我的整个一生又将如何？

6.或者我们换一种表达方式，这个问题就是：我为什么活着，为什么我对世间的事物或成就有所渴望。或者再换一种表达方式：有没有一种生命的意义可以超越每个人必将面对的死亡而永恒？

7.我试图通过人类的知识回答这个问题——不管我们以何种方式表达，这些其实都是同一个问题。我发现，根据它们各自与这一问题的关系，人类知识的所有分支几乎可以分为两个对立的领域，在这两个领域的尽头分别是两个对立的极端：一个是积极的，一个是消极的。然而无论哪一个极端，都没有对生命的问题提供任何答案。

8.其中一个知识分支甚至根本不承认问题的存在，却对它自己另行提出的问题给出了清晰而准确的答案：那就是实验科学领域，位于这一领域最极端的是数学。另一个知识领域承认这一问题的存在却没有作出回答，那就是思辨哲学领域，位于这一领域最极端的是形而上学。

9.我很年轻的时候就学习了思辨哲学，但后来却对数学和自然科学非常着迷。在我明确对自己提出那个问题，且问题本身在我的思想深处越积越深、迫切需要我作出回答之前，我对知识给出的答案一直十分满意。

10.在实验科学领域我对自己说：“一切都在发展，万事万物各有不同，它们越来越复杂精细，在这一切进步中，是有科学规律可循的。你本人就是万事万物的一个组成部分。如果你对整个世界以及主导世界发展的科学规律了解得足够深入，你就会了解自己在这个世界中的位置，那时你就认识了你自己。”尽管我羞于提起，但一度我对这个答案非常满意。那个时候，我本人也在成长，变得越来越复杂。我的肌肉在日益增大加强，我的记忆越来越丰富，我的思考和理解能力与日俱增。我日渐成长和日臻成熟，并且感受到了自己体内的这种成长，自然就会相信，有一个普遍规律引导着整个世界的发展，我可以通过那个普遍规律找到自己生命问题的答案。然而不久后我不再成长；我觉得自己不再发展成熟而是日渐干枯萎缩，肌肉萎缩，牙齿纷纷脱落，因而我不仅觉得那个普遍规律无法为我提供任何解释，甚至觉得世界上从来没有也不可能有这样一个规律。我把自己在生命中的某一段时间看到的东西误认为是普遍规律了。在更加严格地考察了它的定义之后，我明确得出结论，根本没有什么永恒发展的规律。我清楚地看到，什么世间万事万物都在永恒的时间和空间中不断发展，越来越完美、复杂和与众不同，全都是没有任何实际意义的空话。因为在永恒的时间和空间里，根本不存在简单和复杂、之前和之后、更好和更糟的分别。

11.最重要的是，这样的论断对于我个人的问题，有关我和我所有的欲望的问题，没有提出任何解决方案。我发现这些科学研究的确非常有趣和迷人，但是它们的精确性和清晰度与它们与生命问题的相关性成反比：与生命问题的相关性越小的学科，就越清晰、越精确；而越是试图解决生命问题的学科，就越晦涩模糊、枯燥无味。看看那些试图回答生命问题的学科，看看生理学、心理学、生物学和社会学，我们会发现，这些学科几乎根本没有什么思想，所有的语言都混沌模糊，伪装自己能够解决超出其学科范围之外的问题。各位思想家之间还不停地发生冲突（甚至常常自相矛盾）。再看看那些根本不关心生命问题而只是回答其本身的专业科学问题的学科，人们大概会惊叹人类智慧的力量，然而就算不探讨这些学科我们也知道，它们根本不会回答有关生命的根本问题。这些学科全然无视这个问题。它们说：“关于你是谁、你为什么活着这个问题，我们不知道，这个问题也与我们无关。但如果你想知道关于光的定理，或者化学合成，或者有机物生长的机理；如果你想知道物理天体及其形状的各种规律，想知道它们的大小和数目之间的关系；或者如果你想知道人类大脑的生理机制，我们会向你提供清楚、精确而无可辩驳的答案。”

12.总的来说，实验科学与生命问题的关系可以这样来概括。

问：我为什么活着？

答：在无限的空间和永恒的时间里，有无限多的小分子以无限复杂的形式进行着各种变异；一旦你了解了这些变异的规律，你就知道自己为什么活着了。

13.后来我转而探索思想领域，当时的我是这样想的：“整个人类依据一定的精神原则和理想成长、生活和发展成熟。这些思想观念可以分别表达为宗教、科学、艺术和政治。随着这些思想日益提升，人类也会跟着进步，变得更加幸福。我既然是人类的一分子，自然应该以认识和实现这样的理想为己任。”我在没有什么判断力的时期，对这样的说法十分满意。然而一旦我对有关生命的问题有了清晰的认识，这一套理论立刻不堪一击，轰然坍塌。这类知识学科通常在下结论时都显得轻率随便、模棱两可，它们仅对少量样本进行研究就匆忙作出概括性的推断。这一理论体系不同的支持者之间，总是就人类的理想究竟是什么充满了矛盾和争吵，这一观点的古怪之处（或者说愚蠢之处）就在于，为了回答这个摆在每个人面前的问题：“我是谁？”或者，“我为什么活着”，或者，“我应该做些什么”，人们必须先解决“人类的生命是什么”这个问题。关于后一个问题，人们所知实在不多，他们所能探索的，不过是人类历史的一瞬间中一个小片段的一小部分而已。也就是说，要了解自己，必须先了解整个人类的秘密，而所谓人类，正是由像此人一样完全不了解自己的个人组成的。

14.我得承认自己曾经笃信这一理论。那时我有自己偏爱的一套理想来为自己的突发奇想、反复无常找借口。我试图创造一种理论，将自己的这些突发奇想定为适用全人类的普遍规律。然而一旦我从灵魂深处非常清楚地提出了最基本的生命问题，这个答案立即消失得无影无踪了。我开始意识到，和实验科学一样，这个领域也存在着真正的科学和伪科学，二者都力图回答其学科范围之外的问题。这里也同样存在一系列全然不同的学科分支，这些分支同样力图回答其学科范围之外的问题。这些伪科学——包括法律、社会和历史学——全都试图解决人类的各种问题，并假装它们能够以自己的方式解答那个与全人类有关的生命问题。

15.然而，如果说在实验科学领域，一个人认真地提出“他应该怎样活着”这样一个问题，听到有人建议他去研究在无限的时空中无限多的分子以无限复杂的形式进行的变异，他一定不会满意的话，那么同样，如果有人建议他为了解自己就必须先探求整个人类的生命，他也一定不会满意。因为根本没有人知道人类的生命从何处始，至何处终，哪怕其中最小的一部分我们也一无所知。此外，就像实验科学领域的那些伪科学一样，这些科学越是偏离其目的，就越是模棱两可，毫无精确性，愚蠢而矛盾重重。实验科学关心的问题是物质现象的因果顺序，人们只需要问到一个关于终极原因的问题，实验科学就立即变成一堆废纸。思想领域面临的问题是它认为生命的本质是超出因果界定的，人们只要在考察时引入因果现象，如社会或历史数据，就会让这一整套科学变成胡言乱语。

16.因此，实验科学并不在自己的体系中引入终极原因的问题，而只是探讨积极的知识，揭示人类智慧的不同凡响；而抽象的思想领域是后来成为科学的，它完全无视因果现象的顺序问题，而只是考察与某一个终极原因有关的人类，以此来揭示人类智慧的不同凡响。举例来说，在这一领域的最极端就是形而上学，即抽象哲学。这门科学明确提出了：“我是谁？”以及“宇宙是什么？我为什么存在，宇宙又为什么存在？”的问题。自从这门科学产生以来，它为这些问题提出的答案永远都是一样的。无论哲学认为我们生命的本质乃至万事万物的本质是思想还是物质、精神还是意志，其所表达的都只是同一个意思：我存在，而我就是这个本质。然而他并没有解决怎样存在和为什么存在的问题，如果这位哲学家是一个严谨的思想者，他就根本找不到答案。我问：“这个本质又为什么存在？它现在是什么样子，将来又是什么样子？”哲学不仅没有回答这些问题，反而又提出了同样的问题。如果它是真正的哲学，那么它的全部任务就在于明确提出这个问题。而如果它恪守这一原则，那么它对于“我是谁”以及“宇宙是什么”的回答就只有一个：“要么是一切，要么是虚无。”而它对宇宙为什么存在、我又为什么存在这个问题的回答也只有一个，那就是：“不知道。”

17.因此，无论我怎样苦苦思索哲学推测出的这些回答，统统不能称其为答案。个中理由不同于表达较为清楚的实验科学，在实验科学中，答案与问题本身没有关系；而就哲学来说，尽管哲学家们为了回答我的问题而博学强记、绞尽脑汁，他们仍然没有答案。哲学所提供的不是答案，而是同样的问题，只不过是换了一种方式提出来而已。

第六章

1.为了寻找生命问题的答案，我觉得自己就像一个在森林中迷路的旅人。

2.我来到一片空地，爬到一棵树上极目四望，可以看到很远的远方，却看不到一座小木屋或任何栖居之所。我走入一片灌木丛，身处黑暗，四周苍茫一片，却发现那里也没有我要找的小木屋。

3.我以同样的方式徜徉于人类知识的森林，既沐浴了数学知识和实验科学那明媚的光线——在那里我可以远眺地平线，却找不到一座小木屋，也陷入了思想领域那幽深的暗影——在这里我走得越远，笼罩天地的黑暗就越是汹涌。后来我坚信，在这里，我没有也根本不可能有任何出路。

4.当我走向知识的光明一端，我发现那只是在逃避问题。无论在我面前伸出的地平线多么灿烂光明，无论将自己沉迷于这无尽的知识中是多么美妙的诱惑，我已经知道，这些知识越是清楚而条理分明，我就越不需要它，因为它越解答不了我的问题。“嗯，”我自言自语道，“我完全了解了科学所迫切了解的东西，在那条路上，我根本找不到关于生命意义这个问题的答案。”在另一端的思想领域，我知道尽管这类知识的根本目的是要解答我的问题——或许正是因为这个原因——它所能给我的却无非是我自己已经找出的那个一模一样的答案。即，问：“生命的意义是什么？”答：“生命没有意义。”或者，问：“我的生命最终将变成什么样子？”答：“无尽的虚无。”再或者，问：“那么世界为什么存在，我又为什么存在？”答：“因为它们的确存在。”

5.如果为了回答这个问题而去研究人类知识的一个分支，我会得到无数非常精确的答案，只不过那些都不是我提出的问题的答案。什么星体的化学组成啦、太阳朝向武仙星座的运动啦、物种和人类的起源啦、无限小的原子的形状啦，乃至于非常微小且数目无限的大气分子的浮动啦，等等。然而关于我提出的生命意义的问题，这一知识分支给出的唯一答案是：“你就是你所称之为生命的东西，你是一团暂时存在的、偶尔聚集在一起的物质，这些分子物质的相互作用和变化在你的体内构成了所谓的生命。这一聚集体只能在有限的时间内存续，一旦分子之间的相互作用停止了，也就是我们所说的生命停止了，所有的问题也将随之结束。人的生命就是某种物质的随机组合，该组合堆不断分解，其发酵的过程就是所谓的生命；该组合堆最终将彻底解体，发酵过程终将停止，那时所有的问题也将一并消失。”这就是精确的科学知识给出的答案，如果这些学科严格坚持其本身的原则的话，它们也只能提供这一种答案。

6.然而事实是，这个答案根本没有回答我提出的问题。我需要知道自己生命的意义何在，关于“生命乃是无限时空中的一分子”这样的命题不仅未能说出生命的意义，反而消解了它可能会有的任何意义。

7.如果实验科学试图与思想领域的科学进行暧昧的妥协，它会说生命的意义在于发展，以及对这种发展的促进和鼓励。然而这样的说法太过含混朦胧，根本无法称之为答案。

8.位于人类知识领域另一端的思想科学，如果严格坚持其本身的原则，会试图直接解答生命意义的问题。然而自古以来，它给出的永远是同一个答案：“宇宙是无限的、不可理解的，人类的生命是这个莫测高深的‘整体’的一个莫测高深的组成部分。”在这里，我同样排除了思想领域试图与实验科学（它还包括一整套伪科学）进行的妥协，即所谓的法学、政治学和历史学。在这些科学中也同样存在对于发展和完善的错误理解，唯一的区别是，自然科学探讨的是万事万物的发展，而思想科学讨论的是人类生命的发展。二者所犯的错误也一模一样：在无限的时空中，发展和完善既无目的，也无方向，而关于我的问题，没有答案。

9.在精确的思想知识，也就是在真正的哲学而不是叔本华所谓的专业哲学（它唯一的作用是把所有现存的现象归入新的哲学类别并给它们加上新的标签）中，哲学并非没有看到那个基本的问题，而其给出的答案只有一个，那就是苏格拉底、叔本华、所罗门和佛所给出的那个答案。

10.“我们只有在与生命渐行渐远时，才会越来越接近生命的实质，”苏格拉底在垂死之时如是说，“那么，我们这些热爱真理之人在生命中又在苦苦求索些什么呢？脱离肉体，并远离起源于肉体生命的所有邪恶之事。如果是这样，那么为什么当死亡临近，我们竟无论如何也高兴不起来呢？”

11.“智者通过生命走向死亡，因此死亡并不令其有所恐惧。”

12.“认识到世界内在的本质是意志，”叔本华说，“并在一切现象中——从无知觉的自然力的无意识的企图直到人的完全有意识的活动，只承认这种意志的具体性，我们就不能回避一个结果，即随着意志的任意否定和自我消亡，一切现象，世界赖以生存的、持久的、既无目的又不停息的、具有不同程度具体内容的希望和爱好也将消失。因果关系的多样性也将消失，随同形式一起，意志的具有空间和时间这种一般形式的一切现象也就消失。结果是世界最终的基本形式——主体和客体也消失了。没有意志，没有表象，也就没有世界。在我们面前就只有虚无。但是抗拒向寂灭转化的一切，我们的自然界也不过是这种构成我们自身和我们世界的生存意志。我们这样害怕寂灭，或者换一种说法，我们这样想活着。这只意味着我们本身就是这种生存的愿望，除此以外，我们一无所知。因此，对我们这些还充满意志的人说来，意志完全消亡之后，剩下的当然是虚无。与此相反，对于意志发生了变化并已消亡的那些人来说，我们这一非常现实的世界，连同他所有的太阳和银河，都是虚无。”[5]

13.“虚空的虚空，”所罗门说，“凡事都是虚空。人一切的劳碌，就是他在日光之下的劳碌，有什么益处呢？一代过去，一代又来，地球永远长存……已有的事，后必再有；已行的事，后必再行。日光之下，并无新事。岂有一件事人能指着说：这是新的。哪知，在我们以前的世代早已有之。已过的世代，无人记念；将来的世代，后来的人也不记念。我传道者在耶路撒冷做过以色列的王。我专心用智慧寻求查究天下所做的一切事，乃知神叫世人所经练的，是极重的劳苦。我见日光之下所做的一切事，都是虚空，都是捕风……我心里议论说，我得了大智慧，胜过我以前在耶路撒冷的众人，而且我心中多经历智慧和知识的事。我又专心察明智慧、狂妄和愚昧，乃至这也是捕风。因为多有智慧，就多有忧烦；加增知识，就加增忧伤。”[6]“我在心里说：来吧！我以喜乐试试你，你好享福。谁知，这也是虚空。我指着嬉笑说：这是狂妄；论喜乐说：有何功效呢？我心里察究，如何用酒使我肉体舒畅，我心却仍以智慧引导我；又如何持住愚昧，等我看明世人，在天下一生当行何事为美。我为自己动大工程，建造房屋，栽种葡萄园；建造园囿，在其中栽种各种各样果木树；挖造水池，用以浇灌嫩小的树木。我买了奴婢，也有生在家中的奴婢；又有许多牛群羊群，胜过以前在耶路撒冷众人所有的。我又为自己积蓄金银和君主的财宝，以及各省的财宝；又得唱歌的男女和世人取乐之物，如乐器及诸如此类。这样，我就日渐昌盛，胜过以前在耶路撒冷的众人。我的智慧仍然存留。凡我目之所求，我没有不留给他的；我心之所乐的，我没有不享受的；因我的心为我一切所劳碌的快乐，这就是我从劳碌中所得的部分。后来，我查看我亲手经营的一切事和我劳碌所成的功，谁知都是虚空，都是捕风，在日光之下毫无益处。我转念观看智慧、狂妄和愚昧。在王以后而来的人还能做什么呢？也不过行早先所行的就是了。我便看出智慧胜过愚昧，如同光明胜过黑暗。智慧人的眼目光明；愚昧人在黑暗里行。我却看明，这两种人都必遇见相同的事。我在心里说，愚昧人所遇见的，我也必遇见，我为何更有智慧呢？我心里说，这也是虚空。智慧人和愚昧人一样，永远无人纪念，日后都被忘记。可叹智慧人死亡，与愚昧人无异。我所以恨恶生命，因为在日光之下所行的事，我都以为烦恼，都是虚空，都是捕风。我恨恶一切的劳碌，就是我在日光之下的劳碌，因为我得来的必留给我以后的人……人在日光之下劳碌累心，在他一切的劳碌上得着什么呢？因为他日日忧虑，他的劳苦成为忧烦，连夜间心也不安。这也是虚空。人强莫如吃喝，且在劳碌中享福……”[7]

14.“凡临到众人的事，都是一样。义人和恶人都遭遇一样的事；好人、洁净人和不洁净人、献祭的与不献祭的，也是一样。好人如何，罪人也如何；起誓的如何，怕起誓的也如何。在日光之下所行的一切事上，有一件祸患，就是众人所遭遇的都是一样，并且世人的心充满了恶。活着的时候心里狂妄，后来就归死人那里去了。与一切活人相连的，那人还有指望，因为活着的狗总比死去的狮子强。活着的人知道必死，死去的人毫无所知，也不再得赏赐，他们的名无人记念。他们的爱，他们的恨，他们的嫉妒，早都消灭了。在日光之下所行的一切事上，他们永不再有份了。”[8]

15.所罗门，就是那个写下这些话语的人，如是说。

16.以下是一位印度先哲讲述的故事：“释迦牟尼是一位年轻快乐的王子，从不知道疾病、年迈和死亡为何物。有一天他乘坐马车外出，看见一个可怕的老人，老人满嘴的牙掉光了，口水顺着嘴角流下来。王子因为从不知年迈为何物，非常惊诧，就问马夫那是什么，为什么让他遭遇这样一个可怜、可恶又可憎的景象？当他听说这是所有人的宿命，就连他这位年轻的王子有朝一日也会面临同样的境遇时，王子再也无心游玩，命令马车回程，让他好好考虑一下这件事儿。他把自己关在房里，仔细想了几天。或许他在思考中得到了某种安慰，因为过了几天他又乘马车外出了，和前一次一样欢快开心。但这一次他又遇到了一个病人。这个人一脸憔悴、脸色发青，眼里暗淡无光。王子因为从不知疾病为何物，便让车夫停下，问那是什么。当他听说那就是疾病，所有人都会染上疾病，即使他这样健康快乐的王子，恐怕明天便难逃疾病的魔爪，他的快乐心情再度烟消云散，命令车夫回程，他回到王宫，为自己寻找安慰。他大概又找到了安慰，因为过了几天，他第三次乘坐马车外出游玩。”而这一次，他又看见了一个新鲜事物：他看到一些人肩上扛着什么东西。“那是什么？”“死人。”“死人是什么？”王子问。他被告知，人都会死。王子走向死者的尸体，揭开盖子看了一眼。“他会变成什么样子呢？”他问道。王子被告知，死人将被埋在地下。“为什么？”“因为他永不可能复活，只会变成一堆白骨，身上爬满尸虫。”“所有的人都必须有此下场吗？我也会这样吗？我也会被埋在地下，变成一堆白骨，身上爬满尸虫？”“是的。”“回宫！我再也不想出来游玩了，我再也不会出宫了！”

17.释迦牟尼无法在生命中找到安慰，便认定生命本身乃是大恶，他竭尽心力要让自己和他人摆脱生命。他所期望的摆脱生命的方式是，人死后不会在任何地方重生，只会变成虚无，彻头彻尾的虚无。所有的印度先哲们都这么说。

18.让我们总结一下人类凭借自己的智慧就生命的问题给出的答案。

19.“肉体生命是大恶，是谎言。既然肉体生命的消失是我们的福祉，我们就必然渴望它的消失。”苏格拉底说。

20.“生命原不应如此，可它的确是：罪恶。向着虚无的转化乃是生命中唯一神圣的事。”叔本华说。

21.“世间万事万物，凭它是愚是智、是富是穷、是喜是悲，都是虚空。人死之后，什么也不会留下。此乃荒诞。”所罗门说。

22.“人生来苦难，贫病交加，老迈虚弱，必死无疑，人不能念此而生，必须摆脱生命，摆脱一切可能的生命。”佛说。

23.这些伟人们的所说所想，和成千上万的普通人没有分别。我也曾思考过这些，也有过同样的感觉。

24.就这样，我在知识领域的研读不仅未能让我走出绝望，反而加深了我的绝望。一个分支没有解答生命的问题；另一个分支虽给出了答案，却只是再次印证了我的绝望，向我证明，我得出的结论并非因为选择了歧路，也不是因为我的思想出了问题。相反，它让我坚信，我所想的都是正确的，世间最伟大的智者，得出的结论也不过如此。

25.自欺欺人毫无意义，一切都是虚空。只有从未来到世上之人才会快乐，死亡强于生命，我们必须摆脱生命。

第七章

1.既然在知识领域的考察未能给我一个满意的解释，我便开始在生活中寻找，希望能够在周围的人身上找到答案。我开始观察身边那些像我一样的人如何生活，他们又如何解答这个让我陷入绝望的问题。

2.我发现，那些和我处境相同，也就是所受的教育和生活方式相似的人，也都和我一样，陷入了绝望。

3.我发现在这个生活圏子里，人们用四种方式逃避着人人都会面对的可怕困境。

4.第一种逃避方式是无知，是指看不到或无法理解，生命乃是邪恶和荒诞的。大多数这类人要么是女人，要么是小孩，要么是蠢人，他们尚不能了解叔本华、所罗门抑或佛所面对的问题。既看不到在井底张着大口等待的巨龙，也看不到手中紧紧抓住的灌木树枝几乎被老鼠啃得连根拔起，只是自顾自地享受着蜂蜜的甘甜。不过这种享受不会持续太久，他们总会转而注意到巨龙和老鼠，蜂蜜的甘甜终会变得无味。我从这些人那里学不到任何东西，因为知道了就是知道了，你再也不可能佯装不知，回到从前。

5.第二种逃避方式是享乐主义，是指在了解到生命的绝望境地之后，无视巨龙和老鼠的威胁去享受福祉，悠闲地品味蜂蜜的甘甜，当落在灌木树枝上的蜂蜜很多时尤其如此。所罗门如此描述这种方式：

6.“我就称赞快乐，原来人在日光之下，莫强如吃喝玩乐，因为他在日光之下，神赐他……”[9]

7.“你只管去欢欢喜喜吃你的饭，心中快乐地喝你的酒……同你所爱的妻快活度日，因为那是你生前在日光之下劳碌的事上所得的份额。凡你当做的事，要尽力去做，因为在你所必去的阴间，没有工作，没有谋算，没有知识，也没有智慧。”[10]

8.在我的生活圏子中，绝大多数人都采纳这第二种逃避方式。他们身处其中的优渥条件决定了他们拥有更多更好的生活资料；道德上的麻木令其忘记了自己所有的优越地位都是偶然的，不是每个人都可以像所罗门那样拥有一千嫔妃佳丽和奢华宫殿。如果这世间有一个人拥有一千嫔妃，必定有一千人连平凡糟糠都娶之不得。这世间的每一座奢华宫殿必定是一千个人辛勤劳作、大汗淋漓方能建成，如果你今天能够成为所罗门，那么明天你也同样可能成为所罗门的奴隶。这些人由于缺乏想象力而忘记了为什么佛的内心无法平静：疾病、年迈和死亡都是人无以逃遁的宿命，早晚有一天，它们会将世间所有的享乐化为乌有。其中有一些人认为，其思考的迟钝和想象力的缺乏乃是所谓的“积极哲学”。在我看来，即使这样，他们与前一种人也没有任何差别，虽然前一种人根本看不到问题，而只知享受蜂蜜的甘甜。我无法学这些人的作派，因为我不像他们那样缺乏想象力，也无法将自己伪装成他们的样子。和所有真诚生活的人一样，我一旦看见了老鼠和巨龙，就无法再对其视而不见。

9.第三种逃避方式要诉诸力量。这种方式意识到生命是邪恶和无意义的，就企图摧毁生命，少数强壮而坚定的人就是如此。这类人知道生命是造化跟他们开的一个无比愚蠢的玩笑，意识到死亡的福祉要比活着的福祉大得多，世间最好的事情莫过于放弃生命，便立即付诸行动，不惜使用任何方法在一瞬间结束这种愚蠢的玩笑：围着脖颈缠上绳索、投水、用匕首刺向心脏，抑或卧在铁轨上等待下一辆火车的到来。在我们的生活圏子中，越来越多的人选择这种方式。总的来说，这样行事的人都是在青壮年时期作出这一选择的，那时他们的灵魂充满力量，还没有养成什么摧毁理性的坏习惯。我一度觉得这是最有价值的逃避方式，也企图效仿。

10.第四种逃避方式是软弱，是指即使知道生命没有任何意义，也紧紧抓住这邪恶和徒劳的生命不肯放手。这一类人知道死亡强于生命，却缺乏力量采取理性的行动，通过自杀很快结束这种骗局，他们似乎在等待着什么。这便使之成为一种软弱的逃避方式，因为如果知道世上有更好的东西，又唾手可得，为什么不去顺从自己内心的意愿呢？我自己就属这一类人。

11.就这样，与我同类的人们有四种方式可以将自己拯救出这可怕的困境。我苦思冥想，除了这四种逃避方式之外，再也找不到其他的方式。在第一种方式中，人们未能意识到生命是没有意义、徒劳而邪恶的，未能意识到放弃生命乃是更明智的选择。我既然不可避免地知道了，一旦有此意识，便无法对其视而不见。第二种方法选择利用生命，而不去思考未来，这个我也做不到。和释迦牟尼一样，当我知道了苦难、老迈和死亡的存在，就无法再满心欢喜地外出打猎了。我的想象力太过丰富，再说，某些转瞬即逝的事件或许会让我们的生命有些许快乐，我却不能从中得到安慰。第三种方法是意识到生命的邪恶和荒诞之后，通过自杀结束生命。第四种逃避的方式则是像所罗门和叔本华那样生活，知道生命是某种造化的力量跟我们开的一个愚蠢的玩笑，却仍然继续活着，洗漱、穿衣、吃饭、聊天，甚至还写作。我虽然觉得这样活着既屈辱又痛苦，却仍然保留着这种生活方式。

12.如今我终于明白，当初我之所以没有自杀，是因为我隐约模糊地意识到，自己的观点是错误的。无论我觉得自己的思路多么合理而不可辩驳，抑或那些让我们得出生命毫无意义之结论的想法多么明智，自己一直思虑所得的最终结果到底是否合理，我仍然暗地里有些怀疑。

13.当时的我这样表述这种怀疑：我，亦即我的理性，已经认识到生命是非理性的。如果没有什么高于理性（的确如此，我们无法证明世间有什么东西高于理性），那么在我看来，就是理性创造了我。没有理性，我就没有生命。那么，如果理性本身就是生命的创造者，它又怎么可能否定生命呢？或者换一种说法：如果没有生命，那么理性也就不复存在，这就必然意味着理性乃是生命的产物。生命才是一切。理性只是生命的结果，而这种理性本身却否定了生命。我感觉到，整套思路有一个环节出了问题。

14.我对自己说：生命是毫无意义的邪恶之事，这一点毫无疑问，然而我一直活着且至今仍然活着，全人类也一直活着，且至今仍然活着，这是怎么回事呢？如果能够选择不再活着，人们为什么还活着呢？难道说，只有叔本华和我才有天才的心智，能够理解生命的了无意义和邪恶本质？

15.关于生命乃是虚空的论断并不是什么特别深奥的道理，普通人很久以前就知道这个道理，然而他们却仍然一直活着。怎么可能所有的人都这样活着，而从不考虑生命的逻辑呢？

16.我自己的所知经过了历代先哲的智慧验证，我从中明白，万事万物，无论是有机物还是无机物，其生存秩序都显示出极为非凡的智慧，而只有我自己的处境是荒诞的。然而这些蠢人——广大头脑简单的人，根本不知道什么有机物和无机物在世界上的秩序，却仍然活着，且觉得生命的安排是如此合理！

17.之后我忽然想到，或许有些什么是我自己不知道的。毕竟那正是无知的表现，无知者总是嘟囔着我正在说的这些话——如果无知者不知道什么，他就说他不知道的东西是愚蠢的。无论如何，似乎全人类都一直在生活，至今仍然活着，仿佛它知道生命的意义，因为如果不知道生命的意义它就无法继续存活。而我却在说生命是没有意义的，我无法继续生活下去。

18.没有人阻止叔本华和我放弃生命。去吧，去自杀，那样你就不会再想这些了。如果你不喜欢生命，大可以去自杀。如果你活着而又无法了解生命的意义，就结束生命，而不要到处大放厥词或制造文字垃圾，说什么你不了解生命。你看，周围的人都活得很开心，每个人都非常快乐，知道自己在做什么，所以，如果你觉得生活无聊而不愉快，你就走吧！

19.因为毕竟，如果我们相信自杀是必须的且又无法下定决心结束生命，那么我们难道不是最软弱、最言行不一，或者坦白说，最愚蠢的人吗？嘴里高唱着结束生命的赞歌，却又伴着自己的平庸与生命共舞。

20.毕竟，无论我们是怎样无可辩驳的智者，我们的智慧并未有助于我们了解生命的意义。而成千上万的庸人依然活着，从没有怀疑过生命的意义。

21.的确，自从生命在我一无所知的远古时期开始以来，那些了解生命之虚空的论断的人（在我看来，他们的确证明了生命毫无意义）却活了下来，为生命注入了其独特的意义。自从世界上开始存在某种形式的人类生命以来，人们就一直认定生命是没有意义的，却仍然继续活着，并将生命的薪火传到了我的手上。我体内和我身边的一切都是他们理解生命的结果。我用来判断和谴责生命的思想方法也是由他们，而不是由我本人创造的。因为有了他们，我才来到这个世界上，接受教育，长大成人。他们从地下挖出了铁矿，教会我们如何伐木和驯养牛马，教会我们如何种植庄稼，如何群居。他们创造了一种生活的秩序。他们教会我如何思考，如何说话。我是他们的后代，他们给了我食物和水，给了我教育，让我得以用他们的思想和语言，思考和论道。现在，我却在向他们证明，这一切毫无意义！“一定是某个环节出了问题，”我对自己说，“我的某一个推论一定是错误的。”然而我却不知道究竟是哪一个环节出了问题。

第八章

1.如今我已经能够比较清晰连贯地说出这些疑虑了，而当时我却根本说不清它们是什么。当时我只是觉得，尽管我关于生命的虚空本质的推断在逻辑上有其必然性，也经过了许多伟大思想家的验证，却仍然存在问题。我不知道是自己的推理过程有漏洞，还是我对生命问题的陈述不够严密，只是觉得自己在得出结论之前的推理过程虽然完整，却仍然不够充分。所有这些结论都未能说服我服从自己的论证逻辑——选择自杀。如果我说，我是通过自己的理性达到了那样一种状态而没有选择自杀，那一定是在说谎。我的理性仍然在起作用，但是同时起作用的还有其他东西，我只能称之为一种“生命意识”。当时似乎有另一种力量在起作用，它让我更多地关注这种生命意识而非理性。正是这种力量让我走出了自己的绝望状态，将我的理性引向一个截然不同的方向。它促使我关注一个事实，那就是我，以及成百上千和我一样的其他人，并非人类的全部，而我也并不知道全人类的生活是什么样。

2.看看我自己的四周，也就是我的同事们那个狭小的圏子。这些人要么浑浑噩噩，要么寻欢作乐，要么自我终结，要么绝望等待。除此之外，我看不到其他的生活方式。我起初以为这个学者的小圏子，和我的生活圏子中有钱、有名望的这些人便构成了整个人类，而那些一直活着、至今仍然活着的数以千百万计的人们只是“他们”，类似于某种牲口，是庸常麻木的“人们”。

3.如今想来真是奇怪，也完全不可理解，那时我对生活的理性思考中，竟完全无视周围所有人的生活。我竟如此荒谬而错误地认为，我自己的生活，以及所罗门和叔本华的生活，才是真实而正常的生活，而那些数百万平庸人的生活则根本不值一提。无论今天看来多么奇怪，这些的确是我当时真实的想法。在我骄傲地无目的地思考的过程中，我认定所罗门、叔本华和我本人非常诚实而准确地提出了生命的问题，就这个问题来说，不可能再有第二条道路。我非常肯定地认为，那些数百万普通人根本未曾深入该问题的实质，在我为自己寻找生命的意义时，我从来没有问过自己：“那数百万一直活着、如今仍然活在世上的人，他们又如何让自己的生命有意义呢？”

4.很长一段时间，我就生活在这样一种疯狂的状态中。那是更激进、受过更多教育的人们较为典型的状态，如果他们大多数尚未付诸行动，起码在语言上如此。然而或许是因为我对真正的劳动人民有一种多少有些奇怪却出自天然的喜爱，迫使我去理解他们，意识到他们并非我们所想的那样愚昧无知，或许是因为我认定自己除了自杀之外无事可做的信念非常诚实，我觉得无论如何，如果我希望继续活着并了解生命的意义的话，就不能够在那些已经失去生命或希望自杀的人们身上寻找，而应该看看那些创造过生命且愿意为自己和他人的生命负责的人，无论他们仍然活着还是已经逝去。于是我环顾四周，仔细观察简朴的普通大众，他们多半没受过什么教育，也没有钱，却一直活着且仍在活着，我看到了全然不同的东西。除了少数例外情况，那数百万普通人并不适合我的分类，不能够把他们简单地归类为不理解生命问题的人，因为他们自己非常清楚地提出并回答了那个有关生命的问题。我也无法将他们归类为享乐主义者，因为在他们的生活中，匮乏和苦难远远多于富足和快乐。我更不能将他们看作是非理性地继续自己无意义的生活的人，因为他们可以清楚地解释自己生活中的每一个行为，包括死亡。他们认为，自杀是最大的恶。看来，整个人类有其理解生命意义的方式，我自己不知道那种方式，反而还嘲笑他们。也就是说，理性的知识未能为生命注入意义，反而让生命失去了意义；而数百万普通人——整个人类——所赋予生命的意义，其所依据的知识却一直遭到我们的鄙视，被认定为谬误。

5.所谓的学者和智者们制造出来的理性知识否定了生命的意义，而大众——构成整个人类的普通大众——认识到，生命的意义就存在于非理性的知识中。这种非理性的知识就是信仰，那正是我曾经禁不住鄙视和放弃的东西：三位一体的上帝、六天创世说、魔鬼和天使，乃至所有曾经令我无法接受、令我抓狂的东西。

6.我的处境非常可怕。我终于知道，在理性知识的道路上我一无所获，只能不断否定生命。而在信仰中，我只能看到对理性的否定，对我来说，这要比否定生命更为艰难。根据理性的知识，生命是邪恶的，人们知道这一点。他们可以选择结束生命，却总是选择继续活着；正如我自己，尽管很久以前便已清楚地知道生命是邪恶而没有意义的，却仍然继续活着。而根据信仰得出的结论是，为了理解生命的意义我必须放弃理性，唯有理性才让人有必要寻找意义。

第九章

1.一个矛盾产生了，摆脱这个矛盾的出路只有两条：要么我称之为理性的东西并非如我所想的那般理智，要么我以前看来非理性的东西并非我自己认为的那样毫无理智。我开始检验源自理性知识的论证过程。

2.我检验了这一论证过程，发现它是完全正确的，“生命就是虚空”是这一论证的必然结论。不过我发现了一个错误，那就是我的思考过程与我提出的问题并不对应。问题是：我为什么活着？或者，在这虚幻而转瞬即逝的一生中，有没有什么东西可以永恒而不会被人们彻底遗忘？再或者，在一个无限的宇宙中，我有限的生命存在的意义是什么？为了回答这个问题，我开始了对生命的探索。

3.目前已有的对所有可能的生命问题的解答显然无法令我满意，因为我的问题，无论乍看之下多么简单，都需要通过无限对有限作出解释，或者反过来，需要通过有限对无限作出解释。

4.我的问题是：“超越时空和因果循环的生命究竟有何意义？”而我试图回答的问题是：“在时空和因果循环中，我的生命有何意义？”结果，无论经过多长时间，无论我怎样绞尽脑汁地思考，都只能回答：“没有意义。”

5.在思考过程中，我总是在有限和有限之间进行比较，在无限和无限之间进行比较，也不可能另寻他途。因此我所能得到的唯一结论就是：力量就是力量，问题就是问题，意志就是意志，无限就是无限，虚空就是虚空。我无法超越这些，走得更远。

6.这有点像在数学里为求解一个方程式而得到一个恒等式。推断的方法是正确的，然而得到的唯一答案却是a等于a, x等于x，0等于0。我关于生命意义问题的推理过程就出现了这样的问题。科学就此问题所给能出的答案无非就是一堆恒等式。

7.的确，严格遵循理性的知识，如笛卡尔的知识，都是从彻底怀疑一切、否定基于信仰的一切知识开始的，它根据理性和实验的规律重建世界。这样所得出的答案无非就是我已得到的那个答案：含混模糊、悬而未决。只有在最初，我才认为知识给出了一个肯定的答案，也就是叔本华的答案，生命是邪恶而没有意义的。但是一经深入研究那个问题，我立即意识到这个答案并不是肯定的最终答案，只是我自己想当然地这样认为。严格地说，尽管那是文人雅士们、所罗门和叔本华提出的答案，它仍然是一个模糊的恒等式：0等于0，我所面对的虚空的生命就是虚空。因此，哲学知识并没有否定什么，只是回答说它无法解决问题，因为就哲学所能及的范围，任何答案都是含混模糊的。

8.了解这一点之后，我意识到无法通过理性知识回答自己所提出的问题；理性知识所给出的答案无非就是指出：要回答这个问题，就只能以另一种方式重复问题、只能通过引入有限和无限的关系问题。我意识到，无论信仰给出的答案看上去是多么缺乏理性的谬论，它们的优势就在于，每一个答案都回答了有限和无限的关系问题，否则就根本不可能有答案。无论我以何种方式提出这个问题：“我应该如何活着？”答案永远都是：“根据上帝的旨意活着。”或者这个问题：“我的生命中有没有什么东西是真实的？”答案就会是：“永恒的折磨或永恒的福祉。”再或者这个问题：“有没有一种意义是无法被死亡所摧毁的？”答案是：“融入无限、上帝和天堂。”

9.因此除了理性知识（到此为止我一直认为那是唯一的知识）之外，我必然最终意识到，的确存在着另外一种知识——非理性的知识——为全人类所拥有。那就是信仰，人类之所以活着，就是因为他们有信仰。此前在我看来，信仰一直是非理性的，但是我终于意识到，只有信仰，才能为人们提出的生命问题找到答案，让人们继续自己的生命。

10.理性知识最终让我意识到生命是没有意义的。我的生命骤然停止，我想自杀。当我看向四周，看向整个人类，我发现他们活着，且肯定地认为自己了解生命的意义。我又低头看了看我自己，只有当我知道了生命的意义，我才能够继续活着。在我看来，和其他人一样，信仰让我们的生命拥有了意义。有了信仰，我们才有可能继续生活。

11.我进而看向其他国家的人们，看向我同时代的人和先辈们，并有了同样的发现。有生命的地方就必然有信仰。自开天辟地以来，正是信仰赋予了人类生存的可能。所有信仰最基本的方面永远都是一样的，无论在哪个国家。

12.无论信仰给出的答案如何，无论是哪一种信仰，或者信仰所要回答的问题是谁提出的，这些问题永远为人类有限的存在提供了一种无限的意义，那种意义无法被苦难、匮乏或死亡所摧毁。这表明，只有在信仰中，我们才能找到意义，才能继续生活。我意识到，信仰最根本的意义不仅仅在于“表现从没有人看见过的东西”，也不仅仅在于神圣的启示（这只是在描述信仰存在的一种迹象）；它也不仅仅表述了人与上帝的关系（我们必须先定义信仰，之后才能定义上帝，而不能通过信仰定义上帝）；也不仅仅是人全盘接受自己听到的东西，尽管一直以来，人们普遍觉得信仰就是如此。信仰是一种有关人类生命意义的知识，信仰的结果就是，人不会自杀，而只能活着。信仰是生命的力量。如果一个人活着，他就必须有所信，如果他不相信有什么让他必须活着，他就不会继续活着了。如果他看不到也不能够理解有限的虚幻，他就会信仰有限，如果他理解了有限的虚幻，他就一定会信仰无限。没有信仰，人类就不可能生存。

13.我回忆起自己之前在内心深处思考的整个过程，不禁吓出一身冷汗。如今我清楚地意识到，人们要想生存，要么根本意识不到无限的存在，要么能够以某种方式对生命的意义作出解释，使有限等同于无限。我虽作出了这样的解释，但在我相信有限时，这个解释对我毫无用处，于是我开始通过理性来验证它。根据理性，我之前的解释全都烟消云散。后来我不再信仰有限，便开始在理性的基础上，通过我的所知去构建一个可能赋予生命意义的解释，但我最终一无所获。结合最伟大的人类智慧，我得出了0等于0的结论，这样的结论让我无比震惊，且当时的我觉得，根本不可能有其他结论。

14.在实验科学中寻找答案意味着什么呢？我希望了解自己为什么活着，于是去研究存在于我本身之外的一切。我显然能够获得许多发现，却没有一个是我需要的。

15.在哲学领域寻找答案又意味着什么呢？我研究了那些自己也陷入过同样困境的人们的思想，他们对于“我们为什么活着”这个问题没有给出任何答案。显然，我在这里得到的发现无非就是我已经知道，“我们不可能了解世界”。

16.我是什么？是无限中的一部分。问题就在这几个字当中。人们难道最近才看出这个问题吗？有没有可能，在我之前根本没有人提出过这个问题，尽管它如此简单，乃至一个无知的懵懂少年也会在不经意间顺嘴说出？

17.当然不是，事实上自从人类在地球上生存的那一天起，这个问题就已经被提出了。一开始，通过将有限等同于有限来解决这个问题显然不会令人满意，将无限等同于无限也是一样。自古以来，人类就一直力图表达有限与无限之间的关系。

18.所有我们用来比较有限和无限，借此理解生命的概念，或者上帝、自由和良善等概念，人们都力图用逻辑进行验证，但它们根本经不起理性的批判。

19.多么可怕，或者多么可笑，我们这样骄傲和自负，像淘气的孩子，拆开手表，去除发条，把手表变成玩具，然后看到手表不走了，竟然还现出一脸的惊奇。

20.我们必须解决有限和无限之间的矛盾，这是非常重要的，这才是生命问题的答案，找到了这个答案，我们才有可能活着。无论在哪里，所有的人给出的解决方案，无非是那个亘古流传的答案，那是一个非常难以理解的答案，我们自己根本不可能得出类似的答案。于是人们随意推翻这个答案，之后又再次提出那个人人必须面对的问题，而对这个问题，我们又没有自己的答案。

21.万能的上帝、灵魂的圣洁、上帝与俗务的关系、道德上的善恶，所有这些概念都是在历史中，通过我们看不见的人类生活得出的概念。没有这些概念，就根本不可能有生命，也不可能有我自己的存在，然而我竟然轻易否定了人类所有的努力，妄图单枪匹马，以我自己的方式将一切推倒重来。

22.当时我并没有想到这些，但是这些思想已经在我的头脑中生根发芽了。我意识到：（1）尽管叔本华、所罗门和我都是智者，却都犯下了愚蠢的错误——我们认为生命是邪恶的，却仍然继续活着。这显然是愚蠢的，因为如果生命毫无意义，我又这般喜爱理性，那么我必然要摧毁生命，这样就没有谁能够否认我的结论了。（2）我们所有的论证构成了一个恶性循环，就像一个没有附着在马车上的轮子。无论我们没日没夜地进行了多么严谨的思考，都找不到问题的答案，因为0永远等于0，因此，一定是我们使用的方法错了。（3）人类最深邃的智慧存在于信仰给出的答案中，我自己没有权力基于理性否定那些答案，毕竟，那些才是唯一解答了生命问题的答案。

第十章

1.我虽看到了这一点，但问题并没有因此而变得简单。

2.现在我开始准备接受信仰，只要它不要求我直接否定理性。如今看来，这未免虚伪。因此我开始研读关于佛教和伊斯兰教的书籍，当然我接触最多的还是基督教，通过基督教的著述和我周围的人们，我对它有了更深的研究。

3.我最先接触的，自然是我自己生活圏子里的信徒、有学问的人、东正教神学家、德高望重的僧侣、最新式东正教的神学家，甚至通过关于救赎的信仰来教授神学的所谓新基督教徒。我抓住这些信徒，询问他们如何信仰，又如何理解生命的意义。

4.无论我怎样宽容地接受他们的说法，避免一切争论，我仍然无法接受这些人的信仰。我发现他们所谓的信仰根本不能够对生命的意义作出任何解释，而只能使之变得模糊，他们本人根本就不是为了解答生命的问题（那个使我转向信仰的生命问题）才拥有信仰，而是出于我不知道的其他原因。

5.我记得自己当时整日受到恐惧的煎熬，害怕在这么多次满怀希望地与这类人结交之后，再次回到之前的绝望境地。他们越是精确地向我表述自己的教义，我就越清楚地看到他们的错误，直到最后我彻底绝望了，意识到自己根本不可能在他们的信仰中找到任何关于生命意义的解释。

6.我之所以放弃希望，并不完全是因为他们在表述自己的宗教信仰时，将我一直视为至宝的基督教真理与那些不必要、非理性的东西混淆在一起，而是因为，这些人的生活和我自己一模一样，唯一的区别就是他们根本不按照其教义所表述的那些原则生活。我强烈地感觉到，他们只是在自欺欺人，和我一样，他们对生活没有什么想法，只是为活着而活着，及时行乐而已。我能够看到这一点，是因为如果他们真正了解生命的意义，能够驱散对贫困、苦难和死亡的恐惧的话，就不会害怕这些了。然而我们这个阶层的信徒们像我一样过着富足的生活，并始终力图保有和增加自己的财富和地位，对贫困、苦难和死亡充满了恐惧。和我自己以及所有非信徒一样，他们活着只是为了满足自己的欲望，这样的生活不但不比非信徒优越多少，可能还不如非信徒。

7.无论这些人怎样争辩，我都不相信他们是真正的信徒。只有当他们用行动向我证明，他们理解生命，因而不再像我一样惧怕贫困、疾病和死亡，我才可能相信他们。但我在自己生活圏子里的信徒身上看不到这些。就这样，我从没有在所谓的信徒身上看到这些，反而常常在那个圏子里的非信徒身上看到这样的做派。

8.我意识到，这些人所拥有的信仰根本不是我追求的信仰，他们的信仰并非真正的信仰，而只是享乐主义者在生活中找到的安慰而已。我知道，这种信仰即使不能成为某种安慰，或许也能够让悔过的所罗门在临死前不再为生前的所为懊恼不已，然而它完全不适合大多数人，大多数人根本没有机会将自己的快乐建立在他人的辛勤劳作之上，而不过是在谋生度日。为了生活并将生命一直继续下去，为生命注入意义，数百万人必须拥有某种全然不同的、更加真实和纯粹的信仰观。的确，让我坚信这世上一定有信仰存在的，并不是我本人抑或所罗门抑或叔本华没有自杀，而是这数百万人一直活着且依旧活在世上，生活和挣扎在所罗门和我这类人的底层。

9.我开始接近那些穷苦、朴素、没有受过教育的信仰者：虔诚香客、僧侣、教派人士和农民。这些人和我所在的生活圏子中那些伪信徒一样，都信仰基督教。他们也在基督教真理中掺杂了大量迷信，然而不同的是，对于我的生活圏子中的信徒而言，迷信是完全不必要的。与他们的生活没有任何关系，而只是为他们提供了某种享乐主义的消遣，而对于劳动阶层的信仰者而言，迷信是他们生活中必不可少的一部分。他们无法想象没有迷信的生活，那是他们生活的必要条件。在我自己的生活圏子中，信徒们的整个生活方式与他们的信仰截然对立，而劳动阶层的信仰者们用其全部的生活方式验证了信仰赋予其生活的意义。我开始更仔细地观察这些人的生活和信仰，观察越深入，就越坚信他们的信仰才是真正的信仰，信仰是他们生命中不可或缺的元素，信仰本身就为他们的生命注入了意义，让他们的生命得以延续下去。我在自己的阶层看到的人们完全可以没有信仰地生活，一千个人中也没有一个能够坦然承认自己是真正的信徒，那些人则相反，一千个人中也很难有一个没有信仰。我在自己的生活圏子中看到的人们一生都在享乐中虚度却仍对生活充满抱怨，而那些人一生辛勤劳作，却并不像富人对生活有种种不满。我们这个阶层的人们，一旦有求而不能得便反抗和诅咒，愤恨命运的不公，那些人却能够毫无怨言地接受一切贫病和苦难，那么安然地坚信一切都是注定的，不可改变，且必然能够带来福祉。我们这些自诩为聪明智慧的人并不十分了解生命的意义，一旦面临苦难和死亡，便说那是造物主的一个恶作剧，那些人则截然相反，他们宁静地生活、无言地受苦，在走向死亡时安静平和且往往心中充满喜悦。在我们生活的圏子中，一般不会有人平静地走向死亡，人们总是对死亡充满了恐惧和绝望，那些人则截然相反，他们中很少有人因为人之将死而备受煎熬，奋力反抗并郁郁而终。这世上有数百万这样的人，他们一无所有——在所罗门和我这样的人看来那些所有是生命唯一的福祉和意义——却仍然生活得无比快乐。我将观察的目光投向更远处，看到无数生灵活过往昔，仍然在继续生活。理解生命意义的人数并非两三个抑或十来个，而是几百个、几千个、几百万个。所有的人，尽管他们的习惯、思想、教育和社会地位截然不同，却全然不似我这般无知，他们了解生命和死亡的意义，忍受着苦难和煎熬。从生到死，他们并不觉得一切都是虚空，反而认定那是一条向善之路。

10.于是我逐渐爱上了那些人。我越深入地研究自己阅读或听说过的生者和死者的故事，就越热爱他们，也就越容易继续生活下去。像这样生活了大约两年之后，我的思想发生了巨大变化，就仿佛我一直都在等待着这一变化，又好像这种变化的根基始终深植于我的生命中。这一变化就是，我所在阶层的生活，财富和知识，不仅让我厌恶，并且失去了一切意义。我们所有的活动、讨论、科学和艺术在我眼中都变成了纯粹的放任纵容。我意识到，在这样的生活中找不到任何意义。而劳动阶层、那些创造了生命的人的活动，在我看来成了唯一真实而有意义的生活方式。我意识到，这样的生活所呈现的意义才是真理，我欣然接受这样的真理。

第十一章

1.同样是信仰，但我至今仍然记得，当我看到拥有信仰的人们的所作所为却与之背道而驰时，这些信仰让我感到多么厌恶，似乎没有任何意义。而一旦看到那些真正遵照信仰生活的人们，它又对我充满了吸引力，显得明智通达。我终于明白自己为什么一度抛弃了信仰，觉得它毫无意义，现在又全身心地接受了它，觉得它充满了意义。我终于明白，自己曾一度迷失，并且知道自己为什么会迷失。我之所以迷路，不是因为我的思想错误，而是我生活的方式是愚蠢的。我意识到，自己之所以过去看不到这一真理，与其说是被错误的思想蒙住了双眼，不如说是我的生活本身阻隔了通往真理的道路，我过去一直在竭尽全力地满足自己的各种欲望，那是纯粹享乐主义的生活。意识到自己关于生命是什么的问题，乃至关于生命充满邪恶的答案，都十分正确。唯一的错误是，那本是一个只和我自己有关的答案，我却妄图用它来解释整个人类的生命。我对自己提出的问题是：我的生命是什么；答案是，它是邪恶而毫无意义的，这完全正确，因为我沉迷于享乐的追求，的确邪恶而毫无意义，但是这样的答案只适合我自己，不适合全人类。我发现了一条真理，且随后就在《福音书》上找到了这条真理：当人在从事邪恶的行为时，他们往往更喜欢黑暗而不是光明；因为从事恶行的人憎恶光并竭力避免光，生怕自己的行为彰显于光天化日之下。我意识到，为了解生命的本质，生命首先不应该是邪恶而毫无意义的，只有这样，人们才能真正运用理性来阐述这个问题。我终于明白了自己为什么长期在这样一个显而易见的真理附近徘徊却看不到它，我终于明白，要想思考和阐述人类的生命，我们必须思考和阐述整个人类的生命，而不是少数几个寄生虫的生命。真理始终是真理，就像2×2=4一样简单直白，但我们不肯承认这样简单的真理，因为一旦承认了2×2=4，我就不得不承认自己是一个恶人。对我来说，认为自己是一个好人要比承认2×2=4更为重要也更加必要。我开始热爱良善的人们并憎恶自己，我开始承认真理，一切便昭然若揭。

2.想象一下，一个刽子手一生都在对他人行刑，砍掉人们的头颅，一个无望的酒鬼或疯子穷其一生都生活在一间黑暗的屋子里，他虽憎恶这间黑屋，却又害怕一旦离开了黑屋，便会面临死亡——想象一下，如果这样的人问自己：“生命是什么？”他们能够得到的唯一答案显然就是：“生命是万恶中的大恶。”疯子的回答或许绝对正确，但那只是关于他自己生命的答案。假如我是这样一个疯子呢？假如所有拥有财富和学识的人全都是这样的疯子呢？

3.我意识到我们的确是这样一群疯子，起码我自己是个疯子。的确，造物主创造鸟儿便让它们飞上蓝天，收集食物并在树上筑巢，每当我看到鸟儿做这些事的时候，总是感到快乐和欣喜。山羊、野兔和狼来到世上就是为了寻找食物、繁衍后代、喂养幼兽，每看到它们如此行事，我总是确信它们非常快乐，它们的生命充满意义。那么人应该做什么呢？他也必须像动物们一样为生存而努力劳作，不同的是，为了生存他无法单枪匹马地劳作，他的劳作不仅仅为了他自己的生存，也为了整个人类的生存。如果人能如此行事，我确信他的生命是快乐而有意义的。而我在过去三十年有意识的生命中又做了些什么？我非但没有为整个人类的生存而劳作，甚至没有为我自己的生存而劳作。我像寄生虫那样活着，难怪当我问自己为什么活着时会得到这样的回答：“不为什么。”如果人类生存的意义在于用劳作来维系生命，那么我过去三十年的生活不但没有努力维系生命，反而是在毁灭自己和他人的生命。如此一来，我得到的答案当然只能是：“生命是邪恶而毫无意义的。”它的确是邪恶而毫无意义的。

4.整个世界的生命依靠的是某人的意志，我们自己乃至万事万物的生命依靠的却是另一些人的双手。为了能够了解那种意志，我们首先必须行本分之事，满足那种意志。如果我拒绝行本分之事，就永远不可能了解我们注定的本分之事是什么，更不可能了解造物主对于整个人类乃至整个世界的安排。

5.如果一个衣衫褴褛、饥饿潦倒的乞丐被主人从十字街头带到辉煌宫殿的一隅，主人给了他食物和水，之后让他去上下移动一处手柄，显然，在弄清楚自己为什么被带至这里移动手柄之前，在弄清楚这处宫殿的结构是否合理之前，乞丐必须先顺从主人的意志，移动手柄。移动手柄之后，他会看到那是一个水泵装置，水泵从井里抽出水，水流入花园。之后他又被带离宫殿的这一隅，得到了另一份工作，他在那里采摘水果，并顺从主人的意志行事。随着他的任务越来越高级，他会越来越了解整座宫殿的结构并参与其中，他永远不会停止询问自己在哪里，也永远不会责怪那个把他带到宫殿来的主人。

6.同样，那些头脑简单、行为朴素、没有受过教育的劳动阶级——我们总是称之为一群乌合之众——就顺从着主人的意志，从不责怪主人把他们带到这个世界上。而我们这些所谓的智者，吃了主人的食物却不按主人的吩咐做事，反而聚在一堆儿争论：“聪明如我们，怎么能做移动手柄这样愚蠢的活儿呢？”于是我们苦思冥想，认定要么是主人愚蠢，要么根本没有什么主人，我们是世上唯一的智者。只是后来，我们会觉得自己一无所长，必须以某种方式逃避自己，才能从这种苦恼中解脱出来。

第十二章

1.意识到理性知识的错误后，我更容易摆脱徒劳理论解释的诱惑。因为坚信有关真理的知识只能从生命中获得，我开始怀疑自己以往生活方式的价值。让我获救的，是我终于将自己从闭塞孤立的生活中解脱出来，看到朴素的劳动阶层真实的生活，并意识到只有这种生活才是真实的生活。我意识到如果我希望了解生命及其意义，就必须过上真实的生活，而不是做一个寄生虫；既然我已经接受了真正的人类所赋予生命的意义——他们正是真实生活的一部分——我就必须阐述它、验证它。

2.那时我的经历是这样的：在一整年的时间里，几乎每一分钟我都在问自己，是不是应该用一根绳子或一颗子弹结束自己的生命。就在我思考着上述想法和观察结果时，我的心灵却在经受着巨大的折磨。至于这种折磨是什么，我只能称之为“对上帝的求索”。

3.我觉得这种对上帝的求索并不是一种拷问，而是一种情感上的诉求，因为它并非来源于我的头脑，事实上它与思考的过程恰恰相反，而是来自于我的心灵。那是一种被遗弃的恐惧和孤独之感，所有那一切对我而言都非常陌生，另一方面我又隐隐感受到希望——有人能够给我以帮助的希望。

4.尽管我坚信无法证实上帝的存在（康德已经向我证明了这一点，我完全理解那是无法证明的），我仍然在寻找上帝，希望能够找到他。我重拾原有的祈祷习惯，开始对着那个我一直在找寻却无法看到的上帝祈祷。我在自己的头脑中重温了康德和叔本华关于无法证明上帝存在的争论，并开始驳斥那些争论。我对自己说，原因是与时空并不在同一个思考范畴。如果我存在，那就一定有一个存在的理由，这个理由的存在也有一个理由。万事万物存在的理由就是我们所谓的上帝。我执着于这一想法，全身心地承认这一理由的存在。一旦我承认了在自己之上还有一个强大的力量存在，我立刻感受到了生命的可能性。然而我问自己：“这个理由、这个力量究竟是什么？应该如何看待它？我为何应该将这种力量与上帝联系起来？”而浮现在我脑海中的只有那些熟悉的答案：“他乃造物主，无所不在。”这些答案无法让我满意，我觉得自己内心仍然缺乏生存所必需的力量。我陷入绝望，开始对着那个我苦苦追寻的人祈祷，希望他能够帮助我。我越是祈祷，就越清楚他根本听不到我的祈祷，事实上我根本无处求助。我满心悲伤地发现，在我的上方根本没有那个力量，没有上帝，我哭喊道：“主啊，发发慈悲吧。救救我！哦，主啊，请在冥冥中给我以指引吧！”然而没有人发慈悲帮助我，我觉得生命就此走向了尽头。

5.然而我总是一再地从不同的角度得出同样的结论，那就是我来到这个世界上一定有着某种理由、某种原因或某种意义。我不可能像自己感觉的那样，是一只从鸟巢掉落到地上的羽翼未丰的鸟儿。如果我真的像幼鸟那样哭着落在了草丛中，那是因为我知道妈妈把我带到这个世界上，给我温暖、喂我食物，全身心地爱着我。但是妈妈，她在哪里？如果我是一只被抛弃的幼鸟，又是谁将我抛弃？我无法无视这样的事实，那就是给我生命的人一定是爱我的。此人是谁？同样，又是上帝。

6.“上帝知道，也看到了我的追寻、挣扎和悲苦。他的的确确是存在的。”我对自己说。每一次，在我承认这一点的那一瞬间，内心就会燃起生命之光，立刻感受到活着的可能和乐趣。不过同样，一旦承认了上帝的存在，我就开始继续探求我与他的关系；同样，我所追寻的那个上帝，这个世界的造物主，总是三位一体的，他将自己的儿子派到人间，那是我们的救世主。同样，这位将我和世界区分开来的上帝将在我的眼前冰融消逝，让我再次感到眼前虚空一片，体内燃起的那一点生命之光也瞬间熄灭了。我陷入绝望，感到除了自杀之外已经别无出路。最糟的是，我觉得自己连自杀的勇气也没有了。

7.无数次，我的情绪在一瞬间从欢乐和热情转为绝望，就在那一瞬间，我感到自己根本无法继续生存下去。

8.我还记得在一个早春，我独自一人来到森林。我在那里倾听着，集中精力思考着自己过去三年一直有意识地思考的问题。我还在寻找上帝。

9.“那么好吧，”我自言自语道，“那就是说，世界上根本没有上帝，上帝只是我想象出来的，唯一真实的是我自己的生命。没有上帝，也不可能出现奇迹证明上帝的存在，因为那只是我的想象，既然是想象，就不是理性的。”

10.“那么我苦苦求索的有关上帝的想法呢？”我问自己，“这个想法到底源于何处？”同样，每当我这样想问题的时候，体内就升腾起一种欢乐的情绪，周围的一切有了生机，充满意义。然而快乐无法持续很久。我的思绪会继续。“关于上帝的想法并非上帝本身，”我对自己说，“关于上帝的想法只是我随心所欲杜撰的。我求索的不是这个，我求索的是那个将生命带到世间的上帝。”我自己体内和周围万物的生机和生命力再度熄灭，我又想自杀了。

11.但是我随即停住，仔细审视了自己，以及体内的情绪。我记得有几百次，生命之光从我的体内熄灭之后又再度燃起，我只有在坚信上帝的时候才是活着的，那时，和现在一样，我对自己说：我只有相信上帝才能继续活着。如果不再相信他，或者忘记他，我就会立刻死去。这些死亡而后重生的过程究竟是什么呢？显然，一旦我不再相信上帝的存在，就无法继续生活，如果没有心底里隐约出现的能够找到上帝的希望，我在很久以前就已经自杀了。我只有清楚地意识到上帝并寻找他的时候才能存活。“那么你寻找的究竟是什么呢？”一个声音在我的体内高喊道。“那就是上帝！没有他，人类就不可能继续存活。了解上帝和存活是同一回事，上帝就是生命。”

12.“活着就是为了寻找上帝，如果没有上帝，世上就没有生命！”刹那间，我发现自己的体内和周围的万事万物燃起了比以往任何时候都更加强烈的生命之光，从那以后，这一束光辉就再也没有熄灭。

13.就这样，我没有自杀，我得救了。我无法确切地说出这样的变化是什么时候发生、如何发生的。就在我体内的生命力不为人知地逐渐熄灭时，就在我开始感受到生命的不可能性、感受到生命已经在我的体内静止的时候。我需要自杀时，这种生命力同样不为人知地在我的体内逐渐悄然升起。奇怪的是，重新回到我体内的生命力并非什么新鲜事物，而恰是我年轻时吸引过我的东西。我重新捡拾起自己童年和青年时代视之为生命的一部分的东西。我重新相信那种给予我生命并要求我顺从的意志的存在。我重新认为，生命中最最重要的目标乃是完善自我，也就是顺从这种意志生活。我重新坚信，我可以通过一直潜伏于自己体内的某种事物证明这种意志的存在，那是人类在很久以前就已经找到，用于指引前路的东西。换句话说，我开始重新相信上帝，相信道德完善、相信那种赋予生命意义的传统。唯一的区别是，过去我是无意识地接受这一切，而如今我知道，没有这样的信仰，我便无法生活下去。

14.我当时的情况基本上可以这样描述：我在自己未知的情况下，登上了一条已经启航驶向未知的彼岸的小船。有人给我指出彼岸的方向，将船桨塞入我这个毫无经验的舵手手中，接着就抛下我，留下我独自一人。我尽自己最大的努力划桨前行，然而我越是朝着激流的中心划去，湍急的河流就越把我推向离目标更远的地方。我开始遇到越来越多和我一样的划手，他们也正在被湍流带离目标。有些孤独的划手继续驾舟航行，有些人则早已扔掉了双桨。河里有大一些的船只和满载乘客的大轮船，有些人仍在与激流抗争，其他人早已随波逐流。我看着那些顺水而下的漂浮的小船，发现自己越是奋力划桨，就越是忘记了自己曾一度知晓的方向。就在激流的中央，在许多顺流而下的小船和巨轮中间，我迷失了方向，也丢掉了手中的双桨。四面八方的人们都被船帆或船桨带着顺流而下，他们欢乐地高喊着，安慰着我和他们自己：“本来就只有这一个方向！”我相信了他们，与他们一起顺流直下。我随波逐流了很长时间，几乎已经能够听到那注定要将我毁灭的湍滩，看到了已经被它们撞成碎片的小船。就在那时我忽然醒悟过来。很长一段时间，我不知道自己怎么了。除了正在朝之疾驶而去的毁灭之外，我看不到前路上还有其他希望，但是我害怕毁灭，举目四望，竟也看不到任何救赎，茫然不知所措。但是回头望去，我看到无数船只虽无法停下却坚持不懈地与激流抗争，我忽然忆起自己的船桨和彼岸的方向，也开始挣扎着逆流而上，向彼岸划去。

15.彼岸就是上帝，方向就是传说，船桨就是让我向着彼岸划去与上帝团聚的自由。就这样，我心底里重新拥有了生命的力量，我又开始了新的生活。

第十三章

1.我唾弃自己所在阶层的生活，因为我已经意识到，那根本不是生活而只是像生活而已，我们赖以生活的奢华使我们根本无法了解生活。我知道，要想真正了解生活，必须了解的不是我们这些少数寄生虫的生活，而是朴素的劳动阶层的生活，以及他们赋予生活的意义。我周围的普通劳动阶层就是俄国人民，我将目光转向他们，开始观察他们赋予生活的意义。我试着这样描述这种意义：每个人通过上帝的意志来到这个世界上；上帝创造了人，每个人自行选择毁灭或拯救自己的灵魂。人生的目的就在于拯救自己的灵魂；为了拯救自己的灵魂，人必须按照上帝的旨意生活。

2.为了按照上帝的旨意生活，人必须放弃生命中所有的享受，劳作、谦卑、经受苦难而心怀仁慈。这就是人们从所有宗教教义中获得的意义，它由一代代牧师继承下来并教给他们，那些传统已经构成了他们生命的一部分，他们用故事、谚语和传说来表达这样的意义。现在，我清楚地看到了它，并全身心地接受这样的意义。然而，除了根植于劳动人民信仰中的这种意义之外，还有许多与我生活于其中的非教派人士密不可分的东西，令我感到厌恶和不可理解：圣礼圣餐、教会仪式、斋戒，以及在各种遗迹和肖像前面鞠躬等。人们无法将一件事和另一件事彻底区分开来，我也一样不能。无论我觉得人们的信仰中有多少奇怪的东西，仍然选择了全盘接受，参加各种仪式，每天早晚祈祷、斋戒、领圣餐。生平第一次，我的理性没有提出任何异议。之前让我觉得全无可能的事情如今却没有什么可反驳的——我如今对信仰的态度与以往完全不同了。从前，生命似乎充满了意义，信仰似乎就是人们企图主观证实各种完全没有必要也没有理性的命题，这些命题与生命本身毫无关系。那时我问自己，这些命题究竟有什么意义？我坚信它们没有任何意义，就将它们抛在一边。现在则相反，我非常清楚地知道，生命没有也不可能有任何意义。不仅信仰的教条在我看来不再是完全没有必要的东西，我也经由无可辩驳的经验而坚信，只有那些信条才能赋予生命意义。从前，我觉得那些东西就是与我毫无关系的天书，而现在，即使我知道自己仍然不能理解，却明白其中蕴含着意义，并告诫自己必须学着了解那些意义。

3.我作了下面的推论。我对自己说，与人及其理性思维能力一样，对信仰的认知也有一个神秘的来源。那个来源就是上帝，是人类头脑和身体的源头。就像我的身体是上帝给我的一样，我的理性和对生命的理解也得自于上帝，因此这种理解发展的各个阶段都是真实存在的。人们真诚信仰的东西必然是真实的，它可能有各种不同的表达方式，但绝不可能是谎言。因此如果我认为它是个谎言，那只能表明我未能理解它的深意。我还对自己说：任何信仰的关键就在于，它能够让生命拥有意义，这种意义不会随着死亡而消失。无论是在奢靡生活中濒死的沙皇，还是终日劳作、贫病交加的老农奴，抑或顽童智叟、无知老妪、欢喜快活的少妇或充满激情的少年，信仰必然会为他们解答有关生命的问题。因此，如果要回答生活境遇截然不同、所受教育大相径庭的人们提出的问题，如果关于那个永恒的问题——我为什么活着？我生命的目的是什么？——只有一种答案，这个答案，尽管基本上都是同一个答案，也必然会有许多不同的表达方式。这个答案越是精辟独到、真实深刻，它的表达方式就越显得生疏和古怪，全看每个人所受的教育和当时的境况如何。然而，这些争论或许能够证明许多在我看来非常奇怪的宗教仪式都有其合理性，却仍不足以让我作出自己所怀疑的行为，特别是在信仰这个业已成为我生命中唯一关注的问题上。我全身心地希望自己能够和那些忠诚顺从地行使仪式的人们融合在一起，然而我不能。我觉得那么做无异于对自己撒谎，嘲弄自己认为神圣的东西。不过就在这时，一些新的俄国神学成果帮助了我。

4.根据这些神学家的解释，信仰的基本教条是教会的不谬性。遵循这一教条，教会所教授知识和教义的真实性都不言自明。教会作为信徒的集合体，以爱的名义将所有信徒团结在一起，因此它拥有真理，成为我们信仰的基础。我对自己说，宗教真理无法通过单个人的努力获得，只能是所有人以爱的名义团结在一起之后才能够得到启示的。为了获得真理，人们不能彼此分离；因为不能够分离，人们就必须爱，必须和那些与我们意见不一致的人和平相处。真理体现为爱，因此，如果你不遵从教会的仪式，就破坏了爱的原则。破坏了爱的原则，就不大可能再了解真理了。当时的我看不到这一论证过程的谬误，看不到以爱之名团结在一起虽然可以启示大爱、却无法启示神圣的真理，就像《尼西亚信经》[11]中用确切的语词表达的那些神圣的真理。我没有看到，爱永远不足以将真理明确表达为一种必然的团结状态。当时的我看不到这一谬误，也正是因此，我能够在理解有限的情况下接受和服从东正教的许多仪式。当时我正试图彻底放弃所有争论和辩驳，尽可能合理地解释教会的所有信条，尽管其中有些与我的想法矛盾。

在顺从这些教会仪式的过程中，我压制了自己的理性，全盘接受一个全人类共有的传统。我将自己与祖先和我所钟爱的人、与父母和祖父母联系在一起。他们，以及他们的前人都曾信仰过、生活过，是他们将我带到这个世界上。我成为自己如此深爱的无数人中的一员。这些行为本身没有任何错误（“错误”是指沉迷于欲望），每天早上起来便向教堂走去，我觉得自己在做一件向善之事，只要那样我就能压制自己骄傲的头脑而牺牲肉体的舒适享受，和我的祖先和同辈人团结在一起，寻找到生命的意义。

我怀着同样的目标领圣餐、每天祈祷、划十字、屈单膝、斋戒。无论这些献身宗教的行为多么微不足道，它们毕竟是以向善为目的。无论在家里还是在教堂，我领圣餐、斋戒、每天做几个小时的祈祷。在倾听教堂布道时，我每听到一个字都会停下来思考一下，试图赋予它意义。在圣餐仪式上，我听起来最有意义的话是：“在团结中热爱彼此吧。”但接下来我听到这样的话就不再思索了：“我们相信圣父、圣子和圣灵。”因为我无法理解这句话的含义。

第十四章

[12]当时的我迫切需要信仰才能继续生存下去，因此潜意识里不自觉地无视宗教信条中的矛盾和含混之处，但是总有一些仪式是无法为其赋予意义的。如果说我日益明白了启应祷文1中最重要的内容，甚至即便我勉强诠释出以下祷文：“记住我们万能的圣母和一切圣徒，把我们自己、彼此和全体的生命都奉献给基督，我们的主。”即便我诠释出为沙皇及其家人祈祷的那些不断重复的祷词（因为他们比其他更容易受到诱惑，因而更需要祈祷），以及为敌人和对手所做的祷词（因为他们的邪恶行径），事实上这些和其他祷词——例如《智天使颂歌》《威武的将军》以及圣餐礼的一整套仪式——中即使不是全部，也有近三分之二没有任何意义，或者让我觉得赋予其意义无异于说谎，因而将破坏我和上帝之间的关系，那样我就不可能继续信仰了。

2.庆祝主要的节日也让我有同感。守安息日，即用一星期中的一天与上帝交流，这我能够理解。但最重要的节日都是为了纪念耶稣复活，而对于复活的真实性，我既无法想象也无法理解。每周要庆祝的那一天正是以“复活”命名的[13]。每逢这个日子都要举行圣餐礼，对此我完全不理解。除了圣诞节之外，其他十二个重大节日都是纪念奇迹的——为了不至于否定它们，我尽量不去思考其内容：耶稣升天日、圣灵降临日、主现日、圣母节等。在庆祝这些节日时，原本觉得无足轻重的东西硬是要赋予重要意义，每到此时我要么杜撰出一个解释让自己心安理得，要么干脆闭上眼睛，对引发我怀疑的东西视而不见。

3.在参加最常见也被视为最重要的圣礼——洗礼和圣餐——时，这种感觉比任何时候都更加强烈。我在这些仪式上遭遇的不是不可理解的东西，而是完全可以理解的行为：在我看来这些行为充满诱惑，于是我陷入了两难境地——要么否定，要么撒谎。

4.我永远忘不了自己在多年以后第一次受领圣餐时的痛苦感受。仪式、牧师、祈祷词的念法，这些我统统都能理解，并让我不无欢喜地意识到，我正在逐渐接近生命的意义。我认为圣餐本身就是纪念耶稣基督的行为，它象征着净化原罪并全盘接受耶稣基督的教义。如果说这种解释难免牵强，起码我当时并没有注意到这一点。当我在一个简朴而谨慎的司祭面前俯首听命之时，我觉得自己抖掉了灵魂上的尘土，忏悔了所有的罪过，这让我非常快乐，能够在思想上接近写出规范祷文的教父们的远大抱负，与那些曾经生活过、有过信仰的先辈比肩并进，让我非常快乐，以至于我根本没有注意自己的解释有牵强附会之嫌。然而，当我走近圣像屏的中门，神父请我重复自己的信仰，要我承认自己即将下咽的其实是肉体和血的时候，我的心脏开始痛苦得痉挛。那远远不是什么虚伪的调子，那是一个显然从不知何为信仰的人对我提出的残酷要求。

5.我如今可以允许自己承认那是一个残酷的要求了，但是当时我并不这样想，我只是觉得非常难过。我已经不再年轻，年轻时我觉得生命中的一切条理清晰、易于理解。之所以皈依信仰，就是因为我只能在生命中看到毁灭，除此之外一无所获。因此，那时的我不可能放弃信仰，于是我屈服了。我发现自己的灵魂深处有一种感觉能够帮助我忍受那样的残酷，就是自我贬低和谦卑。我俯首听命，吞下了肉体和血而没有觉得那是一种亵渎，因为我是那般渴望信仰，但是我的心灵仍然遭受了打击。既然已经事先知道了结果，我自然无法再次前往受苦了。

6.然而我继续遵行着教会的仪式，且依然相信自己遵行的信条中蕴涵着真理。之后在我身上发生了一件当时看来十分古怪如今却一目了然的事情。

7.就在我倾听一个没有文化的农民信仰者讲述上帝、宗教、生命和救赎时，我突然知晓了信仰的意义。我于是开始接近那些普通人，倾听他们关于生命和宗教的争论，也越来越接近真理。在我阅读《东正教圣徒传略汇编》[14]和《训诫集》[15]的时候也是一样，这些后来成为我最喜欢的读物。不去管那些神迹（姑且认为他们只是表达思想的故事而已），这些读物向我揭示了生命的意义。书中有大马卡里传、约瑟夫王子传（即佛的一生），也有金口约翰[16]的故事、井中旅人的故事、拾金修士的故事、税吏彼得的故事，还有殉教的圣徒传，所有这些人一致声称，死亡并不排斥生命。还有一些关于不识字而愚昧无知的人们得救的故事，尽管他们根本不知道教会的教义。

8.然而只要和那些有学问的信徒在一起，或阅读他们的著述，我就会在心底里对他们的论证产生怀疑和不满，并认定他们夸大其词。我觉得自己越是深入了解他们的论说，就越是远离真理而走向绝望。

第十五章

1.我时常嫉妒那些没上过学、大字识不得几个的农民。那些在我看来显然是废话的冗长教条，他们却觉得正确得无可挑剔。他们接受这些教条、信仰真理，我也信仰真理，但我这个可怜的家伙非常清楚，我们信仰的真理中盘根错节地掺杂着谬误，我无法接受这样的真理。

2.这样的生活大概持续了三年，起初我只是平静地一点一点地接受真理，凭借自己的嗅觉找到最明确的方向，因而这些细节并没有引起我太多注意。那时当我遇到什么无法理解的事物时，就会自言自语道：“我有罪，我是个傻瓜。”可随着我研习的真理越来越多，它们逐渐成为我生命的基石，这些令人头疼的障碍就变得越发难以逾越，未曾理解和永远无法理解之间的界限也越来越分明，除非我撒谎，自欺欺人。

3.尽管深受这些疑虑和痛苦的折磨，我仍然信仰东正教。但有关生命的问题一次次浮现在眼前，必须给予解答。教会关于这些问题的教规有悖于我赖以生存的信仰基础，这最终迫使我彻底断绝了与东正教的联系。首先，也是最重要的一点，这些问题关系到东正教如何看待其他教派，譬如天主教和所谓的分裂教派。那时由于对宗教颇有兴趣，我接触到众多教派的信徒，譬如天主教徒、清教徒、旧礼仪派[17]教徒、莫洛肯派[18]教徒，等等。其中不乏品德高尚而虔诚信教的人，我希望自己能够成为他们中的一员。可现实又怎样呢？我听到的教义许诺信仰与博爱可以团结众人，可正是这一教义，却通过它最高级别的代言人告诉我，这都是些误入歧途的人，他们生命的动力是魔鬼的诱惑，我们才可能拥有唯一的真理。我也看到与东正教教义稍有不同便被斥为异端邪说，这和天主教把东正教徒斥为离经叛道者没有任何分别。我还看到无论东正教如何貌似宽容，他们对所有异教徒——参拜不同圣物、念诵不同祷词的教徒——无不充满敌意。世事注定如此，因为，首先向他人宣告“你的信仰是错误的，我的才正确”太过残忍；其次，对于热爱子女和兄长的人来说，倘若有人想说服他挚爱之人皈依一门错误的信仰，他难免会对此人充满敌意。一个人拥有的神学知识越多，这份敌意就越深。那么如果说真理就蕴含在以爱为纽带的众生团结之中，神学岂不是在阻止它本应该倡导的东西？这个发现令我震惊。

4.在一国多教的国家，我们这些受过教育的人见识过天主教否定东正教和新教、东正教否定天主教和新教、新教否定天主教和东正教时的那种轻慢不屑、自以为是和不可理喻，显然更容易受到这种诱惑。而旧礼仪派、俄国福音派、震颤派[19]以及所有其他教派对异己教派也都采取极为类似的态度。以致起初，这种诱惑明显得令我非常困惑。我告诉自己：“不对，事情绝对不是看上去这么简单。”显然是这样，人们毕竟看不到，假如两种信念互相抵触，那么两派都不可能拥有构成信仰的真理——真理是唯一的。一定还有什么东西我没有看到，是的，这些一定是可以解释的。我确信如此，便开始寻求这一解释，并为此饱读典籍、虚心讨教。但是我最终也未能找到什么合理的解释，无非是各执一词：苏姆斯基骠骑兵团[20]认为他们是世界上最强的兵团，而黄色枪骑兵团[21]觉得他们才是最棒的。不同教派的神父通过其最优秀的代言人所能告诉我的，就是他们坚信自己是拥有真理的一方，而其他人都背离了真理，他们只能为这些人祈祷，仅此而已。我拜见了不少大修道院院长、主教、长老和苦行修士，却没有一个人试着向我阐明这个问题。只有一个人给我作了解释，但他的解释让我以后再也没有提过这个问题。

5.我先前说过，任何非信徒在皈依信仰时（我们的子女也包括在内）首先会问的问题是：为什么真理不在路德教或天主教那里，而只有在东正教的教义中才能找到？事实上新教和天主教也同样确信自己的信仰才是唯一的真理，这一点想必受过中等教育的人都会知道，不了解历史的农民自然无从知晓。史实不足为信——各教派均已出于各自利益篡改了历史。如此一来，如我之前提到的，像真正信仰的人那样，从一个更高的层面来理解宗教教义，使得各种教派之间的分歧大而化小、小而化无何尝不可？沿着旧礼仪派走过的道路继续追求我们的信仰又岂是天大的难事？他们强调说，他们在胸前画十字的顺序、赞美诗的内容、围绕圣坛的圣礼统统与我们不同。但我们的观点是：你们信仰尼西亚信经[22]七大圣事[23]，我们也一样。让我们在这一点上保持一致，其余的部分保持各自的传统好了。如此我们便可以忽视无关紧要的分歧，通过信仰中最关键的方面团结在一起。我们完全可以告诉天主教徒：关键是你们也信仰这个，信仰那个，至于圣灵是自圣父发出还是同时自圣子发出、是否应该坚持罗马教皇的最高领导之类的问题，大家可以仁者见仁，智者见智。同理，我们又何尝不能与新教徒说同样的话，就更为重要的问题达成一致呢？我就此提议请教一个人，他也赞同我的观点，但同时告诉我说如果作出这样的让步，必定招致宗教权威们的批判。因为这样做偏离了先辈们的信仰，并将导致教派内部的分裂。而神职人员的使命就是坚守阵地，确保先辈们代代相传的希腊东正教信仰纯洁而不受侵犯。

6.这么一讲我全都明白了。我追求的是信仰，是一种驱使生命不断向前的力量，而他们追求的却是如何以世人眼中最好的方式完成人类必尽的某些义务。他们以世俗的方式来履行这些世俗的义务。无论他们如何夸夸其谈，炫耀自己对那些迷路的兄弟充满同情，炫耀自己为那些来到万能的主面前的人们虔诚祷告，在履行世俗的义务时总是不可避免地要使用武力，这一点不会随着时间的流逝而有任何改变。如果两种宗教都认为己方拥有真理而对方只是谎言，那么为了让兄弟们皈依真理，他们一定会宣讲己方的教义。如果坚信自己真理在握的教会有经验不足的教众受到蛊惑而相信了错误的教义，那么教会将别无选择，只能焚烧书籍，并将那个误导己派教众的害群之马流放他乡。在东正教会的眼中，如果目的是把天主的恩宠经由教会施予领受的人。那么，一个教会成员经过谬误之火的毒害，在性命攸关的问题——信仰问题上误导教众，此人面临的该是怎样的惩罚？砍头、囚禁。除此之外呢？

在沙皇阿列克谢·米哈伊洛维奇[24]统治时期，他们被绑在木桩上活活烧死，这也是当时最残酷的刑罚。时至今日，这类犯人将被单独囚禁，不得与他人接触，也堪称当代酷刑之首了。当我转而关注那些宗教名义下的所作所为时，不由得毛骨悚然，几近要摒弃东正教。更令我难以接受的，是东正教在战争与死刑问题上的立场。

7.那时，俄国正处于战火硝烟之中，俄国人正在以基督仁爱的名义屠杀自己的同胞。我们没有任何理由不思考这个问题，也没有办法回避这样的事实——杀戮是邪恶的，有悖于任何信仰的最基本原则。然而教堂里众人祈祷祝福我们的士兵在战场上得胜，宗教导师们认为它正是信仰的结果，接受这样的杀戮。这些不仅仅发生在战乱年代，在战后那些艰难岁月，我也曾亲眼目睹教会成员，包括牧师、僧侣和修士纵容屠杀手无寸铁的迷失青年的行为。当我注意到这些口口声声基督仁爱的教徒的所作所为时，我不禁不寒而栗。

第十六章

1.从那时起，我就再也没有疑虑，深信自己信奉的教义并非全是真理。不过我年轻时总说，所有的宗教教义都是谎言，后来不那么讲了。作为整体的人类，无疑掌握着真理，否则他们也不会存活至今。况且，如今我接触到这一真理，它已经成为我生活的精神依靠，我也感受到了它的真实性。但我同样确信它本身也有谬误。此前一直令我厌恶的东西如此清晰地呈现在我面前。尽管我知道自己深感厌恶的这一堆谎言在农民那里并没有在教会代言人那里体现得更为明显，可我仍然能够看到，即使普通人的信仰也是真理与谬误并存。

2.然而这些谬误是从哪里来的，真理又究竟来自何方？谬误和真理都是由所谓的教会传承下来的。但谬误和真理也都存在于传统中，存在于所谓的神圣传统以及《圣经》的章节里。

3.无论我喜欢与否，我开始研究和考察《圣经》和这些传统——考察的过程至今回想起来仍犹如噩梦一般。

4.我当日转而研究的那门神学曾遭到自己的蔑视，我曾经觉得它的存在全无必要。最初它给我的印象不过是一堆毫无意义的废话，那时我身边充溢着生命的启示，我觉得生命的道路明晰且充满意义。如今我很高兴自己能够抛弃那些不利于身心健康的想法，但对具体的做法又深感迷茫。我曾获得启示的生命的一重意义恰在于这种宗教信条，或者至少可以说二者密不可分。无论在我那观念陈旧又意志薄弱的头脑看来，这种意义显得多么牵强，它毕竟是我获得救赎的唯一希望。为了理解这一意义，我必须细心严谨地对它进行考察，尽管其理解方法与科学命题截然不同。我知道宗教知识的性质极为特殊，因而我没有、不能也不应该试图找到能解万物之谜的答案。我知道这样的答案，就好比解释万物起源，只能是永久的秘密。但我希望自己的理解方式能够带我走向那些永恒的不解之谜。我希望自己明白，所有的不解之谜之所以无解，不是因为我的智力希望寻求解释的需求是错误的（这些需求并没有错，否则我将对世界一无所知），而是因为我能够意识到自己的智力有局限性。我希望通过自己的理解方式认识，所有的不解之谜呈现在我面前时便注定无解，而不是我有义务去相信它们的无解。

5.教义之中蕴含真理，对此我深信不疑，但我也同样确信这些教义之中夹杂着谬误，我必须弄清楚哪些是真理，哪些是谬误，将两者区分开来。于是我着手进行这样的研究。我在教义中发现的谬误和真理以及随后得出的结论都出现在本文后面的章节中，如果有人觉得它们有所启示，或许会在某年某地得以出版。

6.以上文字写于三年前。

7.前几天，我重读已经付梓的这部分内容，不由得思绪翻滚，历历往事仿佛就在眼前，恍惚间如入梦境。这个梦境以浓缩的形式向我展示了自己所经历和描述过的一切，因此我觉得对我有所了解的人，描述一下这个梦境会带你们重温并更加清楚和连贯地看到我用这么长的篇幅不厌其烦地讲述的东西。那个梦境是这样的：我看到自己躺在一张床上，谈不上舒服也谈不上不舒服，就是仰面躺着。但我开始思考自己这样躺着到底舒服不舒服。时间一长，两条腿似乎感觉有点别扭，不知道是因为我的腿太短了还是它们压根儿不一般长。我调整了一下腿的位置，同时开始思考自己平躺的姿势以及身下垫着什么东西，这都是刚刚才开始思考的问题。看了看床，我发现自己躺在一些由绳索编织的吊带上，吊带两头系在床的两侧。我的脚就搁在其中的一根吊带上，小腿放在另一根上，因而双腿感到不舒服。不知怎么，我知道这些吊带可以移动，就挪了挪腿，把较远处的那个吊带推到脚下，觉得这样会感觉舒服一些。但我把那个吊带踢得太远，就晃动双腿想把它挪近一些。这么一折腾，小腿下面的吊带滑掉了，小腿就悬空了。我挪了挪身体想换个位置，确信这下一定能解决问题，不料身体下面更多的吊带滑落了下去。情况更糟了：我的整个下半身都滑了下来，吊在半空中，两只脚又着不了地，全身的力量都靠上半个背部支撑着，这时我在感到不舒服的同时，开始害怕起来。也就在这时候，我开始思考那些之前未曾想到的问题：我这是在哪儿，躺在什么上面？我环顾四周，首先想看看自己身体下面垫着什么，我的身体悬在哪里，即将掉落到什么方向。我低头一看，简直不能相信自己的双眼：我所处的高度不只是什么高耸入云的塔顶或山巅，那是一个我根本无法想象的高度。

8.我甚至连身下的东西都看不清楚，底下是一眼望不到底的深渊，我就这么悬空挂着，摇摇欲坠。我的心跳到了嗓子眼，怕得要命。低头看下去简直糟糕透顶。我觉得要是再往下看，会立即从最后一根吊带上滑落下去，一命呜呼。我于是不再乱看，可这样更糟，因为我不停在想自己要是滑下去会如何粉身碎骨。越想越恐怖，身上也越来越无力，背部滑得越来越低，随时都会掉下去。就在那时我想这可能不是真的，只是个梦，马上就会醒过来。我试着让自己醒过来，却醒不过来。“我该怎么办？我该怎么办？”我不停地问自己，抬头向上望去，也是一眼望不到顶。我看向深邃的天空，试着忘却身下的深渊，事实上我真的办到了，身下的无限令我厌恶和恐慌，头顶的无限却吸引着我，安抚我的情绪。就这样，我凭借身下最后一根没有滑落的吊带，身体悬在半空，下面是深不见底的深渊。我知道自己的身体摇摇欲坠，但是我只往上看，恐惧就消失了。就像在梦里发生的那样，有一个声音对我说：“注意，记住这一点！”我向头顶高不可测的天空深处极目远眺，心绪也逐渐镇定下来。我想起所有的一切是怎么发生的：我怎么动了动腿，怎么挂在这儿，当时感到多么害怕，后来又怎么往上看而克服了这种恐惧。我反问自己：“我现在还悬挂在那儿吗？”只要感觉到身体还牢牢地吊在吊带上，没晃也没掉下来，我就不再环顾四周。我觉得自己不再悬挂在那儿摇摇欲坠，而是被身下的吊带稳稳托住了。我反问自己怎么会被托住，摸索着，察看周围的情况，就看见身体下面，就在我身体的正中央有一根吊带，当我向上看的时候，躺在吊带上的姿势获得了最稳定的平衡，一直在支撑着我的只有这一根吊带。然后就像在梦里一样，支撑我的东西一下子变得非常自然，成了完全可以理解的必然事物，尽管醒来之后又好像根本说不通了。我甚至在睡梦中感到惊讶，之前怎么从来没有发现这些。原来在我的头旁边有根柱子，没有那么粗壮，但稳固性不容置疑，尽管柱子插在那里似乎并没有什么根基。一根绳子就那么松松垮垮地从柱子上垂下来，但巧妙之处在于：只要人能用身体的正中央平躺在绳子上往上看，就根本不会掉落下去。这我看得很清楚，我很高兴，也心安了。仿佛听见有人对我说：“务必要记住这些啊！”然后我就醒了。

[1]喀山：苏联伏尔加河中游城市。

[2]天主教译为“达味”，伊斯兰教译作“达吾德”，是以色列的第二任国王。“大卫”的意思是“被爱的”。大部分关于他的记载都出自《塔纳赫》中的《塞缪尔记》上、下两部。大卫虽不是没有缺点，但在以色列所有古代的国王中，他被描述为最富有正义感的国王，还是一位优秀的战士、音乐家和诗人（据说《圣经》中许多赞美上帝的诗篇都是他的创作）。根据《圣经》记录，耶稣是大卫的后裔。

[3]1855年，托尔斯泰于克里木战争结束后来到圣彼得堡。

[4]1俄亩约合1.09公顷。

[5]叔本华《作为意志和表象的世界》，结论部分。商务印书馆，1997年，石冲白译。

[6]《圣经·旧约·传道书》第一章。

[7]《圣经·旧约·传道书》第二章。

[8]《圣经·旧约·传道书》第九章。

[9]《圣经·旧约·传道书》第八章。

[10]《圣经·旧约·传道书》第九章。

[11]《尼西亚信经》：也译为《尼吉亚信经》，是传统基督教的三大信经之一。得名于公元325年第一次尼西亚宗教大会，会议确定了圣父、圣子、圣灵为三位一体的上帝，地位平等。

[12]启应祷文：东正教礼拜仪式上的祷告，由教堂执事背诵的一系列祷文组成，期间交错着众人的固定回应。

[13]在俄语中，“星期日”（BockpeceHbe）的含义就是“复活”。

[14]《东正教圣徒传略汇编》共十二卷，于1860年在莫斯科出版。

[15]古罗斯时代教会中流行的一本书，根据教会日历编排，其中包括圣徒传和训诫诗。

[16]即约翰一世（347—407），君士坦丁堡牧首，因演讲雄辩而被追谥为“金口”。金口约翰是重要的希腊教父，被许多教会封为圣人。他的遗骸曾于1204年被十字军掠至罗马，教皇若望·保禄二世于2004年归还了这批圣物。

[17]旧礼仪派：俄罗斯东正教会中的一个反国教派别，亦称“老信徒派”。成员多为下层贫民、群众和低级教士，他们反对政府的横征暴敛，宣扬平均主义和无政府主义。

[18]莫洛肯派：俄语直译为“喝牛奶的教派”，成员多为拒绝加入东正教的农民。在长达两百天的斋戒中基本上只喝牛奶，由此而得名。

[19]震颤派：1947年源于英国的基督教派，以舞蹈为敬礼上帝的方式之一，因此得名。

[20]苏姆斯基骠骑兵团：Sumsky此为音译，是俄罗斯历史上著名的骠骑兵团。

[21]黄色枪骑兵团：俄罗斯历史上著名的骑兵团，因骑兵身着黄色制服而得名。

[22]天主教相同，分别为圣洗、坚振、告解、圣体、圣秩、病人傅油及婚配。

[23]七大圣事：耶稣亲自建立的有形可见的宗教形式，东正教的七大圣事和天主教相同，分别为圣洗、坚振、告解、圣体、圣秩、病人傅油及婚配。

[24]阿列克谢·米哈伊洛维奇：俄国沙皇，在位时间为1629至1676年，笃信宗教，为彼得大帝之父。

Chapter 1

1. I was baptized and brought up in the Orthodox Christian faith. I was instructed in it both as a child and throughout my boyhood and youth. But when at the age of eighteen I left university in my second year, I no longer believed in any of the things I had been taught.

2. Judging from various memories, I had never believed very seriously but had merely trusted in what I was taught and in what was professed by my elders; but this trust was very unstable.

3. I remember when I was eleven years old a high school boy named Volodya, now long since dead, came to see us one Sunday and announced the latest discovery made at school. The discovery was that there is no God and that everything we were being taught was pure invention (this was in 1838). I remember my older brothers taking a great interest in this news and even allowing me to join in the discussion. We all, I remember, became very excited and took the news as something very enthralling and entirely possible.

4. I remember too that when my older brother Dmitri, who was then at university, suddenly and with characteristic fervour embraced the faith and started to attend all the services, to observe the fasts and to lead a pure and moral life we all, including the older ones, constantly made fun of him and for some reason nicknamed him Noah. And I remember when Mushkin-Pushkin, at the time a curator at the University of Kazan, invited us to a ball and jokingly persuaded my brother, who had declined the invitation, that even David danced before the ark. At the time I used to enjoy these jokes of my elders, and from them I drew the conclusion that it is necessary to learn the Catechism and it is necessary to go to church, but that one need not take it all too seriously. I also recall reading Voltaire when I was very young; I not only failed to be shocked by his humour but even found it quite amusing.

5. The decline of my faith occurred in the way in which it has always happened, and still happens, among those from our kind of background. It seems to me that in the majority of instances it happens like this: people live as everyone lives, but on the basis of principles that not only have nothing in common with religious doctrines but are, on the whole, contrary to them; religious doctrine plays no part in life, or in relations between people, neither are we confronted with it in our personal lives. Religious doctrine is professed in some other realm, at a distance from life and independent of it. If we encounter it, it is only as an external phenomenon, disconnected from life.

6. Now, just as then, it is impossible to judge from a person's life, or behaviour, whether or not he is a believer. If there is a difference between those who openly profess Orthodoxy and those who deny it, then it is not to the advantage of the former. Nowadays, as before, the public declaration and confession of Orthodoxy is usually encountered among dull-witted, cruel and immoral people who tend to consider themselves very important. Whereas intelligence, honesty, straightforwardness, good-naturedness and morality are qualities usually found among people who claim to be non-believers. The Catechism is taught in schools and the pupils are sent to church; officials must be able to produce evidence of having received communion. But a person belonging to our circle, who is no longer at school and has not entered into public service, can still live for ten years or more without once remembering that he is living among Christians and is himself considered to be a practising member of the Orthodox Church. This was even more true in the past.

7. Thus today, just as in earlier times, religious teaching, which is accepted on trust and sustained by external pressure, gradually weakens under the influence of knowledge and experience of life that stands in opposition to the religious doctrines; a person can go on living for a long time imagining that the body of religious instruction imparted to him when he was a child is still there, whereas it has in fact disappeared without leaving a trace.

8. An intelligent and honest man by the name of S. told me the story of how he lost his faith. At the age of twenty-six, while resting overnight on a hunting expedition, he followed an old childhood custom of kneeling down to pray in the evening. His elder brother, who was with him on the expedition, lay on some straw watching him. When S. had finished and was preparing to lie down his brother said to him: 'Do you still do that?' Nothing more was said between them. But from that day on S. stopped saying his prayers and going to church. And for thirty years he has not prayed, has not received communion and has not gone to church. And this is not because he knew his brother's convictions and wanted to share them, nor was it because he had resolved something in his heart, but simply because this comment of his brother's was like a finger being pushed against a wall that was on the verge of collapsing from its own weight. These words indicated that the place where he had thought faith to be had long been empty and that the words he spoke, the signs of the cross and genuflections he made in prayer, were essentially meaningless actions. Having recognized their meaninglessness he could no longer continue doing them.

9. Thus it has happened and still happens, I believe, with the great majority of people. I am speaking about people from our type of background, of people who are sincere with themselves, and not of those who use the profession of faith as a means of obtaining some kind of worldly aims. (These people are the most fundamental non-believers, for if faith is seen by them as a means of achieving various worldly aims, then it is certainly no longer faith.) People of our upbringing find themselves in a situation where the light of knowledge and of life have melted away an artificial edifice, and they have either failed to notice this and swept it away completely, or have simply failed to notice it as yet.

10. The religious instruction communicated to me since childhood faded, as it does with others, only with the difference that since I had begun to read and think a great deal while still very young, my abdication of religious faith occurred very early. When I was sixteen I ceased saying my prayers, going to church or fasting of my own accord. I no longer believed in what I had been taught as a child; but I did believe in something, without being able to say what it was. I believed in God, or rather I did not deny God, but what kind of God I could not have said; neither did I reject Christ or his teachings, but what I understood by the teachings again I could not have said.

11. Now, looking back at that time, I can clearly see that the only real faith I had, apart from the animal instincts motivating my life, was a belief in perfection. But what this perfection consisted of, and what its aim was, were unclear to me. I tried to perfect myself intellectually and studied everything I came upon in life. I tried to perfect my will, setting myself rules I tried to follow. I perfected myself physically, practising all kinds of exercises in order to develop my strength and dexterity, and I cultivated endurance and patience by undergoing all kinds of hardship. All this I regarded as perfection. The beginning of it all was, of course, moral perfection, but this was soon replaced by a belief in general perfection, that is a desire to be better not in my own eyes or before God but in the eyes of other people. And very soon this determination to be better than others became a wish to be more powerful than others: more famous, more important, wealthier.

Chapter 2

1. Some day I will relate the story of my life, and of how touching and instructive were those ten years of my youth. I think a great many people must have experienced something similar. I longed with all my soul to be good, but I was young; I had passions and I was alone, completely alone in my search for goodness. Every time I tried to display my innermost desires - a wish to be morally good - I met with contempt and scorn, and as soon as I gave in to base desires I was praised and encouraged. Ambition, lust for power, self-interest, lechery, pride, anger, revenge, were all respected qualities. As I yielded to these passions I became like my elders and I felt that they were pleased with me. A dear old aunt of mine, the purest of creatures, with whom I lived, was always saying that she wished for nothing as much as that I would have a relationship with a married woman. 'Rien ne forme un jeune homme comme une liaison avec une femme comme il faut.' Another happiness she wished for me was that I should become an adjutant, and preferably to the Emperor. And the greatest happiness of all would be for me to marry a very rich girl and acquire as many serfs as possible through the marriage.

2. I cannot recall those years without horror, loathing, and heartache. I killed people in war, summoned others to duels in order to kill them, gambled at cards; I devoured the fruits of the peasants' labour and punished them; I fornicated and practised deceit. Lying, thieving, promiscuity of all kinds, drunkenness, violence, murder... there was not a crime I did not commit, and yet I was praised for it all and my contemporaries considered, and still consider me, a relatively moral man.

3. For ten years I lived in this fashion.

4. During this time I began to write out of vanity, self-interest and pride. In my writings I did the same as I did in life. In order to achieve the fame and money for which I wrote I had to conceal what was good in myself and display what was bad. And this is what I did. Time and again I would contrive in my writings to conceal under the guise of indifference, or even of light-heartedness, those strivings for goodness which lent meaning to my life. And I succeeded and was praised.

5. After the war, by which time I was twenty-six, I returned to St Petersburg and took up company with writers. They accepted me as one of them and flattered me. I had no time to stop and look around before I had assimilated the view of life held by the group of writers with whom I mixed, and before long all my earlier attempts at improvement had been erased. Their outlook provided a theory that justified my undisciplined life.

6. The view of life adopted by these people, my literary associates, was that generally speaking life is a process of development in the course of which the most important role is played by us, the thinkers; and that among the thinkers it is we, the artists and poets, who have the most influence. Our vocation is to educate people. In order to avoid being confronted by the obvious question-'What do I know and what have I got to teach?' - their theory explained that it is not necessary to know this and that the poet and the artist teach unconsciously. I was considered a superb artist and poet and it was therefore quite natural for me to adopt this theory. I, an artist and poet, wrote without knowing myself what it was I was teaching. And I was paid money for doing this. I was provided with excellent food, lodgings, women, company, and I was famous. It must then be the case that what I was teaching was very good.

7. This faith in the meaning of poetry and in the evolution of life was a religion and I was one of its priests. It was very profitable and pleasant to be one of its priests, and for a considerable length of time I lived in this faith without ever doubting its validity. But in the second, and still more in the third year of this existence, I began to doubt its infallibility and to examine it. The first point of doubt was that I had begun to notice how the priests of this religion disagreed among themselves. Some said: 'We are the finest and most useful teachers and it is we who teach what is needed, while the others teach falsely.' And others said: 'No! We are the real teachers and you teach falsely!' They argued, quarrelled, deceived and tricked one another. Moreover, there were many among us who were unconcerned as to who was right and who wrong, but who simply achieved their own selfish ends by means of this activity of ours. All this forced me to doubt the truth of the faith.

8. Furthermore, once I had begun to doubt the truth of this writer's religion I started observing its priests more closely and became convinced that almost all the priests of this faith - the writers - were immoral men, the majority of bad and worthless character and much inferior to the people I had met during my former dissipated military life. But they were complacent and self-satisfied in a way that is only possible for people who are truly holy, or for those who do not know what holiness is. These people became repugnant to me, and I became repugnant to myself, and realized that the religion was a fraud.

9. But strange to say, even though the utter falsehood of this creed was something I came quickly to understand and to reject, I did not discard the rank these people bestowed on me: that of artist, poet and teacher. I naïvely imagined that I was a poet and an artist, and could teach everybody without myself knowing what I was teaching. And this is what I did.

10. Through my association with these men I acquired a new vice: an unhealthily developed pride, and an insane conviction that it was my vocation to teach people without knowing what I was teaching.

11. Now, when I think about this period and about my state of mind and that of those around me (and incidentally there are thousands of them nowadays), I feel sad, terrible, ridiculous; it arouses in me precisely the same feelings as one might experience in a madhouse.

12. At the time we were all convinced that we must talk and talk and write and publish as quickly as possible, and as much as possible, and that this was all necessary for the good of mankind. And thousands of us, contradicting and abusing one another, published and wrote with the aim of teaching others. Failing to notice that we knew nothing, that we did not know the answer to the most basic question of life－what is good and what is evil－we all spoke at the same time, never listening to one another. At times we indulged and praised each other in order to be indulged and praised in return, at other times we grew angry and shrieked at each other, just as if we were in a madhouse.

13. Thousands of workers toiled day and night, assembling millions and millions of words, which were distributed by post over the whole of Russia; and we taught and taught, but never managed to impart all that we had to teach, and were always annoyed that we were given so little attention.

14. Horribly strange, but I now understand it all. Our genuine, sincere concern was over how to gain as much money and fame as possible. And the only thing we knew how to do in order to achieve this aim was to write books and journals. This is what we did. But in order for us to pursue this utterly useless task and have the assurance that we were very important people we needed an argument that would justify what we were doing. And so we devised the following; everything that exists is rational and all that exists evolves. And it evolves through enlightenment. Enlightenment is measured through the distribution of books and journals. We are paid and respected for writing these books and papers, so we must be the most important and useful people. This theory would have been all very well had we been in agreement; but since any thought expressed by any one of us was always contradicted by the diametrically opposed views of another, we should have been forced to rethink. But we did not notice this; we were paid money and those who sided with us praised us, consequently everyone of us believed himself to be in the right.

15. It is now clear to me that there was no difference between our behaviour and that of people in a madhouse; but at the time I only dimly suspected this and, like all madmen, I thought everyone was mad except myself.

Chapter 3

1. And so I lived, abandoning myself to this madness, for another six years until I married. During this period I went abroad. Life in Europe and the contact I had with advanced and learned Europeans still further reinforced the belief in overall perfection, by which I lived; for I found the same belief among them. With my own self this belief assumed the form it usually takes among the educated men of our time. The belief was expressed in the word 'progress'. At the time I felt that this word had some meaning. Living as I was then, like any individual I was tormented by the problem of how to live a better life. I did not yet understand that in answering 'live in conformity with progress', I was speaking exactly like a person who is in a boat being carried along by wind and waves and who when asked the most important and vital question, 'Where should I steer?' avoids answering by saying, 'We are being carried somewhere.'

2. At the time I noticed none of this. Only occasionally, led more by instinct than reason, I rebelled against the superstition so prevalent in our age by which people shield themselves from their failure to understand life. Thus, during my stay in Paris, the sight of an execution revealed to me the precariousness of my superstition in progress. When I saw the heads being separated from the bodies and heard them thump, one after the next, into the box I understood, and not just with my intellect but with my whole being, that no theories of the rationality of existence and progress could justify this crime. I realized that even if every single person since the day of creation had, according to whatever theory, found this necessary I knew that it was unnecessary and wrong, and therefore that judgements on what is good and necessary must not be based on what other people say and do, or on progress, but on the instincts of my own soul. Another instance in which I felt that the superstition of progress was inadequate in regard to life was the death of my brother. He was an intelligent, kind-hearted, serious man who became ill when he was young, suffered for over a year and died in torment without having understood why he had lived, and still less why he was dying. No theories could provide the answers to these questions, either for him or for me, during his slow and tortuous death.

3. But these were only rare instances of doubt and in truth I continued to live, professing faith only in progress. 'Everything is evolving and I am evolving; and the reason why I am evolving together with all the rest will one day be known to me.' This is how I would have formulated my belief at the time.

4. When I returned from abroad I settled in the country and busied myself with the running of the peasant schools. This occupation was close to my heart because in it was none of the falsehood that had become so apparent to me, and struck me so forcibly when I was a literary teacher. Here too I was acting in the name of progress, but I had already assumed a critical attitude towards this progress. I told myself that in some of its manifestations progress had proceeded incorrectly and that here, when dealing with the primitive peasant children, it was necessary to act in a spirit of freedom, leaving them to choose whatever path to progress they wished to take.

5. In reality I was still confronted with the same insoluble problem of how to teach without knowing what I was teaching. In the higher circles of literary activity it was apparent to me that I could not teach without knowing what it was I taught, for I saw that everyone taught differently and that in our arguments we only concealed our own lack of knowledge from each other. But here with the peasant children I thought I could avoid this difficulty by allowing the children to study whatever they liked. It amused me to recall how I side-tracked in order to fulfil my ambition of teaching, while knowing very well in the depths of my heart that I could not possibly teach what was needed because I did not know what it was. After a year spent occupied with the affairs of the school I went abroad again in order to discover how to teach others what I did not know myself.

6. I thought I learnt this there, and equipped with all this wisdom I returned to Russia in the year of the Emancipation of the Serfs. I took up the position of arbitrator and started teaching the uneducated people in the schools, as well as the educated people through the journal I had begun publishing. This seemed to be going well but I felt that my mental state was not altogether healthy and that this could not continue for long. I might perhaps have fallen at this time into the same despair that I fell into when I was fifty if there had not been one aspect of life I had not yet experienced and which promised salvation: this was family life.

7. For a year I involved myself with arbitration work, with the schools and the journal, and soon exhausted myself. This was largely due to my confusion; the struggle as arbitrator became so burdensome, my school activities so complex and my journalistic prevarications so repulsive to me, since they always consisted of the same thing: the desire to teach everyone while concealing the fact that I did not know what I was teaching. I became ill, spiritually more than physically. I threw in everything and left for the steppes of the Bashkirs to breathe fresh air, drink koumiss and live a primitive life.

8. On my return I married. The new circumstances of happy family life completely distracted me from any search for the overall meaning of life. At the time my whole life was bound up with my family, my wife and my children and thus in concerns for improving our means of living. My striving for self-perfection, which had already been replaced by a striving for perfection in general, that is for progress, was now sublimated beneath the straightforward desire of achieving the best for my family and myself.

9. Thus another fifteen years passed.

10. Despite the fact that during those fifteen years I considered the writer's task unimportant, I continued to write. I had already tasted the temptations of authorship, the temptations of enormous financial gain and applause for my trivial work, and I devoted myself to it as a means of improving my material position and of stifling any questions in my soul regarding the meaning of my own life, or of life in general.

11. I wrote, teaching what was for me the only truth: that we must live in order to give ourselves and our families the best possible in life.

12. And so I lived until five years ago when something very strange started happening to me. At first I began experiencing moments of bewilderment; my life would come to a standstill, as if I did not know how to live or what to do, and I felt lost and fell into despair. But they passed and I continued to live as before. Then these moments of bewilderment started to recur more frequently, always taking the same form. On these occasions, when life came to a standstill, the same questions always arose: 'Why? What comes next?'

13. At first I thought the questions pointless and irrelevant. I felt the answers were well known and that should I wish to resolve them it would not cost me much effort; that for the time being I did not have the time to work it all out, but that when I put my mind to it I would find all the answers. However, the questions repeated themselves over and again, demanding answers with more and more urgency. They fell like full stops, always on the same spot, uniting in one large black spot.

14. And then, what happens to everyone stricken with a fatal inner disease happened to me. At first minor signs of indisposition appear, which the sick person ignores; then these symptoms appear more and more frequently, merging into one interrupted period of suffering. The suffering increases and before the sick man realizes what is happening he discovers that the thing he had taken for an indisposition is in fact the thing that is more important to him than anything in the world: it is death.

15. This is just what happened to me. I realized that it was not just a casual indisposition but something very serious and that if the same questions kept repeating themselves they would have to be answered. And I tried to answer them. The questions seemed so stupid, simple, and childish. But the moment I touched upon them and tried to resolve them I was immediately convinced, firstly, that they were not childish and stupid questions but were the most important and profound questions in life, and secondly, that however much I thought about them I could not resolve them. Before occupying myself with my Samara estate, with the education of my son, or with the writing of books, I had to know why I was doing these things. While I did not know why, I could not do anything. Amidst my thoughts concerning the farm, which at the time kept me very busy, a question would suddenly come into my head: 'Well fine, so you will have 6,000 desyatins in the Samara province and 300 horses, and then what?' And feeling completely taken aback, I would not know what to think next. Or, beginning to reflect on the education of my children, I would ask myself, 'Why?' Or deliberating on how the peasants might achieve prosperity I would suddenly ask myself, 'What concern is it of mine?' Or thinking about the fame my own writing brought me, I would say to myself, 'Well fine, so you will be more famous than Gogal, Pushkin, Shakespeare, Molière, more famous than all the writers in the world, and so what?'

16. And I had absolutely no answer.

Chapter 4

1. My life came to a standstill. I could breathe, eat, drink and sleep and I could not help breathing, eating, drinking and sleeping; but there was no life in me because I had no desires whose gratification I would have deemed it reasonable to fulfil. If I wanted something I knew in advance that whether or not I satisfied my desire nothing would come of it.

2. If a magician had come and offered to grant my wishes I would not have known what to say. If in my intoxicated moments I still had the habit of desire, rather than real desire, in my sober moments I knew that it was a delusion and that I wanted nothing. I did not even wish to know the truth because I had guessed what it was. The truth was that life is meaningless.

3. It was as if I had carried on living and walking until I reached a precipice from which I could see clearly that there was nothing ahead of me other than destruction. But it was impossible to stop, and impossible to turn back or close my eyes in order not to see that there was nothing ahead other than deception of life and of happiness, and the reality of suffering and death: of complete annihilation.

4. Life had grown hateful to me, and some insuperable force was leading me to seek deliverance from it by whatever means. I could not say that I wanted to kill myself. The force beckoning me away from life was a more powerful, complete and overall desire. It was a force similar to my striving after life, only it was going in the other direction. I fought as hard as I could against life. The thought of suicide now came to me as naturally as thoughts of improving my life had previously come to me. This idea was so attractive to me that I had to use cunning against myself in order to avoid carrying it out too hastily. I did not want to rush, simply because I wanted to make every effort to unravel the matter. I told myself that if I could not unravel the matter now, I still had time to do so. And it was at this time that I, a fortunate man, removed a rope from my room where I undressed every night alone, lest I hang myself from the beam between the cupboards; and I gave up taking a rifle with me on hunting trips so as not to be tempted to end my life in such an all too easy fashion. I myself did not know what I wanted. I was afraid of life and strove against it, yet I still hoped for something from it.

5. All this was happening to me at a time when I was surrounded on all sides by what is considered complete happiness: I was not yet fifty, I had a kind, loving and beloved wife, lovely children, and a large estate that was growing and expanding with no effort on my part. I was respected by relatives and friends far more than ever before. I was praised by strangers and could consider myself a celebrity without deceiving myself. Moreover I was not unhealthy in mind or body, but on the contrary enjoyed a strength of mind and body such as I had rarely witnessed in my contemporaries. Physically I could keep up with the peasants tilling the fields; mentally I could work for eight or ten hours at a stretch without suffering any ill effects from the effort. And in these circumstances I found myself at the point where I could no longer go on living and, since I feared death, I had to deceive myself in order to refrain from suicide.

6. This spiritual condition presented itself to me in the following manner: my life is some kind of stupid and evil joke that someone is playing on me. Despite the fact that I did not acknowledge any such 'someone', who might have created me, this concept of there being someone playing a stupid and evil joke on me by bringing me into the world came to me as the most natural way of expressing my condition.

7. I could not help feeling that out there somewhere somebody was amusing himself by looking at me and the way I had lived for thirty or forty years, studying, developing, maturing in mind and body. And how now, with a fully matured intellect, having reached the precipice from which life reveals itself, I stood there like an utter fool, believing so firmly that there is nothing in life, that there never has been, nor ever will be. 'And he laughs...'

8. But whether or not this someone laughing at me really existed did not make it any easier for me. I could not attribute any rational meaning to a single act, let alone to my whole life. I simply felt astonished that I had failed to realize this from the beginning. It had all been common knowledge for such a long time. Today or tomorrow sickness and death will come (and they had already arrived) to those dear to me, and to myself, and nothing will remain other than the stench and the worms. Sooner or later my deeds, whatever they may have been, will be forgotten and will no longer exist. What is all the fuss about then? How can a person carry on living and fail to perceive this? That is what is so astonishing! It is only possible to go on living while you are intoxicated with life; once sober it is impossible not to see that it is all a mere trick, and a stupid trick! That is exactly what it is: there is nothing either witty or amusing, it is only cruel and stupid.

9. There is an old Eastern fable about a traveller who is taken unawares on the steppes by a ferocious wild animal. In order to escape the beast the traveller hides in an empty well, but at the bottom of the well he sees a dragon with its jaws open, ready to devour him. The poor fellow does not dare to climb out because he is afraid of being eaten by the rapacious beast, neither does he dare drop to the bottom of the well for fear of being eaten by the dragon. So he seizes hold of a branch of a bush that is growing in the crevices of the well and clings on to it. His arms grow weak and he knows that he will soon have to resign himself to the death that awaits him on either side. Yet he still clings on, and while he is holding on to the branch he looks around and sees that two mice, one black and one white, are steadily working their way round the bush he is hanging from, gnawing away at it. Sooner or later they will eat through it and the branch will snap, and he will fall into the jaws of the dragon. The traveller sees this and knows that he will inevitably perish. But while he is still hanging there he sees some drops of honey on the leaves of the bush, stretches out his tongue and licks them. In the same way I am clinging to the tree of life, knowing full well that the dragon of death inevitably awaits me, ready to tear me to pieces, and I cannot understand how I have fallen into this torment. And I try licking the honey that once consoled me, but it no longer gives me pleasure. The white mouse and the black mouse - day and night - are gnawing at the branch from which I am hanging. I can see the dragon clearly and the honey no longer tastes sweet. I can see only one thing; the inescapable dragon and the mice, and I cannot tear my eyes away from them. And this is no fable but the truth, the truth that is irrefutable and intelligible to everyone.

10. The delusion of the joys of life that had formerly stifled my fear of the dragon no longer deceived me. No matter how many times I am told: you cannot understand the meaning of life, do not think about it but live, I cannot do so because I have already done it for too long. Now I cannot help seeing day and night chasing me and leading me to my death. This is all I can see because it is the only truth. All the rest is a lie.

11. Those two drops of honey, which more than all else had diverted my eyes from the cruel truth, my love for my family and for my writing, which I called art - I no longer found sweet.

12. 'The family...,' I said to myself. But my family, my wife and children, are also human beings. They are in exactly the same position as I am: they too must either live a lie, or face the terrible truth. What do they live for? Why do I love them and look after them, bring them up and watch over them? In order to reach the same state of despair that fills me, or in order to be dull-witted! If I love them I cannot conceal the truth from them. Each step taken in knowledge leads them to this truth. And the truth is death.

13. 'Art, poetry...' For a long time, under the influence of success and praise from others, I had persuaded myself that this was a thing that could be done, despite the fact of approaching death which obliterates everything: myself, my works and the memory of both. But I quickly realized that this too was a delusion. It was clear to me that art is an adornment and embellishment of life. But it had lost its charm for me, so how could I charm others? While I was not living my own life but was being carried along on the crest of another life, as long as I believed that life had meaning even if I could not express it, the reflection of life in poetry and in art of all kinds gave me joy and I enjoyed watching life through the mirror of art. But when I began to search for the meaning of life, when I began to feel the necessity of living, I found this mirror either unnecessary, superfluous and ridiculous, or tormenting. I could no longer be comforted by what I saw in the mirror, namely my stupid and desperate position. It was all right for me to rejoice in the sight while in the depths of my soul I believed that my life had meaning. Then the play of light and shade, the comic, the tragic, the touching, the beautiful, and the frightening aspects of life comforted me. But when I saw that life is meaningless and terrible, the play in the mirror could no longer amuse me. However sweet the honey, it could not be sweet to me while I saw the dragon and the mice gnawing at my support.

14. But that was not all. Had I simply understood that life has no meaning I might have accepted it peacefully, knowing that it was my lot. But I could not be calmed by this. If I had been like a man in a wood from which he knows there is no way out, I might have been able to live; but I was like a man in a wood who is lost, and terrified by this rushes around hoping to find his way out, knowing that with each step he is getting more lost, and yet unable to stop rushing about.

15. It was all quite dreadful. And so, in order to escape from this horror, I wanted to kill myself. I felt a horror of what lay ahead of me and knew that this horror was worse than my present position, but I could neither drive it away nor patiently await the end. However convincing the argument that said a blood vessel of the heart would collapse anyway, or that something would burst and it would all be over, I could not wait for the end with composure. The horror of the darkness was too great and I wanted to escape from it as quickly as possible by means of a rope or a bullet. It was this feeling that lured me, more strongly than anything else, towards suicide.

Chapter 5

1. Several times I said to myself, 'But perhaps I have overlooked something, or failed to understand something? It cannot be that this state of despair is common to all men.' And I searched for an answer to my questions in all branches of knowledge acquired by man. I sought long and laboriously. I did not search half-heartedly, or out of idle curiosity, but tormentedly, persistently, day and night, like a dying man seeking salvation, and I found nothing.

2. I searched all branches of knowledge and not only found nothing, but was convinced that all those who had searched the realms of knowledge like myself had likewise found nothing. Not only had they found nothing, but they had plainly acknowledged the same thing that had led me to despair: the meaninglessness of life as the only indisputable piece of knowledge available to man.

3. I searched everywhere and thanks to a life spent in study, and to my connections with the world of learning, I had access to scholars of various disciplines. I was not denied insight into their erudition, both through books and in conversation with them, and I learnt everything that knowledge has to answer to the question of life.

4. For a long time I could not believe that knowledge has no answer to the question of life, other than that which it gives. For a long time it seemed to me, as I observed the air of importance and seriousness with which science asserts its propositions (which have nothing to do with human life), that I had failed to understand something. For a long time I cowered before knowledge, and felt that the fact of my receiving no adequate answers to my question was a result of my naïveté and no fault of knowledge. But it was no laughing matter to me, it was no joke but a subject that dominated my life. I was finally forced to conclude that my questions were the only legitimate ones serving as the basis of all branches of knowledge, and that the fault did not lie with me and my questions, but with science if it had the pretension to answer these questions.

5. My question, the one that brought me to the point of suicide when I was fifty years old, was a most simple one that lies in the soul of every person, from a silly child to a wise old man. It is the question without which life is impossible, as I had learnt from experience. It is this: what will come of what I do today or tomorrow? What will come of my entire life?

6. Expressed another way the question can be put like this: why do I live? Why do I wish for anything, or do anything? Or expressed another way: is there any meaning in my life that will not be annihilated by the inevitability of death which awaits me?

7. I searched through human knowledge for an answer to this question, which is the same whatever way it is expressed. I found that according to their relation to the question, all branches of human knowledge are divided, almost into two opposite hemispheres, at the opposite ends of which are two poles: one positive and one negative: yet at neither pole were there any answers to the question of life.

8. One branch of knowledge does not even seem to acknowledge the question and yet gives clear and precise answers to its own independently posed question: this is the realm of experimental knowledge, and at its extreme end stands mathematics. The other realm of knowledge recognizes the question but does not answer it. This is the sphere of speculative philosophy, at the extreme end of which stands metaphysics.

9. From my early youth I had studied speculative philosophy, but was later attracted by both mathematical and natural science. Until I had posed my question clearly to myself and the question itself had grown up within me, demanding an urgent resolution, I was satisfied with the falsified answers given by knowledge.

10. In the experimental sphere I said to myself, 'Everything develops, differentiates, moving towards complexity and refinement and there are laws governing this progress. You are a part of a whole. When you know as much as possible about the whole, and about the laws of its development, you will understand your place in the whole, and your own self.' Although I am ashamed to admit it, there was a time when I seemed to be satisfied with this. It was at a time when I myself was developing and growing more complex. My muscles were growing and strengthening, my memory was richer, my capacity to think and comprehend was increasing. I was growing and developing, and, feeling this growth within myself, it was natural for me to believe that there was a law governing the world, in which I could find the answers to the questions of my life. But the time came when I stopped growing; I felt that I was no longer developing but was drying up, my muscles were growing weaker, my teeth falling out, and I saw that this law not only failed to explain anything to me, but that there had never been and never could be such a law, and that I had taken for a law something which I had discovered in myself at a certain time of my life. I examined its definition more strictly, and it became clear to me that there could be no law of perpetual development. It became apparent to me that to say that in the infinity of time and space everything is developing, becoming more perfect, complex and differentiated, is really to say nothing at all. They are all words without a meaning, for in the infinite there is no simple and complex, no before and after, and no better or worse.

11. The most important thing was that my own personal question, the question of what I am with all my desires, was left completely unanswered. I understood that these studies are very interesting and attractive but that their precision and clarity are inversely proportionate to their applicability to questions concerning life: the less applicable to the questions of life, the clearer and more precise they are, whereas the more they try to provide solutions to the questions of life, the more obscure and unattractive they become. If we turn to those branches of knowledge that attempt to provide solutions to the question of life, to physiology, psychology, biology and sociology, we encounter a startling poverty of thought, extreme lack of clarity and a completely unjustified pretension to resolve questions beyond their scope, together with continual contradiction between one thinker and another (or even with their own selves). If we turn to the branches of knowledge that are not concerned with resolving life's questions, but which answer their own specialized, scientific questions, we may be enraptured by the power of the human intellect, but we know in advance that they will provide no answers to the question of life. These branches ignore the question. They say: 'As for what you are and why you live, we have no answers and do not involve ourselves with it. On the other hand, if you need to know about the laws governing light, or about chemical combinations, or about the laws governing the development of organisms; or if you need to know about the laws governing physical bodies and their forms, and the relationship between their size and quantity; or if you need to know about the laws governing your own mind, then we have clear, precise and irrefutable answers to all this.'

12. In general, the relationship of the experimental sciences to the questions of life can be expressed in this way. Question: why do I live? Answer: in the infinity of space and the infinity of time infinitely small particles mutate with infinite complexity. When you understand the laws of these mutations you will understand why you live.

13. Then moving into the speculative sphere I would say to myself: 'All mankind lives and develops according to spiritual principles and ideals which guide it. These ideals are expressed in religions, sciences, arts and forms of government. As these ideals become more elevated mankind advances towards greater well-being. I am a part of mankind and my duty therefore is to enhance the recognition and realization of these ideals.' During my weak-minded period I was satisfied with this. But as soon as the question of life presented itself to me clearly, the whole of this theory instantly crumbled to dust. As well as the careless vagueness with which this kind of knowledge draws conclusions, and makes generalized deductions about humanity based on a study of only a small proportion of it; as well as the mutual contradictions between the different supporters of this theory as to what man's ideals actually are, the peculiarity, not to say the stupidity, of this view is that in order to answer the question facing us all: what am I? or: why do I live? or: what must I do? man must first resolve the question of what this life of mankind is, of which so little is known and of which he can know only a minute portion in a fraction of a moment of time? In order to understand what he is man must first understand the entire mystery of humanity, a humanity made up of people like himself, who do not understand themselves.

14. I must confess there was a time when I believed this. It was at a time when I had my own favourite ideals which justified my whims, and I endeavoured to concoct a theory by which I could look upon my whims as laws governing mankind. But once the question of life had risen up in my soul with full clarity, this answer immediately vanished into thin air. I came to realize that just as with the experimental sciences there are genuine sciences and semi-sciences, both trying to give answers beyond their scope, there are similarly a whole series of extremely diverse sciences, also trying to answer questions beyond their scope. These semi-sciences, the judicial, social and historical sciences, all endeavour to resolve man's questions by giving the appearance, each in its own way, of resolving the question of life that concerns all mankind.

15. But just as in the realms of experimental sciences a person who sincerely asks how he ought to live cannot be satisfied with an answer advising him to study the infinite complexities and mutations of an infinite number of particles in the infinity of space and time; similarly a person who sincerely asks how he ought to live cannot be satisfied with an answer telling him that in order to understand himself he must first study the life of the whole of humanity, of which neither the beginning nor the end is known, nor even the smallest part. And, as with the experimental semi-sciences, the more these other sciences diverge from their purpose, the more they become filled with vagueness, lack of precision, stupidities and contradictions. The problem concerning experimental science is the sequence of cause and effect in material phenomena. Experimental science only has to be introduced to the question of final causes for it to turn into a nonsense. The problem facing speculative science is acknowledgement of the essence of life that lies beyond cause and effect. And one only has to introduce causative phenomena, such as social or historical data, into the investigations and it turns into a nonsense.

16. Experimental science, therefore, only deals with positive knowledge and reveals the greatness of the human intellect when it does not introduce the question of ultimate causes into its inquiries. Abstract science, on the other hand, only becomes a science and only reveals the greatness of the human intellect when it completely avoids questions concerning the sequence of causative phenomena and examines man only in relation to an ultimate cause. An example of this science, situated at the pole of the hemisphere, is metaphysics, or abstract philosophy. This science clearly poses the question: who am I? And: what is the universe? Why do I exist and why does the universe exist? And since it has existed this science has always given the same answer. Whether the philosopher calls the essence of life that is within me and within everything an idea, or a substance, a spirit or a will, he is saying the same thing: that I exist and that I am this essence. But how and why he does not know, and if he is a precise thinker he does not answer. I ask, 'Why does this essence exist? What comes of the fact that it is and will be?' And philosophy not only fails to answer but can only ask the same thing itself. And if it is a true philosophy, its whole task lies precisely in posing this question clearly. And if it holds firmly to its purpose then it can have no other answer to the question of what I am and what the universe is than: 'All and nothing.' And to the question of why the universe exists and why I exist, then: 'I do not know.'

17. Thus, whatever way I twist these speculative answers of philosophy, I can find nothing resembling an answer. This is not because, as in the case of the clear, experimental sciences, the answer does not relate to the question, but because despite all the intellectual effort directed at my question, there is no answer. And instead of an answer all one gets is the same question, only put in a more complicated form.